<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Matthew 2 | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/matthew-2/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/tag/matthew-2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Matthew 2</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu59ba181d12b9f86a6b06fa85c0a2a62a_406614_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Matthew 2</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/matthew-2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 Nativity</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb04-portions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb04-portions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;9-the-annunciation-to-joseph-of-the-birth-of-jesus&#34;&gt;9. The annunciation to Joseph of the birth of Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mat 1:18-25&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now the birth of Jesus Christ took place in this way. When his mother Mary had been betrothed to Joseph, before they came together she was found to be with child from the Holy Spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And her husband Joseph, being a just man and unwilling to put her to shame, resolved to divorce her quietly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But as he considered these things, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream, saying, “Joseph, son of David, do not fear to take Mary as your wife, for that which is conceived in her is from the Holy Spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She will bear a son, and you shall call his name Jesus, for he will save his people from their sins.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All this took place to fulfill what the Lord had spoken by the prophet:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Behold, the virgin shall conceive and bear a son, and they shall call his name Immanuel” (which means, God with us).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When Joseph woke from sleep, he did as the angel of the Lord commanded him: he took his wife,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but knew her not until she had given birth to a son. And he called his name Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;10-the-birth-of-jesus&#34;&gt;10. The birth of Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 2:1-7&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In those days a decree went out from Caesar Augustus that all the world should be registered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was the first registration when Quirinius was governor of Syria.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And all went to be registered, each to his own town.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Joseph also went up from Galilee, from the town of Nazareth, to Judea, to the city of David, which is called Bethlehem, because he was of the house and lineage of David,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to be registered with Mary, his betrothed, who was with child.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And while they were there, the time came for her to give birth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And she gave birth to her firstborn son and wrapped him in swaddling cloths and laid him in a manger, because there was no place for them in the inn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;11-the-praise-of-the-angels-and-the-homage-of-the-shepherds&#34;&gt;11. The praise of the angels and the homage of the shepherds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 2:8-20&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And in the same region there were shepherds out in the field, keeping watch over their flock by night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And an angel of the Lord appeared to them, and the glory of the Lord shone around them, and they were filled with great fear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the angel said to them, “Fear not, for behold, I bring you good news of great joy that will be for all the people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For unto you is born this day in the city of David a Savior, who is Christ the Lord.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And this will be a sign for you: you will find a baby wrapped in swaddling cloths and lying in a manger.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly host praising God and saying,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace among those with whom he is pleased!”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the angels went away from them into heaven, the shepherds said to one another, “Let us go over to Bethlehem and see this thing that has happened, which the Lord has made known to us.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And they went with haste and found Mary and Joseph, and the baby lying in a manger.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And when they saw it, they made known the saying that had been told them concerning this child.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And all who heard it wondered at what the shepherds told them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But Mary treasured up all these things, pondering them in her heart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all they had heard and seen, as it had been told them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;12-the-circumcision-of-jesus&#34;&gt;12. The circumcision of Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 2:21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And at the end of eight days, when he was circumcised, he was called Jesus, the name given by the angel before he was conceived in the womb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;13-the-presentation-in-the-temple-with-the-homage-of-simeon-and-anna&#34;&gt;13. The presentation in the temple with the homage of Simeon and Anna&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 2:22-38&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And when the time came for their purification according to the Law of Moses, they brought him up to Jerusalem to present him to the Lord&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(as it is written in the Law of the Lord, “Every male who first opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and to offer a sacrifice according to what is said in the Law of the Lord, “a pair of turtledoves, or two young pigeons.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name was Simeon, and this man was righteous and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel, and the Holy Spirit was upon him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And it had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit that he would not see death before he had seen the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Christ.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And he came in the Spirit into the temple, and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him according to the custom of the Law,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;he took him up in his arms and blessed God and said,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Lord, now you are letting your servant depart in peace, according to your word;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for my eyes have seen your salvation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that you have prepared in the presence of all peoples,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to your people Israel.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And his father and his mother marveled at what was said about him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Simeon blessed them and said to Mary his mother, “Behold, this child is appointed for the fall and rising of many in Israel, and for a sign that is opposed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(and a sword will pierce through your own soul also), so that thoughts from many hearts may be revealed.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And there was a prophetess, Anna, the daughter of Phanuel, of the tribe of Asher. She was advanced in years, having lived with her husband seven years from when she was a virgin,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and then as a widow until she was eighty-four. She did not depart from the temple, worshiping with fasting and prayer night and day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And coming up at that very hour she began to give thanks to God and to speak of him to all who were waiting for the redemption of Jerusalem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb04-backgrounds&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the full Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5. The Nazarene</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/5-the-nazarene/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/5-the-nazarene/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3uaVNrYBB0Q&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
