<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gospel Backgrounds I: Early Ministry - Lessons 1-11 | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Gospel Backgrounds I: Early Ministry - Lessons 1-11</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu59ba181d12b9f86a6b06fa85c0a2a62a_406614_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Gospel Backgrounds I: Early Ministry - Lessons 1-11</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>1. The Logos</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb01-portions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb01-portions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-in-his-introduction-john-pictures-christ-as-the-word-logos&#34;&gt;2. In his introduction John pictures Christ as the Word (Logos)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 1:1-18&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He was in the beginning with God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All things were made through him, and without him was not any thing made that was made.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In him was life, and the life was the light of men.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The light shines in the darkness, and the darkness has not overcome it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was a man sent from God, whose name was John.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He came as a witness, to bear witness about the light, that all might believe through him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He was not the light, but came to bear witness about the light.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The true light, which gives light to everyone, was coming into the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He was in the world, and the world was made through him, yet the world did not know him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He came to his own, and his own people did not receive him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But to all who did receive him, who believed in his name, he gave the right to become children of God,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who were born, not of blood nor of the will of the flesh nor of the will of man, but of God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the Word became flesh and dwelt among us, and we have seen his glory, glory as of the only Son from the Father, full of grace and truth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(John bore witness about him, and cried out, “This was he of whom I said, ‘He who comes after me ranks before me, because he was before me.’”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For from his fullness we have all received, grace upon grace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the law was given through Moses; grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No one has ever seen God; the only God, who is at the Father&amp;rsquo;s side, he has made him known.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/01-the_logos&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2a Annunciations Part I</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb02-portions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb02-portions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;11-in-the-dedication-luke-explains-his-method-of-research&#34;&gt;1.1. In the dedication Luke explains his method of research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 1:1-4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inasmuch as many have undertaken to compile a narrative of the things that have been accomplished among us,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;just as those who from the beginning were eyewitnesses and ministers of the word have delivered them to us,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it seemed good to me also, having followed all things closely for some time past, to write an orderly account for you, most excellent Theophilus,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that you may have certainty concerning the things you have been taught.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-the-annunciation-of-the-birth-of-the-baptist-to-zacharias&#34;&gt;4. The annunciation of the birth of the Baptist to Zacharias&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 1:5-25&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the days of Herod, king of Judea, there was a priest named Zechariah, of the division of Abijah. And he had a wife from the daughters of Aaron, and her name was Elizabeth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And they were both righteous before God, walking blamelessly in all the commandments and statutes of the Lord.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But they had no child, because Elizabeth was barren, and both were advanced in years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now while he was serving as priest before God when his division was on duty,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;according to the custom of the priesthood, he was chosen by lot to enter the temple of the Lord and burn incense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the whole multitude of the people were praying outside at the hour of incense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And there appeared to him an angel of the Lord standing on the right side of the altar of incense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Zechariah was troubled when he saw him, and fear fell upon him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But the angel said to him, “Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your prayer has been heard, and your wife Elizabeth will bear you a son, and you shall call his name John.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And you will have joy and gladness, and many will rejoice at his birth,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for he will be great before the Lord. And he must not drink wine or strong drink, and he will be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from his mother&amp;rsquo;s womb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And he will turn many of the children of Israel to the Lord their God,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and he will go before him in the spirit and power of Elijah, to turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the disobedient to the wisdom of the just, to make ready for the Lord a people prepared.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Zechariah said to the angel, “How shall I know this? For I am an old man, and my wife is advanced in years.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the angel answered him, “I am Gabriel. I stand in the presence of God, and I was sent to speak to you and to bring you this good news.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And behold, you will be silent and unable to speak until the day that these things take place, because you did not believe my words, which will be fulfilled in their time.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the people were waiting for Zechariah, and they were wondering at his delay in the temple.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And when he came out, he was unable to speak to them, and they realized that he had seen a vision in the temple. And he kept making signs to them and remained mute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And when his time of service was ended, he went to his home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After these days his wife Elizabeth conceived, and for five months she kept herself hidden, saying,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Thus the Lord has done for me in the days when he looked on me, to take away my reproach among people.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-the-annunciation-to-the-virgin-mary-of-the-birth-of-jesus&#34;&gt;5. The annunciation to the virgin Mary of the birth of Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 1:26-38&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the sixth month the angel Gabriel was sent from God to a city of Galilee named Nazareth,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to a virgin betrothed to a man whose name was Joseph, of the house of David. And the virgin&amp;rsquo;s name was Mary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And he came to her and said, “Greetings, O favored one, the Lord is with you!”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But she was greatly troubled at the saying, and tried to discern what sort of greeting this might be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the angel said to her, “Do not be afraid, Mary, for you have found favor with God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And behold, you will conceive in your womb and bear a son, and you shall call his name Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He will be great and will be called the Son of the Most High. And the Lord God will give to him the throne of his father David,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and he will reign over the house of Jacob forever, and of his kingdom there will be no end.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Mary said to the angel, “How will this be, since I am a virgin?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the angel answered her, “The Holy Spirit will come upon you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow you; therefore the child to be born will be called holy—the Son of God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And behold, your relative Elizabeth in her old age has also conceived a son, and this is the sixth month with her who was called barren.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For nothing will be impossible with God.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Mary said, “Behold, I am the servant of the Lord; let it be to me according to your word.” And the angel departed from her.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/2a-annunciations&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2b Annunciations Part II</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb02b-portions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb02b-portions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;6-the-song-of-elizabeth-to-mary-upon-her-visit&#34;&gt;6. The song of Elizabeth to Mary upon her visit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 1:39-45&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;39&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In those days Mary arose and went with haste into the hill country, to a town in Judah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and she entered the house of Zechariah and greeted Elizabeth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And when Elizabeth heard the greeting of Mary, the baby leaped in her womb. And Elizabeth was filled with the Holy Spirit,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and she exclaimed with a loud cry, “Blessed are you among women, and blessed is the fruit of your womb!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And why is this granted to me that the mother of my Lord should come to me?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For behold, when the sound of your greeting came to my ears, the baby in my womb leaped for joy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And blessed is she who believed that there would be a fulfillment of what was spoken to her from the Lord.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;7-the-magnificat-of-mary&#34;&gt;7. The Magnificat of Mary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 1:46-56&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;46&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Mary said, “My soul magnifies the Lord,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and my spirit rejoices in God my Savior,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for he has looked on the humble estate of his servant. For behold, from now on all generations will call me blessed;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for he who is mighty has done great things for me, and holy is his name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And his mercy is for those who fear him from generation to generation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He has shown strength with his arm; he has scattered the proud in the thoughts of their hearts;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;he has brought down the mighty from their thrones and exalted those of humble estate;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;he has filled the hungry with good things, and the rich he has sent away empty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He has helped his servant Israel, in remembrance of his mercy,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as he spoke to our fathers, to Abraham and to his offspring forever.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Mary remained with her about three months and returned to her home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;8-the-birth-and-childhood-of-the-baptist-and-his-desert-life&#34;&gt;8. The birth and childhood of the Baptist and his desert life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 1:57-80&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;57&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now the time came for Elizabeth to give birth, and she bore a son.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And her neighbors and relatives heard that the Lord had shown great mercy to her, and they rejoiced with her.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And on the eighth day they came to circumcise the child. And they would have called him Zechariah after his father,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but his mother answered, “No; he shall be called John.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And they said to her, “None of your relatives is called by this name.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And they made signs to his father, inquiring what he wanted him to be called.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And he asked for a writing tablet and wrote, “His name is John.” And they all wondered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And immediately his mouth was opened and his tongue loosed, and he spoke, blessing God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And fear came on all their neighbors. And all these things were talked about through all the hill country of Judea,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and all who heard them laid them up in their hearts, saying, “What then will this child be?” For the hand of the Lord was with him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And his father Zechariah was filled with the Holy Spirit and prophesied, saying,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, for he has visited and redeemed his people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and has raised up a horn of salvation for us in the house of his servant David,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as he spoke by the mouth of his holy prophets from of old,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that we should be saved from our enemies and from the hand of all who hate us;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to show the mercy promised to our fathers and to remember his holy covenant,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the oath that he swore to our father Abraham, to grant us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that we, being delivered from the hand of our enemies, might serve him without fear,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in holiness and righteousness before him all our days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And you, child, will be called the prophet of the Most High; for you will go before the Lord to prepare his ways,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to give knowledge of salvation to his people in the forgiveness of their sins,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because of the tender mercy of our God, whereby the sunrise shall visit us from on high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to give light to those who sit in darkness and in the shadow of death, to guide our feet into the way of peace.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the child grew and became strong in spirit, and he was in the wilderness until the day of his public appearance to Israel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/2b-annunciations-part-ii&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Genealogies</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb03-portions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb03-portions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-apparently-josephs-genealogy-in-matthew-and-marys-in-luke&#34;&gt;3. Apparently Joseph&amp;rsquo;s genealogy in Matthew and Mary&amp;rsquo;s in Luke&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The book of the genealogy of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abraham was the father of Isaac, and Isaac the father of Jacob, and Jacob the father of Judah and his brothers,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Judah the father of Perez and Zerah by Tamar, and Perez the father of Hezron, and Hezron the father of Ram,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Ram the father of Amminadab, and Amminadab the father of Nahshon, and Nahshon the father of Salmon,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Salmon the father of Boaz by Rahab, and Boaz the father of Obed by Ruth, and Obed the father of Jesse,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Jesse the father of David the king. And David was the father of Solomon by the wife of Uriah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Solomon the father of Rehoboam, and Rehoboam the father of Abijah, and Abijah the father of Asaph,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Asaph the father of Jehoshaphat, and Jehoshaphat the father of Joram, and Joram the father of Uzziah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Uzziah the father of Jotham, and Jotham the father of Ahaz, and Ahaz the father of Hezekiah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Hezekiah the father of Manasseh, and Manasseh the father of Amos, and Amos the father of Josiah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Josiah the father of Jechoniah and his brothers, at the time of the deportation to Babylon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And after the deportation to Babylon: Jechoniah was the father of Shealtiel, and Shealtiel the father of Zerubbabel,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Zerubbabel the father of Abiud, and Abiud the father of Eliakim, and Eliakim the father of Azor,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Azor the father of Zadok, and Zadok the father of Achim, and Achim the father of Eliud,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Eliud the father of Eleazar, and Eleazar the father of Matthan, and Matthan the father of Jacob,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Jacob the father of Joseph the husband of Mary, of whom Jesus was born, who is called Christ.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So all the generations from Abraham to David were fourteen generations, and from David to the deportation to Babylon fourteen generations, and from the deportation to Babylon to the Christ fourteen generations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus, when he began his ministry, was about thirty years of age, being the son (as was supposed) of Joseph, the son of Heli,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Matthat, the son of Levi, the son of Melchi, the son of Jannai, the son of Joseph,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Mattathias, the son of Amos, the son of Nahum, the son of Esli, the son of Naggai,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Maath, the son of Mattathias, the son of Semein, the son of Josech, the son of Joda,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Joanan, the son of Rhesa, the son of Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, the son of Neri,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Melchi, the son of Addi, the son of Cosam, the son of Elmadam, the son of Er,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Joshua, the son of Eliezer, the son of Jorim, the son of Matthat, the son of Levi,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Simeon, the son of Judah, the son of Joseph, the son of Jonam, the son of Eliakim,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Melea, the son of Menna, the son of Mattatha, the son of Nathan, the son of David,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Jesse, the son of Obed, the son of Boaz, the son of Sala, the son of Nahshon,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Amminadab, the son of Admin, the son of Arni, the son of Hezron, the son of Perez, the son of Judah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Jacob, the son of Isaac, the son of Abraham, the son of Terah, the son of Nahor,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Serug, the son of Reu, the son of Peleg, the son of Eber, the son of Shelah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Cainan, the son of Arphaxad, the son of Shem, the son of Noah, the son of Lamech,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Methuselah, the son of Enoch, the son of Jared, the son of Mahalaleel, the son of Cainan,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Enos, the son of Seth, the son of Adam, the son of God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/3-genealogies&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the full Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 Nativity</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb04-portions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb04-portions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;9-the-annunciation-to-joseph-of-the-birth-of-jesus&#34;&gt;9. The annunciation to Joseph of the birth of Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mat 1:18-25&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now the birth of Jesus Christ took place in this way. When his mother Mary had been betrothed to Joseph, before they came together she was found to be with child from the Holy Spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And her husband Joseph, being a just man and unwilling to put her to shame, resolved to divorce her quietly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But as he considered these things, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream, saying, “Joseph, son of David, do not fear to take Mary as your wife, for that which is conceived in her is from the Holy Spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She will bear a son, and you shall call his name Jesus, for he will save his people from their sins.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All this took place to fulfill what the Lord had spoken by the prophet:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Behold, the virgin shall conceive and bear a son, and they shall call his name Immanuel” (which means, God with us).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When Joseph woke from sleep, he did as the angel of the Lord commanded him: he took his wife,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but knew her not until she had given birth to a son. And he called his name Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;10-the-birth-of-jesus&#34;&gt;10. The birth of Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 2:1-7&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In those days a decree went out from Caesar Augustus that all the world should be registered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was the first registration when Quirinius was governor of Syria.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And all went to be registered, each to his own town.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Joseph also went up from Galilee, from the town of Nazareth, to Judea, to the city of David, which is called Bethlehem, because he was of the house and lineage of David,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to be registered with Mary, his betrothed, who was with child.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And while they were there, the time came for her to give birth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And she gave birth to her firstborn son and wrapped him in swaddling cloths and laid him in a manger, because there was no place for them in the inn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;11-the-praise-of-the-angels-and-the-homage-of-the-shepherds&#34;&gt;11. The praise of the angels and the homage of the shepherds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 2:8-20&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And in the same region there were shepherds out in the field, keeping watch over their flock by night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And an angel of the Lord appeared to them, and the glory of the Lord shone around them, and they were filled with great fear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the angel said to them, “Fear not, for behold, I bring you good news of great joy that will be for all the people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For unto you is born this day in the city of David a Savior, who is Christ the Lord.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And this will be a sign for you: you will find a baby wrapped in swaddling cloths and lying in a manger.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly host praising God and saying,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace among those with whom he is pleased!”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the angels went away from them into heaven, the shepherds said to one another, “Let us go over to Bethlehem and see this thing that has happened, which the Lord has made known to us.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And they went with haste and found Mary and Joseph, and the baby lying in a manger.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And when they saw it, they made known the saying that had been told them concerning this child.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And all who heard it wondered at what the shepherds told them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But Mary treasured up all these things, pondering them in her heart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all they had heard and seen, as it had been told them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;12-the-circumcision-of-jesus&#34;&gt;12. The circumcision of Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 2:21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And at the end of eight days, when he was circumcised, he was called Jesus, the name given by the angel before he was conceived in the womb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;13-the-presentation-in-the-temple-with-the-homage-of-simeon-and-anna&#34;&gt;13. The presentation in the temple with the homage of Simeon and Anna&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luk 2:22-38&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And when the time came for their purification according to the Law of Moses, they brought him up to Jerusalem to present him to the Lord&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(as it is written in the Law of the Lord, “Every male who first opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and to offer a sacrifice according to what is said in the Law of the Lord, “a pair of turtledoves, or two young pigeons.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name was Simeon, and this man was righteous and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel, and the Holy Spirit was upon him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And it had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit that he would not see death before he had seen the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Christ.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And he came in the Spirit into the temple, and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him according to the custom of the Law,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;he took him up in his arms and blessed God and said,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Lord, now you are letting your servant depart in peace, according to your word;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for my eyes have seen your salvation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that you have prepared in the presence of all peoples,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to your people Israel.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And his father and his mother marveled at what was said about him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Simeon blessed them and said to Mary his mother, “Behold, this child is appointed for the fall and rising of many in Israel, and for a sign that is opposed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(and a sword will pierce through your own soul also), so that thoughts from many hearts may be revealed.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And there was a prophetess, Anna, the daughter of Phanuel, of the tribe of Asher. She was advanced in years, having lived with her husband seven years from when she was a virgin,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and then as a widow until she was eighty-four. She did not depart from the temple, worshiping with fasting and prayer night and day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And coming up at that very hour she began to give thanks to God and to speak of him to all who were waiting for the redemption of Jerusalem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb04-backgrounds&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the full Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
