<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CBC Bonham 2023 Israel Talmidim Tour | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>CBC Bonham 2023 Israel Talmidim Tour</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu53652e90a6e4e4f125f22da2a993ec10_403021_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>CBC Bonham 2023 Israel Talmidim Tour</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why go to Israel? (and other questions)</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/why-go-to-israel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/why-go-to-israel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Walk about Zion, go around her, count her towers, consider well her rampart, view her citadels, that you may tell of them to the next generation. For this God is our God forever and ever; He will be our guide even to the end.&amp;rdquo; - Psalm 48:12-14&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Many facts and scenes, which seem to float ghost-like in the clouds to a distant reader, assume flesh and blood in the land of their birth. There is a marvelous correspondence between the Land and the Book. The Bible is the best handbook for the Holy Land, and the Holy Land is the best commentary on the Bible.” Philip Schaff (1813-1893), pp. 383-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“A trip to Israel is worth a year in seminary.” Pastor Chuck Smith (1927-2013)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Christians, the Land of Israel is often called the “5th Gospel”. Seeing the country firsthand can be as revealing as the four Gospels when it comes to understanding the life of Jesus. You will be amazed at how your spiritual life will change and your faith strengthened. You will never read the Bible the same again. What was once black and white is now in color.  One-dimensional words on a page now come alive as you experience with all your senses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-go-to-israel&#34;&gt;Why go to Israel?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sharper comprehension of the Bible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clearer understanding of biblical application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More effective communication of truth to others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A framework for better memory of biblical events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greater confidence in the Word of God—having seen the places the Bible speaks of&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More vibrant spiritual life and deeper love for God (99% of those who go affirm this)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning the Word of God will all your senses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seeing the Bible when you read it for the rest of your life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experiencing a dimension of authenticity and history to your faith you could gain no other way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A window of opportunity that may not last (the political situation and lifting of many Covid restrictions is ideal for tourism now)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is our desire that you fall deeply in love with your Messiah, the Biblical Text and the land of Israel, so that your life is changed forever.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;whats-in-it-for-me&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s in it for me?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this tour, we will help you connect the Bible and its lands to your life. Every site and activity has been prayed over with YOU in mind!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will learn the Word of God right where it happened—with Bible in hand. After seeing where Jesus ministered, you will never read your Bible the same way again!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our Israeli guide will teach you cultural and historical connections as he travels with us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will gain a deeper understanding of Jesus’ purpose and life
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His ministry wasn’t a random set of good deeds, teachings, and miracles on His way to die for our sins in Jerusalem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every step, every stop, every act of His was intentional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will discover how He developed the lives of His &lt;em&gt;talmidim&lt;/em&gt; (disciples)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More importantly, you’ll learn how He is working in your life in the same way; you are His &lt;em&gt;talmid&lt;/em&gt; also!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will have dozens if not hundreds of memories (as well as notes and photographs) to remember and use in your Bible study&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will have a journal (if you choose) and other reference material that will help you recall the wealth of information you will be exposed to along the way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time you open your Bible, you will picture the landscape you walked&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will watch the sun set over the Sea of Galilee—just as Jesus saw it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will get the feel of the land as you experience the Holy City of Jerusalem with all your senses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will hear the Word of God in the Capernaum Synagogue—the very place where Jesus preached&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will enjoy the fragrances in every place—from the aromatic Jerusalem markets to the salty seaside port of Caesarea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will experience the fellowship of other Christians as we travel the lands of the Bible together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will have an opportunity to experience Genesis 12:3 first-hand (God will bless those who bless Israel) through a small service project that can have a big impact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will taste the delicious meals of Israeli culture (which probably hasn&amp;rsquo;t changed all that much since the 1st century)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-will-be-leading-the-tour&#34;&gt;Who will be leading the tour?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We have requested proposals from multiple reputable tour companies.  We will update this page once we have made a selection.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris is coordinating the tour from Bonham.  He has been to Israel multiple times and has a passion for teaching the context of God&amp;rsquo;s Word&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will be using an experienced tour operator: Name TBD &lt;website&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our guide&amp;rsquo;s name is TBD &lt;guide bio&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will have many opportunities for worship through song, prayer, and short teachings/devotionals at each site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-a-typical-day&#34;&gt;What is a typical day?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since for many of us this will be our one and only time to go to Israel, we want the agenda to be full but not overwhelming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:00-7:30: Breakfast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:00-8:30 on the bus
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will do prayer and devotion en-route to the first site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During the touring days we will be visiting 4-6 sites
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historical background from our guide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group worship 1-2 times a day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review of Scripture and short devotional or teaching on the personal application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time for personal reflection and exploring/photos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lunch will be in the field
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lunch is not included in the tour price&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In light of the demanding schedule, we recommend packing some heat-resistant snacks for between meals (e.g., peanuts but not trail mix with chocolate)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6:30-7:00 return to the hotel for dinner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:00 recap, evening devotions, prayer, worship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-should-i-prepare&#34;&gt;How should I prepare?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just a vacation where you need to pack a few things.  This is a &lt;em&gt;spiritual journey&lt;/em&gt;.  The &lt;em&gt;spiritual&lt;/em&gt; part means that to get the most out of our tour, we need to prepare our hearts and minds.  The &lt;em&gt;journey&lt;/em&gt; part means we will be doing a LOT of walking, and much of it on uneven terrain.  We need to make sure our physicial body is ready for what we are about to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve developed tips to address these questions on our &amp;ldquo;prep&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;../physical&#34;&gt;Physical&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;../spiritual&#34;&gt;Spiritual&lt;/a&gt;) pages!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the weeks leading up to the tour, we will be posting information on these pages about various sites and other travel tips. In early 2023, we will offer a multi-week course that teaches about various sites through the life of Jesus, as well as some background on history and geography.  This will give us a greater context in which to understand His powerful words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-will-i-need-to-bring&#34;&gt;What will I need to bring?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a comprehensive packing list on our &lt;a href=&#34;../physical&#34;&gt;Physical Prep&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See the &lt;a href=&#34;../clothing&#34;&gt;Clothing&lt;/a&gt; page for tips on (wait for it) clothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always bring a positive, Christ-like attitude! You are His ambassador in a part of the world that has had valid reasons to be &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jewish_deicide&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;distrustful of Christians&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;do-they-speak-english&#34;&gt;Do they speak English?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YES. English is an official language of Israel. Most signs are in Hebrew, English, and Arabic. Our guide is fluent in both Hebrew and English. See the &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/courses/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Learn Hebrew&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; if you are interested in learning a little Hebrew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-much-will-this-cost-what-is-included-and-when-do-i-pay&#34;&gt;How much will this cost, what is included and when do I pay?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TBD -We are in the process of securing bids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See the &lt;a href=&#34;../money&#34;&gt;Money&lt;/a&gt; page for what the price includes and excludes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be three payment dates to remember&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A due date for submitting a refundable deposit to reserve your spot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A date where 50% of the price will be due&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A due date for the Remaining 50%, along with your &lt;a href=&#34;../passport&#34;&gt;Passport&lt;/a&gt; information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;can-i-invite-others-who-dont-attend-cbc-bonham&#34;&gt;Can I invite others who don&amp;rsquo;t attend CBC Bonham?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As long as space is available, and the person can handle the physical rigor of a tour of this nature, all are welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;can-i-bring-my-kids&#34;&gt;Can I bring my kids?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jr. High or High School kids are more than welcome to participate. Experiencing Israel as a child along with your family is a blessing that will abide in their reading of the Bible forever, and there is no more amazing location to create lifelong family memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the academic nature of this trip, homeschool academic credit may be available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Itinerary</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/itinerary/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/itinerary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Itinerary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Israeli Tour Busses&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /tour/israel2023/itinerary/images/tourbus_hu28b1fe5bda64b5bd7426461f69ed980b_35073_7d3119d859890d0957520b7c457c93d9.webp 400w,
               /tour/israel2023/itinerary/images/tourbus_hu28b1fe5bda64b5bd7426461f69ed980b_35073_79a29471d49b87694804cf99f7c79f02.webp 760w,
               /tour/israel2023/itinerary/images/tourbus_hu28b1fe5bda64b5bd7426461f69ed980b_35073_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/itinerary/images/tourbus_hu28b1fe5bda64b5bd7426461f69ed980b_35073_7d3119d859890d0957520b7c457c93d9.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;580&#34;
               height=&#34;254&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note we may add or rearrange the daily itinerary to maximize our experience in the Holy Land so that it as fascinating, thought-provoking, and extraordinary as possible. We can&amp;rsquo;t stress enough to be flexible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed Itinerary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hotels&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TBD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Depart DFW overnight flight to TLV Ben Gurion Airport&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Night on Plane&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Arrival in Tel Aviv late afternoon, transfer to hotel; introductory meeting&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tel Aviv/Netanya&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Caesarea Maritima, Mt. Carmel, Megiddo, Nazareth Village&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Galilee&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tel Dan (border tour?), Caesarea Philippi, Mt. Bental, eastern shore (Kursi/pigs, Bethsaida?)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Galilee&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sea of Galilee sites: Daniel Carmel Boat, Capernaum, Mt. of Beatitudes, Tabgha; Baptism/Rededication (Yardenit or Sea of Galilee)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Galilee&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tel Jezreel/Harod Springs, Beit Shean, Jericho, Dead Sea float&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dead sea&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ein Gedi, Masada, Old Jericho Road, Mt of Olives overlook&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jerusalem&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Knesset Menorrah, Bible Lands Museum or Israel Museum  Yad Vashem (Holocaust Museum)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jerusalem&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Elah Valley, Tel Azeka, Tel Beth Shemesh, Bethlehem overlook&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jerusalem&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jerusalem Jewish sites: Temple Mount City of David (Jeremiah&amp;rsquo;s Cistern, Hezekiah&amp;rsquo;s Tunnel, Pool of Siloam), Southern Steps, Jewish Quarter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jerusalem&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Day 10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jerusalem Christian sites: Mount of Olives, Palm Sunday Road, Garden of Gethsemane, Stations of the Cross, Church of the Holy Sepulcher, Pools of Bethesda, Mt. Zion, Caiaphas&#39; House, Garden Tomb Farewell dinner Bus to the airport for late evening departure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Night on Plane&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Days 11+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;For anyone interested, Sarah and I are planning to stay for a few days in Jerusalem. We will be in the city on our own and see some extra sights/activities not included in the main tour.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The cost of lodging, food, and activities will be &amp;ldquo;pay as you go.&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.abrahamhostels.com/jerusalem/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Abraham&amp;rsquo;s Hostel&lt;/a&gt; is an inexpensive yet fun hostel in the center of West Jerusalem.  The hostel also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.abrahamtours.com/theme/tours-from-jerusalem/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;offers tours&lt;/a&gt; to places like Bethlehem, Hebron, and other &amp;ldquo;west bank&amp;rdquo; sites, as well as &amp;ldquo;dual narrative&amp;rdquo; (Jewish/Muslim) tours of Jerusalem. The airport is a 20-minute train ride. Trains run until midnight except on Shabbat.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Passports, Customs, and Airport Security</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/passport/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/passport/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crossing a frontier can be an intimidating experience. Security, government, and airline officials speak English and are interested in moving things along, but there may be officials who were born to be suspicious, or who revel in their authority to search you or in their power to deny you entry to their country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, security reigns supreme in a country that can’t have it otherwise. The young men and women asking questions are usually polite, but they take their job very seriously – and passengers should be glad they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottom line: Be patient, expect questions, answer frankly, don&amp;rsquo;t volunteer information unless asked, don’t get uptight or confrontational. They’ve got time; you’ve got a country to see. In short, make it easy for yourself by making it easier for them. If they seem to be getting irritated with you, you keep your cool and keep smiling.  They are just doing their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t worry about memorizing all of these details, and there is no need to print this page (it is better if you didn&amp;rsquo;t).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will review the details once more immediately before we leave.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;passports&#34;&gt;Passports&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All travelers including minors must have a valid passport - valid at least six months AFTER the date you exit Israel
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In other words, if your passport expires on/before 11/15/2023, you MUST get it renewed before you leave home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, you will need your valid passport# and expiration date at the time you book your travel -&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information on &lt;a href=&#34;https://travel.state.gov/content/travel/en/passports/how-apply.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;obtaining a passport is here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you need to renew, do yourself a favor and &lt;a href=&#34;https://travel.state.gov/content/passports/en/passports/renew.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RENEW IT NOW!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No additional paperwork (e.g. visas) or shots are required for US citizens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are not a US citizen, please let Chris know and we can discuss specific requirements for your country&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before leaving home, make &lt;strong&gt;two&lt;/strong&gt; copies of the information page - leave one with someone you could easily contact while you are on your trip and put the other one in your suitcase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While in transit, &lt;strong&gt;keep your passport on your person at all times.&lt;/strong&gt;  You will need to produce it at all airports.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never pack your original passport in your suitcase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not stick it in the seat pocket in front of you (it&amp;rsquo;s too easy to leave behind)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A backpack is fine; just make sure it can&amp;rsquo;t fall out accidentally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neck pouches or waist belts are options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;secondary-security-screening-before-leaving-the-us&#34;&gt;Secondary Security Screening Before Leaving the Us&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will go through the usual TSA screening that all passengers have to do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is different is that before the direct flight to TLV there will usually be a &lt;em&gt;secondary&lt;/em&gt; security screening at the GATE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is almost EXACTLY like the airport security when you first departed from your home airport – coats off, shoes off, laptops out, etc.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ASK if you can bring unopened bottled water. This seems to vary from place to place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These checkpoints generally open two hours before takeoff
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not as bad as it seems - flights sometimes start boarding an hour &lt;em&gt;or more&lt;/em&gt; before departure time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are NO FOOD OR RESTROOMS on the other side of the checkpoint - if you leave the area you will need to be rescreened again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will need to show your Passport here, and then again when you board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;arriving-in-israel&#34;&gt;Arriving In Israel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before You Leave Your Seat:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have your Passport? Phone? Wallet? Camera? Glasses? Name Badge?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no other way to say this - you are likely to be &amp;ldquo;out of it&amp;rdquo; after the long flight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look around between seats, under the seat in front of you as well as under your own seat, etc; be eyes for others in our group as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you are now wearing your Name Badge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soak in the fact that you are now in a very special Land that God calls His own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;israeli-passport-control&#34;&gt;Israeli Passport Control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the level of tension in the region, it will be no surprise that security at Israel’s airports is stringent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As you walk through the terminal you will eventually come to passport control - get in the lines for non-Israeli citizens and have your passport ready&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Between the fatigue, slow-moving lines, and &amp;ldquo;guilty until proven innocent&amp;rdquo; stance from the guards, &lt;strong&gt;Passport Control can truly test a believer&amp;rsquo;s witness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be repeated questions about what you intend to do while in Israel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t know something just say, &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; (the name or address of someone in Israel, for example), and let them ask a follow-up question.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they ask where you are going, an acceptable first answer is that we are going primarily to Galilee and Jerusalem with our tour group
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t give them a day-by-day activity list. Let them follow up with questions if they need more specifics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The type of tour we are doing is probably the most common tour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone on our tour should be wearing their name badge, which may make it easier for the officers to determine who is with whom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes they may act like you&amp;rsquo;re in trouble when you really are not.  They do this to see how you respond. It&amp;rsquo;s OK!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will have our guide&amp;rsquo;s cell and contact information on the formal itinerary.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are stopped for questioning having this type of information can help, but again, it is not necessary to volunteer the itinerary unless they ask for it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be aware that passengers who have recently visited Arabic countries OR who are of Arab or Indian descent, or have an Arabic or Indian name, or in any other way arouse suspicion for any reason, may be subject to further questioning (including email and social media accounts)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are detained please kindly request that you be allowed to notify one of our leaders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once cleared, you will be given a paper receipt which is your 90-day entry visa (Israel does not stamp passports). &lt;strong&gt;Do not lose this.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Answer their questions and do not chat, make jokes, or volunteer information unless you are asked for it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MILLIONS of Americans come and go each year without incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With any luck, we&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;em&gt;over&lt;/em&gt;prepped you and you&amp;rsquo;ll sail through wondering what all the fuss was about!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;israeli-customs&#34;&gt;Israeli Customs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After the Passport Control process is concluded, walk around behind the kiosk and enter the huge baggage claim hall where you will pick up your bags.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure those traveling with you stay together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grab your bag and head through the green &amp;ldquo;nothing to declare&amp;rdquo; sign (unless of course, you have something to declare) - you likely will not be stopped here&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Representatives from our group will be in the waiting area and will be identifiable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You made it to the Promised Land! We&amp;rsquo;re going to have an amazing trip!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;departing-israel&#34;&gt;Departing Israel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Our guides will walk us through all of this again on the day of departure.  Feel free to ask any questions at any time.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After several amazing days it will sadly be time to head back home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certain larger purchases are eligible for Value Added Tax refund.  When you make such a purchase, the vendor may provide you with a form, or you can get one at the airport.  &lt;strong&gt;Complete and drop off any VAT forms before going through security&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep your passport accessible at all times. Just about everyone in the airport will want to see it at some point (at least that&amp;rsquo;s how it feels).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1st Stage-Baggage Screening and interview&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My personal experience is that these guards are always incredibly friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They want you to be relaxed; just follow the same advice as on entry: be honest but not overly chatty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Typical first questions are, “&lt;strong&gt;Did you pack your bag yourself?&lt;/strong&gt;” and “&lt;strong&gt;Where was it after you packed it?&lt;/strong&gt;” (was it standing for an hour in a hotel corridor, for instance, where someone could have tampered with it? In our case, the likely answer will be that our bags were on the bus in a locked compartment.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another question is likely to be, &lt;strong&gt;“Did anyone give you something to take with you?”&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While your mind may immediately go to something illicit and tempt you to answer &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo;, the &lt;strong&gt;answer to this question is almost always &amp;ldquo;yes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our guide may give us items such as maps, or olive wood communion cups as souvenirs. These count.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t let them find it on their own and then ask you why you didn’t mention it in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They may pull different members of our group (including husbands and wives) out of the queue for questioning. Don&amp;rsquo;t be alarmed. This is routine. They will then compare answers.  Since we were all at the same places doing the same things, there shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be any problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next step is a large scanner for your check-through luggage.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow instructions to load your bags&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait for the bags on the other side of the machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The checker on his/her monitor either clears a particular bag by putting a bar-coded paper strip on it, or sends you to another station a few steps away if there is some unidentifiable item or container that requires opening the bag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s on a bag-by-bag not passenger-by-passenger basis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This part is not too unlike TSA screening - if they can&amp;rsquo;t figure out what something is they will do a manual inspection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your bag is pulled, it&amp;rsquo;s not a big deal (unless you have something to hid, which you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t!). Don&amp;rsquo;t get alarmed (and definitely don&amp;rsquo;t get defensive or irritated!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2nd Stage&lt;/strong&gt; - Airline Check in; keep your passport out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3rd Stage&lt;/strong&gt; - usual passenger screening/carry on security and passport control exit.  If you&amp;rsquo;ve made it this far, there is unlikely to be any drama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if all went smoothly we may have an hour or two to chill in the beautiful terminal before boarding. Savor your memories!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;united-stated-re-entry&#34;&gt;United Stated Re-entry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who have never done it, returning into the USA is almost always a non-event for US citizens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check your app store for &amp;ldquo;Mobile Passport Control&amp;rdquo;, which advertises seamless reentry into the US  &lt;strong&gt;you will want to download this before you get on the plane in Israel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be given a customs and border form to complete; again keep this with your passport or they may direct you to use the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re using the app, answer the prompts and you should get a QR code to eventually show to an agent or a machine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who don&amp;rsquo;t want to use the app, there might RFID/biometric machines available to further expedite&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If not, queue up and wait your turn for a US immigration agent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are connecting within another airport in the US you will, go through the process above, then you will have to get your checked bags, clear customs and then re-check for the connecting flight to Dallas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The exact process will depend on your connecting airport and airline - some make it easier than others&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After you check in, the remainder of the process will be the same as if you were on a domestic flight&amp;hellip;because you are on a domestic flight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    If you are connecting to a US-bound flight from an airport outside the US, you likely will not have to go through passport control or customs in the connecting country, but you may have to rescreen for security.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for Reducing Jetlag</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/flight-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/flight-tips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be prepared for a very long flight&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Except for flights to China, American Airlines&#39; proposed nonstop from DFW to TLV would be the carrier&amp;rsquo;s longest route out of DFW: 14:30 flying time; 6,982 nautical miles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If connecting from an east coast city, expect at least a 10 hour flight&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;general&#34;&gt;General&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good article here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifehacker.com/how-to-survive-a-long-haul-flight-with-finesse-1551468782&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How to make the best of a long-haul flight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    The #1 tip for acclimating to a new time zone is to be outside as much as possible.  Your internal clock will naturally sync up with the sun.  Really!
Conversely, the receptors in your skin react to artificial light the same way, especially blue light from screens.  This light tells your body you should be awake.  Don&amp;rsquo;t just wear eye shades, but cover up as much exposed skin as possible.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-to-bring-for-the-flight&#34;&gt;What to bring for the flight:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleep Aid:&lt;/strong&gt; We recommend that you consult your physician for possible sleep aids. Herbal remedies are also recommended. If this is you, you may wish to time when you take it so you aren’t groggy through dinner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neck Pillow&lt;/strong&gt;: This allows you to sleep sitting up without hurting your neck. The kind that blow up or wrap around your neck will take much less room in your carry-on bag. There &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/i8Dpfg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;are all kinds of different styles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleeping Shades:&lt;/strong&gt; Cloth eye covers that block light are essential.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ear Plugs:&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever sat next to a screaming baby on a flight? Noise-canceling head phones are also a great item when traveling.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can even get eyeshades have earphones built-in.  Who knew?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blankets&lt;/strong&gt;: If you do not like to use an airline blanket, you might want to purchase one that folds down to nothing so as not to take space in your carry-on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toothbrush/toothpaste/washcloth&lt;/strong&gt; for the morning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comfortable Shoes&lt;/strong&gt;: Wear comfortable and loose shoes on the overseas flight. Your feet may retain fluids over the course of the flight but should return to normal after landing. Some prefer sandals, however, your feet can get cold so be sure to have some socks available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Therapeutic Socks:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be sitting a long time. Deep Venous Thrombosis (DVT) is a real concern for any flight over 4 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are prone to leg edema you should purchase therapeutic socks and wear them for the duration of the flight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you know you are at risk, talk with your doctor to learn more about how to prevent blood clots,
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FYI - someone on one of our trips had never had an issue with leg edema&amp;hellip;until OUR trip. Therapeutic socks are inexpensive - better safe than sorry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everyone&lt;/strong&gt; consider doing leg stretches periodically while in your seat and getting up and stretching every so often (when permitted). As with domestic flights do not congregate in the galley or lavatory areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sleep-tips-for-the-overnight-flight&#34;&gt;Sleep Tips for the overnight flight&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assuming you can&amp;rsquo;t get upgraded to the &amp;ldquo;Flagship Business Class&amp;rdquo; with the sweet lie-flat seats, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably be stuck in a standard coach class seat.  If you have room and are on a plane that has two aisles, try to grab a seat in the middle section - it will be slightly quieter and darker than the seats by the windows.  If you&amp;rsquo;re a heavier sleeper, a window seat will help keep your head propped up.  Everything&amp;rsquo;s a trade off!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are assigned an aisle seat and want the best chance for uninterrupted sleep, see if you can trade for an interior seat to reduce your chances of being woken up. Conversely, if you say, &amp;ldquo;I have a small bladder and will be up a lot&amp;rdquo; it might score you an aisle seat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many people believe the less you eat, the better you sleep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Others suggest the following regimen as soon as you get to your seat:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kick off your shoes (or just wear flip flops so your feet can breathe)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a sleeping pill (or two) if it&amp;rsquo;s medically appropriate for you around 8:00 or 9:00pm Dallas time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On a flight that leaves from the east coast, they will serve dinner about an hour into the flight (non-stops from DFW will probably be a little later) - go ahead and eat but avoid soda, alcohol, and foods that are gas-inducing (beans, cabbage, onions, cucumber, anything greasy) - the portions are usually small enough that you&amp;rsquo;d be hard-pressed to feel &amp;ldquo;stuffed&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After dinner, throw on the eye shades, ear plugs (or noise-canceling headphones), get your head as comfortable as possible and try to sleep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to avoid the in-seat movies or other electronic screens- the blue light from the screen may interfere with sleep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you absolutely can&amp;rsquo;t sleep, please don&amp;rsquo;t be &amp;ldquo;that person&amp;rdquo; who leaves their reading light on the entire flight! Bring eye shades in case you are seated near &amp;ldquo;that person&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the means and wish to upgrade to premium economy or business class, go for it!
The rest of us may be jealous, but we would do the same thing if we could!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;approaching-ben-gurion&#34;&gt;Approaching Ben Gurion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As soon as you wake up (or after about every three hours if you absolutely can&amp;rsquo;t sleep), head to the bathroom to stretch (isometric and light calisthenics) and down a glass or two of water and try to sleep again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drinking lots of water (as much as 5 16.9 oz bottles!) is recommended -&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes if you drink water, you will have to get up and go to the lavatory, but that movement is also a good thing to help you with jet lag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They will likely serve a light breakfast about two hours prior to landing - you&amp;rsquo;ll know it&amp;rsquo;s coming when they flip all the lights back on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t want too long to use the bathroom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depending on the flight path, a window seat on the &amp;ldquo;A&amp;rdquo; side could get a good view of the New Testament lands of Greece, Crete, Cyprus, and Turkey as we approach Israel in the mid-afternoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At some point during the flight you will be asked to complete an Immigration entry form (the US will require this too on the return flight). Fill it out completely and hold onto it until you get to &lt;a href=&#34;../passport&#34;&gt;Passport control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;landing-at-ben-gurion&#34;&gt;Landing at Ben Gurion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how much you slept, you are likely to be at least a little &amp;ldquo;out of it&amp;rdquo; after the long flight&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before You Leave Your Seat:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have your Passport? Phone? Wallet? Camera? Glasses? Name Badge?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look around between seats, under the seat in front of you as well as under your own seat, etc; be eyes for others in our group as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you are now wearing your Name Badge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soak in the fact that you are now in a very special Land that God calls His own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;../passport&#34;&gt;separate section on Israeli Airport Security&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;returning-to-usa&#34;&gt;Returning to USA&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sleeping on the way home can sometimes be less of a challenge because our flight will usually leave very shortly after midnight local time.  Since we will have been on the go for most of the day, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably be tired. Follow the same advice above for sleeping and avoiding jet leg once back in Texas. Get lots of that Texas sunshine!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clothing</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/clothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/clothing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comfort before fashion is the key to touring in Israel. Casual, travel-ready clothing is all you will need with a few specific guidelines (see &amp;ldquo;Holy sites&amp;rdquo; below). The weather in late spring will be warm, like Texas. You will want to pack lightly, wrinkle-free, and be ready to rewear outfits. Simplicity is the key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-can-you-bring&#34;&gt;What CAN you bring?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One checked bag up to 50 lbs, MAX (airline restriction), plus one personal carry-on, such as a backpack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-should-you-bring&#34;&gt;What SHOULD you bring?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; stuff a suitcase full of clothes doesn’t mean you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Less is more&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The simpler you can make your life on the road, the more time you will have for HIM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More options = more complexity - the more outfits you bring, the more time you will spend digging through your suitcase or closet choosing what to wear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For our type of tour, if your clothes for two weeks in Israel can&amp;rsquo;t fit in a 21&amp;quot; roll-aboard, you&amp;rsquo;ve overpacked.
&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note - Whatever size suitcase you bring, allow extra room to bring back items purchased while in Israel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;general-think-function-over-fashion&#34;&gt;General: think function over fashion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lightweight and wrinkle-free&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally SPF and moisture-wicking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Columbia (outlet store in Allen), REI (store in Plano), Magellan, North Face, Outdoor Research, LL Bean, and other &amp;ldquo;outdoorsy&amp;rdquo; stores have practical travel clothes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Function over fashion&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; - plan to wear and re-wear outfits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For dinners, you might consider bringing one &amp;ldquo;casual dressy&amp;rdquo; outfit - (something other than jeans) but this is your option. Wearing your touring clothes is just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO TIP: Do Laundry in hotel sinks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laundry availability is inconsistent. Bring powdered detergent, a 1-3/8&amp;quot; sink plug, a travel clothesline, and a few clothespins to wash/rinse your clothes in the hotel sink and leave them to dry the next day&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;footwear&#34;&gt;Footwear&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO TIP: Proper footwear is your #1 clothing priority&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short of forgetting or losing your passport, shoes need to be your #1 priority. They can make or break your trip. Blisters are no fun.  Break-in new shoes before arrival.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Links to examples are &lt;strong&gt;Bolded&lt;/strong&gt;, but we are not necessarily recommending these specific products)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/s?k=moisture&amp;#43;wicking&amp;#43;socks&amp;amp;crid=2VJTYNYFR9NSF&amp;amp;sprefix=moisture&amp;#43;wicking&amp;#43;socks%2Caps%2C526&amp;amp;ref=nb_sb_noss_2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moisture-wicking socks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are highly recommended. Recommend Smart Wool or something similar. Cotton is more susceptible to fostering blisters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoes should have solid ankle support – break in extremely well before arrival&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of folks love the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/gp/aw/s/ref=is_s?k=chaco&amp;#43;sandals&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chaco style&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; sandals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Otherwise good walking shoes or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss_2?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;amp;field-keywords=hiking&amp;#43;shoes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hiking shoes/sandals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water shoes are fine for Hezekiah&amp;rsquo;s tunnel or the dead sea but don&amp;rsquo;t use these for other walking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t recommend flip-flops for walking because of the chances of turning an ankle on uneven terrain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t forget sunscreen if the top of your foot is going to be exposed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sandals or other comfortable casual shoes for evenings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;shirts&#34;&gt;Shirts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss_1?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;amp;field-keywords=magellan&amp;#43;shirts&amp;amp;rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Amagellan&amp;#43;shirts&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lightweight, hiking/fishing, moisture-wicking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or knit shirts that dry quickly. You might want a long sleeve if you are sun-sensitive or prefer more coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women - as above or cotton or silk shirt or blouse (one that covers the shoulder down to the middle of your upper arm if you want to be good to go for Holy sites). Note - women and girls should not have exposed midriffs, bring tank tops, blouses with spaghetti straps, or short-shorts as they are too immodest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO TIP: Darker colors are best for photos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/28df0f7a78d822f7bfd69adda62b439d.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; &gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than the well-watered north, most of Israel&amp;rsquo;s terrain and buildings are this tan/sand color. Outdoor travel clothing also tends to be tan-colored. Notice how the dark colors stand out in this photo. Now, imagine if the man was also wearing a tan-colored shirt in addition to his tan pants. He would almost be invisible! Wear contrasting colors!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pantsskirtsshorts&#34;&gt;Pants/Skirts/shorts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lightweight fabric shorts which dry quickly (i.e. Nylon, hiking type)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skirts that cover the knees work as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given the time of year, long pants are likely to be uncomfortable. Suggest the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.columbia.com/search?q=convertible&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;convertible&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; variety for Holy sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modest swimming suit for the Dead Sea (and possible Baptism or other limited swimming opportunities).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;holy-site-special-requirements&#34;&gt;Holy Site Special Requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/a889d8572637de9949cda38927218467.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;30%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; &gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capernaum and a few sites in Jerusalem (including the Temple Mount, Western Wall, and Holy Sepulcher) have dress codes enforced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bare legs (knees and above) and shoulders are inappropriate
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For women, a mid-calf lightweight elastic waist skirt, lightweight jumper or large cotton scarf to wrap around shorts plus a scarf or shawl to quickly cover bare shoulders. Capri pants are fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pair of pants with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Columbia-Mens-Convertible-Pant-Small/dp/B0089PWWZO/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1494461753&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=columbia&amp;#43;pfg&amp;#43;convertible&amp;#43;pants&amp;#43;mens&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;zip on/off legs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; would be helpful for an easy transition when legs must be covered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guides will let us know in advance when a modest dress code is required&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hat&#34;&gt;Hat&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Columbia-Bora-Booney-Hats-Sage/dp/B0058YU1OI/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1494461519&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=columbia&amp;#43;hat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wide-brimmed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a must!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ballcaps do not cover the ears &amp;amp; neck; visors cover even less.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dehydration is more common if the head is uncovered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We strongly recommend a hat with a strap as it can get windy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Head must be COVERED at Western Wall and other Jewish holy sites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Head must be UNCOVERED for the Holy Sepulcher
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the Pope wears a Jewish kippah; go figure&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;jackets&#34;&gt;Jackets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like to wear a jacket or sweatshirt in Texas in late spring, then you might want to bring one to Israel. Other than the airplane trip, most of us will not need one! The chance of rain between May and September is statistically zero, but with God, we never say never! This is up to you. We might advise a travel windbreaker as opposed to a bulky sweatshirt or jacket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-clothing-items&#34;&gt;Other Clothing items&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Durable high-quality sunglasses are a must! You may want a neck cord.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Ergodyne-Chill-Its-6602-Evaporative-Cooling/dp/B001B5I57I/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1494462214&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=ergodyne&amp;#43;chill&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaporative Cooling Towel&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(a&lt;/strong&gt; popular brand is Ergodyne) is becoming popular for participants to bring - even more practical is the &amp;ldquo;Buff&amp;rdquo; (like on Survivor) that convert from a neck-wrap to a beanie (you can also use it as a mask if Covid breaks out again)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are prone to calf swelling on a long flight, or if you think you might be prone, recommend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Kendall-T-E-D-Length-Embolism-Stockings/dp/B0015TGAVS/ref=sr_1_2_a_it?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1494462441&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=ted&amp;#43;hose&amp;#43;compression&amp;#43;stockings&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;compression stockings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the flight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h3 id=&#34;clothing-not-to-bring&#34;&gt;Clothing NOT to bring&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excessive pairs of &lt;strong&gt;anything&lt;/strong&gt; (shoes, shorts, underwear) - just bring 2 or 3 outfits and wear them over and over again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clothing that is prone to wrinkling (unless you like that look)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember simplicity is the key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; bring an outfit that requires ironing, but then you&amp;rsquo;d have to bring a travel iron (irons are not standard in Israeli hotels), then you&amp;rsquo;d spend time ironing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is better to just bring wrinkle-free travel clothes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things that will not dry overnight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clothing with American, political, or Christian symbols/slogans is highly discouraged.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are not being ashamed or unpatriotic - you are loving your neighbors and being a gracious and polite guest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This type of shirt is definitely a no-go! The Crusades are still a sore subject with Muslims and Jews (ask me why sometimes)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/18f5a4b4bca68c715c291997b549134b.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phones, Cameras, Electronics</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/electronics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/electronics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We encourage you to bring and use devices only to supplement your Holy Land experience. Otherwise try to &amp;ldquo;unplug&amp;rdquo; from daily life as much as possible. Make arrangements with work and other obligations to have them leave you alone and for you to be disconnected as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cell-phoneswi-fi&#34;&gt;Cell Phones/Wi-Fi&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will find using a US-based cellular voice/data service on a network in Israel will be expensive, but you have options.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wi-Fi is everywhere, including on the buses. Consider using Wi-Fi for voice/messaging.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your phone should have the ability to shut off cellular data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note that “SMS” messages are still sent using cellular data (so if your cellular data is off, you may not receive them).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are lots of messaging, audio, and video chat apps available for both Apple and Android that work over Wi-Fi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your carrier may offer a short-term international plan for cellular voice and/or data.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure it covers Israel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your company can’t be without you, see if they will pay for the international plan (mine did!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can bring an unlocked phone and buy a pre-paid SIM card once in Israel.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About 10 years ago, this was the way to go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nowadays, WiFi is everywhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You could tell folks back home that you’ll be unavailable!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protip&lt;/strong&gt;: Want to cut down on work voicemail when you return?  Include the following on your outgoing announcement:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain that you are out of the office until whichever date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State that you will NOT be checking voicemail while you are away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide information of someone to contact if they need something that can&amp;rsquo;t wait until you return
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of course that person and your boss should be able to reach you in a crisis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Otherwise, ask them to call back after you return&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And do not say &amp;ldquo;messages will be returned when I get back&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most people will want to respect your personal time and it&amp;rsquo;s often a &amp;ldquo;pride thing&amp;rdquo; that tells us our company won&amp;rsquo;t survive without us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cellphone etiquette&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please do not make or take calls during teachings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you MUST take a call while we are touring, please respect the “space” of those around you so everyone will have a great trip!
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The person next to you might be interested in your conversation but the person in front of you probably is not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your guides (and leaders) may frequently be on the phone coordinating logistics for our group, but they are “on the clock.” You are on vacation!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cameras&#34;&gt;Cameras&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of your cell phone as a swiss army knife; one tool with many uses.  Most cell phones have excellent cameras. Consider leaving the big DLSR at home!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for any opportunity to have one less thing to be a distraction, one less thing to carry around, one less thing to have to charge, one less thing to potentially leave behind somewhere (etc.)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m speaking from personal experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you have enough storage on your phone and a way to offload photos if you happen to run low on space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We typically have long days, so you may consider bringing a lightweight portable charger you can keep with you while touring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are bringing a separate camera, be sure to have sufficient batteries and memory sticks (unless you are bringing a computer to download photos on).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are bringing rechargeable batteries, consider bringing two sets; one to be left in the hotel room charging, the other out and about with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GoPros are great, but battery life is notoriously terrible (the older the model, the worse the battery life)! Plan accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    See our separate pages on &lt;a href=&#34;../photo-tips&#34;&gt;photography tips&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;convertersadapters&#34;&gt;Converters/Adapters:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electricity in Israel is 220v 50hz and their plugs are also configured differently than ours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will need an &lt;strong&gt;adapter&lt;/strong&gt; in order to plug in anything that needs recharging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most modern electronic devices smartphones, cameras, laptops) automatically convert the voltage so a separate converter generally isn’t needed.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check your power supply for the input voltage range. If it says something like 110-250v, all you need is an adapter for the plug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it only says 110v you will need a &lt;strong&gt;converter&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Never plug your 110V appliance into a 220v outlet using only an adapter.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cautions
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beware of cheap, poor-quality adapters. Price them on Amazon or wherever, and don’t buy the cheapest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always make sure your devices are charging before going to bed or you may wake up in the morning and find your device has not charged.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;**TIP-**bring a regular US power strip in your suitcase, and get a good quality European/Israeli adapter. You’ll be able to plug your devices into the power strip and won’t need individual adapters for each plug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You likely will not need a hair dryer as the hotels and guest-houses should have them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TIP&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t bring anything that needs ironing and you won&amp;rsquo;t need to bring an iron!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Other packing considerations</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/other-items/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/other-items/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Other items to bring&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bible&lt;/strong&gt; (hard copy or electronic) -
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want a hardcopy, consider a slimline version for size and weight reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider your phone as a &amp;ldquo;Swiss Army Knife&amp;rdquo; - you may wish to leave your hardcopy books and your large cameras at home and just use your phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure your Bible app can be used without an internet connection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/xnztR7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passport&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; … Passport … &lt;a href=&#34;../passport&#34;&gt;Passport&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also keep other travel documents handy such as your final flight and ground itinerary (to be provided by tour guide)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A travel pouch for these documents (i.e. a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss_1?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;amp;field-keywords=neck&amp;#43;travel&amp;#43;pouch&amp;amp;rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Aneck&amp;#43;travel&amp;#43;pouch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;neck pouch)&lt;/a&gt; is a good idea - your passport should be on your person unless you are in your hotel room&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebook&lt;/strong&gt; for taking notes and journal recordings
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: many people return and wish they had taken better notes. We will be visiting a lot of sites and things will start to run together. Bring a journal!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alternatively you can use something like Evernote to store both text and a few photos of each site; you can also create a simple blog for free with &lt;a href=&#34;https://postach.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;postach.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pens&lt;/strong&gt; (a pen w/ grip is helpful as sweating makes it hard to hold)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some bring a hi-lighter to map the routes we take on a map&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backpack&lt;/strong&gt; or Fanny pack - for carrying camera, wallet, pen, journal
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pack it, you carry it - &amp;ldquo;less is more&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medications&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prescription&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-prescription may include head/muscle ache relief, Immodium-d (better to have it and not need it than to need it and not have it!), sleep-aid, vitamins, or supplements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you forget something, there are drug stores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If applicable, bring a record of any important medical allergies, medicines, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Powdered drink pouches you can mix with a bottle of water, such as for electrolyte replenishment (Gatorade etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protein snacks, such as individual nut bags; avoid chocolate as it melts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small and large ziplock bags for snacks, collectibles (write on the bag what it is and where found)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is against Israeli law to remove historical artifacts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inflatable pillow or neck rest for use on the plane, eye mask, ear plugs (see &lt;a href=&#34;../flight-tips&#34;&gt;Jetlag&lt;/a&gt; article)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small bag (like a mesh tie bag) for items you want to leave on the bus for the day. The driver will always stay with the bus, or it will be locked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packs of disposable cloths (Wet Ones) may come in handy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hand sanitizer, sanitizing wipes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aloe for sunburn and baby or talcum powder for heat rash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you struggle with any hip, knee, or ankle pain, you may want to consider purchasing collapsible &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/s?k=Trekking&amp;#43;poles&amp;#43;collapsing&amp;amp;ref=nb_sb_noss&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;trekking poles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For women, bring feminine hygiene products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are prone to chaffing, bring anti-chafe balm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunscreen (the sport kinds are best as they are generally sweat proof) &amp;amp; Chapstick w/ SPF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    If you are planning to roll aboard luggage and not check, you will have the same liquid quantity restrictions as we have for domestic travel
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-not-to-bring&#34;&gt;What not to bring&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Books, excessive photo/video gear, or anything that adds unnecessary weight, bulk, or complexity that will slow you down or distract you from meeting with Yeshua/Jesus
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just use your phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/covid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As of March 1, 2022 our understanding is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Covid vaccinations are no longer required for entry to Israel, or for US citizens returning
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In fact, Israel&amp;rsquo;s lifting of the vaccine requirement was the signal God used to tell us it was time to go!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As of now, masks remain required on all flights and, in Israel, in indoor public spaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A negative PCR test is required (&amp;ldquo;regardless of age or vaccination status&amp;rdquo;) to enter both countries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will pray these remaining restrictions are relaxed between now and the time we travel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course all of this information is subject to change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For better, if the pandemic is declared resolved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For worse, if COVID resurfaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will keep this page updated should requirements change.  A change for the worse, could mean we need to postpone our trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please make sure your trip cancellation insurance includes global health-related reasons, including your being unwilling/unable to comply with government COVID requirements that may be in place on the date of our departure.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
