<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Revelation Appendices, Extras, and Study Aids | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Revelation Appendices, Extras, and Study Aids</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu9bdc4cc28a100eaa5c154301214e2807_480992_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Revelation Appendices, Extras, and Study Aids</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Testament References and Allusions in Revelation 1-3</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/old-testament-allusions-in-revelation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/old-testament-allusions-in-revelation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 12,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;There is approximately a 2:1 ratio of Old Testament allusions (404 verses in Revelation and over 800 allusions).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also several other Old and New Testament cross-references.  While John was certainly familiar with the other Gospels and perhaps some of Paul&amp;rsquo;s writings, keep in mind there was not a &amp;ldquo;New Testament&amp;rdquo; as we think of it when John received the Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;chap-1-3&#34;&gt;Chap 1-3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:1 The revelation of Yeshua the Messiah, which God gave Him to show to His servants the things that must soon take place. He made it known by sending His angel to His servant John,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 2:28-29; Deut 15:16-17; Rev 1:4,9; Rev 21:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:2 who testified to the word of God and to the testimony of Yeshua the Messiah—to everything he saw.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:19; John 3:11; John 3:32-33; Acts 4:20; Acts 22:15; Acts 26:16; 1 John 1:1; 1 John 4:14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:3 How fortunate is the one who reads the words of this prophecy, and those who hear and keep what has been written in it—for the time is near.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 6:4; Mark 12:29; Rev 22:6,10,12,20; Rom 13:11; James 5:8,9; 1 Pet 4:7; 2 Pet 3:3-4,10; 1 Cor 10:11;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:4 John, To Messiah’s seven communities in Asia: Grace to you and shalom from Him who is and who was and who is to come, as well as from the seven spirits who are before His throne,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 11:2 Rev 3:1; Rev 4:5; Rev 5:6; Zec 3:9; Zec 4:10; Zec 6:5;  1 Cor 12:4-13;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:5 and from Messiah Yeshua, the faithful witness, the firstborn of the dead, and the ruler of the kings of the earth. To Him who loves us and has freed us from our sins by His blood&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 49:11; Ps 89:27 Rev 7:14; Zec 13:1; John 13:8-10; Acts 20:28; 1 Cor 6:11; Heb 9:14; 1 Pet 1:19; 1 John 1:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:6 and made us a kingdom, kohanim to His God and Father—to Him be glory and power forever! Amen!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 19:5-6; Isa 61:6 Rev 4:11; Rev 5:12-14; Psa 72:18,19; Dan 4:34; Mat 6:13; John 5:23; Phil 2:11; 1 Tim 6:16; Heb 13:21; 1 Pet 4:11; 1 Pet 5:11; 2 Pet 3:18; Jude 1:25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:7 “Look, He is coming with the clouds, and every eye shall see Him, even those who pierced Him. And all the tribes of the earth shall mourn because of Him. Yes, amen!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:13; Zech 12:10-14; Isa 52:8 Rev 18:20; Rev 19:1-3; Rev 22:20; Judg 5:31; Psa 68:1; Acts 1:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:8 “I am the Alpha and the Omega,” says Adonai Elohim, “Who is and who was and who is to come, the Almighty!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 41:4 Rev 4:8; Rev 11:17; Rev 16:14; Rev 19:15; Rev 21:22; Gen 17:1; Gen 28:3; Gen 35:11; Gen 43:14; Gen 48:3; Gen 49:25; Exo 6:3; Num 24:4; Isa 9:6; 2 Cor 6:18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:9 I, John, your brother and fellow partaker with you in the tribulation and kingdom and patient endurance that are in Yeshua, was on the island called Patmos because of the word of God and the testimony of Yeshua.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 10:2-4; Rev 1:2; Rev 6:9; Rev 11:7; Rev 12:11,17; Rev 19:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:10 I was in the Ruach on the Day of the Lord, and I heard behind me a loud voice like that of a trumpet,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 2:12, Joe 1:15, Oba 1:15, Mal 4:5-6 Rev 4:1; Rev 10:3-8; 2 Cor 12:2-3; Joel 1:15; 2:1-31; 3:14; Amos 5:18-20;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:11 saying, “Write what you see in a scroll, and send it to Messiah’s seven communities—to Ephesus and to Smyrna and to Pergamum and to Thyatira and to Sardis and to Philadelphia and to Laodicea.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 30:8; Jer 30:2; Hab 2:2 Col 4:15,16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:12 Then I turned to see the voice that was speaking to me. And when I turned, I saw seven golden menorot.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 25:37; Ex 37:23; Zec 4:2 Rev 1:13,20; Rev 2:1; Dan 7:9-14; Dan 10:5-10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:13 In the midst of the menorot, I saw One like a Son of Man, clothed in a robe down to His feet, with a golden belt wrapped around His chest.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 28:4, Dan 7:13; 10:5, 16 Rev 15:6; Exo 28:6-8; Exo 39:5; Lev 8:7; Isa 11:5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:14 His head and His hair were white like wool, white like snow, and His eyes like a flame of fire.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:9; 10:6; Mat 17:2 Rev 2:18; Rev 19:12;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:15 His feet were like polished bronze refined in a furnace, and His voice was like the roar of rushing waters.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 1:7, 24; Ezek 43:2; Dan 10:6; Rev 14:2; Rev 19:6; Psa 93:4; Isa 17:13;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:16 In His right hand He held seven stars, and out of His mouth came forth a sharp, two-edged sword. His face was like the sun shining at full strength.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Judges 5:31; Isa 49:2; Heb 4:12 Rev 10:1; Isa 24:23; Isa 60:19,20; Mal 4:2; Acts 26:13; Gen 1:4 (dividing light); John 3:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:17 When I saw Him, I fell at His feet like a dead man. But He placed His right hand on me, saying, “Do not be afraid! I am the First and the Last,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 41:4; 44:6; 48:12; Dan 8:17-18; 10:9, 10, 12, 15, 19 Rev 1:8,11; Rev 2:8; Rev 22:13; Isa 41:4; Isa 44:6; Isa 48:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:18 and the One who lives. I was dead, but look—I am alive forever and ever! Moreover, I hold the keys of death and Sheol.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 25:8; Hos 13:14 Rev 3:7; Rev 9:1; Rev 20:1,2,14; Psa 68:20; Isa 22:22; Mat 16:19; 1 Cor 15:54&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:19 Therefore write down what you have seen, what is, and what will happen after these things.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 30:8; Jer 30:2; Hab 2:2 Rev 4:1; Dan 10:14,19 (Dan 10:2-19 and Rev 1:9-19 have identical structures)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:20 As for the mystery of the seven stars that you saw in My right hand, and the seven golden menorot—the seven stars are the angels of Messiah’s seven communities, and the seven menorahs are the seven communities.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Zec 4:2;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:1 To the angel of Messiah’s community in Ephesus write: “Thus says the One who holds the seven stars in His right hand, the One who walks in the midst of the seven golden menorot:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:12,13; Eze 28:13,14; Mat 18:20; Mat 28:20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:2 I know all about your deeds and your toil and your patient endurance, and that you cannot bear those who are evil. You have tested those who call themselves emissaries and are not, and have found them to be liars.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2 Cor 11:13-15; 1 John 2:21,22; 1 John 4:1; Acts 20:27-31; Eph 4:14; Mat 7:23; 2 Cor 11:13-15; Mt 13:3-9; 18-23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:3 You have perseverance and have endured for My name’s sake, and you have not grown weary.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Luke 18:1; 2 Cor 4:1,16; Gal 6:9; 2 Thes 3:13; Heb 12:3-5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:4 “But this I have against you, that you have forsaken your first love.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 2:2 Rev 3:14-17; Jer 2:2-5; Mat 24:12,13; Phil 1:9; Phil 3:13-16; 1 Thes 4:9,10; 2 Thes 1:3; Heb 6:10,11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:5 Remember then from where you have fallen. Repent and do the deeds you did at first. If not, I will come to you and remove your menorah from its place—unless you repent.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:16; Rev 3:3; Mat 21:41-43; Mat 24:48-51; Mark 12:9; Luke 12:45,46; Luke 20:16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:6 “Yet you have this going for you, that you hate the deeds of the Nicolaitans, which I also hate.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:14,15; 2ch 19:2; Psa 26:5; Psa 101:3; Psa 139:21,22; 2 John 1:9,10; Acts 15:28-29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:7 He who has an ear, let him hear what the Ruach is saying to Messiah’s communities. To the one who overcomes, I will grant the right to eat from the Tree of Life, which is in the Paradise of God.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 2:9; 3:22-24; Prov 11:30; 13:12; Ezek 31:8 Luke 23:43; 2 Cor 12:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:8 To the angel of Messiah’s community in Smyrna write: “Thus says the First and Last, who was dead and came to life.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:8,11,17,18; Acts 19:10; Acts 20; Isa 41:4; Isa 44:6, Isa 48:12; Rev 22:13; Mt 2:11; Mar 15:23; John 19:39; Isa 60:6 (note no Myrrh)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:9 I know your tribulation and your poverty (yet you are rich), as well as the slander of those who say they are Jewish and are not, but are a synagogue of satan.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:9; James 1:2-3; John 8:44 (most of John 8 is Jesus&amp;rsquo; dialogue with those who say they are Jews but not acting like Jews); Leviticus 19:18; Romans 9-11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:10 Do not fear what you are about to suffer. Behold, the devil is about to throw some of you into prison, so that you may be tested, and you will have tribulation for ten days. Be faithful until death, and I will give you the crown of life.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:11; James 1:12; 1 Pet 5:4; 2 Ti 3:12; Phl 1:29 (see additional verses from Philippians in written commentary)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:11 He who has an ear, let him hear what the Ruach is saying to Messiah’s communities. The one who overcomes shall never be harmed by the second death.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:6,14; Rev 21:8; Mat 13:24-30 (second death)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:12 To the angel of Messiah’s community in Pergamum write: “Thus says the One who has the sharp two-edged sword:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 49:2 Rev 2:16; Rev 1:16; Rev 19:15,21; Isa 11:4; Heb 4:12; John 1:17; 2Th 2:8; 2 Tim 3:16-17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:13 I know where you live—where satan’s throne is. Yet you continue to hold firm to My name, and you did not deny your faith in Me even in the days of Antipas, My faithful witness, who was killed among you, where satan resides.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Acts 22:20; Luke 21:17; Jude 1:4; 2 Tim 2:12 (On Herod Antipas see Mar 6:22; Luke 13:31; Luke 23:11)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:14 “But I have a few things against you. You have some there who hold to the teaching of Balaam, who was teaching Balak to put a stumbling block before Bnei-Yisrael, to eat food sacrificed to idols and to commit sexual immorality.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Num 25:1-3 Rev 21:8; Rev 22:15; 1 Cor 5:1 (Chapter 5 is all about sexual immorality); 1 Cor 6:13-18; 1 Cor 7:2; Heb 13:4; Joshua 13:22; 2 Peter 2:15, 21; Read all of 2 Peter 2 and entire narrative of Balaam and Balak in Num 22-25, 31;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:15 Likewise you also have those who hold to the teaching of the Nicolaitans.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:16 Repent then! If not, I will come to you soon and make war against them with the sword of My mouth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:12; Rev 1:16; Rev 19:15,21; Isa 11:4; Isa 49:2; Eph 6:17; 2 Thes 2:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:17 He who has an ear, let him hear what the Ruach is saying to Messiah’s communities. To the one who overcomes I will give some of the hidden manna, and I will give him a white stone—and written on the stone a new name that no one knows except the one who receives it.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 16:31-35; Isa 62:2; 65:15 1 Cor 2:14; John 6:31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:18 To the angel of Messiah’s community in Thyatira write: “Thus says the Son of God, who has eyes like a flame of fire and feet like polished bronze:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 10:6 Rev 1:14,15; Ps 2:7; Mal 3:2-4; Mat 3:17; Mat 16:15-16; John 3:16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:19 I know your deeds and your love and faith and service and patient endurance, and that your last deeds are greater than the first.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:4; Job 17:9; Psa 92:14; Pro 4:18; John 15:2; 2 Pet 3:18; Gal 5:22-23; 1 Th 1:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:20 “But this I have against you, that you tolerate that woman Jezebel, who calls herself a prophetess—yet she is teaching and deceiving My servants to commit sexual immorality and to eat food sacrificed to idols.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 Kings 16:31-32; 2 Kings 9:7, 22 Rev 2:14; Exo 34:15; Num 25:1,2; Acts 15:20,29; 1 Cor 8:10-12; 1 Cor 10:18-21,28; Deu 13:1-5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:21 I gave her time to repent, but she refuses to repent of her immorality.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:20,21; Jer 8:4-6; Rom 2:4,5; Rom 9:22; 1 Pet 3:20; 2 Pet 3:9,15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:22 Behold, I will throw her into a sickbed, and those who commit adultery with her into great tribulation—unless they repent of her doings.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 36:3; Eze 18:30-32; Eze 33:11; Zeph 3:7; Luke 13:3,5; 2 Cor 12:21; 2 Tim 2:25,26; Rom 1:26; Deu 13:10-11; 1 Kings 18:40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:23 I will also strike her children with a deadly disease. Then all of Messiah’s communities will know that I am the One who searches minds and hearts, and I will give to each of you according to your deeds.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 7:9; 26:2; 28:4; Jer 11:20; 17:10 Rev 20:12; Psa 62:12; Isa 3:10,11; Mat 16:27; Rom 2:5-11; Rom 14:12; 2 Cor 5:10; Gal 6:5; 1 Pet 1:17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:24 “But to the rest of you in Thyatira, who do not hold to this teaching and have not learned the so-called ‘deep things’ of satan—I place on you no other burden.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Acts 15:28; 1 Cor 2:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:25 Only hold firm to what you have until I come.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:7; Rev 22:7,20; John 14:3; John 21:22,23; 1 Cor 4:5; 1 Cor 11:26; 2 Pet 3:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:26 To the one who overcomes and guards My deeds until the end, ‘I will give him authority over the nations&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:21; Rev 20:4; Rev 22:5; Psa 49:14; Dan 7:18,22,27; Mat 19:28; Luke 22:29,30; 1 Cor 6:3,4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:27 and he shall rule them with an iron rod, as when clay pots are broken into pieces.’&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 2:7-9; Isa 30:14; Jer 19:11 Mat 11:27; Luke 22:29; John 17:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:28 Even as I have received from My Father, so I will give him the morning star.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:16; Luke 1:78,79; 2 Pet 1:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:29 He who has an ear, let him hear what the Ruach is saying to Messiah’s communities.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:1 To the angel of Messiah’s community in Sardis write: “Thus says the One having the seven spirits of God and the seven stars: I know your deeds—you have a reputation for being alive, but you are dead.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 4:1 Luke 15:24,32; Eph 2:1,5; Col 2:13; 1 Tim 5:6; James 2:26; Jude 1:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:2 Wake up, and strengthen what remains that was about to die. For I have not found your deeds complete in the sight of My God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 King 11:4; 1 King 15:3; 2ch 25:2; Isa 57:12; Dan 5:27; Mat 6:2-4; Mat 23:5,28-38&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:3 So remember what you have received and heard—keep it, and repent. If you will not wake up, I will come like a thief, and you will not know at what hour I will come upon you.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mat 25:13; Mark 13:33,36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:4 “But still, you have a few people in Sardis who have not stained their clothes. They will walk with Me in white, because they are worthy.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eccles 9:8 Mat 10:11; Luke 20:35; Luke 21:36; 2 Thes 1:5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:5 The one who overcomes thus will be dressed in white clothes; I will never blot his name out of the Book of Life, and will confess his name before My Father and His angels.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 32:32-33 Mal 3:17; Mat 10:32; Luke 12:8; Jude 1:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:6 He who has an ear, let him hear what the Ruach is saying to Messiah’s communities.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:7 To the angel of Messiah’s community in Philadelphia write: “Thus says the Holy One, the True One, who has the key of David, who opens and no one will shut, and who shuts and no one opens:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 22:22 Rev 5:3-5,9; Job 11:10; Job 12:14; Mat 16:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:8 I know your deeds. Behold, I have set before you an open door that no one is able to shut—because you have little power, but you have kept My word and have not denied My name.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:13; Pro 30:9; Mat 26:70-72; Luke 12:9; Acts 3:13,14; 1 Tim 5:8; 1 John 2:22,23; Jude 1:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:9 Behold, I will cause those of the synagogue of satan—who say they are Jewish and are not, but lie—behold, I will cause them to come and bow down before your feet, so that they acknowledge that I have loved you!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 43:4; 49:23; 60:14 Exo 11:8; Exo 12:30-32; 1 Sam 2:36; es 8:17; Job 42:8-10; Isa 49:23; Isa 60:14; Zec 8:20-23; Acts 16:37-39&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:10 “Because you have kept My word about patient endurance, I will also keep you from the hour of trial that is coming upon the whole world to test those who dwell on the earth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 24:17; Dan 12:10; Zec 13:9; James 3:12; 1 Pet 4:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:11 I am coming soon—hold on to what you have, so that no one will take away your crown.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:10; Rev 4:4,10; 1 Cor 9:25; 2 Tim 2:5; 2 Tim 4:8; James 1:12; 1 Pet 5:3,4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:12 The one who overcomes, I will make him a pillar in the Temple of My God, and he will never leave it. And on him I will write the name of My God and the name of the city of My God—the New Jerusalem, which comes down out of heaven from My God—and My own new Name.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 62:2; Ezek 48:35 Rev 22:4; Isa 65:15; Eph 3:15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:13 He who has an ear, let him hear what the Ruach is saying to Messiah’s communities.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:14 To the angel of Messiah’s community in Laodicea write: “Thus says the Amen, the Faithful and True Witness, the Originator of God’s creation:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 49:3; Deut 21:17 Col 1:15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:15 I know your deeds, that you are neither cold nor hot. Oh, that you were either cold or hot!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Josh 24:15-24; 1 King 18:21; Pro 23:26; ho 7:8; ho 10:2; Zeph 1:5,6; Mat 6:24; Mat 10:37; Luke 14:27,28; 1 Cor 16:22; James 1:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:16 So because you are lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I am about to spew you out of My mouth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:5; Jer 14:19; Jer 15:1-4; Zec 11:8,9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:17 For you say, ‘I am rich, I have made myself wealthy, and I need nothing.’ But you do not know that you are miserable and pitiable and poor and blind and naked.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:15; Gen 3:7,10,11; Exo 32:35&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:18 I advise you to buy from Me gold refined by fire so that you may be rich, and white clothes so that you may dress yourself and so the shame of your nakedness will not be revealed, and eye salve to anoint your eyes so that you may see.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 55:1; John 9:6-11; 1 John 2:20-27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:19 Those whom I love, I rebuke and discipline. Therefore, be zealous and repent.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Prov 3:12 Rev 2:5,21,22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:20 Behold, I stand at the door and knock. If anyone hears My voice and opens the door, I will come in to him and will dine with him, and he with Me.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:9; Luke 12:37; Luke 17:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:21 To the one who overcomes I will grant the right to sit with Me on My throne, just as I myself overcame and sat down with My Father on His throne.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:6-8; Rev 7:17; Dan 7:13,14; Mat 28:18; John 5:22,23; Eph 1:20-23; Phil 2:9-21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:22 He who has an ear, let him hear what the Ruach is saying to Messiah’s communities.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:6,13; Rev 2:7,11,17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;List adapted from Chuck Missler, &lt;em&gt;Cosmic Codes: Hidden Messages From The Edge Of Eternity&lt;/em&gt; (Koinonia House, 2013) Appendix C.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Testament References and Allusions in Revelation 4-8</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/ref4-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/ref4-8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 12,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h3 id=&#34;chap-4-8&#34;&gt;Chap 4-8&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Rev (TLV)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:1 After these things I looked, and behold, a door was standing open in heaven. And the first voice, which I had heard speaking with me like a trumpet, said, “Come up here, and I will show you what must take place after these things.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 26:20; Ezek 1:1 Rev 1:19; Rev 22:6; John 16:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:2 Immediately I was in the Ruach; and behold, a throne was standing in heaven, and One seated on the throne.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 6:1; Ezek 1:26-28;Dan 7:9 Rev 4:9; Rev 3:21; Rev 5:1,6,7,13; Rev 6:16; Rev 7:9-17; Rev 12:5; Rev 19:4; Rev 21:5; Rev 22:1-3; Isa 6:1; Dan 7:9; Heb 8:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:3 And the One who was seated was like jasper and carnelian in appearance, and a rainbow around the throne, like an emerald in appearance.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 1:26, 28; 10:1 Rev 21:19; Exo 28:18; Exo 39:11; Eze 28:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:4 Around the throne were twenty-four thrones, and seated on the thrones were twenty-four elders dressed in white clothes with golden crowns on their heads.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 Chron 24:5 Rev 2:10; Rev 9:7; es 8:15; Psa 21:3; 2 Tim 4:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:5 And out from the throne come flashes of lightning and rumblings and clashes of thunder—and seven torches of fire burning before the throne, which are the seven spirits of God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 19:16; 25:37; Isa 11:2; Ezek 1:13 Rev 1:4; Rev 3:1; Rev 5:6; Mat 3:11; Acts 2:3; 1 Cor 12:4-11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:6 And before the throne was something like a sea of glass, like crystal. In the middle of the throne and around it were four living creatures, full of eyes in front and behind.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 1:5, 18, 22, 26;10:1, 12 Rev 4:8; Eze 1:18; Eze 10:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:7 The first living creature was like a lion, the second living creature was like an ox, the third living creature had a face like a man, and the fourth living creature was like a flying eagle.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 1:10; 10:14 Deut 28:49; 2 Sam 1:23; Isa 40:31; Eze 1:8,10; Eze 10:14; Dan 7:4; ob 1:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:8 The four living creatures, each having six wings, were full of eyes all around and within. They do not rest day or night, chanting, “Kadosh, kadosh, kadosh Adonai Elohei-Tzva’ot, asher haya v’hoveh v’yavo! Holy, holy, holy is the Lord God of Hosts, who was and who is and who is to come!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 6:2-3; Ezek 1:18; 10:12, 14 Rev 4:4; Heb 13:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:9 And whenever the living creatures give glory and honor and thanks to the One seated on the throne, who lives forever and ever,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 32:40; Dan 4:34; 6:26; 12:7 Rev 1:18; Rev 5:14; Rev 10:6; Rev 15:7; Exo 15:18; Psa 48:14; Heb 7:8,25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:10 the twenty-four elders fall down before the One seated on the throne and worship Him who lives forever and ever. And they throw their crowns down before the throne, chanting,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:4; 1ch 29:11-16; Psa 115:1; 1 Cor 15:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:11 “Worthy are You, our Lord and God, to receive glory and honor and power, For You created all things, and because of Your will they existed and were created!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 1:1 Pro 16:4; Rom 11:36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:1 And I saw in the right hand of the One seated upon the throne a scroll, written on both the front and the back, sealed with seven seals.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 2:9-10; Dan 12:4,9; Zech 5:1-4 Rev 6:1; Isa 8:16; Isa 29:11; Dan 8:26; Dan 12:4-9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:2 I also saw a mighty angel proclaiming with a loud voice, “Who is worthy to open the scroll and to break its seals?”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 25:23-25 Rev 5:5; Isa 29:11,12; Isa 41:22,23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:3 No one in heaven or on the earth or under the earth was able to open the scroll or to look into it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:13; Isa 40:13,14; Isa 41:28; Rom 11:34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:4 I began to weep loudly because no one was found worthy to open the scroll or to look into it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:1; Dan 12:8,9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:5 Then one of the elders tells me, “Stop weeping! Behold, the Lion of the tribe of Judah, the Root of David, has triumphed—He is worthy to open the scroll and its seven seals.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 49:9-10; Isa 11:1,10; Hos 5:14 Rev 1:1; Rev 6:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:6 And in the midst of the throne and the four living creatures, and in the midst of the elders, I saw a Lamb standing, as having been slain—having seven horns and seven eyes, which are the seven spirits of God sent out into all the earth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 11:2; Zech 3:8-9; 4:10 Rev 4:5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:7 He came and took the scroll from the right hand of the One seated on the throne.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:1; Rev 4:2,3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:8 When He had taken the scroll, the four living creatures and the twenty-four elders fell down before the Lamb, each holding a harp and golden bowls full of incense—which are the prayers of the kedoshim.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 111:2 Rev 8:3,4; Psa 141:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:9 And they are singing a new song, saying, “You are worthy to take the scroll and to open its seals. For You were slain, and by Your blood You redeemed for God those from every tribe and tongue and people and nation.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 40:3; 98:1; 144:9;149:1; Isa 42:10; Dan 5:19 Rev 7:9; Rev 11:9; Rev 14:6; Dan 4:1; Dan 6:25; Mark 16:15,16; Col 1:23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:10 You have made them for our God a kingdom and kohanim, and they shall reign upon the earth.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 19:6; Isa 61:6 Rev 20:6; Dan 7:18,27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:11 Then I looked, and I heard the voice of many angels around the throne and the living creatures and the elders—their number was myriads of myriads and thousands of thousands.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:10 Rev 19:6; Deut 33:2; Psa 68:17; Dan 7:10; Heb 12:22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:12 They were chanting with a loud voice, “Worthy is the Lamb who was slain, to receive power and riches and wisdom and might and honor and glory and blessing!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:11; Rev 7:12; Rev 19:1; Mat 28:18; John 3:35,36; John 17:2; 2 Cor 8:9; Phil 2:9-11; 1 Tim 1:17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:13 And I heard every creature in heaven and on the earth and under the earth and on the sea and everything in them, responding, “To the One seated on the throne and to the Lamb be blessing and honor and glory and power forever and ever!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:6,9; Rev 6:16; Rev 7:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:14 And the four living creatures kept saying, “Amen!” And the elders fell down and worshiped.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:9-11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:1 Then I saw when the Lamb opened one of the seven seals, and I heard one of the four living creatures say with a voice like thunder, “Come!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:3,5,7; Rev 4:6,7; Acts 4:20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:2 I looked, and behold, there was a white horse. The one riding on it had a bow, and a crown was given to him. He went out as a conqueror so he might conquer.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Zech 1:8; 6:3; Rev 11:15,18; Rev 15:2; Rev 17:14; Psa 98:1; Psa 110:2; Isa 25:8; Rom 15:18,19; 1 Cor 15:25,55-57; 2 Cor 10:3-5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:3 When the Lamb opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature saying, “Come!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:1; Rev 4:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:4 Then another horse came out, fiery red. The one riding on it was permitted to take peace from the earth, so that people would slaughter one another. He was given a great sword.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 25:29; Zech 1:8; 6:2 Psa 17:13; Isa 10:5,6; Eze 30:24,25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:5 When the Lamb opened the third seal, I heard the third living creature saying, “Come!” And behold, I saw a black horse. The one riding on it held a balance scale in his hand.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 14:1, 2; Zech 6:2 Lev 26:26; la 5:10; Eze 4:10,16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:6 Then I heard something like a voice in the midst of the four living creatures saying, “A quart of wheat for a denarius, and three quarts of barley for a denarius—but do no harm to the oil and wine!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 26:25-33; Ezek 4:10, 11 Rev 9:4; Psa 76:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:7 When the Lamb opened the fourth seal, I heard the fourth living creature saying, “Come!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:1,3,5; Rev 4:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:8 Behold, I saw a horse, pale greenish gray. The name of the one riding on it was Death, and Sheol was following with him. Authority was given to them over a fourth of the earth, to kill by sword and by famine and by plague and by the wild beasts of the earth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 15:2-3; 24:10;29:17; Ezek 14:21; Hos 13:14; Zech 6:3 Lev 26:22-33; Jer 15:2,3; Jer 16:4,16; Jer 43:11; Eze 5:15-17; Eze 14:13-21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:9 When the Lamb opened the fifth seal, I saw under the altar the souls of those slaughtered for the sake of the word of God and for the witness they had.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:9; Rev 2:13; Rev 11:3-7; Rev 12:11-17; Rev 19:10; 2 Tim 1:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:10 And they cried out with a loud voice, saying, “O Sovereign Master, holy and true, how long before You judge those who dwell on the earth and avenge our blood?”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:18; Rev 16:5-7; Rev 18:20,24; Rev 19:2; Deut 32:36-43; Judg 16:28; 1 Sam 24:12; Psa 58:10,11; Isa 61:2; Isa 63:1-6; Luke 21:22; Rom 12:19; 2 Thes 1:6-8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:11 Then a white robe was given to each of them, and they were told to rest a little while longer, until the number of their fellow servants was complete—their brothers and sisters who were to be killed as they had been.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:14; Rev 13:15; Rev 17:6; Mat 10:21; Mat 23:34,35; John 16:2; Heb 11:40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:12 I saw when the Lamb opened the sixth seal, and there was a great earthquake. The sun became as black as sackcloth made of goat’s hair, and the full moon became like blood.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 50:3; Joel 2:10 Isa 13:9,10; Isa 24:23; Isa 60:19,20; Eze 32:7,8; Joel 2:10,30,31; Joel 3:15; Amo 8:9; hag 2:6,7,21,22; Mat 24:29; Mat 27:45; Mark 13:24,25; Mark 15:33; Luke 23:44,45; Acts 2:19,20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:13 The stars of heaven fell to the earth like a fig tree drops unripe figs when shaken by a great wind.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 34:4 Isa 7:2; Isa 33:9; Dan 4:14; Nah 3:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:14 The heaven ripped apart like a scroll being rolled up, and every mountain and island was moved from their places.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 34:4; Nah 1:5 Rev 16:20; Isa 2:14-17; Jer 3:23; Jer 4:23-26; Jer 51:25; Hab 3:6,10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:15 Then the kings of the earth and the great men and the military commanders and the rich and the mighty and everyone—slave and free—hid themselves in the caves and among the rocks of the mountains.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Josh 10:16; Ps 48:4-6; Isa 2:10-12, 19 Josh 10:16,17; Judg 6:2; 1 Sam 13:6; Isa 2:10,19; Isa 42:22; Mic 7:17; Heb 11:38&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:16 And they tell the mountains and the rocks, “Fall on us, and hide us from the face of the One seated on the throne and from the wrath of the Lamb.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hos 10:8 Rev 6:10; Rev 19:15; Psa 2:9-12; Psa 14:5; Psa 21:8-12; Psa 110:5,6; Zec 1:14,15; Mat 26:64; 2 Thes 1:7-9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:17 For the great day of their wrath has come, and who is able to stand?”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 76:7; Jer 30:7;Nah 1:6; Zeph 1:14-18; Mal 3:2 Psa 76:7; Psa 130:3,4; Joel 2:11; Mal 3:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:1 After this, I saw four angels standing at the four corners of the earth, holding back the four winds of the earth so that no wind would blow on the earth or on the sea or against any tree.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 11:2; Jer 49:36; Ezek 7:2; 37:9; Dan 7:2; Zech 6:5 Rev 6:6; Rev 9:4; Isa 27:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:2 Then I saw another angel coming up from the east, having the seal of the living God. He cried out with a loud voice to the four angels who were permitted to harm the earth and the sea,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:3; Rev 8:7-12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:3 saying, “Do no harm to the earth or the sea or the trees, until we have put a seal on the foreheads of the servants of our God.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 9:4-6 Rev 13:16; Rev 14:1; Rev 20:4; Rev 22:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:4 Now I heard the number of those marked with the seal: 144,000 from every tribe of Bnei-Yisrael—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 49:1-28 Eze 47:13; Eze 48:19,31; Zec 9:1; Mat 19:28; Luke 22:30; Acts 26:7; James 1:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:5 12,000 from the tribe of Judah; 12,000 from the tribe of Reuben; 12,000 from the tribe of Gad;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exo 1:2-4; Num 1:4-15; Num 10:14-27; Num 13:4-16; 1 Cor 2:1,2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:6 12,000 from the tribe of Asher; 12,000 from the tribe of Naphtali; 12,000 from the tribe of Manasseh;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Luke 2:36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:7 12,000 from the tribe of Simeon; 12,000 from the tribe of Levi; 12,000 from the tribe of Issachar;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 30:18; Gen 35:23; Gen 49:11; Josh 19:17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:8 12,000 from the tribe of Zebulun; 12,000 from the tribe of Joseph; 12,000 from the tribe of Benjamin.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:9 After these things I looked, and behold, a vast multitude that no one could count—from every nation and all tribes and peoples and tongues—was standing before the throne and before the Lamb. They were clothed in white robes, with palm branches in their hands&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 23:40 Lev 23:40; John 12:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:10 and crying out with a loud voice, saying, “Salvation belongs to our God, who sits on the throne, and to the Lamb!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 3:8 Rev 4:6,9; Rev 22:3; John 1:29,36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:11 And all the angels were standing around the throne, along with the elders and the four living creatures; and they fell on their faces before the throne and worshiped God,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:10; Rev 15:4; Rev 19:4; Rev 22:9; Psa 45:11; Psa 97:7; Mat 4:10; John 5:23; Heb 1:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:12 saying, “Amen, blessing and glory and wisdom and thanksgiving and honor and power and might belong to our God forever and ever. Amen!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Neh 12:8,46; Psa 50:14; Psa 95:2; Psa 100:4; Psa 107:22; Psa 116:17; Psa 147:7; Isa 51:3; Jer 33:9,11; jon 2:9; 2 Cor 4:15; 2 Cor 9:11,12; Col 2:7; Col 3:17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:13 Then one of the elders answered, saying to me, “Who are these dressed in white robes, and where have they come from?” I said to him, “Sir, you know.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 16:8; Judg 13:6; John 7:28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:14 Then he said to me, “These are the ones coming out of the great tribulation. They have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 49:11 Rev 5:9; Rev 12:11; Heb 13:12; 1 Pet 1:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:15 For this reason, they are before the throne of God, and they serve Him day and night in His Temple. The One seated on the throne will shelter them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 26:11 Rev 21:3,4; Rev 22:3; Exo 29:45; 1 King 6:13; 1ch 23:25; Psa 68:16-18; Isa 4:5,6; John 1:14; 1 Cor 3:16; 2 Cor 6:16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:16 They shall never again go hungry, nor thirst anymore; the sun shall not beat down on them, nor any scorching heat.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 121:5-6; Isa 49:10 Rev 21:4; Psa 121:6; so 1:6; Isa 4:5,6; Isa 25:4; Isa 32:2; jon 4:8; Mat 13:6,21; Mark 4:6,17; James 1:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:17 For the Lamb in the midst of the throne shall shepherd them and guide them to springs of living water, and God shall wipe away every tear from their eyes.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 23:1-2; Ezek 34:23 Rev 4:11; Rev 21:4; Isa 25:8; Isa 30:19; Isa 35:10; Isa 60:20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:1 Now when the Lamb opened the seventh seal, there was silence in heaven for about half an hour.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Josh 6:10 Job 4:16; Psa 37:7; Psa 62:1; Hab 2:20; Zec 2:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:2 Then I saw the seven angels who stand before God, and seven trumpets were given to them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Josh 6:4 Rev 8:6-12; Rev 9:1,13,14; Rev 11:15; Num 10:1-10; 2ch 29:25-28; Amo 3:6-8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:3 Another angel came and stood at the altar, holding a golden incense burner. He was given much incense to offer up along with the prayers of all the kedoshim upon the golden altar before the throne.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 141:2 Rev 6:9; Rev 9:13; Exo 37:25,26; Exo 40:26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:4 And the smoke of the incense, with the prayers of the kedoshim, rose before God from the angel’s hand.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 141:2 Rev 8:3; Rev 15:8; Exo 30:1; Psa 141:2; Luke 1:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:5 Then the angel took the incense burner and filled it with fire from the altar, and threw it to the earth; and there were clashes of thunder and rumblings and flashes of lightning and earthquakes.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 10:2; 8:5,6; Ex 19:16 Rev 11:13,19; 1 King 19:11; Isa 29:6; Zec 14:5; Mat 24:7; Mat 27:52-54; Acts 4:31; Acts 16:26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:6 Then the seven angels holding the seven trumpets prepared to sound them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 19:16 Rev 8:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:7 The first trumpeted, and there was hail and fire mixed with blood, and they were thrown upon the earth. A third of the earth burned up, a third of the trees burned up, and all the green grass burned up.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 9:23-24; Josh 10:11; Ps 18:13; Isa 28:2 Rev 8:9,10,12; Rev 6:8; Rev 9:4; Isa 2:12,13; Isa 10:17,18; James 1:11; 1 Pet 1:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:8 The second angel trumpeted, and something like a huge mountain ablaze with fire was thrown into the sea. A third of the sea turned into blood,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 7:17-19; 8:10; Isa 14:12 Rev 8:7; Rev 16:3-21; Exo 7:17-21; Eze 14:9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:9 a third of the creatures living in the sea died, and a third of the ships were destroyed.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 48:7; Isa 2:16; Isa 23:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:10 The third angel trumpeted, and a great star fell from the heavens, burning like a torch. It fell on a third of the rivers and on the springs of water.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 14:12 Rev 16:4; Exo 7:20,21; Judg 15:11; 2 King 2:19-22; 2ch 32:3; Isa 12:3; ho 13:15,16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:11 Now the name of the star is Wormwood; and a third of the waters became wormwood, and many people died from the waters that were made bitter.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 9:15; 23:15 Exo 15:23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:12 The fourth angel trumpeted, and a third of the sun and a third of the moon and a third of the stars were struck, so that a third of them were darkened. A third of the day would not shine, as well as a third of the night.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Josh 10:12; Isa 13:10 Exo 10:21-23; 2 Cor 4:4; 2 Thes 2:9-12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:13 Then I looked, and I heard an eagle crying out with a loud voice as it flew high in the sky, saying, “Woe, woe, woe to those who dwell on the earth, because of the remaining blasts of the trumpets the three angels are about to sound!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:1,12; Rev 11:14; Eze 2:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Testament References and Allusions in Revelation 9-12</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/ref9-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/ref9-12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 12,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h3 id=&#34;chap-9-12&#34;&gt;Chap 9-12&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation (TLV)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:1 Then the fifth angel trumpeted, and I saw a star that had fallen from heaven to earth. The key to the bottomless pit was given to him.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 14:12-14 Rev 9:2,11; Rev 17:8; Rev 20:10; Luke 8:31; Rom 10:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:2 He opened the pit, and smoke rose from the pit like the smoke of a gigantic furnace. The sun and the air were darkened by the smoke from the pit.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 19:28; Ex 19:8 Rev 8:12; Exo 10:21-23; Joel 2:2,10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:3 Then from the smoke came locusts upon the earth, and power was given to them like the scorpions have power over the earth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 10:12-15 Rev 9:5,10,11; Deut 8:15; 1 King 12:11; Eze 2:6; Luke 10:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:4 They were told to do no harm to the grass of the earth or any green plant or any tree, but only the people who do not have the seal of God on their foreheads.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 9:4 Rev 7:3,4; Rev 14:1; Exo 12:23; Job 2:6; Eze 9:4,6; Eph 4:30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:5 And they were permitted not to kill them, but to torment them for five months—and their torment was like the torment of a scorpion when it stings a person.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:6 In those days, people will seek death but will not find it; they will long to die, but death will flee from them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Job 3:21 Rev 6:16; 2 Sam 1:9; Job 3:20-22; Job 7:15,16; Isa 2:19; Jer 8:3; ho 10:8; John 4:8,9; Luke 23:30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:7 Now the appearance of the locusts was like horses prepared for battle. On their heads were something like crowns of gold, and their faces were like human faces.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:4,8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:8 They had hair like women’s hair, and their teeth were like those of lions.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joel 1:6 Psa 57:4; Joel 1:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:9 They had chests like iron breastplates; and the noise of their wings was like the noise of many horse-drawn chariots rushing into battle.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joel 2:5 Job 39:25; Isa 9:5; Joel 2:5-7; Nah 2:4,5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:10 They have tails like scorpions with stingers; and in their tails is their power to harm people for five months.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:3,5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:11 They have as king over them the angel of the abyss. His name in Hebrew is Abaddon, and in Greek he has the name Apollyon.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Job 26:6; 28:22; 31:12; Ps 88:11; Prov 15:11; 30:27; Amos 7:11 (LXX) John 8:44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:12 The first woe is past. Behold, two woes are still coming after these things.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:13-21; Rev 8:13; Rev 11:14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:13 The sixth angel trumpeted, and I heard a single voice from the four horns of the golden altar before God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:3-5; Heb 9:24; Heb 10:21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:14 It said to the sixth angel, the one holding the trumpet, “Release the four angels who are bound at the great river Euphrates.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 15:18; Deut 1:7; Josh 1:4 Gen 2:14; 2 Sam 8:3; Jer 51:63&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:15 So the four angels—who had been prepared for the hour and day and month and year—were released to kill a third of mankind.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:18; Rev 8:7,9,11,12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:16 The number of mounted troops was two hundred million—I heard their number.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:17 Now here is how I saw the horses and those riding on them: they had breastplates that were fiery red, hyacinth blue, and sulfur yellow. The heads of the horses were as heads of lions, and out of their mouths came fire and smoke and brimstone.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1ch 12:8; Isa 5:28,29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:18 By these three plagues a third of mankind was killed—by the fire and the smoke and the brimstone that came out of their mouths.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:15,17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:19 For the power of the horses is in their mouths and in their tails; for their tails are like serpents, having heads by which they inflict injuries.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:10; Isa 9:15; Eph 4:14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:20 But the rest of mankind, those not killed by these plagues, did not repent and turn away from the works of their hands—they would not stop worshiping demons and the idols of gold and silver and stone and wood, which cannot see or hear or walk.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 115:4-8; Psa 135:15-18; Isa 40:19,20; Isa 41:7; Isa 42:17,18; Isa 44:9-20; Isa 46:5-7; Jer 10:3-5,8,9,14,15; Jer 15:19,20; Jer 51:17; Dan 5:23; Hab 2:18-20; Acts 17:29; Rom 1:21-23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 9:21 And they did not repent and turn away from their murders or their sorceries or their sexual immorality or their stealing.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:8; Rev 17:2,5; Rev 18:3; Rev 19:2; Mat 15:19; 2 Cor 12:21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:1 Then I saw another powerful angel coming down from heaven, wrapped in a cloud with a rainbow over his head. His face was like the sun and his feet like pillars of fire.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eze 1:26-28 Rev 1:15; so 5:15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:2 He had in his hand a little scroll that was open. He set his right foot on the sea and his left foot on the land,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 11:24 Rev 10:5,8; Psa 2:8; Psa 65:5; Pro 8:15,16; Isa 59:19; Mat 28:18; Eph 1:20-22; Phil 2:10,11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:3 and he cried out with a loud voice, just as a lion roars. When he cried out, the seven thunders spoke.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joel 3:16 Rev 8:5; Rev 14:2; Rev 15:1,7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:4 And when the seven thunders had spoken, I was about to write; but I heard a voice from heaven saying, “Seal up what the seven thunders have said. Do not write it down!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 8:26; 12:4-9 Deut 29:29; Isa 8:16; Isa 29:11; Dan 8:26; Dan 12:4,9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:5 Then the angel whom I saw standing on the sea and on the land raised his right hand toward heaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 32:40; Dan 12:7 Rev 16:17; Dan 12:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:6 and swore by the One who lives forever and ever, who created heaven and what is in it, the earth and what is in it, the sea and what is in it, that there would be no more delay.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 1:1; Deut 32:40; Neh 9:6; Dan 12:7 Rev 10:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:7 But in the days of the voice of the seventh angel—when he is about to trumpet—the mystery of God is completed, just as He declared to His servants the prophets.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Amos 3:7 Luke 24:44-47; Acts 3:21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:8 Then the voice that I heard from heaven spoke to me again, saying, “Go, take the scroll that is open in the hand of the angel standing on the sea and on the land.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:4,5; Isa 30:21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:9 So I went to the angel, telling him to give me the little scroll. And he tells me, “Take and eat it. It will be bitter to your stomach, but sweet as honey in your mouth.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 15:16; Ezek 2:8-3:3 Job 23:12; Jer 15:16; Eze 2:8; Eze 3:1-3,14; Col 3:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:10 So I took the little scroll from the angel’s hand and ate it. It was sweet as honey in my mouth; but when I had swallowed it, my stomach was made bitter.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eze 2:10; Eze 3:14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:11 And they tell me, “You must prophesy again about many peoples and nations and tongues and kings.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 37:4, 9 Rev 11:9; Rev 14:6; Rev 17:15; Jer 1:9,10; Jer 25:15-30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:1 Then a measuring rod like a staff was given to me, saying, “Get up and measure the Temple of God and the altar, and count those worshiping in it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 40:3-4; Zech 2:1-2 Num 33:18; Eze 40:1-48; 1 Cor 3:16,17; 2 Cor 6:16; Eph 2:20-22; 1 Pet 2:5,9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:2 But do not measure the court outside the Temple—leave it out, because it has been given to the nations, and they shall trample the holy city for forty-two months.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 40:17-20 Rev 11:3,11; Rev 12:6; Rev 13:5; Num 14:34; Dan 7:25; Dan 12:7,11,12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:3 And I will grant authority to My two witnesses and they will prophesy for 1,260 days, dressed in sackcloth.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 37:34; 1ch 21:16; es 4:1,2; Job 16:15; Isa 22:12; la 2:10; John 3:5-8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:4 These are the two olive trees and the two menorot that are standing before the Lord of the earth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Zech 4:1-2, 11-14 Exo 8:22; Isa 54:5; Mic 4:13; Zec 4:14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:5 If anyone wishes to harm them, fire comes out of their mouths and consumes their enemies. If anyone wants to harm them, he must be killed in this way.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Num 16:35; 1 Kings 18:37; 2 Kings 1:10-12 Num 16:28-35; 2 King 1:10-12; Psa 18:8; Isa 11:4; Jer 1:10; Jer 5:14; Eze 43:3; ho 6:5; Zec 1:6; Zec 2:8; Acts 9:4,5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:6 These two have the power to shut the heavens, so that no rain may fall during the days of their prophesying. And they have power over the waters to turn them into blood, and to strike the earth with every kind of plague as often as they wish.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 7:19-25; 8:12; 1 Kings 17:1 Eze 7:1-12; Psa 105:26-36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:7 When they have finished their testimony, the beast that rises from the abyss will make war on them, and overcome them and kill them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:3, 7, 8, 21 Rev 9:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:8 And their corpses will lie in the open street of the great city that figuratively is called Sodom and Egypt—where also their Lord was crucified.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 1:9-10; 3:9; Jer 23:14; Ezek 16:49, Ezek 23:3, Ezek 23:8 Ezek 23:19, Ezek 23:27 Rev 18:24; Luke 13:33,34; Acts 9:4; Heb 6:6; Heb 13:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:9 Some from the peoples and tribes and tongues and nations will look at their corpses for three and a half days, not allowing them to be placed into a grave.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 79:2-3 Rev 5:8; Rev 19:17,18; Psa 79:2,3; ec 6:3; Isa 33:1; Jer 7:33; Mat 7:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:10 Those who dwell on the earth will rejoice over them. They will celebrate and send gifts to one another, because these two prophets tormented those who dwell on the earth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:5,6; Rev 16:10; 1 King 18:17; 1 King 21:20; 1 King 22:8,18; Jer 38:4; John 7:7; Acts 5:33; Acts 7:54-57; Acts 17:5,6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:11 But after the three and a half days, the breath of life from God entered them, and they stood up on their feet; and great fear fell on those who were watching them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 37:9-10 Rev 11:13; Josh 2:9; Jer 33:9; ho 3:5; Acts 5:5,11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:12 Then they heard a loud voice from heaven saying to them, “Come up here!” And they went up to heaven in a cloud, while their enemies watched them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exo 14:25; 2 King 2:1,5,7; Psa 86:17; Psa 112:10; Mal 3:18; Luke 16:23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:13 At that hour there was a great earthquake, and a tenth of the city collapsed. Seven thousand people were killed in the earthquake, and the rest were terrified and gave glory to the God of heaven.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:7; Rev 15:4; Rev 16:9; Josh 7:19; 1 Sam 6:5; Isa 26:15,16; Jer 13:16; Mal 2:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:14 The second woe is past. The third woe is coming soon.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 8:13; Rev 9:12; Rev 15:1; Rev 16:1-21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:15 Then the seventh angel trumpeted, and there were loud voices in heaven saying, “The kingdom of this world has become the kingdom of our Lord and of His Anointed One. And He shall reign forever and ever!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 15:18; Dan 2:44-45; 7:13-14, 27 Exo 15:18; Psa 110:4; Psa 146:10; Isa 9:7; Eze 37:25; Dan 2:44; Dan 7:14,18,27; Mic 4:7; Mat 6:13; Luke 1:33; Heb 1:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:16 And the twenty-four elders seated on their thrones before God fell on their faces and worshiped God,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:4,10; Rev 5:5-8,14; Rev 7:11; Rev 19:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:17 saying, “We thank you, Adonai Elohei-Tzva’ot, who is and who was, because You have taken Your great power and begun to reign.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:15; Rev 19:6,11-21; Rev 20:1-3; Psa 21:13; Psa 57:11; Psa 64:9,10; Psa 98:1-3; Psa 102:13-8; Isa 51:9-11; Isa 52:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:18 The nations were enraged, but Your wrath has come and the time for the dead to be judged—to reward Your servants, the prophets and kedoshim, and those who fear Your name, the small and the great, and to destroy the destroyers of the earth.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 2:1-3; 46:6; 115:13 Rev 13:10; Rev 18:6,16-24; Rev 19:19,21; Dan 7:26; Dan 8:25; Dan 11:44,45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:19 Then the Temple of God in heaven was opened, and the Ark of His Covenant appeared in His Temple. And there were flashes of lightning and rumblings and clashes of thunder and an earthquake and heavy hail.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 3:16 Rev 8:7; Rev 16:21; Exo 9:18-29; Josh 10:11; Job 38:22,23; Psa 18:12; Psa 105:32; Isa 28:2; Isa 30:30; Isa 32:19; Eze 13:11; Eze 38:22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:1 A great sign appeared in heaven: a woman clothed with the sun, with the moon under her feet, and on her head a crown of twelve stars.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 37:9-11 Rev 1:20; Rev 21:14; Isa 62:3; Zec 9:16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:2 She is pregnant—crying out in birth pains, in agony to give birth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 26:17; 66:7; Micah 4:9-10 Rev 12:4; Isa 53:11; Isa 54:1; Isa 66:7,8; Mic 5:3; John 16:21; Gal 4:19,27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:3 Then another sign appeared in heaven: a great fiery red dragon that had seven heads and ten horns, and seven royal crowns on his heads.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 27:1; Dan 7:7, 20, 24 Rev 13:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:4 His tail sweeps away a third of the stars of heaven—it hurled them to the earth. Now the dragon stood before the woman who was about to give birth, so that whenever she gave birth he might devour her child.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 8:10 Rev 12:2; Exo 1:16; Mat 2:3-16; John 8:44; 1 Pet 5:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:5 And she gave birth to a son, a male child, who is to rule all the nations with an iron rod. And her child was snatched away to God and to His throne.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 2:8-9; Isa 66:7 Rev 11:12; Mark 16:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:6 Then the woman fled into the wilderness, where she has a place prepared by God so they might take care of her for 1,260 days.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:2,3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:7 And war broke out in heaven, Michael and his angels making war against the dragon. The dragon and his angels fought,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 10:13-21; 12:1 Rev 12:9; Psa 78:49; Mat 25:41; 2 Cor 12:7; 2 Pet 2:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:8 but they were not strong enough, and there was no longer any place for them in heaven.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Job 7:10; Job 8:18; Job 20:9; Job 27:21-23; Psa 37:10; Acts 1:25; Jude 1:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:9 And the great dragon was thrown down—the ancient serpent, called the devil and satan, who deceives the whole world. He was thrown down to the earth, and his angels were thrown down with him.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:1; Job 1:6; 2:1; Zech 3:1 Job 1:7; Job 2:2; Isa 14:12; Isa 65:25; John 14:30; John 16:11; 2 Cor 4:4; 1 Pet 5:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:10 Then I heard a loud voice in heaven saying, “Now have come the salvation and the power and the kingdom of our God and the authority of His Anointed One, for the accuser of our brothers and sisters—the one who accuses them before our God day and night—has been thrown out.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Job 1:9-11; 2:4-5; Zech 3:1 Job 1:9; Job 2:5; Zec 3:1,2; Luke 22:31; Titus 2:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:11 They overcame him by the blood of the Lamb and by the word of their testimony, and they did not love their lives even in the face of death.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:10,13; Rev 20:4; Luke 14:26; Acts 20:24; Acts 21:13; Heb 11:35-38&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:12 Therefore rejoice, O heavens, and you who dwell in them! Woe to the earth and the sea, for the devil has come down to you with great rage, knowing that his time is short.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:6; Heb 10:37; 2 Pet 3:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:13 Now when the dragon saw that he had been thrown to the earth, he stalked the woman who had given birth to the male child.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:4,5; Gen 3:15; Psa 37:12-14; John 16:33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:14 But the woman was given two wings of the great eagle, so that she might fly away from the presence of the serpent into the wilderness, to the place where she is taken care of—for a time, times, and half a time.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 19:4; Deut 32:11; Isa 40:31; Dan 7:25; 12:7; Hos 2:14-15 Rev 11:2,3; Dan 7:25; Dan 12:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:15 And from out of his mouth, the serpent spewed water like a river after the woman, in order to sweep her away with a flood.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hos 1:5-10 Rev 17:15; Psa 18:4; Psa 65:7; Psa 93:3,4; Isa 8:7; Isa 28:2; Isa 59:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:16 But the earth came to the aid of the woman. The earth opened its mouth and swallowed the river that the dragon had spewed from his mouth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exo 12:35,36; 1 King 17:6; 2 King 8:9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:17 So the dragon became enraged at the woman and went off to make war with the rest of her offspring—those who keep the commandments of God and hold to the testimony of Yeshua.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:15 Rev 12:11; Rev 1:2,9; Rev 6:9; Rev 20:4; 1 Cor 2:1; 1 John 5:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 13-18 References and Allusions</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/ref13-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/ref13-18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 12,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h3 id=&#34;chap-13-18&#34;&gt;Chap 13-18&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation (TLV)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:1 (And he stood on the shore of the sea.) Then I saw a beast rising out of the sea, that had ten horns and seven heads. On his horns were ten royal crowns, and upon his heads were slanderous names.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:3, 7, 8; Rev 13:5,6; Rev 17:3,5; Dan 7:25; Dan 11:36; 2 Thes 2:3,4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:2 Now the beast that I saw was like a leopard, his feet like a lion’s, and his mouth like a bear’s. And the dragon gave him his power and his throne and great authority.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:4-6, 8; Rev 16:10; Rev 17:12; Rev 19:20; Rev 20:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:3 One of his heads seemed to have been slain, but the fatal wound was healed. The whole earth was amazed and followed the beast.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:8 Rev 17:6,8,13,17; Luke 2:1; John 12:19; Acts 8:10,11,13; 2 Thes 2:9-12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:4 And they worshiped the dragon, because he had given authority to the beast. They also worshiped the beast, chanting, “Who is like the beast, and who can make war against him?”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 15:11; Dan 8:24;  Rev 17:14; Deut 9:2; 1 Sam 17:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:5 The beast was given a mouth uttering great boasts and blasphemies. It was given authority to act for forty-two months.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 14:13-15; Dan 7:8, 11; Dan 7:20-25; 11:36 Rev 13:7; Rev 11:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:6 Then he opened his mouth with blasphemies against God, to slander His name and His tabernacle—that is, those dwelling in heaven.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:8; Rev 4:1,4; Rev 5:13; Rev 7:9; Rev 11:12; Rev 12:12; Rev 18:20; Rev 19:1-6; Heb 12:22,23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:7 He was also permitted to make war against the kedoshim and overcome them, and he was given authority over every tribe and people and tongue and nation.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:21; Rev 10:11; Rev 11:18; Rev 17:15; Exo 9:16; Isa 10:15; Isa 37:26; Jer 25:9; Jer 27:6,7; Jer 51:20-24; Dan 5:18-23; Luke 4:6; John 19:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:8 All who dwell on the earth shall worship him—everyone whose name has not been written from the foundation of the world in the Book of Life of the Lamb who was slain.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 12:1 Rev 17:8; Eph 1:4; Titus 1:2; 1 Pet 1:19,20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:9 If anyone has an ear, let him hear.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:7,11,17,29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:10 If anyone is meant for captivity, to captivity he goes. If anyone is to be killed by the sword, by the sword he must be killed. Here is the perseverance and faith of the kedoshim.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 15:2; 43:11; Rev 1:9; Rev 2:2,19; Rev 3:3,10; Rev 14:12; la 3:26; Hab 2:3; Luke 18:1-8; Luke 21:19; Col 1:11; Heb 6:12; Heb 10:36,37; Heb 12:3,4; James 1:2-4; James 5:7,8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:11 Then I saw another beast rising out of the earth. He had two horns like a lamb and spoke like a dragon.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 8:3; Job 40:15; Rev 13:17; Rev 12:3,4,17; Rev 17:6; Dan 7:8,24,25; 2 Thes 2:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:12 He exercises all the authority of the first beast before him, and he makes the earth and all those who dwell in it worship the first beast, whose fatal wound was healed.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:3,14-17; Rev 17:10,11; 2 Thes 2:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:13 He performs great signs, even making fire come down from heaven in the sight of men.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 Kings 1:9-12; 1 Kings 18:38; Rev 11:5; Num 16:35; 2 King 1:10-14; Mat 16:1; Luke 9:54-56; 2 Tim 3:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:14 And he deceives those who dwell on the earth through the signs he is permitted to perform, telling those who dwell on the earth to make an image in honor of the beast who has the sword wound yet lived.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mark 13:21-23; Rev 14:9,11; Rev 15:2; Rev 16:2; Rev 19:20; Rev 20:4; 2 King 20:7; Eze 8:10; Eze 16:17; Dan 11:36; 2 Thes 2:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:15 The second beast was permitted to give life to the image of the first beast, so that the image of the beast could even speak and cause all who would not worship the image of the beast to be killed.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 3:1-7; Dan 7:20,25; Rev 16:2,5; Rev 17:6,14,17; Rev 18:20,24; Rev 19:20; Rev 20:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:16 He also causes all—the small and the great, the rich and the poor, the free and the slave—to receive a mark on their right hand or upon their forehead.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:3; Exo 13:9; Deut 6:8 (contrast); Deut 11:18; Eze 9:4; 2 Tim 3:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:17 And so no one can buy or sell unless he has the mark—either the name of the beast or the number of his name.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:18; Rev 15:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13:18 Here is wisdom: let the one who has understanding calculate the number of the beast, for it is a number of a man, and his number is 666.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:17; Deut 3:11; Rom 3:5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:1 Then I looked, and behold, the Lamb was standing on Mount Zion, and with Him were 144,000 who had His name and His Father’s name written on their foreheads.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 2:6; Ezek 9:4 Rev 3:12; Rev 7:3; Rev 13:16,17; Luke 12:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:2 And I heard a voice from heaven like the roar of rushing waters and the booming of loud thunder. The voice I heard was like harpists playing on their harps.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 1:24; 43:2 Rev 5:8; Rev 15:2; Rev 18:22; 2 Sam 6:5; 1ch 25:1-7; Psa 33:2; Psa 43:4; Psa 57:8; Psa 92:3; Psa 98:5; Psa 147:7; Psa 149:3; Psa 150:3-6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:3 And they are singing a new song before the throne and before the four living creatures and the elders; and no one is able to learn the song except the 144,000 who had been redeemed from the earth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 96:1-6,144:9 Rev 5:9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:4 These are the ones who have not defiled themselves with women, for they are virgins. These are the ones who follow the Lamb wherever He goes. These have been redeemed from among mankind as firstfruits for God and the Lamb.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 2:3; Amo 6:1; 1 Cor 16:15; James 1:18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:5 And in their mouth was found no lie—they are blameless.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Son 4:7; Dan 6:4; Hos 10:2; Zeph 3:13; Mal 2:6; Luke 23:4; Eph 5:27; Col 1:22; Jude 1:24; 2 th 2:11-12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:6 And then I saw another angel flying high in the sky, having a timeless message of good news to proclaim to those who dwell on the earth—to every nation and tribe and tongue and people.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:11; Rev 13:7; Dan 4:1; Dan 6:25,26; Eph 3:9; Gal 1:6-9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:7 He said in a loud voice, “Fear God and give Him glory, because the hour of His judgment has come. Worship the One who made heaven and earth and sea and springs of water.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 20:11 Rev 4:11; Exo 20:11; Neh 9:6; Psa 33:6; Psa 95:5; Psa 124:8; Psa 146:5,6; Pro 8:22-31; Jer 10:10; Acts 14:15; Acts 17:23-25 (Compare with &amp;ldquo;Repent, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand.&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:8 Another angel, a second one, followed, saying, “Fallen, fallen, is Babylon the great—she who made all nations drink of the wine of the fury of her immorality.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 21:9; Jer 51:7-8; Gen 10:9-10; Rev 13:15-17; Rev 17:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:9 And another angel, a third one, followed them, saying in a loud voice, “If anyone worships the beast and his image and receives a mark on his forehead or on his hand,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 25:15; Rev 14:11; Rev 13:3-6,11-17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:10 he shall also drink the wine of God’s fury, poured full strength into the cup of His wrath. And he shall be tormented with fire and brimstone before the holy angels and before the Lamb.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 19:24; Ps 75:8; Isa 51:17 Psa 37:34; Psa 52:6; Psa 91:8; Eze 20:48; Mat 13:41,42,49,50; 2 Thes 1:8,9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:11 The smoke of their torment goes up forever and ever. Those who worship the beast and its image and those who receive the mark of his name have no rest day or night.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 34:10; 66:24 Deut 28:65; Isa 57:20; Mat 11:28; Mark 9:43-49; Luke 16:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:12 Here is the perseverance of the kedoshim—those who keep the commandments of God and the faith of Yeshua.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:8,10; 2 Tim 4:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:13 Then I heard a voice from heaven saying, “Write: How fortunate are the dead—those who die in the Lord from now on!” “Yes,” says the Ruach, “that they may rest from their labors, for their deeds follow them.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 19:11; Psa 85:13; Mat 25:35-40; Luke 16:9; 1 Cor 15:58; Gal 6:7,8; Phil 2:17; 2 Tim 4:7,8; Heb 6:10,11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:14 Then I looked, and behold, there was a white cloud—and seated on the cloud was one like a son of man. He had a golden crown on His head and a sharp sickle in His hand.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:13; Joel 3:12,13; Mat 13:30; Mark 4:29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:15 Then another angel came out of the Temple, crying out with a loud voice to the One seated on the cloud, “Put in your sickle and reap, for the hour to reap has come, because the harvest of the earth is fully ripe.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 15:6; Zec 5:6-11; Mat 13:36-42, 23:32; 1 Thes 2:16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:16 So the One seated on the cloud swung his sickle over the earth, and the earth was harvested.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:19; Rev 16:1-21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:17 Then another angel came out of the Temple in heaven, and he also had a sharp sickle.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 15:5,6; Rev 16:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:18 Then another angel—the one who has authority over fire—came out from the altar; and he called out with a loud voice to the one holding the sharp sickle, saying, “Put in your sickle and gather the grape clusters from the vineyard of the earth, because her grapes are ripe.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joel 3:12-14; Jer 25:30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:19 So the angel swung his sickle over the earth and gathered the clusters from the vineyard of the earth and threw them into the great winepress of the wrath of God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 63:1-6; Rev 19:15-21; Deut 32:32,33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:20 And the winepress was stomped on outside the city, and blood flowed from the winepress as high as a horse’s bridle for 1,600 stadia.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joel 3:13; Isa 63:1-3; Rev 19:14-21; Isa 34:5-7; Isa 66:24; Eze 39:17-21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 15:1 Then I saw another great and wonderful sign in heaven: seven angels who have seven plagues—the last ones, for with them God’s wrath is finished.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 26:21 Rev 15:7; Rev 14:10,19; Rev 16:19; Rev 19:15; Dan 12:6,7,11,12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 15:2 And I saw something like a sea of glass mixed with fire, and those who had overcome the beast and his image and the number of his name standing by the sea of glass, holding the harps of God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 5:8; Rev 14:2; Rev 19:1-7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 15:3 And they are singing the song of Moses the servant of God and the song of the Lamb, saying, “Great and wonderful are Your deeds, Adonai Elohei-Tzva’ot! Just and true are Your ways, O King of the nations!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 15:1-18; Deut 31:30, 32:44; Psa 92:5; 111:2; 139:14 Rev 17:14; Rev 19:16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 15:4 Who shall not fear and glorify Your name, O Lord? For You alone are Holy. All the nations shall come and worship before You, for Your righteous acts have been revealed!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 15:11; Ps 86:9; Isa 66:23; Jer 10:7 Rev 16:7; Rev 19:2; Psa 97:8; Psa 105:7; Isa 26:9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 15:5 After these things I looked, and the Temple of the Tent of Witness in heaven was opened.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 38:21 Rev 11:19; Exo 25:21; Num 1:50,53; Mat 27:51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 15:6 Out of the Temple came the seven angels having the seven plagues, dressed in pure bright linen and wearing wide gold sashes around their chests.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 26:21 Rev 1:13; Exo 28:5-8; Eze 44:17,18; Luke 24:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 15:7 Then one of the four living creatures gave the seven angels seven golden bowls full of the wrath of God, who lives forever and ever.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 37:16; Rev 4:9; Rev 10:6; 1 Thes 1:9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 15:8 And the Temple was filled with smoke from the glory of God and from His power. No one was able to enter the Temple until the seven angels’ seven plagues were finished.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 40:34-35; Lev 26:21; 1 Kings 8:10-11; 2 Chron 5:13-14; Isa 6:1-4 Rev 15:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:1 Then I heard a loud voice from the Temple saying to the seven angels, “Go and pour out on the earth the seven bowls of God’s wrath.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 75:8, 79:6; Jer 10:25; Ezek 22:31; Isa 51:17; Rev 14:9-11; Rev 15:7; 1 Sam 15:3,18; Eze 9:5-8; Eze 10:2; Mat 13:41,42; (compare bowls with 10 plagues: Exo 7-12)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:2 So the first angel went and poured out his bowl on the earth, and foul and painful boils came upon the people having the mark of the beast and worshiping his image.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 9:9-11; Deut 28:35; Psa 79:1-7; Zep 3:8; Rev 13:15-18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:3 Next the second angel poured out his bowl into the sea, and it became blood like that of a corpse; and every living thing in the sea died.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 7:17-25 Rev 8:9; Gen 7:22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:4 Then the third angel poured out his bowl into the rivers and the springs of water, and they became blood.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 7:17-21; Ps 78:44 Rev 16:5; Rev 14:7; Exo 7:20; Exo 8:5; Isa 50:2; Eze 35:8; ho 13:15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:5 Then I heard the angel of the waters saying, “Righteous are You—the Holy One, who is and who was—because You have passed these judgments.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 145:17 Rev 1:4,8; Rev 4:8; Rev 11:17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:6 For they have poured out the blood of kedoshim and prophets, and You have given them blood to drink—they are deserving!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 49:26 Rev 11:18; Rev 18:20; Jer 26:11,16; Luke 12:48; Heb 10:29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:7 Then I heard the altar saying, “Yes, Adonai Elohei-Tzva’ot, true and righteous are Your judgments!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 19:9; 145:17 Rev 13:10; Rev 14:10; Rev 19:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:8 The fourth angel poured out his bowl on the sun, and it was permitted to scorch people with fire.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:16; Rev 9:17,18; Rev 14:18; Psa 19:9; Mal 4:1; Jon 4:8; Mat 13:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:9 People were scorched with fierce heat, and they cursed the name of God—the One who has power over these plagues. But they did not repent, to give Him glory.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:13; Rev 14:7; Josh 7:19; Jer 13:6; Amo 4:6-12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:10 Then the fifth angel poured out his bowl on the throne of the beast, and his kingdom was plunged into darkness. People gnawed their tongues in pain&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 10:21-23 Rev 11:10; Mat 13:42,50; Mat 24:51; Luke 13:28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:11 and cursed the God of heaven because of their pains and their boils. But they did not repent of their deeds.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:9; 2 Tim 3:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:12 The sixth angel poured out his bowl over the great river Euphrates; and its water was dried up, to prepare the way for the kings from the east.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 15:8; 2 Sam 8:3; Isa 11:15-16; 41:2,3, 25; 46:11; Jer 51:36; Eze 38-39; Dan 11:43-45; Rev 9:14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:13 Then I saw—coming from the dragon’s mouth and from the beast’s mouth and from the false prophet’s mouth—three unclean spirits like frogs.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 8:6 Rev 19:20; Rev 20:10; Joel 3:11; Zep 3:8, Isa 43:9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:14 For they are demonic spirits performing miraculous signs, who go out to the kings of the whole world—to gather them for battle on the great Day of Elohei Tzva’ot.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 Kings 22:21-23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:15 “Behold, I am coming like a thief! How fortunate is the one who stays alert and keeps his clothes on, lest he walk around naked and they see his shamefulness.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:4,18; Exo 32:25; Isa 47:3; Eze 16:37; ho 2:3; Hab 2:15; 2 Cor 5:3; 1 Th 5:4;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:16 Then the spirits gathered the kings to the place called in Hebrew Har-Megiddo.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Judges 5:19; 2 Kings 23:29-30; 2 Chron 35:22; Zech 12:11 Judg 5:19; 2 King 23:29,30; Zec 12:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:17 The seventh angel poured out his bowl into the air. A loud voice came out of the Temple from the throne, saying, “It is done!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 10:6,7; Rev 21:6; Dan 12:7-13; John 19:30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:18 And there were flashes of lightning and rumblings and clashes of thunder and a great earthquake—such as never happened since mankind has been on the earth, so mighty was the quake.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:13; Dan 12:1; Zech 14:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:19 Then the great city was split into three parts, and the cities of the nations collapsed. Babylon the great was remembered before God, to force her to drink the cup of the wine of His furious wrath.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 25:15 Rev 14:8-10; Rev 18:5; Isa 49:26; Isa 51:17-23; Jer 25:15,16,26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:20 Every island fled away, and no mountains were to be found.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:14; Rev 20:11; Isa 2:14-17; Jer 4:23-25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:21 Enormous hail—about a hundred pounds each—falls from heaven on the people. And the people cursed God because of the plague of hail—so extreme was that plague.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 9:18-25 Rev 16:9,11; Isa 8:21; Job 2:9; Eze 38:22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:1 Then one of the seven angels holding the seven bowls came and spoke with me, saying, “Come, I will show you the sentencing of the great prostitute, who sits on many waters.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 51:7,13; Nah 3:4; Isa 1:21; Rev 14:18 (Isa 13-14 and Jer 50-51 are the Babylon chapters)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:2 The earth’s kings committed sexual immorality with her, and those who dwell on the earth got drunk with the wine of her immorality.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 23:17; Rev 14:8; Rev 18:3,9,23; Jer 51:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:3 So he carried me away in the Ruach into a wilderness, and I saw a woman sitting on a scarlet beast that was full of blasphemous names and had seven heads and ten horns.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:7,24; Rev 12:3,14; Rev 13:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:4 The woman was clothed in purple and scarlet, and adorned with gold and precious stones and pearls. She was holding a golden cup in her hand full of detestable things and the filth of her immorality,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 51:7; Ezek 28:13 Ezr 9:11; Lam 1:9; Eze 24:11,13; Eze 36:25; Rev 18:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:5 and on her forehead was written a name, a mystery: “Babylon the Great, the mother of prostitutes and the detestable things of the earth.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:9; Rev 19:2; Rev 22:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:6 And I saw the woman drunk with the blood of the kedoshim and with the blood of the witnesses of Yeshua. When I saw her, I was totally astounded.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hab 1:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:7 But the angel said to me, “Why are you astonished? I will tell you the mystery of the woman and of the beast that carries her, which has the seven heads and ten horns.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:1-6,8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:8 The beast that you saw was, and is not, and yet is about to rise up from the abyss and head for destruction. Those who dwell on the earth—whose names have not been written in the Book of Life from the foundation of the world—will be astonished when they see the beast, because he was and is not and is to come.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 32:32-33; Dan 12:1 Rev 13:1-4,11,12; (contrast Rev 1:4)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:9 This calls for a mind having wisdom. The seven heads are seven mountains on which the woman is seated. They are also seven kings—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:3,7,18; Rev 13:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:10 five have fallen, one is, the other has not yet come; and when he comes, he must remain a little while.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:11 The beast that was and is not—he himself is the eighth, and is one of the seven, and is heading for destruction.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:12 The ten horns that you saw are ten kings who have not yet received royal power, but receive authority as kings with the beast for one hour.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:24-25 Rev 12:3; Rev 13:1; Dan 2:40-43; Dan 7:7,8,20,24; Zec 1:18-21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:13 These kings are of one mind, and they give their power and authority to the beast.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:17; Isa 10:5-7; Eze 38:10; Acts 4:28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:14 They will make war against the Lamb, and the Lamb will overcome them—because He is Lord of lords and King of kings, and those with Him are called and chosen and faithful.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:10; Deut 10:17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:15 Then he tells me, “The waters that you saw, where the prostitute is seated, are peoples and multitudes and nations and tongues.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 51:11-14; Eze 16:37; Eze 23:35; Rev 10:11; Rev 11:9; Rev 13:7,8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:16 The ten horns that you saw, and the beast—these will hate the prostitute. They will make her desolate and naked, and devour her flesh and burn her up with fire.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 21:9 Rev 18:8,16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:17 For God has put it into their hearts to do His will, and to be of one mind, and to give their royal power to the beast until the words of God are fulfilled.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:11; Rev 10:7; Rev 15:1; Pro 19:21; Isa 45:17; Isa 46:10,11; Jer 27:6,7; Eze 38:16,17; Dan 12:7; John 10:35; John 12:39,40; John 19:24,28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17:18 And the woman that you saw is the great city exercising kingship over the kings of the earth.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:1 After these things, I saw another angel coming down from heaven, having great authority, and the earth was illuminated by his glory.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 43:2 Rev 21:23; Isa 60:1-3; Eze 43:2; Luke 17:24; 2 Thes 2:8; Dan 10:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:2 He cried out with a mighty voice, saying: “Fallen, fallen is Babylon the great! She has become a den for demons, a haunt for every unclean spirit and for every unclean bird and for every unclean and detestable beast.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 21:9; 34:13-15; Jer 50:30; 51:8, 51:37; Lev 11:13-19; Isa 13:19-22; Isa 14:23; Isa 21:8; Isa 34:11-15; Jer 50:39,40; Jer 51:37; Mark 5:3-5; Luke 8:27,28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:3 For all the nations have drunk of the wine of the fury of her immorality. The kings of the earth have committed sexual immorality with her, and the merchants of the earth grew rich off the power of her self-indulgence.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 51:7 Jer 51:34; Lam 4:5; Luke 7:25; Isa 48:20; Isa 52:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:4 Then I heard another voice from heaven saying, “Come out of her, my people, lest you participate in her sins and receive her plagues!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 52:11; Jer 50:8-9; 51:6-8, 45; Zech 2:10-11; Psa 50:18; Mat 23:30; 1 Tim 5:22; 2 John 1:11; 2 Cor 6:16; Luke 21:20-22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:5 For her sins have piled up to heaven, and God has remembered her crimes.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 41:9 Rev 16:19; On counting sin: Genesis 15:16 and 2 Kings 22:11-20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:6 Pay her back just as she has paid out, and give her back double for her deeds! In the cup she has mixed—mix a double dose for her!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 137:1-9; Jer 50:15, 29; Oba 1:15; Rev 14:10; Rev 16:19; Rev 17:2,4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:7 As she has exalted herself and indulged herself in luxury, so give her the same measure of torment and grief! For in her heart she says, ‘I sit as a queen—I am no widow; I shall never see grief.’&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 47:7-8; Zeph 2:15 Isa 47:7,8; Lam 1:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:8 For this reason her plagues will arrive in a single day—death and grief and famine—and she shall be burned down with fire. For mighty is Adonai Elohim who judges her!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 47:9; Jer 50:31-32 Rev 11:17; Job 9:19; Psa 62:11; Isa 27:1; Jer 50:31,34; 1 Cor 10:22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:9 Then the kings of the earth, who committed sexual immorality and indulged in luxury with her shall weep and wail over her when they see the smoke of her burning—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 50:46 Rev 18:18; Rev 14:11; Rev 19:3; Gen 19:28; Deut 29:23; Isa 13:19; Isa 30:33; Isa 34:9,10; Jer 50:40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:10 standing far off because of the terror of her torment, saying: “Alas, alas, O great city—O Babylon, the mighty city! For in a single hour your judgment has come!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 13:1 Rev 18:8,17,19; Jer 51:8,9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:11 And the merchants of the earth weep and mourn for her, because no one buys their merchandise anymore—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pro 3:14; Mat 22:5; John 2:16; 2 Pet 2:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:12 shipments of gold, silver, precious stones, and pearls; fine linen, purple, silk, and scarlet; all kinds of citron wood; all kinds of ivory products; all kinds of products made of costly wood, bronze, iron, and marble;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 27:12-25 1 King 10:11; 2ch 2:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:13 cinnamon, spice, incense, myrrh, and frankincense; wine, oil, fine flour, and wheat; cattle, sheep, horses, and chariots; and slaves—that is, human souls.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2 Pet 2:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:14 The fruit of your soul’s desire has gone from you, and all the expensive and beautiful things are lost to you—never again will people find them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Luke 12:20; Luke 16:25; Eze 26:17-18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:15 The merchants of these things, who became rich from her, shall stand far off for fear of her torment, weeping and mourning,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:11; Judg 18:23,24; Eze 27:31; Amo 5:16,17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:16 saying, “Alas, alas, O great city—clothed in fine linen and purple and scarlet, adorned with gold and precious stones and pearls!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:10,11; Rev 17:4; Luke 16:19-31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:17 For in a single hour so much wealth has been ruined!” And every ship captain and passenger, sailors and all who make their living at sea, stood at a distance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:11; Isa 23:14; Eze 27:27-36; jon 1:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:18 and were crying out, seeing the smoke of her burning, saying, ‘What city is like the great city?’&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:10; Rev 13:4; Isa 23:8,9; Jer 51:37; Eze 27:30-32&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:19 And they threw dust on their heads and were crying out, weeping and mourning, “Alas, alas, O great city—in her all who had ships at sea grew rich from her wealth! For in a single hour has she been ruined!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:20 Rejoice over her, O heaven, and you kedoshim, emissaries and prophets! For God has judged her condemnation of you!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 51:48 Rev 6:10; Rev 19:2; Deut 32:42; Psa 18:47; Psa 94:1; Isa 26:21; Luke 11:49,50; Luke 18:7,8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:21 Then a mighty angel picked up a stone like a great millstone and threw it into the sea, saying: “So shall Babylon, the great city, be thrown down with violence, never to be found again!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 51:63-64 Rev 18:22; Rev 12:8; Rev 16:20; Rev 20:11; Job 20:8; Psa 37:36; Eze 26:21; Dan 11:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:22 And the sound of harpists and musicians, flautists and trumpeters, shall never be heard in you again! And the craftsman of any craft shall never be found in you again! And the sound of a mill shall never be heard in you again!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 13:20; Jer 25:10; Ezek 26:13 Isa 24:8,9; Jer 7:34; Jer 16:9; Jer 25:10; Jer 33:11; Eze 26:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:23 And the light of a lamp shall never shine in you again! And the voice of the bridegroom and bride shall never be heard in you again! For your businessmen were the tycoons of the world, for all the nations were deceived by your sorcery!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 7:34; 16:9; 25:10; Nah 3:4; Luke 17:26-29; Rev 12:9; Rev 13:13-16; Rev 17:2,5; Rev 21:8; Rev 22:15; 2 King 9:22; Isa 47:9; Nah 3:4; Acts 8:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:24 And in her was found the blood of the prophets and kedoshim and all those slaughtered on the earth.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 51:49; Rev 6:10, 16:6, 17:6, 19:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 19-22 References and Allusions</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/ref19-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/ref19-22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 14,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h3 id=&#34;chap-19-22&#34;&gt;Chap 19-22&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation (TLV)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:1 After these things, I heard something like the loud voice of a great multitude in heaven, shouting: “Halleluyah! Salvation and glory and power belong to our God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:10,11; Rev 5:9-13; Rev 7:10-12; Rev 11:15; Rev 12:10; 1ch 29:11; Psa 3:8; jon 2:9; Mat 6:13; 1 Tim 1:16,17; Ps 104:35&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:2 For His judgments are true and just. For He has judged the great prostitute who corrupted the earth with her whoring, and has avenged the blood of His servants caused by her hand.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 32:43; Ps 119:137; Jer 51:48 Rev 6:10; Rev 18:20,24; Deut 32:35,43; Psa 19:9; Num 35:19; Rom 12:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:3 And a second time they shouted, “Halleluyah! The smoke from her goes up forever and ever!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 34:9-10; Jer 51:48 Rev 14:11; Rev 18:9,18; Gen 19:28; Isa 34:10; Jude 1:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:4 Then the twenty-four elders and the four living creatures fell down and worshiped God who is seated on the throne, saying, “Amen! Halleluyah!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:1; Psa 106:48; Psa 115:12-13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:5 Then a voice came from the throne, saying: “Praise our God, all you His servants and all who fear Him, both the small and the great!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 22:23; 134:1; 135:1 Rev 11:18; Rev 20:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:6 Then I heard something like the voice of a great multitude—like the roar of rushing waters or like the rumbling of powerful thunder—saying, “Halleluyah! For Adonai Elohei-Tzva’ot reigns!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 93:1; 97:1; Ezek 1:24; 43:2; Dan 10:6 Rev 11:15-18; Rev 12:10; Rev 21:22; Psa 47:2,7; Psa 93:1; Psa 97:1,12; Psa 99:1; Isa 52:7; Mat 6:13; Ex 15:18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:7 Let us rejoice and be glad and give the glory to Him! For the wedding of the Lamb has come, and His bride has made herself ready,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 52:1; Isa 25:6-9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:8 She was given fine linen to wear, bright and clean! For the fine linen is the righteous deeds of the kedoshim.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:13,14; Psa 132:9; (contrast Rev 17:4); Lev 16:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:9 Then the angel tells me, “Write: How fortunate are those who have been invited to the wedding banquet of the Lamb!” He also tells me, “These are the true words of God.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:11; Rev 21:5; Rev 22:6; 1 Tim 1:15; 1 Tim 4:9; 2 Tim 2:11; Titus 3:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:10 Then I fell down at his feet and worshiped him. But he said to me, “See that you do not do that—for I am only a fellow servant with you and your brothers and sisters who hold to the testimony of Yeshua. Worship God! For the testimony of Yeshua is the Spirit of Prophesy.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Luke 24:25-27,44; John 5:39; Acts 3:12-18; Acts 10:43; Acts 13:27; Rom 3:21,22; 1 Pet 1:10-12; 2 Pet 1:19-21; Col 2:18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:11 Then I saw heaven opened, and behold, a white horse! The One riding on it is called Faithful and True, and He judges and makes war in righteousness.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 18:10; 45:3-4; Isa 11:4-5; Ezek 1:1 Rev 15:3-7; Psa 45:3-7; Psa 50:6; Psa 72:2-4; Psa 96:13; Psa 98:9; Psa 99:4; Isa 11:3-5; Isa 32:1; Isa 45:21; Isa 63:1-5; Jer 23:5,6; Jer 33:15; Zec 9:9,10; Heb 7:1,2; Jer 42:5; Titus 2:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:12 His eyes are like a flame of fire, and many royal crowns are on His head. He has a name written that no one knows except Himself.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:16; Rev 2:17; Rev 3:12; Gen 32:29; Exo 23:21; Judg 13:18; Isa 9:6; Mat 11:27; Luke 10:22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:13 He is clothed in a robe dipped in blood, and the name by which He is called is “the Word of God.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 63:3; John 1:1,14; 1 John 1:1; 1 John 5:7; Rev 5:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:14 And the armies of heaven, clothed in fine linen, white and clean, were following Him on white horses.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:8; Rev 4:4; Rev 7:9; Mat 28:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:15 From His mouth comes a sharp sword—so that with it He may strike down the nations—and He shall rule them with an iron rod, and He treads the winepress of the furious wrath of Elohei-Tzva’ot.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 2:8-9; Isa 11:4; 63:3-6 Rev 14:17-20; Isa 63:2-6; Isa 49:2; Hosea 6:5; Isaiah 11:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:16 On His robe and on His thigh He has a name written, “King of kings, and Lord of lords.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 10:17 Rev 17:14; Psa 72:11; Pro 8:15,16; Dan 2:47; Phil 2:9-11; 1 Tim 6:15; 1 Sam 24:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:17 Then I saw a single angel standing in the sun, and with a loud voice he cried out to all the birds flying high in the sky, “Come, gather for the great banquet of God—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 34:6-7; Ezek 39:17 Rev 19:21; Isa 56:9; Jer 12:9; Eze 39:17-20; Gen 15:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:18 to eat the flesh of kings and the flesh of generals and the flesh of mighty men, the flesh of horses and those riding on them, the flesh of all men, both free and slave, both small and great!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 34:6-7; Ezek 39:18 Rev 6:15; Rev 13:16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:19 Also I saw the beast and the kings of the earth and their armies gathered together to make war against the One who sat on the horse and against His army.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 2:2; Joel 3:9-11 Rev 19:11-14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:20 Then the beast was captured, and along with him the false prophet who had performed the signs before him by which he deceived those who had received the mark of the beast, as well as those who had worshiped his image. These two were thrown alive into the lake of fire burning with brimstone.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 30:33; Dan 7:11 Rev 14:10; Rev 21:8; Gen 19:24; Deut 29:23; Job 18:15; Psa 11:6; Isa 30:33; Isa 34:9; Eze 38:22; Mt 25:41&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:21 The rest were killed with the sword coming out of the mouth of the One riding on the horse. And all the birds gorged themselves with their flesh.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 39:19-20 Rev 19:17,18; Rev 17:16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:1 Then I saw an angel coming down from heaven, holding in his hand the key to the abyss and a great chain.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2 Pet 2:4; Jude 1:6; Rev 9:1-3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:2 He seized the dragon—the ancient serpent, who is the devil and satan—and bound him for a thousand years.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:1, 13-14; Isa 24:21-22 Rev 9:11; Rev 12:9,13,15,17; Rev 13:2,4; Job 1:7; Job 2:1,2; 1 Pet 5:8; 2 Pet 2:4; Jude 1:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:3 He also threw him into the abyss and locked and sealed it over him, so that he would not deceive the nations any longer, until the thousand years were completed. After these things, he must be released for a short while.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:7-10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:4 Then I saw thrones, and people sat upon them—those to whom authority to judge was given. And I saw the souls of those who had been beheaded because of their testimony for Yeshua and because of the word of God. They had not worshiped the beast or his image, nor had they received his mark on their forehead or on their hand. And they came to life and reigned with the Messiah for a thousand years.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:9, 22, 27, 12:2 Rev 5:9; Rev 11:11,15; Dan 2:44; Dan 7:18,27; Mat 19:28; Rom 8:17; Rom 11:15; 1 Cor 6:2; 2 Tim 2:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:5 The rest of the dead did not come to life until the thousand years were completed. This is the first resurrection.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 26:14 Rev 11:11,15; Eze 37:2-14; Rom 11:15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:6 How fortunate and holy is the one who has a share in the first resurrection! Over such the second death has no authority, but they shall be kohanim of God and the Messiah, and they shall reign with Him for a thousand years.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 19:6; Isa 26:19 Rev 20:4; Rev 1:6; Rev 5:10; Rom 8:17; 2 Tim 2:12; Rev 1:6; Rev 22:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:7 When the thousand years has ended, satan shall be released from his prison,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:8 and he shall come out to deceive the nations at the four corners of the earth, Gog and Magog, to gather them for the battle. Their number is like the sand of the sea.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 2:1; Ezek 7:2, 38:2-3; 39:1, 6 Judg 7:12; 1 Sam 13:5; 1 King 4:20; Isa 10:22; Jer 33:22; Heb 11:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:9 And they came up on the broad plain of the earth and surrounded the camp of the kedoshim and the beloved city—but fire fell from heaven and consumed them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 23:14; 2 Kings 1:9-12; Psa 87:2;  Ezek 38:22; 39:6 Rev 11:5; Rev 13:13; Gen 19:24; Exo 9:23,24; Lev 10:2,3; Num 11:1; Num 16:35; 2 King 1:10-15; Psa 97:3; Psa 106:18; Isa 30:33; Isa 37:36; Eze 38:22; Eze 39:6; Luke 9:54; Luke 17:29; 2 Thes 1:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:10 And the devil who deceived them was thrown into the lake of fire and brimstone, where the beast and the false prophet are too, and they shall be tortured day and night forever and ever.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 14:10; Mat 25:41,46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:11 Then I saw a great white throne, and the One seated on it. The earth and heaven fled from His presence, but no place was found for them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 2:35 Rev 12:8; Job 9:6; Romans 2:16; Romans 14:10; 2 Cor 5:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:12 And I saw the dead—the great and the small—standing before the throne. The books were opened, and another book was opened—the Book of Life. And the dead were judged according to what was written in the books, according to their deeds.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 18:20-23; Ex 32:32-33; Ps 62:12; 69:28; Dan 7:10 Rev 20:13; Rev 2:23; Rev 22:12; Psa 28:4; Psa 62:12; Pro 24:12,29; Ecc 12:14; Jer 17:10; Jer 32:19; Mal 3:18; Mat 16:27; Luke 10:26-28; John 5:27-29; Rom 2:6; 2 Cor 5:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:13 The sea gave up the dead that were in it, and death and Sheol gave up the dead in them. Then they were each judged, each one of them, according to their deeds.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mt 25:46; Hos 13:14; Rev 20:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:14 Then death and Sheol were thrown into the lake of fire. This is the second death—the lake of fire.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 25:8; Rev 20:6; Rev 21:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:15 And if anyone was not found written in the Book of Life, he was thrown into the lake of fire.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 32:32-33; Dan 12:1 Rev 19:20; Mat 25:41; Mark 9:43-48&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:1 Then I saw a new heaven and a new earth; for the first heaven and the first earth had passed away, and the sea was no more.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 65:17; 66:22 Rev 13:1; Isa 27:1; Isa 57:20; Dan 7:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:2 I also saw the holy city—the New Jerusalem—coming down out of heaven from God, prepared as a bride adorned for her husband.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:7,8; Psa 45:9-14; Isa 54:5; Isa 61:10; Isa 62:4; John 3:29; 2 Cor 11:2; Eph 5:25-27,30-32&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:3 I also heard a loud voice from the throne, saying, “Behold, the dwelling of God is among men, and He shall tabernacle among them. They shall be His people, and God Himself shall be among them and be their God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 26:11-12; Ezek 37:27 Zec 8:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:4 He shall wipe away every tear from their eyes, and death shall be no more. Nor shall there be mourning or crying or pain any longer, for the former things have passed away.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 25:8; 35:10; 51:11; 65:19 Rev 21:1; Psa 144:4; Mat 24:35; 1 Cor 7:31; 2 Cor 6:17; 2 Pet 3:10; 1 John 2:17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:5 And the One seated upon the throne said, “Behold, I am making all things new!” Then He said, “Write, for these words are trustworthy and true.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:6 Then He said to me, “It is done! I am the Alpha and the Omega, the Beginning and the End. To the thirsty I will freely give from the spring of the water of life.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hos 14:4; Rom 3:24; Rom 8:32; 1 Cor 2:12; 1 Cor 3:5,12,21; 1 John 5:4,5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:7 The one who overcomes shall inherit these things, and I will be his God and he shall be My son.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:3; Zec 8:8; Rom 8:15-17; Heb 8:10; 1 John 3:1-3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:8 But for the cowardly and faithless and detestable and murderers and sexually immoral and sorcerers and idolaters and all liars—their lot is in the lake that burns with fire and brimstone, which is the second death.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:9 Then came one of the seven angels holding the seven bowls full of the seven final plagues, and he spoke with me, saying, “Come, I will show you the bride, the wife of the Lamb.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 26:21 Rev 21:2; Rev 19:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:10 Then he carried me away in the Ruach to a great and high mountain, and he showed me the holy city, Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 40:2 Rev 21:2; Eze 40:1-49; Eze 48:15-22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:11 having the glory of God—her radiance like a most precious stone, like a jasper, sparkling like crystal.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 60:1-2; Ezek 43:2 Rev 21:18; Rev 4:6; Rev 22:1; Job 28:17; Eze 1:22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:12 She had a great, high wall, with twelve gates, and above the gates twelve angels. On the gates were inscribed the names of the twelve tribes of Bnei-Yisrael—&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:4-8; Num 2:2-32; Acts 26:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:13 three gates on the east, three gates on the north, three gates on the south, and three gates on the west.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eze 48:31-34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:14 And the wall of the city had twelve foundations, and on them the twelve names of the twelve emissaries of the Lamb.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18:20; Mat 10:2-4; Mat 16:18; 1 Cor 3:10,11; Gal 2:9; Eph 2:20; Eph 3:5; Eph 4:11; Jude 1:17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:15 The angel speaking with me had a gold measuring rod to measure the city and its gates and walls.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 40:3, 5 Rev 11:1,2; Exo 40:3-5; Eze 41:1-5; Zec 2:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:16 The city is laid out as a square—its length the same as its width. He measured the city with the rod—12,000 stadia. Its length and width and height are equal.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eze 48:8-19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:17 He also measured its wall—144 cubits by human measurement, which is also an angel’s measurement.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 7:4; Rev 14:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:18 The material of the city’s wall was jasper, while the city was pure gold, clear as glass.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:11,21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:19 The foundations of the city wall were decorated with every kind of precious stone—the first foundation was jasper; the second, sapphire; the third, chalcedony; the fourth, emerald;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exo 28:17-21; Exo 29:10-14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:20 the fifth, sardonyx; the sixth, carnelian; the seventh, yellow topaz; the eighth; beryl; the ninth, topaz; the tenth, chrysoprase; the eleventh, jacinth; the twelfth, amethyst.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:21 And the twelve gates were twelve pearls—each of the gates was from a single pearl. And the street of the city was pure gold, transparent as glass.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:11,18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:22 I saw no temple in her, for its Temple is Adonai Elohei-Tzva’ot and the Lamb.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;John 2:19-21; John 10:30; Col 1:19; Col 2:9; Heb 9:1-12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:23 And the city has no need for the sun or the moon to shine on it, for the glory of God lights it up, and its lamp is the Lamb.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 60:19-20 Luke 2:32; John 1:4,9,14,18; John 5:23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:24 The nations shall walk by its light, and the kings of the earth bring their glory into it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 60:3-5, 16 Psa 72:10,11; Isa 60:3-10,13; Isa 66:11,12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:25 Its gates shall never be shut by day, for there shall be no night there!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 60:11; Zech 14:7 Rev 22:5; Isa 60:20; Zec 14:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:26 And they shall bring into it the glory and honor of the nations.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 60:5, 16 Rev 21:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:27 And nothing unholy shall ever enter it, nor anyone doing what is detestable or false, but only those written in the Book of Life.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 52:1; Ezek 44:9; Zech 14:21 Rev 3:5; Rev 13:8; Rev 20:12,15; Phil 4:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:1 Then the angel showed me a river of the water of life—bright as crystal, flowing from the throne of God and of the Lamb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 46:4; Ezek 47:1; Zech 14:8 Rev 3:21; Rev 4:5; Rev 5:6,13; Rev 7:10,11,17; John 14:16-18; John 15:26; John 16:7-15; Acts 1:4,5; Acts 2:33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:2 down the middle of the city’s street. On either side of the river was a tree of life, bearing twelve kinds of fruit, yielding its fruit each month; and the leaves of the tree were for the healing of the nations.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 2:9; 3:22-24; Ezek 47:12 Rev 21:24; Psa 147:3; Isa 6:10; Isa 57:18,19; Jer 17:14; Eze 47:8-11; ho 14:4; Mal 4:2; Luke 4:18; 1 Pet 2:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:3 No longer will there be any curse. The throne of God and of the Lamb shall be in the city, and His servants shall serve Him.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:17-19; Zech 14:11 Rev 7:15; John 12:26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:4 They shall see His face, and His name shall be on their foreheads.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 17:15; Ezek 9:4 Rev 3:12; Rev 14:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:5 Night shall be no more, and people will have no need for lamplight or sunlight—for Adonai Elohim will shine on them. And they shall reign forever and ever!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 60:19; Dan 7:18, 22, 27; Zech 14:7 Rev 3:21; Rev 11:15; Dan 7:18,27; Mat 25:34,46; Rom 5:17; 2 Tim 2:12; 1 Pet 1:3,4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:6 He said to me, “These words are trustworthy and true! Adonai, the God of the spirits of the prophets, has sent His angel to show His servants what must happen soon.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:7; Gen 41:32; 1 Cor 7:29; 2 Pet 3:8,9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:7 Behold, I am coming soon! How fortunate is the one who keeps the words of the prophecy of this book.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:9; Rev 1:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:8 I, John, am the one hearing and seeing these things. And when I heard and saw them, I fell down to worship at the feet of the angel showing me these things.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:10,19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:9 But he tells me, “See that you do not do that! I am a fellow servant with you and your brothers the prophets and those keeping the words of this book. Worship God!”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:10; Rev 9:20; Rev 14:7; Rev 15:4; Exo 34:14; 2 King 17:36; Psa 45:11; Mat 4:9; Luke 4:7; John 4:22,23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:10 Then he tells me, “Do not seal up the words of the prophecy of this book, for the time is near.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 8:26; 12:4, 9 Rev 1:3; Isa 13:6; Eze 12:23; Rom 13:12; 2 Thes 2:3; 1 Pet 4:7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:11 Let the evildoer still do evil, and the filthy still be filthy, and the righteous still do righteousness, and the holy still be holy.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ezek 3:27; Dan 12:10 Rev 22:3; Rev 7:13-15; Job 17:9; Pro 4:18; Mat 5:6; Eph 5:27; Col 1:22; Jude 1:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:12 Behold, I am coming soon, and My reward is with Me, to pay back each one according to his deeds.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ps 62:12; Isa 40:10; 62:11 Rev 20:12; Mat 16:27; Rom 2:6-11; Rom 14:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:13 “I am the Alpha and the Omega, the First and the Last, the Beginning and the End.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 44:6 Rev 1:8,11; Rev 21:6; Isa 41:4; Isa 44:6; Isa 48:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:14 How fortunate are those who wash their robes, so that they may have the right to the Tree of Life and may enter through the gates into the city.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 2:9; 3:22-24; Prov 11:30 Rev 21:27; John 10:7,9; John 14:6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:15 Outside are the dogs and the sorcerers and the sexually immoral and the murderers and the idolaters, and everyone who loves and practices falsehood.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 23:18 Rev 21:8,27; 1 King 22:8,21-23; Isa 9:15,16; Jer 5:31; John 3:18-21; John 8:46; 2 Thes 2:10-12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:16 I, Yeshua, have sent My angel to testify these things to you for My communities. I am the Root and the Offspring of David, the Bright and Morning Star.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:28; Num 24:17; Mat 2:2,7-10; Luke 1:78; 2 Pet 1:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:17 The Ruach and the bride say, “Come!” And let the one who hears say, “Come!” Let the one who is thirsty come—let the one who wishes freely take the water of life!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rom 3:24; 1 Cor 2:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:18 I testify to everyone who hears the words of the prophecy of this book. If anyone adds to them, God shall add to him the plagues that are written in this book;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 4:2; 12:32 Rev 14:10,11; Rev 15:1; Rev 16:1; Rev 19:20; Rev 20:10,15; Lev 26:18,24,25,28,37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:19 and if anyone takes away from the words of the book of this prophecy, God shall take away his share in the Tree of Life and the Holy City, which are written in this book.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 29:19-20 Rev 22:12; Rev 1:3; Rev 2:7,11,17,26; Rev 3:4,5,12,21; Rev 7:9-17; Rev 14:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:20 The One giving testimony to these things says, “Yes! I am coming soon!” Amen! Come, Lord Yeshua!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:18; so 8:14; Isa 25:9; John 21:25; 2 Tim 4:8; Heb 9:28; 2 Pet 3:12-14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:21 May the grace of the Lord Yeshua be with all!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:4; Rom 1:7; Rom 16:20,24; 2 Cor 13:14; Eph 6:23,24; 2 Thes 3:18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation Finishes what Genesis Started</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/revelation-finishes-what-genesis-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/revelation-finishes-what-genesis-started/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 12,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;In Hebrew, the name for &amp;ldquo;Genesis&amp;rdquo; (Hebrew בְּרֵאשִׁית) means &amp;ldquo;in the beginning.&amp;rdquo; Below is a partial list of things that had their beginning in Genesis but have their end, fulfillment, or completion in Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Topic&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Genesis&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Earth Created&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 1:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Earth Passed away&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sun, moon, stars&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 1:14-16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 6:12; Rev 8:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Earth’s government&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Earth’s judgment&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 16:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sun to govern Day&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 1:16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No need of sun&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Darkness called night&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 1:5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No night there&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Waters He called seas&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 1:10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No more sea&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A river for earth’s blessing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 2:10-14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A river for New Earth&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:1-2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Man in God’s Image&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 1:26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Man Headed by Satan’s Image&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Entrance of sin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;End of sin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21, Rev 22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Curse pronounced&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:14-17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No more curse&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Death entered&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No more death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 21:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cherubim first mentioned&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cherubim final mention&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Man driven out of Eden&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Man restored&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tree of life guarded&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Access to Tree of life&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sorrow &amp;amp; suffering enter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No more sorrow&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22:4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Religion, art, and science separated from God&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Religion, art, and science judged, destroyed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nimrod founds Babylon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 10:8-10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Babylon falls&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 17, Rev 18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;God’s Flood to Destroy evil generation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 6-9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Satan’s flood to Destroy elect generation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A bow: God’s promise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 9:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A bow for remembrance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 4:3, Rev 10:1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sodom &amp;amp; Egypt: Corruption, judgement&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 13, 19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;“Sodom &amp;amp; Egypt”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 11:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A confederation vs. Abraham’s people&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A confederation vs. Abraham’s Seed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A bride for Abraham’s son&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A bride for Abraham’s Seed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Marriage of First Adam&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 2:18-23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Marriage of Last Adam&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promised Seed Possess gate of enemies&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 29:8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promised Seed possessing Earth&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Man’s dominion ceased and Satan’s begun&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Satan’s domain ended and man’s restored&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seven Letters Extra</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/a3-seven-letters-extra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/r04/a3-seven-letters-extra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#each-letter-has-seven-design-elements&#34;&gt;Each Letter has Seven Design Elements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#each-letter-has-a-pauline-epistle-counterpart&#34;&gt;Each Letter has a Pauline Epistle Counterpart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#each-letter-has-a-matthew-13-counterpart&#34;&gt;Each Letter has a Matthew 13 Counterpart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#layers-of-interpretation&#34;&gt;Layers of Interpretation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#seven-letters-as-prophecy-of-the-gentile-church&#34;&gt;Seven letters as prophecy of the Gentile church&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 14,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The Seven Letters have a number of different layers of application.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;each-letter-has-seven-design-elements&#34;&gt;Each Letter has Seven Design Elements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Elements&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Name of the Church&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The underlying meaning of the town&amp;rsquo;s name is also significant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Attribute of Jesus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ties back to Revelation 1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Commendation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;This is omitted for Sardis and Laodicea&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Concern&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;This is omitted for Smyrna and Philadelphia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exhortation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Usually, what the believers are to do in response to the concern&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promise to the Overcomer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CJB: &amp;ldquo;wins the victory&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;ldquo;Those who have ears, let them hear&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elements six and seven are inverted starting with Thyatira.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will include a summary in the main commentary sections as we discuss each city&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;ecclesia&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;each-letter-has-a-pauline-epistle-counterpart&#34;&gt;Each Letter has a Pauline Epistle Counterpart&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you know Paul also wrote seven letters to seven messianic communities?  He wrote 13 letters, three of which were written to pastors and three of them have two letters.  If we exclude those written to pastors and combine those who received two letters, we are left with (wait for it&amp;hellip;) seven!  According to Missler, thematically, Paul&amp;rsquo;s seven letters roughly (though not always perfectly) correspond with Jesus&amp;rsquo; seven letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Paul&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First love/devotion not just doctrine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Smyrna&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philipians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joy through suffering/endure persecution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pergamos&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Corinthians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The carnal church / married to the world / need to be pure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thyatria&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Galatians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A call out of religiousity/paganism&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sardis&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Romans&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Devotion to Orthodoxy but must be with love&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thessalonians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hope in second coming/missionary outreach&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Laodicea&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Colossians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Only a few miles apart, instructed to trade with each other, and there are Greek phrases that only occur in the New Testament in these two letters/ prosperous compromise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;each-letter-has-a-matthew-13-counterpart&#34;&gt;Each Letter has a Matthew 13 Counterpart&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Missler, thematically, Jesus&amp;rsquo; seven parables of the Kingdom roughly (though not always perfectly) correspond with Jesus&amp;rsquo; seven letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matthew 13&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sower/Four Soils&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tested those could be similar to the first three soils&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Smyrna&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tares/Wheat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Adversary/enemy has infiltrated&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pergamos&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mustard Seed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;We assume the mustard &amp;ldquo;tree&amp;rdquo; is bad (though this is debated). Generally, mustard plants only grow to a few feet tall - one in which the birds of the air (also typically evil) could lodge would mean it&amp;rsquo;s become a monstrosity. Pergamos became married to the world and followed the way of Balaam. They followed their flesh instead of God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thyatria&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Woman &amp;amp; Leaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Assuming the leaven is also used negatively in Matthew 13 (as leaven usually represents sin in the Old Testament), Jezebel contaminates the community just like the woman with leaven introduces sin into the batch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sardis&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Treasure in Field&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The treasure is hidden.  Most don&amp;rsquo;t see it.  A few found worthy will be clothed in white&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pearl of Great Price&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Persevere through trials (a pearl grows in response to an introduce irritation;); sold out for Jesus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Laodicea&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dragnet&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The judgment.  Separation of Good and Bad (good are kept, bad are cast away/vomitted out)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;layers-of-interpretation&#34;&gt;Layers of Interpretation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholars have pointed out at least five different layers of interpretation/application of the Seven Letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Application&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Immediate, first century context, real fellowships with real struggles&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Admonitory to all fellowships&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The things the seven fellowships struggled with are the same things all fellowships struggle with (but not to say that these are the ONLY things fellowships struggle with)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Personal - he who as an ear&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The things the seven fellowships struggled with are the same things you and I struggle with (though not exclusively)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reflexive - did the fellowships see themselves the way Jesus saw them?  Do we see ourselves the way He sees us?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;History of the Gentile Church &lt;em&gt;in order&lt;/em&gt;, from the Apostolic Church (Ephesus) in the first century, to the Apostate Church (Laodicea) today&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;See discussion below.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;seven-letters-as-prophecy-of-the-gentile-church&#34;&gt;Seven letters as prophecy of the Gentile church&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing the Seven Letters as a prophetic history of the gentile church is an interesting theory, though proponents must admit they are entirely speculating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can&amp;rsquo;t prove it from Scripture nor can we believe this interpretation would have remotely entered the minds of the original recipients.  Also, it is potentially myopic as it entirely ignores the history of the &lt;em&gt;Eastern&lt;/em&gt; church, including Russian/Greek/Armenian Orthodox, Arab Christian, Coptic, African and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll present it here since the theory is very widely accepted, especially among Protestant commentators (all of whom naturally see themselves as being in &amp;ldquo;Philadelphia&amp;rdquo; not &amp;ldquo;Laodicea&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who hold the belief that the seven letters spell out the history of the Gentile church would see the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Age&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apostolic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;From Resurrection through late 1st century or the time of the Jewish/Gentile split in the 2nd century&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Smyrna&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Persecuted&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jewish and Roman persecutions - late 1st/early 2nd through early 4th century&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pergamos&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Constantine/Byzantine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The church became the state religion (&amp;ldquo;married to the world&amp;rdquo;) in a way that Jesus never intended for it to be&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thyatria&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Catholic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Medieval period, at the lastest, dated to &amp;ldquo;great schism&amp;rdquo; of 1054 or earliest, to St. Benedict in 530, who is considered the father of the European monasticism.  The church became mixed with extra-biblical traditions, &amp;ldquo;queen of heaven&amp;rdquo; etc.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sardis&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reformation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16th century.  You have a &amp;ldquo;name&amp;rdquo; (denomination) that you are alive, but are dead&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Missionary/evangelical&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18th century&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Laodicea&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Comfortable/apostate&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;late 20th century&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chuck Missler, &lt;em&gt;The Book of Revelation Handbook&lt;/em&gt; (Koinonia House, 2020), 97–104.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
