<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Talmidim Way</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu59ba181d12b9f86a6b06fa85c0a2a62a_406614_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Talmidim Way</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>1. The Logos</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/01-the_logos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/01-the_logos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-11&#34;&gt;John 1:1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-12-6&#34;&gt;John 1:2-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-17&#34;&gt;John 1:7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-18-13&#34;&gt;John 1:8-13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-114-15&#34;&gt;John 1:14-15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-11618&#34;&gt;John 1:16:18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#study-questions&#34;&gt;Study Questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#image-gallery&#34;&gt;Image Gallery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/f7OZlMhy3GI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gospels are Jewish documents. 1st Century “Christianity” was a Jewish sect.
John is often viewed as contrasting the correct way of Christianity with the incorrect way of Judaism, but this represents what is called an anachronistic fallacy, often shortened to “Anachronism” - misappropriation of concepts and ideas in time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often see anachronisms in period piece movies.  Someone will be wearing a digital watch in a movie set in the 18th century.  at the 1955 enchantment under the sea dance, Marty McFly is playing a 1958 gibson guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a challenge to restrain our own presuppositions, our set of established beliefs, when we read the Bible.  It is natural to assume a biblical speaker to affirm our presuppositions in order to justify our positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An overarching anachronistic fallacy Many commentators commit is to take what is called “the parting of the ways” between Judaism and Christianity that occurred much later (2nd-4th centuries CE) and reading it back into this text in the 1st century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, since it had not occurred yet, there is absolutely no way John or any other biblical writer could have the split between Judaism and Christianity in view when they were writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is called eisegesis - reading into the text.  Modern conservative scholars would all agree that eisegesis is bad yet many of them do it almost automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we strive for is EXEGESIS, understanding the text IN CONTEXT to extract what the author was saying.  To do this, we must first realize the gospels are Jewish documents written within a historical context of 2nd Temple Judaism.  The audience were Jewish Christ followers together with many non-Jews who had joined a Jewish sect..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early church fathers affirmed John’s authorship of this Gospel strongly and unanimously. Some of the fathers claim to have personally known those who knew John in Ephesus in his later years, thus making a direct link to the tradition of Johannine authorship. The evangelist John is shown here with the symbol of an eagle, the one of the four living creatures which is traditionally associated with him (Ezekiel 1:5-10 and Revelation 4:6-7).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-11&#34;&gt;John 1:1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;1 In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logos in the normal sense means “word or speech”.  In this prologue, John uses it in the mystical sense.  He alludes directly to the beginning of the Torah and the beginning of creation.  He starts this with an intentional allusion to Genesis 1:1 “In the beginning”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-12-6&#34;&gt;John 1:2-6&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;2 He was in the beginning with God. 3 All things were made through him, and without him was not anything made that was made. 4 In him was life, and the life was the light of men. 5 The light shines in the darkness, and the darkness has not overcome it. 6 There was a man sent from God, whose name was John.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall the first act of Creation. “and God said Let there be Light, and there was light.”&lt;br&gt;
In verse 4  John declares that this life had always been available through God’s word, which is the same word that he identifies with Jesus (IVP). 
In John 1:5, The divine light from the first day of creation shines once again into the dark world of man, signifying a new creation (COM)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There came a man, sent from God, whose name was John
Excavations in the early 2000s revealed this cave west of Jerusalem near Ein Kerem. Archaeologist Shimon Gibson identified it with the ministry of John the Baptist on the basis of a stick-figure drawing of a man inside the cave. Gibson’s theory was published in The Cave of John the Baptist (Doubleday, 2004).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For responses, see that by James F. Strange (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biblicalarchaeology.org/reviews/the-cave-of-john-the-baptist/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.biblicalarchaeology.org/reviews/the-cave-of-john-the-baptist/&lt;/a&gt;) and Todd Bolen (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bibleplaces.com/cave-of-john-the-baptist/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.bibleplaces.com/cave-of-john-the-baptist/)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the writing of the church father Origen (AD 185-254), the location of John’s baptizing at Bethany beyond the Jordan has been located at a point near the river opposite Jericho.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-17&#34;&gt;John 1:7&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;7  He came as a witness, to bear witness about the light, that all might believe through him&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some scholars note that John has a “legal” feel.  As you read John&amp;rsquo;s gospel, be on the lookout for the terms Witness, Testimony, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, John is interested not only in establishing Jesus’ credentials, he is also interested in “convicting” the corrupt Jerusalem establishment on the grounds of usurption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/01-the_logos_files/01.Picture7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;30%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discovered in Cave 4 of Qumran in the early 1950s, this text contains five biblical verses that focused on the coming of the Messiah. This artifact was photographed in the Amman Museum.&lt;br&gt;
A few scholars suspect John may have been part of the Essene sect, but in any case he was definitely influenced by them.  The Essenes believed that the forces controlling Jerusalem and the Temple were usurpers and priests of darkness.  They juxtaposed darkness and light just as John does throughout his writings.   “in the Dead Sea Scrolls, the forces of light and darkness were engaged in mortal combat, but light was predestined to triumph” (IVP)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-18-13&#34;&gt;John 1:8-13&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;8 He was not the light, but came to bear witness about the light. 9 The true light, which gives light to everyone, was coming into the world. 10 He was in the world, and the world was made through him, yet the world did not know him. 11 He came to his own, and his own people did not receive him. 12 But to all who did receive him, who believed in his name, he gave the right to become children of God, 13 who were born, not of blood nor of the will of the flesh nor of the will of man, but of God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal is spiritual rebirth, not ethnic descent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerusalem was the home of David and place where his greater Son was appointed to rule over the nation.  John uses a term Ioudaioi, which get’s translated as “jews” but many scholars believe this is too generic.  Think of the term “Americans” -The Americans won the Gold medal in 1980 (a group of 20 hockey players).  The Americans invaded Normandy (those members of the Army and the Navy in June 1944).  The Americans imposed Tariffs on China (specifically referring to the Government).  The Americans pay their taxes on April 15 (most Americans but not all - children don’t pay taxes).  The Americans are guaranteed freedoms under the Constitution (all Americans)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the term &amp;ldquo;Jews&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot; could be anywhere from All Jews - which we know is not in view here because the 1st Century church was nearly 100% Jewish.   Unfortunately many commentators, view it as exactly this: John is an early Christian Anti-Jewish document.  It is more likely that what is in view is not rejection by all-Israel, but rather rejection by a sub-group within Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What might some of these sub-groups be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could maybe refer those in Judea who generally rejected as opposed to those in Galilee where Jesus was largely accepted. But even here, not all Judeans rejected him.  Nicodemus for example.  Several scholars believe Ioudaoi specifically refers to the ruling establishment, which for the most part wanted Jesus out of the picture.  Again Nicodemus is an exception and there were probably others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many commentaries place the blame on all Israel, which could be painting with too broad of a brush.  It would be like holding all 300 million Americans responsible for something done by a small group of corrupt politicians in Washington DC.  With that said, a national guilt might also be in view- America is a sinful and unrepentant nation, even though many Americans do repent of their sin.  Deuteronomy 9:23 states, “You rebelled against the command of the LORD your God; you neither believed Him nor listened to His voice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, we must allow God to own the business of judgment.   it is wrong to use our holy book to specifically condemn a group of people (as the church as done to Jews for the last 2000 years).  We are to love our neighbors and pray for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Jewish thought of the day was that to be a true Child of God, one had to be a Child of Abraham, either through birth or conversion (even today, Ben Avraham is a common name a gentile takes when converting to Judaism).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John is setting the stage that it is not ethnic affiliation but spiritual rebirth that matters.  A topic that will be developed in John Chapter 3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-114-15&#34;&gt;John 1:14-15&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;14  And the Word became flesh and dwelt among us, and we have seen his glory, glory as of the only Son from the Father, full of grace and truth. 15  (John bore witness about him, and cried out, “This was he of whom I said, ‘He who comes after me ranks before me, because he was before me.’”)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A father’s only son” would remind readers of Genesis 22, where God instructed Abraham “take your son, your only son whom you love, Isaac&amp;hellip;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/01-the_logos_files/01.Picture8.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:left&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The star in the Church of Nativity in Bethlehem marks the spot where tradition says that Mary gave birth to Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the Greek mind, the invisible spiritual real is far superior to the earthly realm.  However, God created man spirit and flesh.  Our flesh only became corrupt AFTER the fall.  God intended there to be a union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The verb translated above as “dwelt” (skenoo) is related to the Greek word for “tabernacle” (skene). Just as God dwelt with his people in the tabernacle, so the Word tabernacled with his people in the incarnation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-11618&#34;&gt;John 1:16:18&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;16 For from his fullness we have all received, grace upon grace. 17 For (as) the (Torah) was given through Moses, grace and truth came through Jesus Christ. 18 No one has ever seen God; the only God, who is at the Father&amp;rsquo;s side, he has made him known.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verse 17 is often translated “for the law came through Moses &lt;em&gt;BUT&lt;/em&gt; Grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “BUT” is a mistranslation (possibly intentional) - it is not in the Greek.  John just got through saying that Jesus was there in the beginning.  This means Grace and Truth where there in the beginning.  The Law has a special role to play for the nation of Israel but it is not in any way antithetical to the Gospel of Jesus.  John sees Jesus as affirming the covenant promises God made in the Torah.  A better reading might be “for AS the Torah was given through Moses, Grace and Truth came through Jesus Christ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “but” originally occurred in the King James Version.  The anachronistic error here involves the 16th Century division between Protestants and Catholics regarding the function of the law in the life of the believer.  One of the Reformation cries was “Faith alone”.  It wasn’t until Luther that “Law” and “Grace” became opposites.  Superimposing this view on the Biblical Text is simply not correct.  The oppose of Law is lawlessness.  The oppose of grace is disgrace.  It is wrong to view any part of the Bible as lawless or disgraceful!  God’s Law is a good and beautiful thing.  Read Psalm 119!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;study-questions&#34;&gt;Study Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can anachronisms and eisegesis be a problem in my studies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In what ways does John 1:1-5 parallel Genesis 1 and how does that change my thinking of Genesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I think “His own” in verse 11 refers to all Jews?  Why or why not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did my opinionAs I reflect on the “tabernacle” discussion in John 1:14, how does (or how should) this affect my walk with Jesus?
change after this lesson?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did my understanding of the Law/Old Testament change after studying 1:17?  How can I apply this going forward?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;image-gallery&#34;&gt;Image Gallery&lt;/h3&gt;











&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-logos&#34; href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide09.JPG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide09_hucc3822ca92039ed2723b5f2421810168_218035_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Slide09.JPG&#34; width=&#34;253&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-logos&#34; href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide11.JPG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide11_hu622c91bf76232f5749ab6b92d1ceb150_314922_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Slide11.JPG&#34; width=&#34;253&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-logos&#34; href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide12.JPG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide12_hu622c91bf76232f5749ab6b92d1ceb150_236786_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Slide12.JPG&#34; width=&#34;253&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-logos&#34; href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide14.JPG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide14_hu454f48da207cd9e826583f9a2b448d4d_123313_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Slide14.JPG&#34; width=&#34;253&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-logos&#34; href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide16.JPG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide16_hu6052f67ee3c83471aa3a4cc37ec0569c_361754_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Slide16.JPG&#34; width=&#34;253&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-logos&#34; href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide17.JPG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide17_hu73d4dc48084b0c86e22d667a90abe0df_339344_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Slide17.JPG&#34; width=&#34;253&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-logos&#34; href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide19.JPG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide19_hu70fa3a6f17ce22a74ee95779fb2803ca_269491_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Slide19.JPG&#34; width=&#34;253&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-logos&#34; href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide20.JPG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide20_hu70fa3a6f17ce22a74ee95779fb2803ca_212204_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Slide20.JPG&#34; width=&#34;253&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-logos&#34; href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide21.JPG&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/media/albums/logos/Slide21_hu70fa3a6f17ce22a74ee95779fb2803ca_182331_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Slide21.JPG&#34; width=&#34;253&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images used are courtesy of the Photo Companion to the Bible or the Pictorial Library of Bible Lands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bolen, Todd. “John 1.” PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keener, Craig S. The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament. 2nd edition. Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lancaster, Daniel T. “The Logos.” In Chronicles of the Messiah, edited by Boaz D. Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster. Second edition. Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lizorkin-Eyzenberg, Eli. The Jewish Gospel of John: Discovering Jesus, King of All Israel. CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform, 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schlegel, William. The Land and the Bible: A Historical Geographical Companion to the Satellite Bible Atlas. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.  2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;mdash;. Satellite Bible Atlas. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/satellite-bible-atlas-schlegel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/satellite-bible-atlas-schlegel/&lt;/a&gt;  2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2a. Annunciations</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/2a-annunciations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/2a-annunciations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_d5ldH_6zQ4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2b. Annunciations Part II</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/2b-annunciations-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/2b-annunciations-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6urbUYtM05M&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3. Genealogies</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/3-genealogies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/3-genealogies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LzkfziqSCps&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4a. Nativity Part I</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/4a-nativity-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/4a-nativity-part-i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hMJcruBECds&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4b. Nativity Part II</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/4b-nativity-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/4b-nativity-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YDPN624dbqk&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EARLY MINISTRY</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/beginnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/beginnings/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5. The Nazarene</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/5-the-nazarene/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/5-the-nazarene/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3uaVNrYBB0Q&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6. John the Immerser</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/6-john-the-immerser/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/6-john-the-immerser/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C63y8Qq--lc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7. Immersion and Temptation</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/7-immersion-and-temptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/7-immersion-and-temptation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-n_WN2q1cqM&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>8. The First Sign</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/8-the-first-sign/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/8-the-first-sign/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/siLcYcZ6zi8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9a In Jerusalem</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/9a-in-jerusalem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/9a-in-jerusalem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VzXanXvHuAY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9b. In Judea</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/9b-in-judea/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/9b-in-judea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0OjjQiGK0eQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9c. In Samaria</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/9c-in-samaria/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/9c-in-samaria/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-OzsA2EDODU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10. A Prophet Without Honor</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/10-a-prophet-without-honor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/10-a-prophet-without-honor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8akjSR2asLE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11. Pools of Bethesda</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/11-pool-of-bethesda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/11-pool-of-bethesda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/G6XOcfHcchQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GALLILEAN MINISTRY</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/public-gallilean-ministry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/public-gallilean-ministry/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>37 Beyond the Jordan</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/beyond-the-jordan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/beyond-the-jordan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;video-part-i&#34;&gt;Video Part I&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IxJTLlEQlp4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video-part-ii&#34;&gt;Video Part II&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ACTS 17:11 (The Bereans) received the word with all eagerness, examining the Scriptures daily to see if these things were so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode, we&amp;rsquo;re going to see that as a society, that culture had strayed a bit from God&amp;rsquo;s original intent.  Moreover, they fully believed they were interpreting the Bible faithfully regarding permissible situations for divorce.  Jesus is not just going to redirect them back to the Hebrew Bible, not just the Torah, not just Genesis, but Genesis chapter 1 shows God&amp;rsquo;s intent for marriage.  This is why Acts 17:11 must be first and foremost in our study.  It&amp;rsquo;s what Jesus did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;topics&#34;&gt;Topics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lengthy and Groundbreaking Halacha (Jewish Legal Argument) on Divorce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Better not to marry”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus on Children – entering “as a child”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Good Rabbi, what should I do to inherit internal life?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“We have left everything to follow You.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parable of the Hired Workers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Are you able to drink the up that I drink?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the topics are probably familiar to us.  For example, divorce, and the man who is told to sell everything is sad.  Let&amp;rsquo;s not let our familiarity be an excuse to not ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chuck Missler used to say that the greatest obstacle to truth was the assumption you already have it.  Missler also used to say, &amp;ldquo;where two people agree one is redundant.&amp;rdquo; these are familiar passages with familiar Protestant interpretations that tend to be repeated from one commentator to the next.  As usual, the commentators I am using for this series bring added clarity based on their study of the first century legal and cultural backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is value in legitimate academic inquiry and applying Acts 17:11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, of course, this is a sensitive topic, as many families are affected by divorce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps some of us realize we didn&amp;rsquo;t act according to the Biblical model for marriage. Or we were a relatively innocent victim of a partner who acted unbiblically.  Or maybe there was a legitimate reason other than sexual misconduct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another good memory verse is Romans 8:1 – there is now, therefore, no condemnation for those who are in Jesus the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these words on divorce may pinch and the practical effects of divorce can&amp;rsquo;t be minimized, because of who Jesus is and everything he has done on behalf of sinners, you should not feel condemned as long as you are living in unison with Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;geography&#34;&gt;Geography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/map.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;66%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus has now left the fertile Jezreel and Harod valleys and has most likely crossed the Jordan to make His way down the East Bank towards Jericho.  This area, south of the cities of the Decapolis, was Jewish.  The terrain is such that water is more plentiful from the numerous brooks on the east side that feed the Jordan.  This area is the ancient Gilead, where the tribes of Gad, Reuben, and ½ of Manasseh settled.  And we use settled literally and figuratively.  They literally settled here (in the sense of settlers) because the land was pleasing to the eye and excellent for raising livestock (which is true).  They settled figuratively (in the sense of compromising; settling for less) because God wanted them to Enter and possess the land on the WEST side of the Jordan in the Land of Israel.  The &amp;ldquo;Eastsiders,&amp;rdquo; as my friend Dan Stolebarger, calls them were usually the first people picked off by armies invading from the North.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s return to our narrative.  At this stage, there is most likely a caravan forming of pilgrims on their way to Jerusalem for the Passover &lt;click and read&gt; Says Schlegel, &amp;ldquo;One cannot overstate both the excitement and tension that accompanied Jesus on His way to Jerusalem for the Passover festival.  Every question, every word was loaded.&amp;rdquo; Many other events happened in this region.  At Sukkoth, right above where Box 8 is, Jacob built a house and made booths for his cattle.  This is where we get the name &amp;ldquo;sukkot&amp;rdquo; for the feast of booths, what we might know as the feast of Tabernacles in the fall.  Gideon was also in this area in Judges 8 after the rout of the Midinettes.  The most notable event was when Joshua led the Israelites across the Jordan on dry ground.  When the Israelites crossed the Jordan near Jericho, we are told the waters dried up all the way to Adam (Joshua 3:16), which you can see just below Box 8.  God commanded them to set up stones of remembrance in Joshua 4:3.   Some scholars speculate that it was those very stones John the Baptist was referring to when he said, &amp;ldquo;And do not presume to say to yourselves, &amp;lsquo;We have Abraham as our father,&amp;rsquo; for I tell you, God is able from these stones to raise up children for Abraham.&amp;rdquo; (Matthew 3 and Luke 3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;matthew-191-3--mark-101-3&#34;&gt;Matthew 19:1-3 / Mark 10:1-3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Matthew 19&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Mark 10&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;1 Now when Jesus had finished these sayings, he went away from Galilee and entered the region of &lt;mark&gt;Judea beyond the Jordan&lt;/mark&gt;. 2 And large crowds followed him, and he healed them there. 3 And Pharisees came up to him and tested him by asking, “Is it lawful to divorce one&amp;rsquo;s wife for any cause?”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;1 And he left there and went to the &lt;mark&gt;region of Judea and beyond the Jordan&lt;/mark&gt;, and crowds gathered to him again. And again, as was his custom, he taught them. 2 And Pharisees came up and in order to test him asked, “Is it lawful for a man to divorce his wife?” 3 He answered them, &lt;mark&gt;“What did Moses command you?”&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /commentary/gospels/gb3/beyond-the-jordan/images/Slide6_hua5c9c6d093924288be88ed3675a9baed_379315_90064ca971ae9e98f7dbdfadf1722310.webp 400w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb3/beyond-the-jordan/images/Slide6_hua5c9c6d093924288be88ed3675a9baed_379315_c75c24ed17758eb5c254da7a1b53b854.webp 760w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb3/beyond-the-jordan/images/Slide6_hua5c9c6d093924288be88ed3675a9baed_379315_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/beyond-the-jordan/images/Slide6_hua5c9c6d093924288be88ed3675a9baed_379315_90064ca971ae9e98f7dbdfadf1722310.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jewish travelers in the first century AD usually traveled on the eastern side of the Jordan River because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this allowed them to travel in Jewish territory instead of Samaritan, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;freshwater springs are found on this side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schlegel also notes that these crowds probably provided Jesus a certain degree of anonymity from those who meant Him harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we&amp;rsquo;re told that the Pharisees wanted to &lt;mark&gt;test&lt;/mark&gt; him on the matter of divorce.  Here, the traditional Christian viewpoint is that the Pharisees are setting a trap for him.  As they were now back in Antipas&#39; territory of Perea, perhaps they saw an opportunity for history to repeat itself.  After all, John the Baptist was arrested and ultimately beheaded when he spoke against the Divorce of Herod Antipas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I&amp;rsquo;m never opposed to a good conspiracy theory, let&amp;rsquo;s look at what we are and are not told by the text.  Matthew and Mark indeed say they said this to &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In John 6:6, Jesus uses the same Greek word when he &amp;ldquo;tested&amp;rdquo; one of the disciples.  G3985 Pieradzo.  Do we honestly think Jesus wanted to set a trap for his disciples?  Actually, the word is used positively (legitimate inquiry, due diligence) and negatively (tempt to sin).  Paul encourages us to Pieradzo ourselves to see whether we are in the faith (2 Cor 13:5).  Abraham was Pieradzo&amp;rsquo;ed to offer Isaac (Heb 11:17).  In other words, without added context, the word itself is as neutral as our word &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; is.  We are simply not given enough context to conclude the Pharisees are up to no good, so I suggest we give them the benefit of the doubt.  I believe this is what God would have us do in any circumstance where we don&amp;rsquo;t have enough information.   As a side note, entangle, or snare is a different Greek word.  Keener points out that testing an extraordinary person&amp;rsquo;s wisdom was a common theme in the Old Testament.  He cited how the Queen of Sheba sought to &amp;ldquo;prove Solomon with hard questions&amp;rdquo; (1st Kings 10:1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know it&amp;rsquo;s a nearly automatic reaction for us to see the Pharisees as evil - I think some commentators seem to be as obsessed with taking out the Pharisees as bad as poor Elmer Fudd is with Buggs Bunny, which is why I jokingly sometimes say, &amp;ldquo;wascawwy Phawisees&amp;rdquo; to remind us not to take these overly negative views on the Pharisees too seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know I repeat this a lot, but as I&amp;rsquo;ve gone through this study, now at lesson 37 of 54, one thing God has revealed to me is that I need to have a more charitable spirit and give others the benefit of the doubt if I don&amp;rsquo;t have all the facts.  That is a good lesson for everyone – especially currently where civil discourse is hard to come by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look, the Pharisees may indeed have been up to no good in this circumstance; in my view, though, it would be better to be wrong on the side of giving another grace and mercy than wrong on the side of incorrect and premature judgment and condemnation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, there is an entirely plausible explanation for their question that doesn&amp;rsquo;t involve a sinister plot.  maybe they just wanted to know the answer to this critically important and controversial spiritual and societal question?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, note Jesus&#39; Acts 17:11 response: in Marks version, he asks, &amp;ldquo;what did Moses write&amp;rdquo;; in Matthew&amp;rsquo;s version, He says &amp;ldquo;Have you not read…&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tb010703126&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deuteronomy 24:11 &amp;ldquo;When a man takes a wife and marries her, if then she finds no favor in his eyes because he has found some indecency in her, and he writes her a certificate of divorce and puts it in her hand and sends her out of his house, and she departs out of his house.  Keener notes that historically, other ancient societies held that there must be clear grounds for the divorce.  He writes &amp;ldquo;a bill of divorcement is drawn up specifying these particulars, which if it follows the manner of other legal proceedings, would be reviewed by a body of elders and testimony would be given.&amp;rdquo; In other words, the original intent was NEVER any random or petty dissatisfaction.  A court had to decide whether the divorce would be granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This high standard eroded over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-1&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They said, &amp;ldquo;Moses allowed a man to write a certificate of divorce and send her away&amp;rdquo;
Remember we have mentioned that there were two primary Pharisaic schools of thought.  One was the House of Hillel, and the other was the house of Shammai.  They usually agree but when they don’t, they fought to the death.  It&amp;rsquo;s sort of like two different Baptist denominations.  Maybe one is Calvinist, and the other is Armenian.  They agree on everything else, but if you bring up fate versus free-will, there could be bloodshed.   It was sort of like that with Hillel and Shammai.  Hillel was generally more permissive (in good ways usually) while Shammai was narrower and more restrictive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mat18982&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-2&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They said, &amp;ldquo;Moses allowed a man to write a certificate of divorce and send her away&amp;rdquo;
The big question is &amp;ldquo;what does the Torah mean by &amp;ldquo;he has found some &amp;ldquo;indecency&amp;rdquo; in her&amp;rdquo; – traditionally and logically this refers to sexual impurity.  Keep in mind that Adultery was a capital offense.  When the death penalty could not be delivered, the Jewish law compelled a husband to divorce his wife – this was the underlying tension between Joseph and Mary when Joseph had resolved to put Mary away quietly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shammai held that &amp;ldquo;unseemingly thing&amp;rdquo; should be interpreted no further than sexual impropriety.  &amp;ldquo;Hillel interpreted the &amp;ldquo;indecency &amp;ldquo;of Deuteronomy 24:1 as just about anything that the husband found disagreeable about his wife&amp;rdquo; including being a bad cook or even finding another woman more attractive.&lt;br&gt;
Even within the Hillel camp, Stern writes that there was a Rabbi Elazar who said, &amp;ldquo;When a man divorces his first wife, even the altar sheds tears, &amp;ldquo;So they were not unanimous even within one camp or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the permissiveness of Hillel sounds absurd by our standards but pretty much isn&amp;rsquo;t that the way it is today.  Anyone can serve papers at any time.  As I say often, we are not one to point fingers at their ability to compromise and justify our sin as something that is &amp;ldquo;OK&amp;rdquo;.  We are no different.  Just compare a TV show from the 60s to one from the 80s to one from today and you&amp;rsquo;ll see what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I&amp;rsquo;m inclined to give these Pharisees here some credit for pressing the issue.  I like to think that the reason they asked the question was because perhaps after a few decades of Hillel&amp;rsquo;s interpretation, they were starting to see the damaging effect a liberal position divorce was having.  If they knew anything about Jesus, they knew He was highly likely to take a strict and narrow interpretation.  Maybe they wanted him to say this &amp;ldquo;on the record&amp;rdquo;, which He did.  This is pure speculation on my part but it&amp;rsquo;s not outside the realm of possibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tb031416458&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-3&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the beginning of the creation, He made them male and female
&amp;ldquo;And God created man in His own image, in the image of God He created him; male and female He created them&amp;rdquo; (Gen 1:27).  This Yemenite Torah scroll was photographed at The Master&amp;rsquo;s Seminary in California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hebrew or Aramaic, Jesus would have said something like ??????????, &amp;ldquo;from the beginning&amp;rdquo; which is related to ????????, &amp;ldquo;in the beginning&amp;rdquo; which is also the Hebrew name of the book we call Genesis.  So, Jesus could just as well have said &amp;ldquo;as it is written in Genesis, He created them male and female.  From this the sages came to an understanding that God&amp;rsquo;s design for a marriage was one man and one woman, inseparable (the two shall become one flesh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moses never commanded divorce.  The Bible PERMITS divorce because it makes provisions and to a certain extent concessions for man&amp;rsquo;s fall and propensity to sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hardness of heart certainly recalls God&amp;rsquo;s description of Pharoah during the 10 plagues and the exodus.  The Torah allows it, but it does not Will it any more than the creation of cities of refuge is intended to command and sanction manslaughter.   Divorce is contrary to God&amp;rsquo;s plan; however, when it happens, God&amp;rsquo;s law is prepared to direct us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener notes that &amp;ldquo;concession&amp;rdquo; was a legal category among Jewish teachers.  It is something that was permitted only because it was better to regulate the sin than to relinquish control over it altogether.&amp;rdquo; Divorce is going to happen even though it is contrary to God&amp;rsquo;s will.  We can&amp;rsquo;t pretend it won&amp;rsquo;t ever happen, so we need to make provisions when it does is the thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it has happened to you or someone close to you; God&amp;rsquo;s mercy and forgiveness is similarly available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a related and often problematic note, the same logic can be used for polygamy.  The Bible tacitly permits a man to have more than one wife (as was more common in ancient cultures), but from the beginning it should not be this way.  The standard for male believers today is one single lifetime wife.  The Torah creates certain parameters as a concession, but God never once says Polygamy is a good thing just like He never calls divorce good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tb031416331&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-4&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That Mark leaves out &amp;ldquo;except for sexual immorality&amp;rdquo; creates a problem.  Lancaster presents a couple of options, honestly neither of which fully satisfies.  One possibility is that Mark understood sexual immorality as a marriage failure that goes without saying.  Maybe Matthew was more interested in the Hillel Shammai distinction than Mark was.  There is also the thought we looked at in Luke a few lessons ago, where the Greek could be translated as &amp;ldquo;whoever divorces another for the sole purpose of marrying another commits adultery.  Whereas today, a divorced partner may choose to remain single, that possibility was less likely in the ancient world.; although perhaps Jesus is implying that divorce without remarriage is allowable for lesser reasons.  Paul supplies one of these reasons in 1 Corinthians 7:15 &amp;ldquo;if an unbelieving partner separates, let it be so&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, Jesus ultimate message seems to be that an illegitimate divorce (for whatever reason) meant that the divorce paper was not worth the paper it was written on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effectively in the eyes of God if not man, the couple is still married.  Therefore, any sexual contact outside of that marriage would be inappropriate.  On the other hand, as Lancaster writes, &amp;ldquo;if the divorce had been issued for a legitimate reason, the divorce was then valid, and remarriage permitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-5&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever divorces his wife, except for fornication, and marries another, commits adultery (Mark &amp;ldquo;commits adultery against her&amp;rdquo;)
Another nuance is that adultery was narrowly defined as sexual relations with another man&amp;rsquo;s wife.  A man who strayed with a married woman was subject to the death penalty, but A man who strayed with an unmarried woman would be guilty of immorality or perhaps rape, but not adultery.  In fact, the man could arrange to marry the girl, and all would be legitimate.  We see an example of this in the sordid episode with Shechem and Dinah in Genesis 34.  We also see this with David and Bathsheba.  In a certain sense, with Uriah out of the way, at the time it occurred, the marriage between David and Bathsheba was considered legitimate (despite all the other sins and havoc David&amp;rsquo;s indiscretion caused).  Specifically, Solomon was not considered an illegitimate offspring but was entitled to take his place on David&amp;rsquo;s throne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember this is the ancient world we&amp;rsquo;re talking about which had different standards and sensitivities than our world today does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster considers the statement &amp;ldquo;adultery against her&amp;rdquo; one of the most radical Halachic statements Jesus made.  First century Jewish women had little say in divorce and specifically did not have the prerogative to divorce their husbands.  With this said, most Jewish courts forced men to issue their wives a certificate of divorce if she had a legitimate grievance against him (and women were sometimes able to seek relief from roman courts to obtain a divorce).  Nonetheless – Jesus is here holding husbands up to the same standards of marital fidelity.   Jesus is breaking with the common thought but not with the Torah.  The Torah &amp;ldquo;from the beginning&amp;rdquo; always held mutual fidelity as the Will of God.    Just like with the sermon on the mount, he is holding us all to a higher standard of behavior.  Keener agrees and says, &amp;ldquo;Because men could divorce women unilaterally, but women could demand a divorce only under certain very narrow conditions (and then needed the court&amp;rsquo;s help), Jesus&#39; opposition to this sort of divorce is a defense of married women.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we&amp;rsquo;ve often said, it may be tempting to blame the Jews of Jesus&#39; day for their legalism and bending rules to fit their circumstances.  I submit to you that we are no different in our ability to rationalize our personal choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mat19635&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-6&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the male-dominated society the disciples grew up in, Jesus words were shocking.  In their minds Jesus was potentially condemning these men to a lifetime of misery should they find some displeasure in their wives that fell short of sexual impropriety.   Many of us forget the covenantal nature of a marriage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This clearly made the disciples nervous.  Keener explains why: &amp;ldquo;Jewish men took the right to divorce for granted.  To marry without an escape clause in case it did not work—parents arranged the marriages and partners did not always turn out as expected—made the prospect of marriage itself frightening.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A covenant is not supposed to be easy to break so conversely, one should not enter a covenant lightly.  The Hebrew word for making a covenant is literally the word &amp;ldquo;cut&amp;rdquo; (ka-Raht).  This is because in the Old Testament days, as the contract or covenant was being executed, they would typically sacrifice an animal.  The parties would essentially communicate to each other &amp;ldquo;if I fail to keep my terms of this covenant, let me be hacked to pieces like this animal.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the disciples&#39; reaction and Jesus’ response reminds me of Jesus&#39; words on discipleship.  Marriage, like discipleship should not be taken lightly.  Maybe you need to go tend to your fields or bury your father first if you aren&amp;rsquo;t ready to join me.  You better count the cost because in a sense it can cost you everything.  Not everyone can receive this saying, but if you can receive it, you have no idea what tremendous rewards await you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These words regarding being a eunuch are a little troubling.  Jesus appears to be saying celibacy is a higher calling than marriage and if you can&amp;rsquo;t be a eunuch than you should get married.  There are several problems with this interpretation.  First, the Torah prohibits physical mutilation.  While many pagan societies castrated slaves both as a protection for the families they served and as a sign of loyalty on the part of the slave, this was never the case in Jewish society.  The Bible teaches that &amp;ldquo;it is not good for man to be alone&amp;rdquo; and God&amp;rsquo;s plan was one man and one woman from the Beginning.  He commands his people to &amp;ldquo;be fruitful and multiply.  “Rabbis were almost always married, and a good Jewish Rabbi would never espouse celibacy.  We&amp;rsquo;re about to read of Jesus&#39; position on Children; how basically since He had no children of his own, ALL OF US are his children.  It would be difficult to place such a high value on children if he was commanding his followers to be celibate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern has an excellent summary: &amp;ldquo;Judaism has always considered marriage both normal and desirable-&amp;ldquo;The unmarried person lives without joy, without blessing and without good&amp;hellip;.  An unmarried man is not fully a man&amp;rdquo; (Talmud: Yevamot 62b-63a).  On the other hand, some branches of Christianity came to grant abnormally high status to celibacy (on this phenomenon see 1Co_7:1-40).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the calling and preferences of the individual, Yeshua allows that either the married or the single life can be one of service to God and humanity; and he takes care to minimize needless guilt on the part of those making the choice.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also historically, the fact that segments of Christianity require celibacy, both in the past and currently, can trace its roots in the gnostic movement, which generally held that anything physical or material was sinful.  This is rightfully called a gnostic heresy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an exception, Jesus appears to be saying that the celibate path may be right for a very few individuals.  Lancaster guesses that Jesus avoided marriage for the sake of maintaining a constant state of ritual purity.  This is consistent with Paul, who recommends short-term abstinence, with mutual consent of husband and wife for the purposes of prayer.  On that note, I had a pastor (married of course) who liked to say &amp;ldquo;well…I can&amp;rsquo;t say I&amp;rsquo;ve never been called to that particular kind of fast.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-7&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being the shortest Gospel, mark includes many details the other writers don&amp;rsquo;t.  Here in verse 14, it says that Jesus was not just correcting the disciples, but he was actually ANGRY with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In part two when we get to the rich young ruler, Mark adds that Jesus looked at the ruler and &amp;ldquo;loved him&amp;rdquo;.  No other gospel writer adds that detail.  This made me think that it&amp;rsquo;s funny how many Christians condemn the man for being greedy, miserly, idolatrous or whatever.  Yet Jesus loved him.  I think if Jesus loved him, we should love him also, not condemn him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let the little children come to Me; do not hinder them
The disciple&amp;rsquo;s initial instinct is understandable.  With the throng of people that surrounded Jesus at times, we can see how they had to be bodyguards.  Also bestowing blessings seemed frivolous.  To Jesus, nothing like this is frivolous.  I&amp;rsquo;ll be forthright; as I&amp;rsquo;m typing this and looking at this picture with my two sons now grown and away at college, I&amp;rsquo;m regretting the missed opportunities where I could have received my kids like Jesus does here.  But perhaps I can take solace in Jacob.  While he was pretty much a train wreck as a person and as a father, he was ultimately able to lay his hands on his grandsons, Ephraim and Manasseh and bless them.  Lancaster writes &amp;ldquo;similar to Jacob, when Jesus laid his hands on the children and blessed them, He demonstrated that although He remained unmarried and had no natural children, he nonetheless had MANY children&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This episode recalls an earlier time in Peter&amp;rsquo;s home where Jesus uttered nearly identical words about letting the children come to Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener makes another interesting observation that I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen anywhere else, he&amp;rsquo;s good at that.  He writes, &amp;ldquo;Insensitive disciples trying to keep from the master those seeking his help might remind Jewish hearers of Gehazi, a disciple of Elisha who eventually lost his position&amp;rdquo; This struck me hard.  And I need to explain why.  Last lesson we mentioned an event where Naaman the Syrian sought an audience with Elisha who refused, sending an instruction by way of his servant.  That servant was Gehazi.  After Naaman was healed, he wanted to bestow some gift upon Elisha.  Again, Elisha refused.  Gehazi decided that the boss would never find out if I went to Naaman and accept the tribute, so he did.  This is too good, so I must read it:  &lt;click&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s possible to be second in command to a man of God and none of that rubs off on you.  That was Gehazi&amp;rsquo;s case.  In the disciples’ case, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to walk in Jesus&#39; dust and still not have a heart for the things he has a heart for.  That&amp;rsquo;s me in a lot of areas.  This pinches quite a bit.   For you it may or may not be children, but it may be something else.  What areas of your life do you know you are not acting like Jesus would act?  &lt;click&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In context, when Jesus says, &amp;ldquo;Truly, I say to you, whoever does not receive the kingdom of God like a child shall not enter it.&amp;rdquo; he is likely referring to the lowly social status of a child as opposed to any specific behavior trait.  Although Children were and are to be cared for and raised to be mature adults, a child occupies the lowest position in society (whether they like it or not).  This is true even today, where a child doesn&amp;rsquo;t obtain the majority of his or her constitutional rights until the 18th birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many of our kids would probably disagree with this, Lancaster says, &amp;ldquo;to become like a child is to set aside concerns of prestige, to relinquish one&amp;rsquo;s personal dignity and prerogatives, and to accept the lowest place at the table.  The one who truly humbles himself and considers others more important than himself is the one who will find himself first in the kingdom.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like we studied last time; we do not present Jesus our own righteousness.  Like a child who must rely on a parent or guardian, we must rely on Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt; button above to view the built-in slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides can be added in a few ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create&lt;/strong&gt; slides using Wowchemy&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; feature and link using &lt;code&gt;slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upload&lt;/strong&gt; an existing slide deck to &lt;code&gt;static/&lt;/code&gt; and link using &lt;code&gt;url_slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embed&lt;/strong&gt; your slides (e.g. Google Slides) or presentation video on this page using &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further event details, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;page elements&lt;/a&gt; such as image galleries, can be added to the body of this page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Jordan </title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/across-the-jordan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/across-the-jordan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;images/37.map.png&#34; title=&#34;map&#34; width=&#34;65%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel Backgrounds&lt;/em&gt; Lesson 37 is titled &amp;ldquo;Beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo;  After leaving the Harod Valley [#7 on the map], Jesus makes His way to the Jordan, just south of where it exits the Sea of Galilee.  The north-south path along the river in this vicinity was along the eastern shore, which the Gospel writers call &amp;ldquo;Judea beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo; [8]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus will engage a group of inquisitive (but not necessarily trecharous) Pharisees who want to know the Master&amp;rsquo;s position on divorce.  As it is today, divorce was a critical and controversial topic because of its impact on family and society.  The Pharisees themselves were divided on when divorce was permissible.  The majority view held that a man could divorce his wife for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; reason, including not liking her cooking or even finding another woman more attractive.  The minority view held that the Torah had in view sexual misconduct as the only permissible reason.  Jesus sided with the minority.  The disciples are so taken-aback by Jesus&#39; response that they exclaim &amp;ldquo;in that case, it is better not to marry!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus also teaches about the role of children and we will understand what it means to &amp;ldquo;become like a child&amp;rdquo; in order to enter heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/37.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Children playing in Jerusalem&#34; width=&#34;75%&#34; style=&#34;float:left&#34; padding_right=&#34;3&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus then receives a question from a &amp;ldquo;rich, young ruler&amp;rdquo; about what must be done to inherit eternal life. Jesus responds &amp;ldquo;Keep the Commandments.&amp;rdquo; When the man says that he&amp;rsquo;s done this, Jesus then tells him to sell everything. His response again befuddles the disciples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The section concludes with Jesus receiving a request from James and John to sit at Jesus&#39; right and left hands during the millenial kingdom, which is often portrayed as a great banquet.  Instead of rebuking their pride, Jesus explains what it means to sit by his side and &amp;ldquo;drink His cup&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/beyond-the-jordan&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Watch the video and read the complete Gospel Backgrounds Lesson!&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Between Samaria and Galilee</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/between-samaria-and-galilee/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/between-samaria-and-galilee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel Backgrounds&lt;/em&gt; Lesson 36 is titled &amp;ldquo;Between Samaria and Galilee,&amp;rdquo; and is taken from Luke 17:11 where we are told Jesus is making his way up to Jerusalem for His final passover and passes between Samaria and Galilee.  The video will explore the geography of the region know as the Harod Valley, where many scholars believe this episode took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/36.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central story is that of Jesus healing ten lepers.  While all ten were healed, only one, a Samaritan, returned to give thanks and praise to Jesus.  In that day, most Jews had a dim view of Samaritans as evidenced by the three stories where Samaritans are featured prominently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Woman at the Well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The parable of the Good Samaritan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Ten Lepers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson for us is if even a Samaritan has enough heart to give thanks, how much more should we, as followers/disciples/talmidim of Yeshua have a humble and thankful heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TKbltCM2Hus&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example preprint / working paper</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/publication/preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/publication/preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code, math, and images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/slides/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/slides/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;create-slides-in-markdown-with-wowchemy&#34;&gt;Create slides in Markdown with Wowchemy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wowchemy&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://owchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiently write slides in Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-in-1: Create, Present, and Publish your slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports speaker notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile friendly slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;controls&#34;&gt;Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next: &lt;code&gt;Right Arrow&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previous: &lt;code&gt;Left Arrow&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start: &lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish: &lt;code&gt;End&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overview: &lt;code&gt;Esc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaker notes: &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fullscreen: &lt;code&gt;F&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoom: &lt;code&gt;Alt + Click&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hakimel/reveal.js#pdf-export&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF Export&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-highlighting&#34;&gt;Code Highlighting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inline code: &lt;code&gt;variable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code block:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;porridge = &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;
if porridge == &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;:
    print(&amp;quot;Eating...&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;math&#34;&gt;Math&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In-line math: $x + y = z$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Block math:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
f\left( x \right) = ;\frac{{2\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x - 4} \right)}}{{\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x + 1} \right)}}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fragments&#34;&gt;Fragments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make content appear incrementally&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{% fragment %}} One {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} **Two** {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} Three {{% /fragment %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt; to play!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
   One 
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
   **Two** 
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
   Three 
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fragment can accept two optional parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;class&lt;/code&gt;: use a custom style (requires definition in custom CSS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;weight&lt;/code&gt;: sets the order in which a fragment appears&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;speaker-notes&#34;&gt;Speaker Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add speaker notes to your presentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{% speaker_note %}}
- Only the speaker can read these notes
- Press `S` key to view
{{% /speaker_note %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press the &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view the speaker notes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only the speaker can read these notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;themes&#34;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;black: Black background, white text, blue links (default)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;white: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;league: Gray background, white text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beige: Beige background, dark text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sky: Blue background, thin dark text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;night: Black background, thick white text, orange links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serif: Cappuccino background, gray text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simple: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;solarized: Cream-colored background, dark green text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;section data-noprocess data-shortcode-slide
  
      
      data-background-image=&#34;/media/boards.jpg&#34;
  &gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-slide&#34;&gt;Custom Slide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customize the slide style and background&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{&amp;lt; slide background-image=&amp;quot;/media/boards.jpg&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide background-color=&amp;quot;#0000FF&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide class=&amp;quot;my-style&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-css-example&#34;&gt;Custom CSS Example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s make headers navy colored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;assets/css/reveal_custom.css&lt;/code&gt; with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-css&#34;&gt;.reveal section h1,
.reveal section h2,
.reveal section h3 {
  color: navy;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wowchemy/wowchemy-hugo-modules/discussions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>External Project</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/project/external-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/project/external-project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internal Project</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/project/internal-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/project/internal-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Duis posuere tellus ac convallis placerat. Proin tincidunt magna sed ex sollicitudin condimentum. Sed ac faucibus dolor, scelerisque sollicitudin nisi. Cras purus urna, suscipit quis sapien eu, pulvinar tempor diam. Quisque risus orci, mollis id ante sit amet, gravida egestas nisl. Sed ac tempus magna. Proin in dui enim. Donec condimentum, sem id dapibus fringilla, tellus enim condimentum arcu, nec volutpat est felis vel metus. Vestibulum sit amet erat at nulla eleifend gravida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nullam vel molestie justo. Curabitur vitae efficitur leo. In hac habitasse platea dictumst. Sed pulvinar mauris dui, eget varius purus congue ac. Nulla euismod, lorem vel elementum dapibus, nunc justo porta mi, sed tempus est est vel tellus. Nam et enim eleifend, laoreet sem sit amet, elementum sem. Morbi ut leo congue, maximus velit ut, finibus arcu. In et libero cursus, rutrum risus non, molestie leo. Nullam congue quam et volutpat malesuada. Sed risus tortor, pulvinar et dictum nec, sodales non mi. Phasellus lacinia commodo laoreet. Nam mollis, erat in feugiat consectetur, purus eros egestas tellus, in auctor urna odio at nibh. Mauris imperdiet nisi ac magna convallis, at rhoncus ligula cursus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cras aliquam rhoncus ipsum, in hendrerit nunc mattis vitae. Duis vitae efficitur metus, ac tempus leo. Cras nec fringilla lacus. Quisque sit amet risus at ipsum pharetra commodo. Sed aliquam mauris at consequat eleifend. Praesent porta, augue sed viverra bibendum, neque ante euismod ante, in vehicula justo lorem ac eros. Suspendisse augue libero, venenatis eget tincidunt ut, malesuada at lorem. Donec vitae bibendum arcu. Aenean maximus nulla non pretium iaculis. Quisque imperdiet, nulla in pulvinar aliquet, velit quam ultrices quam, sit amet fringilla leo sem vel nunc. Mauris in lacinia lacus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suspendisse a tincidunt lacus. Curabitur at urna sagittis, dictum ante sit amet, euismod magna. Sed rutrum massa id tortor commodo, vitae elementum turpis tempus. Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Aenean purus turpis, venenatis a ullamcorper nec, tincidunt et massa. Integer posuere quam rutrum arcu vehicula imperdiet. Mauris ullamcorper quam vitae purus congue, quis euismod magna eleifend. Vestibulum semper vel augue eget tincidunt. Fusce eget justo sodales, dapibus odio eu, ultrices lorem. Duis condimentum lorem id eros commodo, in facilisis mauris scelerisque. Morbi sed auctor leo. Nullam volutpat a lacus quis pharetra. Nulla congue rutrum magna a ornare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aliquam in turpis accumsan, malesuada nibh ut, hendrerit justo. Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis parturient montes, nascetur ridiculus mus. Quisque sed erat nec justo posuere suscipit. Donec ut efficitur arcu, in malesuada neque. Nunc dignissim nisl massa, id vulputate nunc pretium nec. Quisque eget urna in risus suscipit ultricies. Pellentesque odio odio, tincidunt in eleifend sed, posuere a diam. Nam gravida nisl convallis semper elementum. Morbi vitae felis faucibus, vulputate orci placerat, aliquet nisi. Aliquam erat volutpat. Maecenas sagittis pulvinar purus, sed porta quam laoreet at.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example journal article</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/publication/journal-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/publication/journal-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code, math, and images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example conference paper</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/publication/conference-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/publication/conference-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code, math, and images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
