<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu53652e90a6e4e4f125f22da2a993ec10_403021_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revlation 2 Part I (2:1-11): Ephesus, Smyrna</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/revlation-2-part-i-2-1-11-ephesus-smyrna/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/revlation-2-part-i-2-1-11-ephesus-smyrna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ephesus&#34;&gt;Ephesus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1) &amp;ldquo;To the angel of the (&lt;em&gt;ecclesia)&lt;/em&gt; Messianic Community in Ephesus, write: &amp;lsquo;Here is the message from the one who holds the seven stars in his right hand and walks among the seven gold menorahs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mat 18:20 For where two or three are gathered in my name, there am I among them.”  &lt;br&gt;Joh 1:1 In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(2) &amp;ldquo;I know what you have been doing, how hard you have worked (or &amp;ldquo;I know your works and your labor&amp;rdquo;), how you have persevered, and how you can&amp;rsquo;t stand wicked people; so you tested those who call themselves emissaries but aren&amp;rsquo;t—and you found them to be liars. (3) You are persevering, and you have suffered for my sake without growing weary.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eph 4:14 We will then no longer be infants tossed about by the waves and blown along by every wind of teaching, at the mercy of people clever in devising ways to deceive.   Mat 7:23 Then I will tell them to their faces, &amp;lsquo;I never knew you! Get away from me, you workers of lawlessness!&amp;rsquo;  &lt;br&gt; 1 John 4:1 Beloved, do not believe every spirit but test the spirits to see whether they are from God, for many false prophets have gone out into the world. &lt;br&gt;2 Cor 11:13-15 For such men are false apostles, deceitful workmen, disguising themselves as apostles of Christ. 14 And no wonder, for even Satan disguises himself as an angel of light. 15 So it is no surprise if his servants, also, disguise themselves as servants of righteousness. Their end will correspond to their deeds.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(4) But I have this against you: you have lost the love you had at first. (5) Therefore, remember where you were before you fell, turn from this sin, and do what you used to do before. Otherwise, I will come to you and remove your menorah from its place—if you don&amp;rsquo;t turn from your sin!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 2:2 “Go and proclaim in the hearing of Jerusalem, Thus says the LORD, “I remember the devotion of your youth, your love as a bride, how you followed me in the wilderness, in a land not sown.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(6) But you have this in your favor: you hate what the Nicolaitans do—I hate it too.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 26:5 I hate the assembly of evildoers, and I will not sit with the wicked&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(7) Those who have ears, let them hear what the Spirit is saying to the Messianic communities.  To him winning the victory (or &amp;ldquo;him who overcomes&amp;rdquo;), I will give the right to eat from the Tree of Life which is in God&amp;rsquo;s Gan-`Eden.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:22-24 Then the LORD God said, “Behold, the man has become like one of us in knowing good and evil. Now, lest he reach out his hand and take also of the tree of life and eat, and live forever—” 23 therefore the LORD God sent him out from the garden of Eden to work the ground from which he was taken. 24 He drove out the man, and at the east of the garden of Eden he placed the cherubim and a flaming sword that turned every way to guard the way to the tree of life. &lt;br&gt;Is 51:3  For the LORD comforts Zion; he comforts all her waste places and makes her wilderness like Eden, her desert like the garden of the LORD; joy and gladness will be found in her, thanksgiving and the voice of song.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;smyrna&#34;&gt;Smyrna&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(8) &amp;ldquo;And to the angel of the (&lt;em&gt;ecclesia)&lt;/em&gt; Messianic Community in Smyrna, write: ‘The words of the first and the last, who died and came to life.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 41:4 Who has performed and done this, calling the generations from the beginning? I, the LORD, the first, and with the last; I am he Isa 44:6 Thus says the LORD, the King of Israel and his Redeemer, the LORD of hosts: “I am the first and I am the last; besides me there is no god &lt;br&gt;Isa 48:12 “Listen to me, O Jacob, and Israel, whom I called! I am he; I am the first, and I am the last.  &lt;br&gt;Rev 22:13 I am the Alpha and the Omega, the first and the last, the beginning and the end.”  &lt;br&gt;Mat 2:11 And going into the house, they saw the child with Mary his mother, and they fell down and worshiped him. Then, opening their treasures, they offered him gifts, gold and frankincense and myrrh. &lt;br&gt;Mar 15:23 And they offered him wine mixed with myrrh, but he did not take it. &lt;br&gt;Joh 19:39 Nicodemus also, who earlier had come to Jesus by night, came bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about seventy-five pounds in weight. &lt;br&gt;Isa 60:6 A multitude of camels shall cover you, the young camels of Midian and Ephah; all those from Sheba shall come. They shall bring gold and frankincense, and shall bring good news, the praises of the LORD. &lt;em&gt;(note: no Myrrh)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(9) “‘ I know how you are suffering and how poor you are (though in fact you are rich!)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jas 1:2-3 Regard it all as joy, my brothers, when you face various kinds of temptations; (3) for you know that the testing of your trust produces perseverance.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(10) Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid of what you are about to suffer. Look, the Adversary is going to have some of you thrown in prison, in order to put you to the test; and you will face an ordeal for ten days. Remain faithful, even to the point of death; and I will give you life as your crown.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fear not&amp;rdquo; ~150x &lt;br&gt;2Ti 3:12 And indeed, all who want to live a godly life united with the Messiah Yeshua will be persecuted,   &lt;br&gt;Jas 1:2-3 Regard it all as joy, my brothers, when you face various kinds of temptations; (3) for you know that the testing of your trust produces perseverance.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(11) Those who have ears, let them hear what the Spirit is saying to the Messianic communities. He who wins the victory will not be hurt at all by the second death.&amp;rdquo; &#39;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:6 Blessed and holy &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; he that hath part in the first resurrection: on such the second death hath no power, but they shall be priests of God and of Christ, and shall reign with him a thousand years. &lt;br&gt;Rev 20:14 And death and hell were cast into the lake of fire. This is the second death. &lt;br&gt;Rev 21:8 But the fearful, and unbelieving, and the abominable, and murderers, and whoremongers, and sorcerers, and idolaters, and all liars, shall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimstone: which is the second death.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seven-letters-outline&#34;&gt;Seven Letters Outline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ephesus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smyrna&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pergamum&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thyatira&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sardis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laodicea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Darling; desired&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Myrrh;death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;From&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Holds 7 stars/ walks among lampstands&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First/last dead/alive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t tolerate evil; Persevered; Acts 17:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Suffering (pressing, tribulation) and insults&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lost love they had at first&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hates deeds of people who do things their own way instead of God&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Do not fear suffering; remain faithful&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ear&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before promise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat from Tree/Life&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not taste 2nd death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Age&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apostolic (70-170)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Persecuted (170-312)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Parable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Four Soils&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wheat/tares&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paul&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philippians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-videos&#34;&gt;Watch the videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ephesus-1&#34;&gt;Ephesus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8IN3cVRqa7I&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-were-the-nicolaitans&#34;&gt;Who were the Nicolaitans?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OMVfJ23kxWc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;smyrna-1&#34;&gt;Smyrna&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RbefUO1YdDE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/ephesus&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Ephesus lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/smyrna&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Smyrna lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 2, part I: Intro to Seven letters</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/intro-to-seven-letters/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/intro-to-seven-letters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We will find that that each of the Seven Letters in Revelation 2 and 3 contain an identical outline; however not all elements are present in each letter.  We will want to pay particular attention when there are these exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will also explore some conjectures.  One view holds that Paul&amp;rsquo;s Seven Letters and the Seven Kingdom Parables have correlations to the Seven Letters of Revelation. A view that is widely held is the so-called &amp;ldquo;Church Age Theory.&amp;rdquo;  We will explain what that is and what it means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gL3rJWSmlkU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/seven-letters-intro&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 1 Part II (1:12-20): One like a Son of Man</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/one-like-son-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/one-like-son-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Revelation Backgrounds lesson 4 is titled, &amp;ldquo;One Like a Son of Man&amp;rdquo; based on John&amp;rsquo;s description of the divine being he sees.  Note that he does not say this is Jesus speaking directly.  In fact, we know from verses 1:1 and 22:8 that it is NOT Jesus speaking to John but an Angel.  Nonetheless, the depiction is assuredly that of Jesus Messiah in His glorified state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our background, we will read Daniel chapters 7 and 10 along with Revelation 1 and note the consistency of idioms used throughout the Bible, Old and New Testaments, specifically the descriptions of the &amp;ldquo;one like a Son of Man&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;Ancient of Days&amp;rdquo;.  For this reason, we like to say that our Bible is 66 separate books, but one integrated message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/f37a1158a991a6a4d9acb4a8284cc1ff.jpeg&#34; caption=&#34;Temple Menorah&#34; width=&#34;25%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ended last lesson with John hearing a great voice behind him.  Now here in verse 12, we see John turning to look and he sees the gold seven branched Menorah.  This menorah probably looked much like the one in the picture. Next we learn that the one like a Son of Man was in the midst of the Menorah and later we will see that each branch, each light, is one of the seven congregations  A Menorah is one object with seven branches, which draws images of John 15. Jesus said, &amp;ldquo;I am the vine, you are the branches.&amp;rdquo;  We are supposed to be the vessels through which God&amp;rsquo;s light shines.  Jesus also said in John 15 &amp;ldquo;abide in Me.&amp;rdquo;  We must remain connected to the source.  A Menorah is a great picture of Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we have a description of the person John saw, which is nearly identical to Daniel&amp;rsquo;s visions. This description bears some resemblance to the High Priest carrying out his duties in the Tabernacle.  One commentator said, &amp;ldquo;The garments are highly symbolic, showing that Jesus is the heavenly priest, fully prepared and qualified to carry out His duties.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In verse 19, we will look at this Greek phrase &lt;mark&gt;μετα ταυτα&lt;/mark&gt; (meta tauta), which is often translated as &amp;ldquo;after these things.&amp;rdquo;  The phrase appears exactly ten times in Revelation and acts as a signpost to let us know where we are.  In what is called gematria, certain numbers that reappear throughout the Bible appear to be associated with specific themes.  We&amp;rsquo;ve talked previously how the number seven indicates perfection or completeness.  All this means is that scholars have looked at where seven (or groups/multiples of seven) appear and they have noticed the theme of completeness.  Along these lines, 10 indicates divine order.  The most obvious examples are the Ten Commandments and the Ten plagues.  There were also ten generations from Adam to Noah, then the Flood came.  Meta Tauta will signify an additional stage of God setting things in order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson will conclude with a side-by-side comparison of Revelation 1 and Daniel 10.  This demonstrates that our 66 books we call the Bible is ONE integrated message and it consistent from Genesis to Revelation.  There was no &amp;ldquo;plan B,&amp;rdquo; where God decided the Old Testament was irrelevant (God forbid!). Jesus Himself says this.  Not until all things have been fulfilled will one jot or tittle pass away from the Torah (Mat 5:18).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also read Daniel 7 and Daniel 10 straight through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revelation 1:12-20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12. I turned around to see who was speaking to me; and when I had turned, I saw seven gold menorahs;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exodus 37:23 And he made its seven lamps and its tongs and its trays of pure gold. &lt;br&gt;Zec 4:2 And he said to me, “What do you see?” I said, “I see, and behold, a lampstand all of gold, with a bowl on the top of it, and seven lamps on it, with seven lips on each of the lamps that are on the top of it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13. and among the menorahs was someone like a Son of Man, wearing a robe down to his feet and a gold band around his chest&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exo 28:4 These are the garments that they shall make: a breast piece, an ephod, a robe, a coat of checker work, a turban, and a sash. They shall make holy garments for Aaron your brother and his sons to serve me as priests.  &lt;br&gt;Dan 7:13 “I saw in the night visions, and behold, with the clouds of heaven there came one like a son of man, and he came to the Ancient of Days and was presented before him. &lt;br&gt;Dan 10:5 I lifted up my eyes and looked, and behold, a man clothed in linen, with a belt of fine gold from Uphaz around his waist. Dan 10:16 And behold, one in the likeness of the children of man touched my lips. Then I opened my mouth and spoke. I said to him who stood before me, “O my lord, by reason of the vision pains have come upon me, and I retain no strength.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14. His head and hair were as white as snow-white wool, his eyes like a fiery flame,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:9 “As I looked, thrones were placed, and the Ancient of Days took his seat; his clothing was white as snow, and the hair of his head like pure wool; his throne was fiery flames; its wheels were burning fire.  &lt;br&gt;Dan 10:6 His body was like beryl, his face like the appearance of lightning&lt;br&gt;Mat 17:2 And he was transfigured before them, and his face shone like the sun, and his clothes became white as light.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15. his feet like burnished brass refined in a furnace, and his voice like the sound of rushing waters.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 10:6 … his arms and legs like the gleam of burnished bronze, and the sound of his words like the sound of a multitude. &lt;br&gt;Eze 1:7, 24 Their legs were straight, and the soles of their feet were like the sole of a calf’s foot. And they sparkled like burnished bronze.  24 And when they went, I heard the sound of their wings like the sound of many waters, like the sound of the Almighty, a sound of tumult like the sound of an army. When they stood still, they let down their wings. &lt;br&gt;Eze 43:2 And behold, the glory of the God of Israel was coming from the east. And the sound of his coming was like the sound of many waters, and the earth shone with his glory.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16. In his right hand he held seven stars, out of his mouth went a sharp double-edged sword, and his face was like the sun shining in full strength.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jdg 5:31 “So may all your enemies perish, O LORD! But your friends be like the sun as he rises in his might.” &lt;br&gt;Isa 49:2 He made my mouth like a sharp sword; in the shadow of his hand he hid me; he made me a polished arrow; in his quiver he hid me away. &lt;br&gt;Heb 4:12 For the word of God is living and active, sharper than any two-edged sword, piercing to the division of soul and of spirit, of joints and of marrow, and discerning the thoughts and intentions of the heart&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17. When I saw him, I fell down at his feet like a dead man. He placed his right hand upon me and said, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid! I am the First and the Last,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 8:17-18 So he came near where I stood. And when he came, I was frightened and fell on my face. But he said to me, “Understand, O son of man, that the vision is for the time of the end.” 18 And when he had spoken to me, I fell into a deep sleep with my face to the ground. But he touched me and made me stand up. &lt;br&gt;Dan 10:9-10,12,15 followed by Dan 10:19 And he said, “O man greatly loved, fear not, peace be with you; be strong and of good courage.” And as he spoke to me, I was strengthened and said, “Let my lord speak, for you have strengthened me.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18. the Living One. I was dead, but look!—I am alive forever and ever! And I hold the keys to Death and Sh&amp;rsquo;ol.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 25:8 He will swallow up death forever; and the Lord GOD will wipe away tears from all faces, and the reproach of his people he will take away from all the earth, for the LORD has spoken.  &lt;br&gt;Hos 13:14 I shall ransom them from the power of Sheol; I shall redeem them from Death. O Death, where are your plagues? O Sheol, where is your sting?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19. So write down what you see, both what is now, and what will happen afterward.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 30:8; Jer 30:2; Hab 2:2 (see Rev 1:11)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20. Here is the secret meaning of the seven stars you saw in my right hand, and of the seven gold menorahs: the seven stars are the angels of the seven Messianic communities, and the seven menorahs are the seven Messianic communities.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Zech 4:2 And he said to me, “What do you see?” I said, “I see, and behold, a lampstand all of gold, with a bowl on the top of it, and seven lamps on it, with seven lips on each of the lamps that are on the top of it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VrImdKWK4dU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/one-like-a-son-of-man&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 1 Part 1 (1:1-11): Greetings</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/revelation-1-1-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/revelation-1-1-11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This third lesson is titled, &amp;ldquo;Greetings&amp;rdquo; because John includes an introduction and salutation very much in the style of correspondence of that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John will give us the sequence of the delivery:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From God to Yeshua/Jesus, from Yeshua to an angel, from an angel to John, and from John to Yeshua&amp;rsquo;s servants.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus had to learn of this from the Father.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is important to note that &lt;em&gt;it is the ANGEL who is speaking to John&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What makes this challenging is that the angel speaks of members of the Godhead in the 1st person.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Old Testament, we often see &amp;ldquo;the Angel of the LORD&amp;rdquo; also speaking of God the Father in the 1st person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have often assumed that the Angel of the LORD was a pre-incarnate appearance of Jesus.  We call this a &amp;ldquo;theophany.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now after studying the context of chapter 1, it may not be that simple.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The immediate recipients were His servants at the seven churches in Asia.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As we work through the book, begin to notice when things are out of place and how God sets things in their proper order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These Jewish congregations are outside of the land of Israel
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The promise made by God to their ancestors was to inherit the Land.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the end of Revelation, God will set this right and they will be back inside the Land.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then the document would have spread to all believers at the end of the first century.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then, indirectly, Revelation is written for all believers since, including you and me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/greek_letter_101ce.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;30%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John frequently uses the terms &amp;ldquo;testimony,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;witness.&amp;rdquo;  The picture to the right is a Dead Sea Scroll fragment (4Q175) called &lt;em&gt;Testimonia&lt;/em&gt; (“Messianic Anthology”), 1st century BC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He employs courtroom terminology in all his writings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Gospel of John, he is providing evidence that Jesus is the promised Messiah for all Israel in addition to evidence that the corrupt Jerusalem Temple establishment is usurping their power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Revelation, he testifies that not only is Jesus the coming king, this time it&amp;rsquo;s not just the corrupt Temple establishment but the corrupt world system that is on trial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation is unique because it is the only book in the Bible that promises a blessing for those who read, hear and obey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In chapter 1 we see the first of several patterns of seven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The commentary section of &lt;em&gt;talmidimway.org&lt;/em&gt; will list many of these.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example &amp;ldquo;Messiah&amp;rdquo; (v.1) and &amp;ldquo;Amen&amp;rdquo; (v.7) each occur exactly seven times throughout the book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are seven &amp;ldquo;blessings&amp;rdquo;, beginning with v.3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The description of Jesus in vs. 5-6 has seven attributes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the lesson, we will also unpack what John may have meant by, &amp;ldquo;I was in the Spirit on the Day of the Lord.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to read the cross-references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revelation 1:1-11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:1. This is the revelation which God gave to Yeshua the Messiah, so that he could show his servants what must happen very soon. He communicated it by sending his angel to his servant Yochanan,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Daniel 2:28 but there is a God in heaven who reveals mysteries, and he has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar what will be in the latter days. Your dream and the visions of your head as you lay in bed are these: 29 To you, O king, as you lay in bed came thoughts of what would be after this, and he who reveals mysteries made known to you what is to be.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:2. who bore witness to the Word of God and to the testimony of Yeshua the Messiah, as much as he saw&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:3. Blessed are the reader and hearers of the words of this prophecy, provided they obey the things written in it! For the time is near!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:4. From: Yochanan To: The seven Messianic communities in the province of Asia: Grace and shalom to you from the One who is, who was and who is coming; from the sevenfold Spirit before his throne;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 11:2 And the Spirit of the LORD shall rest upon him, the Spirit of wisdom and understanding, the Spirit of counsel and might, the Spirit of knowledge and the fear of the LORD.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:5. and from Yeshua the Messiah, the faithful witness, the firstborn from the dead and the ruler of the earth&amp;rsquo;s kings. To him, the one who loves us, who has freed us from our sins at the cost of his blood,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 49:11 Binding his foal to the vine and his donkey’s colt to the choice vine, he has washed his garments in wine and his vesture in the blood of grapes.&lt;br&gt; Psa 89:27 And I will make him the firstborn, the highest of the kings of the earth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:6. who has caused us to be a kingdom, that is, Cohanim for God, his Father—to him be the glory and the rulership forever and ever. Amen.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 19:5-6 Now therefore, if you will indeed obey my voice and keep my covenant, you shall be my treasured possession among all peoples, for all the earth is mine; 6 and you shall be to me a kingdom of priests and a holy nation.’ These are the words that you shall speak to the people of Israel.” &lt;br&gt;Isa 61:6 but you shall be called the priests of the LORD; they shall speak of you as the ministers of our God; you shall eat the wealth of the nations, and in their glory you shall boast.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:7. Look! He is coming with the clouds! Every eye will see him, including those who pierced him; and all the tribes of the Land will mourn him. Yes! Amen!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:13-14 “I saw in the night visions, and behold, with the clouds of heaven there came one like a son of man, and he came to the Ancient of Days and was presented before him. 14 And to him was given dominion and glory and a kingdom, that all peoples, nations, and languages should serve him; his dominion is an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass away, and his kingdom one that shall not be destroyed.  &lt;br&gt;Isa 52:8 The voice of your watchmen—they lift up their voice; together they sing for joy; for eye to eye they see the return of the LORD to Zion.  &lt;br&gt;Zech 12:10-12 “And I will pour out on the house of David and the inhabitants of Jerusalem a spirit of grace and pleas for mercy, so that, when they look on me, on him whom they have pierced, they shall mourn for him, as one mourns for an only child, and weep bitterly over him, as one weeps over a firstborn. 11 On that day the mourning in Jerusalem will be as great as the mourning for Hadad-rimmon in the plain of Megiddo. 12 The land shall mourn, each family by itself:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:8. &amp;ldquo;I am the &amp;lsquo;A&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;lsquo;Z,&amp;rsquo; &amp;quot; says Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, the One who is, who was and who is coming.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 41:4 Who has performed and done this, calling the generations from the beginning? I, the LORD, the first, and with the last; I am he.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:9. I, Yochanan, am a brother of yours and a fellow-sharer in the suffering, kingship and perseverance that come from being united with Yeshua. I had been exiled to the island called Patmos for having proclaimed the message of God and borne witness to Yeshua.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 10:2-4 In those days I, Daniel, was mourning for three weeks. 3 I ate no delicacies, no meat or wine entered my mouth, nor did I anoint myself at all, for the full three weeks. 4 On the twenty-fourth day of the first month, as I was standing on the bank of the great river (that is, the Tigris)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:10. I came to be, in the Spirit, on the Day of the Lord; and I heard behind me a loud voice, like a trumpet,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 2:12 For the LORD of hosts has a day against all that is proud and lofty, against all that is lifted up—and it shall be brought low; &lt;br&gt; Joe 1:15 Alas for the day! For the day of the LORD is near, and as destruction from the Almighty it comes. &lt;br&gt; Oba 1:15 For the day of the LORD is near upon all the nations. As you have done, it shall be done to you; your deeds shall return on your own head.  &lt;br&gt;Mal 4:5-6 “Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the great and awesome day of the LORD comes. (6) And he will turn the hearts of fathers to their children and the hearts of children to their fathers, lest I come and strike the land with a decree of utter destruction.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:11. saying, &amp;ldquo;Write down what you see on a scroll, and send it to the seven Messianic communities—Ephesus, Smyrna, Pergamum, Thyatira, Sardis, Philadelphia and Laodicea!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 30:8 And now, go, write it before them on a tablet and inscribe it in a book, that it may be for the time to come as a witness forever.&lt;br&gt;Jer 30:2 “Thus says the LORD, the God of Israel: Write in a book all the words that I have spoken to you.&lt;br&gt;Hab 2:2 And the LORD answered me: “Write the vision;  make it plain on tablets, so he may run who reads it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HDLBhn4p3mQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;listen-to-the-podcast&#34;&gt;Listen to the Podcast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/2-greetings-rev-1-1-11&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Next Gospel Backgrounds Lesson: Triumphal Entry Part I</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/next-gospel-backgrounds-lesson-triumphal-entry-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/next-gospel-backgrounds-lesson-triumphal-entry-part-i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This lesson is titled “The Triumphal Entry” because we have finally arrived at the most significant week in all human history. The next seven days are a roller coaster of emotions, ending on the highest peak of all, the Resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lesson 39 will be in two parts. Part I will review the Ascent of Adummim, which connects Jericho to Jerusalem. We’ll meet up with Jesus and the recently resurrected Lazarus in Bethany, look at how Jesus procures a donkey for his entry into Jerusalem, and examine the crowd’s reaction as they welcomed Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/2bafbd3f9ccec62efdf0eaf9ce825b36.png&#34; alt=&#34;Elevation from Jericho to Jerusalem&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson begins with Jesus and His talmidim leaving Jericho to make the 18-mile journey to Jerusalem. We can recreate this journey when we go to Israel (albeit from an air-conditioned bus with wi-fi). Although 18 miles is not that far, the elevation gain is steep, so one had to be in excellent physical shape to do it on foot. As the “Following the Messiah” hosts point out, it would be challenging to do that strenuous hike and carry on a conversation simultaneously. What was going through Jesus&#39; mind, knowing what would happen? What was going through the disciples&#39; minds, wondering what would happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, in John, we have the &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt; wondering whether Jesus would come to the feast? This is an odd thought, as attendance at the feast was compulsory for all able-bodied Jewish men. In John 11:56-57, John distinguishes the “Ioudaioi” and the “chief priests and the Pharisees.” Not all “Jews” (&lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt;) were in on the plot, and we also know that not all Pharisees were in on the plot either (Nicodemus, for one). If we keep reading in John 12:9-11, we see that many &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt; were “believing in Jesus.” This was because of Lazarus&#39; testimony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/9aed9aa5c1d2045b2e8c5dbbf23fc17c.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;a donkey in Bethany Israel&#34; width=&#34;33%&#34; style=&#34;float:left&#34;/&gt;
We assume Jesus spends Shabbat (Friday sundown to Saturday sundown) with Mary, Martha, and Lazarus (John may be indicating this in John 12:2-8). Then on Sunday morning, Jesus gives instructions to procure a donkey. We briefly discuss whether this represents a prophecy or whether Jesus was taking advantage of the hospitality system of that day (perhaps combined with His familiarity with the area). Just as with the beggars in Jericho, Matthew says “a colt and his mother,” whereas Mark and Luke focus only on the “colt.” Matthew occasionally says there were two of something when Luke/Mark focuses on the more significant one (perhaps this is a result of his former job as a tax collector!).
&lt;p&gt;The Triumphal entry is a big deal for one primary reason. Every other time before this, when the people wanted to anoint Jesus as their leader, He said, “my hour has not yet come.” Now, Jesus not only permits it, but He also arranges it in a way that has direct parallels to Solomon, another “son of David.” He would ride a donkey into Jerusalem, indicating that he comes not as a conqueror but in peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crowds shout “Hosanna” (Hebrew for “save us now” or “save us please!&amp;quot;) and wave palm branches, which was a direct allusion to the days of the Maccabees, who defeated the Seleucid Greeks in 166 BCE. In other words, they were encouraging Jesus to take over politically. They also chant Psalms 118, another messianic reference. It was unmistakable that they were crowning Jesus as the messiah, which Jesus is Ok with (Luke 19:40) .  The problem is (to borrow a quote), “this is not the messiah you’re looking for.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/IMG_1037.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;33%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
To close the lesson, we look at the “cheapest souvenir in Israel.” When the Pharisees heard the people chanting that Psalm in THAT circumstance, they feared reprisal from the leadership, this is one indication that these Pharisees were not against Jesus but were on his side. They simply feared for his safety.
&lt;p&gt;Jesus said, “If these kept quiet, the very stones would cry out.” So the cheapest souvenir is to bring home one of the stones that didn’t cry out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part II will continue with Jesus weeping over Jerusalem, a precise prophecy that would be fulfilled around 40 years later, and other activities in the Temple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew 21:1-17&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark 11:1-11&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luke 19:28-40&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John 11:55-12:1, John 12:9-16&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Note: There is a known textual problem with John 12:2-8, which we will discuss when we get to Matthew 26.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-videos&#34;&gt;Watch the videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gospel Backgrounds Lesson Video:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6YKiE6NzcV0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beginning of the Following the Messiah episode 8 has an excellent segment about the Triumphal Entry. Watch through 8:55.

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8UaThqyEBzc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb4/39-triumphal-entry-i&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to study the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historical Prelude to Revelation</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/historical-prelude-to-revelation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/historical-prelude-to-revelation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a supplement to our Revelation background series. We’re going to take a look at significant events in the period between the Jewish Revolt of 66CE, including the destruction of the Jewish Temple in 70, through the mid-90s that resulted in John’s exile on Patmos, where he received the Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This interval history is surprisingly relevant if we wish to better understand the context for Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if history wasn’t your best subject in school, I believe you’ll find this background helpful as we prepare to study Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b5iQBoBvy_0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/historical-prelude&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New series! Revelation Backgrounds</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/new-series-revelation-backgrounds/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/new-series-revelation-backgrounds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;images/e45914e26cc0be101f69fd4d54a746be.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to our series on the book of Revelation we call &amp;ldquo;Revelation Backgrounds.&amp;rdquo;  In this introductory episode, we will provide an introduction to the book, some background into Jewish Apocalyptic literature, and we&amp;rsquo;ll provide what we see are Seven Keys to Interpretation.  Revelation can be a complex book, but these keys will help assure we get started on the right path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many commentators focus on what Revelation may mean to us living in the 21st Century, very few Protestant commentators take the time to understand the historical, first-century context.  Revelation, as it turns out, is the &lt;em&gt;most Jewish book&lt;/em&gt; in the New Testament. There are over 800 allusions to the Old Testament in the book&amp;rsquo;s 404 verses.  The reasons many people struggle with the book is because we ignore its Jewishness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have developed &amp;ldquo;Seven Keys to Interpretation,&amp;rdquo; which we will discuss in the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow the &amp;ldquo;Talmidim Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; -  We want to learn to walk in the dust of Yeshua our Rabbi just as His original Talmidim, His disciples such as John did.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be open to the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s leading&lt;/strong&gt; - Understanding what God wants us to learn is way more important that making sure others know our beliefs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be a Berean&lt;/strong&gt; - Check everything out against scripture.  If our interpretation doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit, it might be something we need to discard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand the intended audience&lt;/strong&gt; - They were Jewish, or if they were gentiles, they were worshipping in a Jewish setting, which would have almost nothing in common with our western protestant churches today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revelation is a Jewish Book&lt;/strong&gt; - For every verse in Revelation there is a 2:1 ratio of Old Testament illusions.  If we try to understand Revelation without this background, we&amp;rsquo;ll be lost.  With it, we&amp;rsquo;ll be much better off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be suspicious if an interpretation does not fit the original context&lt;/strong&gt; - that is to say, if it could not have been within the realm of possibility for John or the original audience.  This is not to say that the book can&amp;rsquo;t have multiple layers of interpretation, but for our historical and cultural approach, we want to start by making sure it&amp;rsquo;s something that would have made sense to the original audience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No fear allowed&lt;/strong&gt; -  While books and websites present the events of Revelation as something that should scare an unbeliever (and they probably should be scared), fear has no place in a believer&amp;rsquo;s heart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will also look at who wrote the book and some other details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who wrote Revelation?  &lt;strong&gt;John the Apostle&lt;/strong&gt;.  We don&amp;rsquo;t have 100% concrete proof, but the earliest and best evidence suggests it was none other than John, the author of the Gospel and three letters that bear his name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where was it written?  &lt;strong&gt;Patmos&lt;/strong&gt;, which is an island some 35 miles off the coast of Turkey. Revelation 1:9 is our source for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When was it written?  Most conservative scholars land on &lt;strong&gt;90-95 of the Common Era&lt;/strong&gt;.  Iraneus is the earliest source for this information.  He was a disciple of Polycarp, who was a disciple of John.  Iraneus states John received the relevation during the time of Emperor Domitian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How was Revelation given?  &lt;strong&gt;Signs and Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;! Revelation 1:1 contains the Greek word σημαίνω, which literally means &amp;ldquo;rendered into signs.&amp;rdquo; Every sign in the Bible points to something.  Every sign in Revelation points to a verse (sometimes more than one) in the Old Testament.  The pattern of the number seven is also quite conspicuous.  Sevens are everywhere in Revelation.  Since sevens are also conspicuous throughout the entire Bible, this is often seen as the &amp;ldquo;fingerprints of the Holy Spirit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To whom was Revelation written? &lt;strong&gt;The seven messianic congregations in Asia Minor.&lt;/strong&gt;.  We are told this in Revelation 1:4.  Note that although your Bible may say &amp;ldquo;seven churches,&amp;rdquo; the &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; either as a building or an organization did not exist when Revelation was given.  We need to avoid what is called an &lt;em&gt;anachronistic fallacy&lt;/em&gt;.  See the lesson detail for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why was Revelation written? &lt;strong&gt;The Hope of HIS RETURN and the Restoration of all things!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to beginning this study!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation 1:1-9&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SfuWhCybaYU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;audio-only&#34;&gt;Audio only&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&#34;Introduction - Revelation Backgrounds #1&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; style=&#34;border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; data-name=&#34;pb-iframe-player&#34; src=&#34;https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=txkgm-11a4bf1-pb&amp;from=pb6admin&amp;share=1&amp;download=1&amp;rtl=0&amp;fonts=Arial&amp;skin=1&amp;font-color=auto&amp;btn-skin=3&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/revelation-introduction&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zacchaeus and Bartimaeus</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/38-zaccheaus-and-bartimaus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/38-zaccheaus-and-bartimaus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This lesson is titled &amp;ldquo;Zacchaeus and Bartimaeus&amp;rdquo; because of the healings, one physical and one spiritual of Blind Bartimaeus and Zacchaeus, the wealthy tax collector. In Luke, Jesus also gives the double-parable of the Minas (Pounds) and the King&amp;rsquo;s Return. The lesson begins with Jesus passing through Jericho on His way up to Jerusalem for the Passover, where we are presented with two potential textual problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew says they were leaving Jericho, while Mark/Luke says they drew near to Jericho.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew says there were two beggars, while Mark/Luke list only one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both tensions are easily reconciled and need not distract us from the core teachings of the passage.  There are several lessons for us with the healing of Bartimaeus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/ad09ca3fccdb82076f4cf3d075fcbe64.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Sycamore tree in Jericho&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Luke alone tells the story of Zacchaeus, the repentant tax collector.  Zacchaeus would have been extremely wealthy, but mainstream Jewish society viewed tax collectors as outcasts.  To his credit, he wanted to see Jesus, and, as it turns out, Jesus wanted to see him. Zacchaeus was likely less than five feet tall, so he decided to climb a Sycamore tree to get a better view. Jesus notices the man in the tree, then says He &amp;ldquo;must&amp;rdquo; stay with him.  Apparently, without any prompting from Jesus, Zacchaeus pledges to give half his goods to the poor. To the extent he defrauded anyone (which he did), he promised to repay with 4x damages.  Jesus tells him, “Today salvation has come.” Jesus chose to honor an outcast, and he repented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke concludes this section with Jesus telling (but not explaining) two parables. Both fall into the category of “Journey parables.” With these parables in Luke 19, Luke makes it a point to tell us that Jesus told the parables “BECAUSE they supposed that the kingdom of God was to appear immediately.” So whatever interpretation and application we come up with, it must connect somehow to the fact that (as we, the readers, know) the Messianic Kingdom did NOT appear immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is curious about these parables is that Jesus deliberately compares the King-on-a-journey to the hated and wicked Herod Archelaus. Archelaus was so bad even the Romans got rid of him.  So, the reader is presented with a curious question: if Jesus is allegorically speaking of Himself as the King in the parables, why would He so obviously compare Himself to the wicked Archelaus?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video and lesson detail will explore some plausible interpretations and applications of these parables, including one that we might say goes against the grain of our typical expectations. We’ll don our “Acts 17:11 thinking caps” to work through these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson concludes with Luke writing, “when He had said these things, he went on ahead, going up to Jerusalem.” In the next lesson, we will examine the Triumphal Entry, which is the first of the most significant seven days in all human history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readhear-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/hear the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew 20:29-34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark 10:46-52&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luke 18:35-19:38 (Primary)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6o6Y8OogPgw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/38-zacchaeus-and-bartimaeus/&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Jordan Part II</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/beyond-the-jordan-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/beyond-the-jordan-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part II of the Gospel Backgrounds lesson titled, &amp;ldquo;Beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin the lesson, Jesus receives a question from a &amp;ldquo;rich, young ruler&amp;rdquo; about what must be done to inherit eternal life. We often think that the young man has a &amp;ldquo;works righteousness&amp;rdquo; mindset - in other words, if a person has enough good deeds, he or she will merit eternal salvation. This is true to some degree, but notice Jesus&#39; answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t say &amp;ldquo;to get eternal life, all you need to do is accept Me into your heart.&amp;rdquo; In response to the immediate question, Jesus says first &amp;ldquo;keep the commandments&amp;rdquo;.  Then when pressed further, He says, &amp;ldquo;one thing you lack: sell everything, give it to the poor, then follow Me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that Jesus doesn&amp;rsquo;t rebuke the young man about being self-righteous, nor does Jesus correct the man&amp;rsquo;s errant theology. The man had a heart issue, not a head issue. There is a lot more going on with this exchange than it may first appear.  We will take a peek under the hood to get at some of the lessons for our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/mat05686.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exchange befuddles the disciples.  They &amp;ldquo;remind&amp;rdquo; Jesus that they HAVE left everything and followed their Rabbi as His talmidim.  Jesus assures them that their sacrifices will not go unrewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 20 begins with one of my favorite parables, the parable of the workers.  A man needs workers for his vineyard.  He finds some early in the day, but also at various points throughout the day, including at the &amp;ldquo;11th hour&amp;rdquo; right before the work is to end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the work is done, the owner calls the workers from last to first and, to the surprise of those hired early, everyone is paid a denarious, a full day&amp;rsquo;s wage.  Those hired early in the day gripe that this is unfair.  Is is right that someone who did 1/12 of the work get paid the same as those who did a full day&amp;rsquo;s work?  The owner replies that the first group agreed to the wage, and besides what He does with his money is his business and no one else&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parable is rich with meaning and has several practical and spiritual applications.  We will discuss a few of these in the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The section concludes with Jesus receiving a request from James and John to sit at Jesus&#39; right and left hands during the millennial kingdom, which is often portrayed as a great banquet.  Instead of rebuking their pride, Jesus explains what it means to sit by his side and &amp;ldquo;drink His cup&amp;rdquo;.  This act of presumption, naturally, irks the other ten disciples.  Jesus explains that our mission as disciples is not to be serve but to serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew 19:16-20:28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark 10:17-45&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luke 18:18-34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MNGvRWEF5PU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/37b-beyond-the-jordan-ii&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Jordan Part I </title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/across-the-jordan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/across-the-jordan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;images/37.map.png&#34; title=&#34;map&#34; width=&#34;65%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel Backgrounds&lt;/em&gt; Lesson 37 is titled &amp;ldquo;Beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo;  We will do this in two parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After leaving the Harod Valley [#7 on the map], Jesus makes His way to the Jordan, just south of where it exits the Sea of Galilee.  The north-south path along the river in this vicinity was along the eastern shore, which the Gospel writers call &amp;ldquo;Judea beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo; [8]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus will engage a group of inquisitive (but not necessarily trecharous) Pharisees who want to know the Master&amp;rsquo;s position on divorce.  As it is today, divorce was a critical and controversial topic because of its impact on family and society.  The Pharisees themselves were divided on when divorce was permissible.  The majority view held that a man could divorce his wife for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; reason, including not liking her cooking or even finding another woman more attractive.  The minority view held that the Torah had in view sexual misconduct as the only permissible reason.  Jesus sided with the minority.  The disciples are so taken-aback by Jesus&#39; response that they exclaim &amp;ldquo;in that case, it is better not to marry!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus also teaches about the role of children and we will understand what it means to &amp;ldquo;become like a child&amp;rdquo; in order to enter heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IxJTLlEQlp4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/beyond-the-jordan&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds commentary&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Between Samaria and Galilee</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/between-samaria-and-galilee/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/between-samaria-and-galilee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel Backgrounds&lt;/em&gt; Lesson 36 is titled &amp;ldquo;Between Samaria and Galilee,&amp;rdquo; and is taken from Luke 17:11 where we are told Jesus is making his way up to Jerusalem for His final passover and passes between Samaria and Galilee.  The video will explore the geography of the region know as the Harod Valley, where many scholars believe this episode took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/36.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central story is that of Jesus healing ten lepers.  While all ten were healed, only one, a Samaritan, returned to give thanks and praise to Jesus.  In that day, most Jews had a dim view of Samaritans as evidenced by the three stories where Samaritans are featured prominently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Woman at the Well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The parable of the Good Samaritan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Ten Lepers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson for us is if even a Samaritan has enough heart to give thanks, how much more should we, as followers/disciples/talmidim of Yeshua have a humble and thankful heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TKbltCM2Hus&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
