<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu53652e90a6e4e4f125f22da2a993ec10_403021_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genesis Lesson Audio</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/genesis-1-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/genesis-1-1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 7 - the 144,000</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/rev07/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/rev07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ugnF0Dz_PV8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/uploads/rev-7-verses.pdf&#34;&gt;Revelation 7 Cross-reference Verses PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rev 7:1-17&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After this, I saw four angels standing at the four corners of the earth, holding back the four winds of the earth, so that no wind would blow on the land, on the sea or on any tree. I saw another angel coming up from the east with a seal from the living God, and he shouted to the four angels who had been given power to harm the land and the sea, &amp;ldquo;Do not harm the land or the sea or the trees until we have sealed the servants of our God on their foreheads!&amp;rdquo; I heard how many were sealed—144,000 from every tribe of the people of Isra&amp;rsquo;el: From the tribe of Y&amp;rsquo;hudah 12,000 were sealed, from the tribe of Re&amp;rsquo;uven 12,000, from the tribe of Gad 12,000, from the tribe of Asher 12,000, from the tribe of Naftali 12,000, from the tribe of M&amp;rsquo;nasheh 12,000, from the tribe of Shim`on 12,000, from the tribe of Levi 12,000, from the tribe of Yissakhar 12,000, from the tribe of Z&amp;rsquo;vulun 12,000, from the tribe of Yosef 12,000, from the tribe of Binyamin 12,000. After this, I looked; and there before me was a huge crowd, too large for anyone to count, from every nation, tribe, people and language. They were standing in front of the throne and in front of the Lamb, dressed in white robes and holding palm branches in their hands; and they shouted, &amp;ldquo;Victory to our God, who sits on the throne, and to the Lamb!&amp;rdquo; All the angels stood around the throne, the elders and the four living beings; they fell face down before the throne and worshipped God, saying, &amp;ldquo;Amen! &amp;ldquo;Praise and glory, wisdom and thanks, honor and power and strength belong to our God forever and ever! &amp;ldquo;Amen!&amp;rdquo; One of the elders asked me, &amp;ldquo;These people dressed in white robes—who are they, and where are they from?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Sir,&amp;rdquo; I answered, &amp;ldquo;you know.&amp;rdquo; Then he told me, &amp;ldquo;These are the people who have come out of the Great Persecution. They have washed their robes and made them white with the blood of the Lamb. That is why they are before God&amp;rsquo;s throne. &amp;ldquo;Day and night they serve him in his Temple; and the One who sits on the throne will put his Sh&amp;rsquo;khinah upon them. &amp;ldquo;They will never again be hungry, they will never again be thirsty, the sun will not beat down on them, nor will any burning heat. &amp;ldquo;For the Lamb at the center of the throne will shepherd them, will lead them to springs of living water, and God will wipe every tear from their eyes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/rev07&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 5</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/rev05/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/rev05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation 5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5:1 Next I saw in the right hand of the One sitting on the throne a scroll with writing on both sides and sealed with seven seals; (2) and I saw a mighty angel proclaiming in a loud voice, &amp;ldquo;Who is worthy to open the scroll and break its seals?&amp;rdquo; (3) But no one in heaven, on earth or under the earth was able to open the scroll or look inside it. (4) I cried and cried, because no one was found worthy to open the scroll or look inside it. (5) One of the elders said to me, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t cry. Look, the Lion of the tribe of Y&amp;rsquo;hudah, the Root of David, has won the right to open the scroll and its seven seals.&amp;rdquo; (6) Then I saw standing there with the throne and the four living beings, in the circle of the elders, a Lamb that appeared to have been slaughtered. He had seven horns and seven eyes, which are the sevenfold Spirit of God sent out into all the earth. (7) He came and took the scroll out of the right hand of the One sitting on the throne. (8) When he took the scroll, the four living beings and the twenty-four elders fell down in front of the Lamb. Each one held a harp and gold bowls filled with pieces of incense, which are the prayers of God&amp;rsquo;s people; (9) and they sang a new song, &amp;ldquo;You are worthy to take the scroll and break its seals; because you were slaughtered; at the cost of blood you ransomed for God persons from every tribe, language, people and nation. (10) You made them into a kingdom for God to rule, cohanim to serve him; and they will rule over the earth.&amp;rdquo; (11) Then I looked, and I heard the sound of a vast number of angels—thousands and thousands, millions and millions! They were all around the throne, the living beings and the elders; (12) and they shouted out, &amp;ldquo;Worthy is the slaughtered Lamb to receive power, riches, wisdom, strength, honor, glory and praise!&amp;rdquo; (13) And I heard every creature in heaven, on earth, under the earth and on the sea—yes, everything in them—saying, &amp;ldquo;To the One sitting on the throne and to the Lamb belong praise, honor, glory and power forever and ever!&amp;rdquo; (14) The four living beings said, &amp;ldquo;Amen!&amp;rdquo; and the elders fell down and worshipped.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vJv32aYI7VY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/uploads/rev-5-verses.pdf&#34;&gt;Revelation 5 Cross-reference Verses PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/rev05&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 4</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/rev-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/rev-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portion&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation 4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After these things, I looked; and there before me was a door standing open in heaven; and the voice like a trumpet which I had heard speaking with me before said, &amp;ldquo;Come up here, and I will show you what must happen after these things.&amp;rdquo; (2) Instantly I was in the Spirit, and there before me in heaven stood a throne, and on the throne Someone was sitting. (3) The One sitting there gleamed like diamonds and rubies, and a rainbow shining like emerald encircled the throne. (4) Surrounding the throne were twenty-four other thrones, and on the thrones sat twenty-four elders dressed in white clothing and wearing gold crowns on their heads. (5) From the throne came forth lightnings, voices and thunderings; and before the throne were seven flaming torches, which are the sevenfold Spirit of God. (6) In front of the throne was what looked like a sea of glass, clear as crystal. In the center, around the throne, were four living beings covered with eyes in front and behind. (7) The first living being was like a lion, the second living being was like an ox, the third living being had a face that looked human, and the fourth living being was like a flying eagle. (8) Each of the four living beings had six wings and was covered with eyes inside and out; and day and night they never stop saying, &amp;ldquo;Holy, holy, holy is Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies the One who was, who is and who is coming!&amp;rdquo; (9) And whenever the living beings give glory, honor and thanks to the One sitting on the throne, to the One who lives forever and ever, (10) the twenty-four elders fall down before the One sitting on the throne, who lives forever and ever, and worship him. They throw their crowns in front of the throne and say, (11) &amp;ldquo;You are worthy, Adonai Eloheinu, to have glory, honor and power, because you created all things—yes, because of your will they were created and came into being!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/uploads/rev-4-verses.pdf&#34;&gt;Revelation 4 Cross-reference Verses PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DK6fxCGuxoA&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/rev-4&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laodicea</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/laodicea/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/laodicea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This lesson is titled, &amp;quot;&amp;quot; because&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/mat05686.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Revelation 3:14-22&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rev 3:14&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;To the angel of the Messianic Community in Laodicea, write: &amp;lsquo;Here is the message from the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the Ruler of God&amp;rsquo;s creation:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 1:1 In the beginning God created &amp;hellip; &lt;br&gt;Joh 1:1-3 In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. (2) He was in the beginning with God. (3) All things were made through him, and without him was not any thing made that was made.  &lt;br&gt;Isa 65:16 so that he who blesses himself in the land shall bless himself by the God of truth, and he who takes an oath in the land shall swear by the God of truth; because the former troubles are forgotten and are hidden from my eyes. Deu 6:4 &amp;ldquo;Sh&amp;rsquo;m&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;, Yisra&amp;rsquo;el! Adonai Eloheinu, Adonai echa&lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:15-16 &amp;ldquo;I know what you are doing: you are neither cold nor hot. How I wish you were either one or the other! (16) So, because you are lukewarm, neither cold nor hot, I will vomit you out of my mouth!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 18:24-25 “Do not make yourselves unclean by any of these things, for by all these the nations I am driving out before you have become unclean, (25) and the land became unclean so that I punished its iniquity, and the land vomited out its inhabitants.  &lt;br&gt;1Ki 18:20-21 So Ahab sent to all the people of Israel and gathered the prophets together at Mount Carmel. (21) And Elijah came near to all the people and said, “How long will you go limping between two different opinions? If the LORD is God, follow him; but if Baal, then follow him.” And the people did not answer him a word. &lt;br&gt;Jas 1:8 he is a double-minded man, unstable in all his ways. &lt;br&gt;Mat 6:24 “No one can serve two masters, for either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will be devoted to the one and despise the other. You cannot serve God and money&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:17-18 For you keep saying, &amp;lsquo;I am rich, I have gotten rich, I don&amp;rsquo;t need a thing!&amp;rsquo; You don&amp;rsquo;t know that you are the one who is wretched, pitiable, poor, blind and naked! (18) My advice to you is to buy from me gold refined by fire, so that you may be rich; and white clothing, so that you may be dressed and not have to be ashamed of your nakedness; and eyesalve to rub on your eyes, so that you may see.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hos 12:6-8 “So you, by the help of your God, return, hold fast to love and justice, and wait continually for your God.” (7) A merchant, in whose hands are false balances, he loves to oppress. (8) Ephraim has said, “Ah, but I am rich; I have found wealth for myself; in all my labors they cannot find in me iniquity or sin.”  &lt;br&gt;Joh 15:5 I am the vine; you are the branches. Whoever abides in me and I in him, he it is that bears much fruit, for apart from me you can do nothing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:19 As for me, I rebuke and discipline everyone I love; so exert yourselves, and turn from your sins!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pro 3:11-12 My son, do not despise the LORD&amp;rsquo;s discipline or be weary of his reproof, (12) for the LORD reproves him whom he loves, as a father the son in whom he delights. (also quoted in Heb 12:6) &lt;br&gt;Jas 5:19-20 My brothers, if anyone among you wanders from the truth and someone brings him back, (20) let him know that whoever brings back a sinner from his wandering will save his soul from death and will cover a multitude of sins.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:20 Here, I&amp;rsquo;m standing at the door, knocking. If someone hears my voice and opens the door, I will come in to him and eat with him, and he will eat with me.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:8-9 And they heard the sound of the LORD God walking in the garden in the cool of the day, and the man and his wife hid themselves from the presence of the LORD God among the trees of the garden. (9) But the LORD God called to the man and said to him, “Where are you?”  &lt;br&gt;Zec 1:1-4 In the eighth month, in the second year of Darius, the word of the LORD came to the prophet Zechariah, the son of Berechiah, son of Iddo, saying, (2) “The LORD was very angry with your fathers. (3) Therefore say to them, Thus declares the LORD of hosts: Return to me, says the LORD of hosts, and I will return to you, says the LORD of hosts. (4) Do not be like your fathers, to whom the former prophets cried out, ‘Thus says the LORD of hosts, Return from your evil ways and from your evil deeds.’ But they did not hear or pay attention to me, declares the LORD. &lt;br&gt;Luk 22:28-30 “You are those who have stayed with me in my trials, (29) and I assign to you, as my Father assigned to me, a kingdom, (30) that you may eat and drink at my table in my kingdom and sit on thrones judging the twelve tribes of Israel.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:21-22 I will let him who wins the victory sit with me on my throne, just as I myself also won the victory and sat down with my Father on his throne. (22) Those who have ears, let them hear what the Spirit is saying to the Messianic communities.&amp;rdquo; &amp;rsquo; &amp;quot;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Heb 4:14-16 Since then we have a great high priest who has passed through the heavens, Jesus, the Son of God, let us hold fast our confession. (15) For we do not have a high priest who is unable to sympathize with our weaknesses, but one who in every respect has been tempted as we are, yet without sin. (16) Let us then with confidence draw near to the throne of grace, that we may receive mercy and find grace to help in time of need.   &lt;br&gt;He who has an ear 7x in Revelation and 7x in the Gospels: Mat 11:15, Mat 13:9, Mat 13:43; Mar 4:9, Mar 4:23, Luk 8:8, Luk 14:34  &lt;br&gt;1Jn 5:4-5 For everyone who has been born of God overcomes the world. And this is the victory that has overcome the world—our faith. (5) Who is it that overcomes the world except the one who believes that Jesus is the Son of God?  &lt;br&gt;Joh_16:33 I have said these things to you, that in me you may have peace. In the world you will have tribulation. But take heart; I have overcome the world.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-videos&#34;&gt;Watch the videos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/c86AZPr0a50&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/buaDbpPRosg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HZDxpy-UQOg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seven-letters-summary-table&#34;&gt;Seven Letters Summary Table&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Ephesus&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Smyrna&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pergamum&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Thyatira&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Sardis&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Laodicea&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Darling; desired&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Myrrh; death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Height; Mixed (strange) Marriage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Daughter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Precious stone&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Brotherly Love&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;People ruling&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;From&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Holds 7 stars/ walks among lampstands&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First/last dead/alive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sharp two-edged sword&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Son of God; eyes of fire; feet of brass&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sevenfold Spirit &amp;amp; Seven Stars&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Holy, True, Key of David Open Door&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Amen, faithful and true witness, head of God&amp;rsquo;s creation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Praise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t tolerate evil; Persevered; Acts 17:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Suffering (pressing, tribulation) and insults&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not denied faith; holds fast to His name; know they live where Satan has his throne&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;love, trust, service, and perseverance; improving&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NONE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kept Word and not denied&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NONE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Judgment&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lost love they had at first&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tolerate those with sexual and dietary sin (Balaam)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jezebel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;False reputation; they are dead! Works are incomplete. Repent or He will come like a thief&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None directed to Philadelphia – will sit in judgment of false Jews who will learn He loves&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lukewarm – to be vomited; think they are rich and in need of nothing but truly are wretched, poor, pitiable, blind, and naked.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Secondary Encouragement&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hates deeds of people who do things their own way instead of God&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Do not fear suffering; remain faithful&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hold fast against teaching of deep things of Satan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A few who have not soiled clothes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Patient endurance will keep them from the worldwide hour of trial for earth-dwellers&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Buy gold refined by fire (not poor), white clothing (not naked), eysalve (not blind). He rebukes those whom He loves, so repent! Those who open the door He will eat with them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Location of &amp;ldquo;Ear&amp;rdquo; clause&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat from Tree/Life&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not taste 2nd death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat of Hidden Manna / A white stone/new name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Authority over nations; morning star&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dressed in white; name in Book, be acknowledged in Heaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pillar in Millennial temple; write on him name of my God, name of new Jerusalem, and His own Name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sit on his throne&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Neglected priorities&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Expect Satanic opposition&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beware spiritual compromise: (worshipping God AND something else)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beware of pagan practices mixed in and corrupting the true faith: (worshipping something else pretending it&amp;rsquo;s God)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Be watchful and diligently guard the heart (not just doctrine)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Loyal ambassadorship&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beware of apostasy and denying what we once held true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Age&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apostolic (70-170)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Persecuted (170-312)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;State Religion (312-606)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Catholic (606-present)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Protestant (1517 - present)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Missionary &amp;ldquo;on fire&amp;rdquo;; Raptured (1750-present)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lazy, apostate (1900 – present)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Parable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Four Soils&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wheat/tares&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mustard seed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Woman/leaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Treasure/Field&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pearl of Great Price&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dragnet&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paul&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philippians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1/2 Corinthians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Galatians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Romans&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1/2 Thessalonians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Colossians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/laodicea&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 2 Part 4 (2:18-29): Thyatira</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/thyatira/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/thyatira/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Click the link, then click on the speaker icon to hear ESV verse audio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation 2:18-29&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18 &amp;ldquo;To the angel of the Messianic Community in Thyatira, write: &amp;lsquo;Here is the message from the Son of God, whose eyes are like a fiery flame and whose feet are like burnished brass:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 2:7 I will tell of the decree: The LORD said to me, “You are my Son; today I have begotten you.  &lt;br&gt; Dan 10:6 His body was like beryl, his face like the appearance of lightning, his eyes like flaming torches, his arms and legs like the gleam of burnished bronze, and the sound of his words like the sound of a multitude. &lt;br&gt; Mal 3:2-4 But who can endure the day of his coming, and who can stand when he appears? For he is like a refiner&amp;rsquo;s fire and like fullers&amp;rsquo; soap. (3) He will sit as a refiner and purifier of silver, and he will purify the sons of Levi and refine them like gold and silver, and they will bring offerings in righteousness to the LORD. (4) Then the offering of Judah and Jerusalem will be pleasing to the LORD as in the days of old and as in former years.  &lt;br&gt; Mat 3:17 and behold, a voice from heaven said, “This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased.”  &lt;br&gt; Mat 16:15-16 He said to them, “But who do you say that I am?” (16) Simon Peter replied, “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God.”  &lt;br&gt; Joh 3:16 “For God so loved the world, that he gave his only Son, that whoever believes in him should not perish but have eternal life.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(19) I know what you are doing, your love, trust, service, and perseverance. And I know that you are doing more now than before.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Job 17:9  Yet the righteous holds to his way,  and he who has clean hands grows stronger and stronger.&lt;br&gt;  Pro 4:18  But the path of the righteous is like the light of dawn,  which shines brighter and brighter until full day.&lt;br&gt;  John 15:2 Every branch in me that does not bear fruit he takes away, and every branch that does bear fruit he prunes, that it may bear more fruit.&lt;br&gt; Gal 5:22-23 But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, faithfulness, (23) gentleness, self-control; against such things, there is no law. &lt;br&gt;Th 1:3 We ought always to give thanks to God for you, brothers, as is right, because your faith is growing abundantly, and the love of every one of you for one another is increasing.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(20) But I have this against you: you continue to tolerate that Izevel woman, the one who claims to be a prophet, but is teaching and deceiving my servants to commit sexual sin and eat food that has been sacrificed to idols.  &lt;br&gt;(21) I gave her time to turn from her sin, but she doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to repent of her immorality.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deu 13:1-5 “If a prophet or a dreamer of dreams arises among you and gives you a sign or a wonder, (2) and the sign or wonder that he tells you comes to pass, and if he says, ‘Let us go after other gods,’ which you have not known, ‘and let us serve them,’ (3) you shall not listen to the words of that prophet or that dreamer of dreams. … (5) But that prophet or that dreamer of dreams shall be put to death because he has taught rebellion against the LORD your God…&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(24) But to the rest of you in Thyatira, to those who do not hold this teaching, who have not learned what some people call the &amp;lsquo;deep things&amp;rsquo; of the Adversary, I say this: I am not loading you up with another burden; &lt;br&gt;(25) only hold fast to what you have until I come.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Act 15:28-29 For it has seemed good to the Holy Spirit and to us to lay on you no greater burden than these requirements: (29) that you abstain from what has been sacrificed to idols, and from blood, and from what has been strangled, and from sexual immorality. If you keep yourselves from these, you will do well. Farewell.” &lt;br&gt;1 Cor 2:10 these things God has revealed to us through the Spirit. For the Spirit searches everything, even the depths of God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 2:26-29 To him who wins the victory and does what I want until the goal is reached, I will give him authority over the nations;  &lt;br&gt;(27) he will rule them with a staff of iron and dash them to pieces like pottery,  &lt;br&gt;(28) just as I have received authority from my Father. I will also give him the morning star.  &lt;br&gt;(29) Those who have ears, let them hear what the Spirit is saying to the Messianic communities.&amp;rdquo; &#39;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 2:1-12 Why do the nations rage and the peoples plot in vain? (2) The kings of the earth set themselves, and the rulers take counsel together, against the LORD and against his Anointed, saying, (3) “Let us burst their bonds apart and cast away their cords from us.” (4) He who sits in the heavens laughs; the Lord holds them in derision. (5) Then he will speak to them in his wrath, and terrify them in his fury, saying, (6) “As for me, I have set my King on Zion, my holy hill.” (7) I will tell of the decree: The LORD said to me, “You are my Son; today I have begotten you. (8) Ask of me, and I will make the nations your heritage, and the ends of the earth your possession. (9) You shall break them with a rod of iron and dash them in pieces like a potter&amp;rsquo;s vessel.” (10) Now therefore, O kings, be wise; be warned, O rulers of the earth. (11) Serve the LORD with fear, and rejoice with trembling. (12) Kiss the Son, lest he be angry, and you perish in the way, for his wrath is quickly kindled. Blessed are all who take refuge in him.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seven-letters-outline&#34;&gt;Seven Letters Outline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ephesus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smyrna&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pergamum&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thyatira&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sardis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laodicea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Darling; desired&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Myrrh; death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Height; Mixed (strange) Marriage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Daughter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;From&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Holds 7 stars/ walks among lampstands&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First/last dead/alive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sharp two-edged sword&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Son of God&lt;/strong&gt;; eyes of fire; feet of brass&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t tolerate evil; Persevered; Acts 17:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Suffering (pressing, tribulation) and insults&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not denied faith; holds fast to His name; know they live where Satan has his throne&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;love, trust, service, and perseverance; improving&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lost love they had at first&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tolerate those with sexual and dietary sin (Balaam)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jezebel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hates deeds of people who do things their own way instead of God&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Do not fear suffering; remain faithful&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hold fast against teaching of deep things of Satan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ear&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat from Tree/Life&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not taste 2nd death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat of Hidden Manna / A white stone/new name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Authority over nations; morning star&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Neglected priorities&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Expect Satanic opposition&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beware spiritual compromise: (worshipping God AND something else)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beware of pagan practices mixed in and corrupting the true faith: (worshipping something else pretending it&amp;rsquo;s God)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Age&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apostolic (70-170)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Persecuted (170-312)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;State Religion (312-606)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Catholic (606-present)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Parable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Four Soils&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wheat/tares&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mustard seed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Woman/leaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paul&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philippians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1/2 Corinthians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Galatians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-videos&#34;&gt;Watch the videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part I: Thyatira background, trade guilds,  Revelation 2:18-21 (verses 22-29 are covered in Part II); Elijah and prophets of Baal at Mount Carmel.  Jezebel and Naboth&amp;rsquo;s vineyard at Jezreel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pevw5haAxME&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part II: Revelation 2:22-29; Does it fit?  Church Age = Catholic Church; Parable= Woman &amp;amp; Leaven; Paul=Galatians&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AKGu6Tzraoc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;audio-commentary&#34;&gt;Audio Commentary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&#34;Thyatira I - Revelation Backgrounds 9a&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; style=&#34;border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; data-name=&#34;pb-iframe-player&#34; src=&#34;https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=8qnih-11cc6f3-pb&amp;from=pb6admin&amp;share=1&amp;download=1&amp;rtl=0&amp;fonts=Arial&amp;skin=3267a3&amp;font-color=auto&amp;btn-skin=3267a3&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&#34;Thyatira II - Revelation Backgrounds 9b&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; style=&#34;border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; data-name=&#34;pb-iframe-player&#34; src=&#34;https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=jv2yw-11cc700-pb&amp;from=pb6admin&amp;share=1&amp;download=1&amp;rtl=0&amp;fonts=Arial&amp;skin=f6f6f6&amp;font-color=auto&amp;btn-skin=3267a3&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/thyatira&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 3 Part 1 (3:1-6): Sardis</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/sardis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/sardis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Click the link, then click on the speaker icon to hear ESV verse audio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation 3:1-6&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1a) &amp;ldquo;To the angel of the Messianic Community in Sardis, write: &amp;lsquo;Here is the message from the one who has the sevenfold Spirit of God and the seven stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joh 15:26-27 “But when the Helper comes, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth, who proceeds from the Father, he will bear witness about me. (27) And you also will bear witness, because you have been with me from the beginning.  &lt;br&gt;1Pe 1:10-12 Concerning this salvation, the prophets who prophesied about the grace that was to be yours searched and inquired carefully, (11) inquiring what person or time the Spirit of Christ in them was indicating when he predicted the sufferings of Christ and the subsequent glories. (12) It was revealed to them that they were serving not themselves but you, in the things that have now been announced to you through those who preached the good news to you by the Holy Spirit sent from heaven, things into which angels long to look. &lt;br&gt; Zechariah 4:2,6,10  (2) And he said to me, “What do you see?” I said, “I see, and behold, a lampstand all of gold, with a bowl on the top of it, and seven lamps on it, with seven lips on each of the lamps that are on the top of it (6) Then he said to me, “This is the word of the LORD to Zerubbabel: Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, says the LORD of hosts. (10) “These seven are the eyes of the LORD, which range through the whole earth.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1b) &amp;ldquo;I know what you are doing—you have a reputation for being alive, but in fact you are dead!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 Sa 16:7 But the LORD said to Samuel, “Do not look on his appearance or on the height of his stature, because I have rejected him. For the LORD sees not as man sees: man looks on the outward appearance, but the LORD looks on the heart.”  &lt;br&gt;Pro 21:2 Every way of a man is right in his own eyes, but the LORD weighs the heart. &lt;br&gt;Deu 12:8 “You shall not do according to all that we are doing here today, everyone doing whatever is right in his own eyes, &lt;br&gt;Jdg 17:6 In those days there was no king in Israel. Everyone did what was right in his own eyes.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(2) Wake up, and strengthen what remains, before it dies too! For I have found what you are doing incomplete in the sight of my God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joh 11:11 After saying these things, he said to them, “Our friend Lazarus has fallen asleep, but I go to awaken him.”  &lt;br&gt; Mar 14:38 Watch and pray that you may not enter into temptation. The spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak.”  &lt;br&gt;Jas 1:22-24 But be doers of the word, and not hearers only, deceiving yourselves. (23) For if anyone is a hearer of the word and not a doer, he is like a man who looks intently at his natural face in a mirror. (24) For he looks at himself and goes away and at once forgets what he was like.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(3) So remember what you received and heard, and obey it, and turn from your sin! For if you don&amp;rsquo;t wake up, I will come like a thief; and you don&amp;rsquo;t know at what moment I will come upon you.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deu 6:3-9 Hear therefore, O Israel, and be careful to do them, that it may go well with you, and that you may multiply greatly, as the LORD, the God of your fathers, has promised you, in a land flowing with milk and honey.  (4) “Hear, O Israel: The LORD our God, the LORD is one.  (5) You shall love the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your might.  (6) And these words that I command you today shall be on your heart.  (7) You shall teach them diligently to your children, and shall talk of them when you sit in your house, and when you walk by the way, and when you lie down, and when you rise.  (8) You shall bind them as a sign on your hand, and they shall be as frontlets between your eyes.  (9) You shall write them on the doorposts of your house and on your gates.  &lt;br&gt;Mat 24:42-43 So stay alert, because you don&amp;rsquo;t know on what day your Lord will come. (43) But know this, that if the master of the house had known in what part of the night the thief was coming, he would have stayed awake and would not have let his house be broken into.   &lt;br&gt;1Th 5:2 because you yourselves well know that the Day of the Lord will come like a thief in the night.   &lt;br&gt;Rev 16:14-16 For they are demonic spirits, performing signs, who go abroad to the kings of the whole world, to assemble them for battle on the great day of God the Almighty. (15) (“Behold, I am coming like a thief! Blessed is the one who stays awake, keeping his garments on, that he may not go about naked and be seen exposed!”) (16) And they assembled them at the place that in Hebrew is called Armageddon.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(4) Nevertheless, you do have a few people in Sardis who have not soiled their clothes; and they will walk with me, clothed in white, because they are worthy.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 61:10 I will greatly rejoice in the LORD; my soul shall exult in my God, for he has clothed me with the garments of salvation; he has covered me with the robe of righteousness, as a bridegroom decks himself like a priest with a beautiful headdress, and as a bride adorns herself with her jewels.  &lt;br&gt;Rev 19:8 it was granted her to clothe herself with fine linen, bright and pure”— for the fine linen is the righteous deeds of the saints.  Ecc 9:8 Let your garments be always white. Let not oil be lacking on your head.   &lt;br&gt;Isa_61:10 I will greatly rejoice in the LORD; my soul shall exult in my God, for he has clothed me with the garments of salvation; he has covered me with the robe of righteousness, as a bridegroom decks himself like a priest with a beautiful headdress, and as a bride adorns herself with her jewels. &lt;br&gt;Mat 23:27 “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you are like whitewashed tombs, which outwardly appear beautiful, but within are full of dead people&amp;rsquo;s bones and all uncleanness.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(5) He who wins the victory will, like them, be dressed in white clothing; and I will not blot his name out of the Book of Life; in fact, I will acknowledge him individually before my Father and before his angels.  &lt;br&gt;(6) Those who have ears, let them hear what the Spirit is saying to the Messianic communities.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exo 32:30-33 The next day Moses said to the people, “You have sinned a great sin. And now I will go up to the LORD; perhaps I can make atonement for your sin.”  (31) So Moses returned to the LORD and said, “Alas, this people has sinned a great sin. They have made for themselves gods of gold.  (32) But now, if you will forgive their sin—but if not, please blot me out of your book that you have written.”  (33) But the LORD said to Moses, “Whoever has sinned against me, I will blot out of my book. &lt;br&gt;Psa 69:27-28 Add to them punishment upon punishment; may they have no acquittal from you.  (28) Let them be blotted out of the book of the living; let them not be enrolled among the righteous.  &lt;br&gt;Dan 12:1 “At that time shall arise Michael, the great prince who has charge of your people. And there shall be a time of trouble, such as never has been since there was a nation till that time. But at that time your people shall be delivered, everyone whose name shall be found written in the book.  &lt;br&gt;Mal 3:16 Then those who feared the LORD spoke with one another. The LORD paid attention and heard them, and a book of remembrance was written before him of those who feared the LORD and esteemed his name.  &lt;br&gt;Rev 20:12 And I saw the dead, great and small, standing before the throne, and books were opened. Then another book was opened, which is the book of life. And the dead were judged by what was written in the books, according to what they had done. Rev_20:15 And if anyone&amp;rsquo;s name was not found written in the book of life, he was thrown into the lake of fire.  &lt;br&gt;Rev 20:12 And I saw the dead, great and small, standing before the throne, and books were opened. Then another book was opened, which is the book of life. And the dead were judged by what was written in the books, according to what they had done. Rev_20:15 And if anyone&amp;rsquo;s name was not found written in the book of life, he was thrown into the lake of fire.  &lt;br&gt;Luk 12:8-9 “And I tell you, everyone who acknowledges me before men, the Son of Man also will acknowledge before the angels of God,  (9) but the one who denies me before men will be denied before the angels of God. Mat_26:75 And Peter remembered the saying of Jesus, “Before the rooster crows, you will deny me three times.” And he went out and wept bitterly. .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seven-letters-outline&#34;&gt;Seven Letters Outline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ephesus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smyrna&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pergamum&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thyatira&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sardis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laodicea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Darling; desired&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Myrrh; death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Height; Mixed (strange) Marriage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Daughter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Precious stone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;From&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Holds 7 stars/ walks among lampstands&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First/last dead/alive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sharp two-edged sword&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Son of God; eyes of fire; feet of brass&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sevenfold Spirit &amp;amp; Seven Stars&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Praise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t tolerate evil; Persevered; Acts 17:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Suffering (pressing, tribulation) and insults&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not denied faith; holds fast to His name; know they live where Satan has his throne&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;love, trust, service, and perseverance; improving&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NONE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Judgment&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lost love they had at first&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tolerate those with sexual and dietary sin (Balaam)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jezebel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;False reputation; they are dead! Works are incomplete. Repent or He will come like a thief&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Secondary Encouragement&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hates deeds of people who do things their own way instead of God&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Do not fear suffering; remain faithful&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hold fast against teaching of deep things of Satan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A few who have not soiled clothes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Location of &amp;ldquo;Ear&amp;rdquo; clause&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat from Tree/Life&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not taste 2nd death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat of Hidden Manna / A white stone/new name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Authority over nations; morning star&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dressed in white; name in Book, be acknowledged in Heaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Neglected priorities&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Expect Satanic opposition&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beware spiritual compromise: (worshipping God AND something else)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beware of pagan practices mixed in and corrupting the true faith: (worshipping something else pretending it&amp;rsquo;s God)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Be watchful and diligently guard the heart (not just doctrine)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Age&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apostolic (70-170)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Persecuted (170-312)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;State Religion (312-606)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Catholic (606-present)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Protestant (1517 - Present)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Parable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Four Soils&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wheat/tares&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mustard seed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Woman/leaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Treasure/Field&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paul&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philippians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1/2 Corinthians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Galatians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Romans&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-videos&#34;&gt;Watch the Videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part I: Historical background and Rev 3:1-6 commentary

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/72uHUchbPu8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part II: &amp;ldquo;Does it fit?&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; conjectures; errors of Protestantism (Emo Philips 1985 joke about denominations)

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fpZdKHB_MQQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brief (3:41) Tour Guide clip of Sardis and Pergamum&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/666915120&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;vimeo video&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/sardis&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 3 Part 2 (3:7-12): Philadelphia</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/philadelphia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/philadelphia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Click the link, then click on the speaker icon to hear ESV verse audio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation 3:7-12&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(7) &amp;ldquo;To the angel of the Messianic Community in Philadelphia, write: &amp;lsquo;Here is the message of HaKadosh, the True One, the one who has the key of David, who, if he opens something, no one else can shut it, and if he closes something, no one else can open it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lev 19:2 “Speak to all the congregation of the people of Israel and say to them, You shall be holy, &lt;strong&gt;for I the LORD your God am holy&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;br&gt;Isa 47:4 Our Redeemer—the LORD of hosts is his name— is the &lt;strong&gt;Holy One of Israel&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joh 14:6&lt;/strong&gt; Jesus said to him, “I am the way, and &lt;strong&gt;the truth&lt;/strong&gt;, and the life. No one comes to the Father except through me.  &lt;br&gt;1 Jn 5:20 And we know that the Son of God has come and has given us understanding, so that we may &lt;strong&gt;know him who is true&lt;/strong&gt;; and we are &lt;strong&gt;in him who is true&lt;/strong&gt;, in his Son Jesus Christ**. He is the true God and eternal life**.  &lt;br&gt;Isa 22:20-22 In that day I will call my servant Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, (21) and I will clothe him with your robe, and will bind your sash on him, and will commit your authority to his hand. And he shall be a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem and to the house of Judah. (22) And I will place on his shoulder the &lt;strong&gt;key of the house of David&lt;/strong&gt;. He shall open, and none shall shut; and he shall shut, and none shall open. &lt;br&gt;Luk 1:31-35 And behold, you will conceive in your womb and bear a son, and you shall call his name Jesus. (32) He will be great and will be called the Son of the Most High. And the Lord God will give to him the &lt;strong&gt;throne of his father David,&lt;/strong&gt; (33) and he will reign over the house of Jacob forever, and of his kingdom, there will be no end.” And Mary said to the angel, “How will this be since I am a virgin?” (35) And the angel answered her, “The Holy Spirit will come upon you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow you; therefore the child to be born will be called &lt;strong&gt;holy&lt;/strong&gt;—the Son of God. &lt;br&gt;Mat 16:19 I will give you the &lt;strong&gt;keys of the kingdom of heaven&lt;/strong&gt;, and whatever you bind on earth shall be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven.”   &lt;br&gt;Act 15:15-18 And with this the words of the prophets agree, just as it is written, (16) “‘After this, I will return, and I will rebuild the tent of David that has fallen; I will rebuild its ruins, and I will restore it, (17) that the remnant of mankind may seek the Lord, and all the Gentiles who are called by my name, says the Lord, who makes these things (18) known from of old.’ (Quoting Amos 9:11-12 and referencing Isaiah 16:5)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(8) &amp;ldquo;I know what you are doing. Look, I have put in front of you an open door, and no one can shut it. I know that you have but little power, yet you have obeyed my message and have not disowned me.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 25:6-8 On this mountain the LORD of hosts will make for all peoples a feast of rich food, a feast of well-aged wine, of rich food full of marrow, of aged wine well refined. (7) And he will swallow up on this mountain the covering that is cast over all peoples, the veil that is spread over all nations. (8) He will swallow up death forever; and the Lord GOD will wipe away tears from all faces, and the reproach of his people he will take away from all the earth, for the LORD has spoken. &lt;br&gt;Joh 10:7-9 So Jesus again said to them, “Truly, truly, I say to you, I am the door of the sheep. (8) All who came before me are thieves and robbers, but the sheep did not listen to them. (9) I am the door. If anyone enters by me, he will be saved and will go in and out and find pasture. &lt;br&gt;1 Cor 16:8-9 But I will stay in Ephesus until Pentecost, (9) for a wide door for effective work has opened to me, and there are many adversaries. &lt;br&gt;2 Cor 2:12 When I came to Troas to preach the gospel of Christ, even though a door was opened for me in the Lord,   &lt;br&gt;Col 4:3 At the same time, pray also for us, that God may open to us a door for the word, to declare the mystery of Christ, on account of which I am in prison—   &lt;br&gt;2 Cor 12:10 For the sake of Christ, then, I am content with weaknesses, insults, hardships, persecutions, and calamities. For when I am weak, then I am strong.   &lt;br&gt;Joh 14:21 Whoever has my commandments and keeps them, he it is who loves me. And he who loves me will be loved by my Father, and I will love him and manifest myself to him.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(9) Here, I will give you some from the synagogue of the Adversary, those who call themselves Jews but aren&amp;rsquo;t—on the contrary, they are lying—see, I will cause them to come and prostrate themselves at your feet, and they will know that I have loved you.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Is 49:23 Kings shall be your foster fathers, and their queens your nursing mothers. With their faces to the ground, they shall bow down to you and lick the dust off your feet. Then you will know that I am the LORD; those who wait for me shall not be put to shame.”  &lt;br&gt;Isa 45:22-25 “Turn to me and be saved, all the ends of the earth! For I am God, and there is no other. (23) By myself I have sworn; from my mouth has gone out in righteousness a word that shall not return: ‘To me, every knee shall bow, every tongue shall swear allegiance.’ (24) “Only in the LORD, it shall be said of me, are righteousness and strength; to him shall come and be ashamed all who were incensed against him. (25) In the LORD all the offspring of Israel shall be justified and shall glory.”  &lt;br&gt;Est 8:17 And in every province and in every city, wherever the king&amp;rsquo;s command and his edict reached, there was gladness and joy among the Jews, a feast and a holiday. And many from the peoples of the country declared themselves Jews, for fear of the Jews had fallen on them.   &lt;br&gt;Psa 72:10-11 May the kings of Tarshish and of the coastlands render him tribute; may the kings of Sheba and Seba bring gifts! (11) May all kings fall down before him, all nations serve him! &lt;br&gt;Php 2:10-11 so that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, in heaven and on earth and under the earth, (11) and every tongue confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(10) Because you did obey my message about persevering, I will keep you from the time of trial coming upon the whole world to put the people living on earth to the test.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Luk 21:20-21 “But when you see Jerusalem surrounded by armies, then know that its desolation has come near. (21) Then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains, and let those who are inside the city depart, and let not those who are out in the country enter it,  &lt;br&gt;Isa 26:18 we were pregnant, we writhed, but we have given birth to wind. We have accomplished no deliverance in the earth, and the inhabitants of the world have not fallen.  &lt;br&gt;2 Pe 2:9 then the Lord knows how to rescue the godly from trials, and to keep the unrighteous under punishment until the day of judgment,   &lt;br&gt;Zec 13:9 And I will put this third into the fire, and refine them as one refines silver, and test them as gold is tested. They will call upon my name, and I will answer them. I will say, ‘They are my people’; and they will say, ‘The LORD is my God.’&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(11) I am coming soon; hold on to what you have so that no one will take away your crown.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2Ti 4:8 Henceforth, there is laid up for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, will award to me on that day, and not only to me but also to all who have loved His appearing.  &lt;br&gt;Jas 5:9 Do not grumble against one another, brothers, so that you may not be judged; behold, the Judge is standing at the door.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 3:12-13 I will make him who wins the victory a pillar in the Temple of my God, and he will never leave it. Also, I will write on him the name of my God and the name of my God&amp;rsquo;s city, the new Yerushalayim coming down out of heaven from my God, and my own new name. &lt;br&gt;(13) Those who have ears, let them hear what the Spirit is saying to the Messianic communities.&amp;rdquo; &#39;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1Ki 7:21 He set up the pillars at the vestibule of the temple. He set up the pillar on the south and called its name Jachin, and he set up the pillar on the north and called its name Boaz.  &lt;br&gt;Jer 1:18-19 And I, behold, I make you this day a fortified city, an iron pillar, and bronze walls, against the whole land, against the kings of Judah, its officials, its priests, and the people of the land. (19) They will fight against you, but they shall not prevail against you, for I am with you, declares the LORD, to deliver you.”  &lt;br&gt;Isa 56:4-5 For thus says the LORD: “To the eunuchs who keep my Sabbaths, who choose the things that please me and hold fast my covenant, (5) I will give in my house and within my walls a monument and a name better than sons and daughters; I will give them an everlasting name that shall not be cut off.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seven-letters-table&#34;&gt;Seven Letters Table&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Ephesus&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Smyrna&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pergamum&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Thyatira&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Sardis&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Laodicea&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Darling; desired&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Myrrh; death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Height; Mixed (strange) Marriage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Daughter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Precious stone&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Brotherly Love&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;From&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Holds 7 stars/ walks among lampstands&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First/last dead/alive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sharp two-edged sword&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Son of God; eyes of fire; feet of brass&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sevenfold Spirit &amp;amp; Seven Stars&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Holy, True, Key of David Open Door&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Praise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t tolerate evil; Persevered; Acts 17:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Suffering (pressing, tribulation) and insults&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not denied faith; holds fast to His name; know they live where Satan has his throne&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;love, trust, service, and perseverance; improving&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NONE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kept Word and not denied&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Judgment&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lost love they had at first&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tolerate those with sexual and dietary sin (Balaam)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jezebel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;False reputation; they are dead! Works are incomplete. Repent or He will come like a thief&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;None directed to Philadelphia – will sit in judgment of false Jews who will learn He loves&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Secondary Encouragement&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hates deeds of people who do things their own way instead of God&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Do not fear suffering; remain faithful&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hold fast against teaching of deep things of Satan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A few who have not soiled clothes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Patient endurance will keep them from the worldwide hour of trial for earth-dwellers&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Location of &amp;ldquo;Ear&amp;rdquo; clause&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat from Tree/Life&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not taste 2nd death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat of Hidden Manna / A white stone/new name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Authority over nations; morning star&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dressed in white; name in Book, be acknowledged in Heaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pillar in Millennial temple; write on him name of my God, name of new Jerusalem, and His own Name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Neglected priorities&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Expect Satanic opposition&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beware spiritual compromise: (worshipping God AND something else)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beware of pagan practices mixed in and corrupting the true faith: (worshipping something else pretending it&amp;rsquo;s God)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Be watchful and diligently guard the heart (not just doctrine)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Loyal ambassadorship&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Age&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apostolic (70-170)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Persecuted (170-312)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;State Religion (312-606)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Catholic (606-present)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Protestant (1517 - present)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Missionary &amp;ldquo;on fire&amp;rdquo;; Raptured (1750-present)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Parable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Four Soils&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wheat/tares&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mustard seed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Woman/leaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Treasure/Field&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pearl of Great Price&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paul&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philippians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1/2 Corinthians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Galatians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Romans&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1/2 Thessalonians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-videos&#34;&gt;Watch the Videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part I: Rev 3:7-9 | Historical background | Davidic Covenant | More on Synagogue of Satan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B0T8k8MMmXI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part II: Rev 3:10-12, Missionary church age | Pearl of Great Price | Thessalonians&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Aty5ZBDDwbg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/philadelphia&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 2 Part 3 (2:12-17): Pergamum</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/pergamum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/pergamum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;click the link, then click on the speaker icon to hear ESV verse audio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation  2:12-17&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(12) &amp;ldquo;To the angel of the Messianic Community in Pergamum, write: &amp;lsquo;Here is the message from the one who has the sharp double-edged sword:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:16 In his right hand, he held seven stars, from his mouth came a sharp two-edged sword, and his face was like the sun shining in full strength.  &lt;br&gt;Joh 1:17 For (just as) the law was given through Moses, grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.  &lt;br&gt;Isa 11:4 but with righteousness, he shall judge the poor, and decide with equity for the meek of the earth; and he shall strike the earth with the rod of his mouth, and with the breath of his lips he shall kill the wicked.  &lt;br&gt;Isa 49:2 He made my mouth like a sharp sword; in the shadow of his hand he hid me; he made me a polished arrow; in his quiver, he hid me away.  &lt;br&gt;2 Th 2:8 And then the lawless one will be revealed, whom the Lord Jesus will kill with the breath of his mouth and bring to nothing by the appearance of his coming. &lt;br&gt; 2 Ti 3:16-17 All Scripture is breathed out by God and profitable for teaching, for reproof, for correction, and for training in righteousness, (17) that the man of God may be complete, equipped for every good work.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(13) &amp;ldquo;I know where you are living, there where the Adversary&amp;rsquo;s throne is. Yet you are holding onto my name. You did not deny trusting me even at the time when my faithful witness Antipas was put to death in your town, there where the Adversary lives.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;br&gt;Luke 21:17 You will be hated by all for my name&amp;rsquo;s sake.  &lt;br&gt;Jude 1:4 For certain people have crept in unnoticed who long ago were designated for this condemnation, ungodly people, who pervert the grace of our God into sensuality and deny our only Master and Lord, Jesus Christ.  &lt;br&gt;2 Ti 2:12 if we endure, we will also reign with him; if we deny him, he also will deny us;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(14) Nevertheless, I have a few things against you: you have some people who hold to the teaching of Bil`am, who taught Balak to set a trap for the people of Isra&amp;rsquo;el, so that they would eat food that had been sacrificed to idols and commit sexual sin. &lt;br&gt;(15) Likewise, you too have people who hold to the teaching of the Nicolaitans.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Numbers 22-25, 31 &lt;br&gt;Joshua 13:22 Balaam also, the son of Beor, the one who practiced divination, was killed with the sword by the people of Israel &lt;br&gt;2 Pe 2:15 Forsaking the right way, they have gone astray. They have followed the way of Balaam, the son of Beor, who loved gain from wrongdoing,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(16) Therefore, turn from these sins. Otherwise, I will come to you very soon and make war against them with the sword of my mouth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;br&gt;Rev 19:15 And out of his mouth comes to a sharp sword with which to strike down nations—&amp;ldquo;He will rule them with a staff of iron.&amp;rdquo; It is he who treads the winepress from which flows the wine of the furious rage of Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies.  &lt;br&gt;Rev 19:21 The rest were killed with the sword that goes out of the mouth of the rider on the horse, and all the birds gorged themselves on their flesh.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(17) Those who have ears, let them hear what the Spirit is saying to the Messianic communities. To him winning the victory, I will give some of the hidden manna. I will also give him a white stone, on which is written a new name that nobody knows except the one receiving it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exo 16:31-35 Now the house of Israel called its name manna. It was like coriander seed, white, and the taste of it was like wafers made with honey. (32) Moses said, “This is what the LORD has commanded: ‘Let an omer of it be kept throughout your generations, so that they may see the bread with which I fed you in the wilderness, when I brought you out of the land of Egypt.’” (33) And Moses said to Aaron, “Take a jar, and put an omer of manna in it, and place it before the LORD to be kept throughout your generations.” (34) As the LORD commanded Moses, so Aaron placed it before the testimony to be kept. (35) The people of Israel ate the manna forty years, till they came to a habitable land. They ate the manna till they came to the border of the land of Canaan. &lt;br&gt;Joh 6:31 Our fathers ate the manna in the wilderness; as it is written, ‘He gave them bread from heaven to eat.’”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seven-letters-outline&#34;&gt;Seven Letters Outline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ephesus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smyrna&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pergamum&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thyatira&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sardis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laodicea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Darling; desired&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Myrrh; death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Height; Mixed (strange) Marriage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;From&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Holds 7 stars/ walks among lampstands&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First/last dead/alive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sharp two-edged sword&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t tolerate evil; Persevered; Acts 17:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Suffering (pressing, tribulation) and insults&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not denied faith; holds fast to His name; know they live where Satan has his throne&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lost love they had at first&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tolerate those with sexual and dietary sin (Balaam)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hates deeds of people who do things their own way instead of God&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Do not fear suffering; remain faithful&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ear&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat from Tree/Life&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not taste 2nd death                         It&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat of Hidden Manna / A white stone/new name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Neglected priorities&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Expect Satanic opposition&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Beware spiritual compromise (worshipping God AND something else)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Age&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apostolic (70-170)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Persecuted (170-312)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;State Religion (312-606)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Parable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Four Soils&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wheat/tares&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mustard seed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Woman/leaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paul&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philippians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1/2 Corinthians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-videos&#34;&gt;Watch the videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video Part 1: Intro and 2:12-13&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pergamum archaeological sites, Roman Imperial Cult and enforced paganism, two-edged Sword&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NcftNgsIHWw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video Part 2: 2:14-17 and conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Balaam and Balak, Hidden Manna, White Stone, Constantine&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Conversion&amp;rdquo;/enforced Christianity, Matthew 13, 1st Corinthians&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/H7n5tgsgC2Q&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/pergamum&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Pergamum lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revlation 2 Part 2 (2:1-11): Ephesus, Smyrna</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/revlation-2-part-i-2-1-11-ephesus-smyrna/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/revlation-2-part-i-2-1-11-ephesus-smyrna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;click the link, then click on the speaker icon to hear ESV verse audio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ephesus&#34;&gt;Ephesus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation 2:1-7&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(1) &amp;ldquo;To the angel of the (&lt;em&gt;ecclesia)&lt;/em&gt; Messianic Community in Ephesus, write: &amp;lsquo;Here is the message from the one who holds the seven stars in his right hand and walks among the seven gold menorahs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mat 18:20 For where two or three are gathered in my name, there am I among them.”  &lt;br&gt;Joh 1:1 In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(2) &amp;ldquo;I know what you have been doing, how hard you have worked (or &amp;ldquo;I know your works and your labor&amp;rdquo;), how you have persevered, and how you can&amp;rsquo;t stand wicked people; so you tested those who call themselves emissaries but aren&amp;rsquo;t—and you found them to be liars. (3) You are persevering, and you have suffered for my sake without growing weary.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eph 4:14 We will then no longer be infants tossed about by the waves and blown along by every wind of teaching, at the mercy of people clever in devising ways to deceive.   Mat 7:23 Then I will tell them to their faces, &amp;lsquo;I never knew you! Get away from me, you workers of lawlessness!&amp;rsquo;  &lt;br&gt; 1 John 4:1 Beloved, do not believe every spirit but test the spirits to see whether they are from God, for many false prophets have gone out into the world. &lt;br&gt;2 Cor 11:13-15 For such men are false apostles, deceitful workmen, disguising themselves as apostles of Christ. 14 And no wonder, for even Satan disguises himself as an angel of light. 15 So it is no surprise if his servants, also, disguise themselves as servants of righteousness. Their end will correspond to their deeds.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(4) But I have this against you: you have lost the love you had at first. (5) Therefore, remember where you were before you fell, turn from this sin, and do what you used to do before. Otherwise, I will come to you and remove your menorah from its place—if you don&amp;rsquo;t turn from your sin!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jer 2:2 “Go and proclaim in the hearing of Jerusalem, Thus says the LORD, “I remember the devotion of your youth, your love as a bride, how you followed me in the wilderness, in a land not sown.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(6) But you have this in your favor: you hate what the Nicolaitans do—I hate it too.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Psa 26:5 I hate the assembly of evildoers, and I will not sit with the wicked&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(7) Those who have ears, let them hear what the Spirit is saying to the Messianic communities.  To him winning the victory (or &amp;ldquo;him who overcomes&amp;rdquo;), I will give the right to eat from the Tree of Life which is in God&amp;rsquo;s Gan-`Eden.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 3:22-24 Then the LORD God said, “Behold, the man has become like one of us in knowing good and evil. Now, lest he reach out his hand and take also of the tree of life and eat, and live forever—” 23 therefore the LORD God sent him out from the garden of Eden to work the ground from which he was taken. 24 He drove out the man, and at the east of the garden of Eden he placed the cherubim and a flaming sword that turned every way to guard the way to the tree of life. &lt;br&gt;Is 51:3  For the LORD comforts Zion; he comforts all her waste places and makes her wilderness like Eden, her desert like the garden of the LORD; joy and gladness will be found in her, thanksgiving and the voice of song.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;smyrna&#34;&gt;Smyrna&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation 2:8-11&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(8) &amp;ldquo;And to the angel of the (&lt;em&gt;ecclesia)&lt;/em&gt; Messianic Community in Smyrna, write: ‘The words of the first and the last, who died and came to life.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 41:4 Who has performed and done this, calling the generations from the beginning? I, the LORD, the first, and with the last; I am he Isa 44:6 Thus says the LORD, the King of Israel and his Redeemer, the LORD of hosts: “I am the first and I am the last; besides me there is no god &lt;br&gt;Isa 48:12 “Listen to me, O Jacob, and Israel, whom I called! I am he; I am the first, and I am the last.  &lt;br&gt;Rev 22:13 I am the Alpha and the Omega, the first and the last, the beginning and the end.”  &lt;br&gt;Mat 2:11 And going into the house, they saw the child with Mary his mother, and they fell down and worshiped him. Then, opening their treasures, they offered him gifts, gold and frankincense and myrrh. &lt;br&gt;Mar 15:23 And they offered him wine mixed with myrrh, but he did not take it. &lt;br&gt;Joh 19:39 Nicodemus also, who earlier had come to Jesus by night, came bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about seventy-five pounds in weight. &lt;br&gt;Isa 60:6 A multitude of camels shall cover you, the young camels of Midian and Ephah; all those from Sheba shall come. They shall bring gold and frankincense, and shall bring good news, the praises of the LORD. &lt;em&gt;(note: no Myrrh)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(9) “‘ I know how you are suffering and how poor you are (though in fact you are rich!)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jas 1:2-3 Regard it all as joy, my brothers, when you face various kinds of temptations; (3) for you know that the testing of your trust produces perseverance.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(10) Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid of what you are about to suffer. Look, the Adversary is going to have some of you thrown in prison, in order to put you to the test; and you will face an ordeal for ten days. Remain faithful, even to the point of death; and I will give you life as your crown.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fear not&amp;rdquo; ~150x &lt;br&gt;2Ti 3:12 And indeed, all who want to live a godly life united with the Messiah Yeshua will be persecuted,   &lt;br&gt;Jas 1:2-3 Regard it all as joy, my brothers, when you face various kinds of temptations; (3) for you know that the testing of your trust produces perseverance.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(11) Those who have ears, let them hear what the Spirit is saying to the Messianic communities. He who wins the victory will not be hurt at all by the second death.&amp;rdquo; &#39;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 20:6 Blessed and holy &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; he that hath part in the first resurrection: on such the second death hath no power, but they shall be priests of God and of Christ, and shall reign with him a thousand years. &lt;br&gt;Rev 20:14 And death and hell were cast into the lake of fire. This is the second death. &lt;br&gt;Rev 21:8 But the fearful, and unbelieving, and the abominable, and murderers, and whoremongers, and sorcerers, and idolaters, and all liars, shall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimstone: which is the second death.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seven-letters-outline&#34;&gt;Seven Letters Outline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ephesus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smyrna&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pergamum&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thyatira&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sardis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philadelphia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laodicea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Darling; desired&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Myrrh;death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;From&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Holds 7 stars/ walks among lampstands&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First/last dead/alive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t tolerate evil; Persevered; Acts 17:11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Suffering (pressing, tribulation) and insults&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lost love they had at first&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hates deeds of people who do things their own way instead of God&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Do not fear suffering; remain faithful&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ear&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before promise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Before&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eat from Tree/Life&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not taste 2nd death&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Age&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apostolic (70-170)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Persecuted (170-312)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Parable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Four Soils&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wheat/tares&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paul&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ephesians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philippians&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-videos&#34;&gt;Watch the videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ephesus-1&#34;&gt;Ephesus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8IN3cVRqa7I&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-were-the-nicolaitans&#34;&gt;Who were the Nicolaitans?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OMVfJ23kxWc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;smyrna-1&#34;&gt;Smyrna&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RbefUO1YdDE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/ephesus&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Ephesus lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/smyrna&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Smyrna lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 2, part I: Intro to Seven letters</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/intro-to-seven-letters/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/intro-to-seven-letters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We will find that that each of the Seven Letters in Revelation 2 and 3 contain an identical outline; however not all elements are present in each letter.  We will want to pay particular attention when there are these exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will also explore some conjectures.  One view holds that Paul&amp;rsquo;s Seven Letters and the Seven Kingdom Parables have correlations to the Seven Letters of Revelation. A view that is widely held is the so-called &amp;ldquo;Church Age Theory.&amp;rdquo;  We will explain what that is and what it means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gL3rJWSmlkU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/seven-letters-intro&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 1 Part II (1:12-20): One like a Son of Man</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/one-like-son-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/one-like-son-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Revelation Backgrounds lesson 4 is titled, &amp;ldquo;One Like a Son of Man&amp;rdquo; based on John&amp;rsquo;s description of the divine being he sees.  Note that he does not say this is Jesus speaking directly.  In fact, we know from verses 1:1 and 22:8 that it is NOT Jesus speaking to John but an Angel.  Nonetheless, the depiction is assuredly that of Jesus Messiah in His glorified state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our background, we will read Daniel chapters 7 and 10 along with Revelation 1 and note the consistency of idioms used throughout the Bible, Old and New Testaments, specifically the descriptions of the &amp;ldquo;one like a Son of Man&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;Ancient of Days&amp;rdquo;.  For this reason, we like to say that our Bible is 66 separate books, but one integrated message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/f37a1158a991a6a4d9acb4a8284cc1ff.jpeg&#34; caption=&#34;Temple Menorah&#34; width=&#34;25%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ended last lesson with John hearing a great voice behind him.  Now here in verse 12, we see John turning to look and he sees the gold seven branched Menorah.  This menorah probably looked much like the one in the picture. Next we learn that the one like a Son of Man was in the midst of the Menorah and later we will see that each branch, each light, is one of the seven congregations  A Menorah is one object with seven branches, which draws images of John 15. Jesus said, &amp;ldquo;I am the vine, you are the branches.&amp;rdquo;  We are supposed to be the vessels through which God&amp;rsquo;s light shines.  Jesus also said in John 15 &amp;ldquo;abide in Me.&amp;rdquo;  We must remain connected to the source.  A Menorah is a great picture of Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we have a description of the person John saw, which is nearly identical to Daniel&amp;rsquo;s visions. This description bears some resemblance to the High Priest carrying out his duties in the Tabernacle.  One commentator said, &amp;ldquo;The garments are highly symbolic, showing that Jesus is the heavenly priest, fully prepared and qualified to carry out His duties.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In verse 19, we will look at this Greek phrase &lt;mark&gt;μετα ταυτα&lt;/mark&gt; (meta tauta), which is often translated as &amp;ldquo;after these things.&amp;rdquo;  The phrase appears exactly ten times in Revelation and acts as a signpost to let us know where we are.  In what is called gematria, certain numbers that reappear throughout the Bible appear to be associated with specific themes.  We&amp;rsquo;ve talked previously how the number seven indicates perfection or completeness.  All this means is that scholars have looked at where seven (or groups/multiples of seven) appear and they have noticed the theme of completeness.  Along these lines, 10 indicates divine order.  The most obvious examples are the Ten Commandments and the Ten plagues.  There were also ten generations from Adam to Noah, then the Flood came.  Meta Tauta will signify an additional stage of God setting things in order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson will conclude with a side-by-side comparison of Revelation 1 and Daniel 10.  This demonstrates that our 66 books we call the Bible is ONE integrated message and it consistent from Genesis to Revelation.  There was no &amp;ldquo;plan B,&amp;rdquo; where God decided the Old Testament was irrelevant (God forbid!). Jesus Himself says this.  Not until all things have been fulfilled will one jot or tittle pass away from the Torah (Mat 5:18).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also read Daniel 7 and Daniel 10 straight through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revelation 1:12-20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12. I turned around to see who was speaking to me; and when I had turned, I saw seven gold menorahs;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exodus 37:23 And he made its seven lamps and its tongs and its trays of pure gold. &lt;br&gt;Zec 4:2 And he said to me, “What do you see?” I said, “I see, and behold, a lampstand all of gold, with a bowl on the top of it, and seven lamps on it, with seven lips on each of the lamps that are on the top of it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13. and among the menorahs was someone like a Son of Man, wearing a robe down to his feet and a gold band around his chest&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exo 28:4 These are the garments that they shall make: a breast piece, an ephod, a robe, a coat of checker work, a turban, and a sash. They shall make holy garments for Aaron your brother and his sons to serve me as priests.  &lt;br&gt;Dan 7:13 “I saw in the night visions, and behold, with the clouds of heaven there came one like a son of man, and he came to the Ancient of Days and was presented before him. &lt;br&gt;Dan 10:5 I lifted up my eyes and looked, and behold, a man clothed in linen, with a belt of fine gold from Uphaz around his waist. Dan 10:16 And behold, one in the likeness of the children of man touched my lips. Then I opened my mouth and spoke. I said to him who stood before me, “O my lord, by reason of the vision pains have come upon me, and I retain no strength.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14. His head and hair were as white as snow-white wool, his eyes like a fiery flame,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:9 “As I looked, thrones were placed, and the Ancient of Days took his seat; his clothing was white as snow, and the hair of his head like pure wool; his throne was fiery flames; its wheels were burning fire.  &lt;br&gt;Dan 10:6 His body was like beryl, his face like the appearance of lightning&lt;br&gt;Mat 17:2 And he was transfigured before them, and his face shone like the sun, and his clothes became white as light.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15. his feet like burnished brass refined in a furnace, and his voice like the sound of rushing waters.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 10:6 … his arms and legs like the gleam of burnished bronze, and the sound of his words like the sound of a multitude. &lt;br&gt;Eze 1:7, 24 Their legs were straight, and the soles of their feet were like the sole of a calf’s foot. And they sparkled like burnished bronze.  24 And when they went, I heard the sound of their wings like the sound of many waters, like the sound of the Almighty, a sound of tumult like the sound of an army. When they stood still, they let down their wings. &lt;br&gt;Eze 43:2 And behold, the glory of the God of Israel was coming from the east. And the sound of his coming was like the sound of many waters, and the earth shone with his glory.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16. In his right hand he held seven stars, out of his mouth went a sharp double-edged sword, and his face was like the sun shining in full strength.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jdg 5:31 “So may all your enemies perish, O LORD! But your friends be like the sun as he rises in his might.” &lt;br&gt;Isa 49:2 He made my mouth like a sharp sword; in the shadow of his hand he hid me; he made me a polished arrow; in his quiver he hid me away. &lt;br&gt;Heb 4:12 For the word of God is living and active, sharper than any two-edged sword, piercing to the division of soul and of spirit, of joints and of marrow, and discerning the thoughts and intentions of the heart&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17. When I saw him, I fell down at his feet like a dead man. He placed his right hand upon me and said, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid! I am the First and the Last,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 8:17-18 So he came near where I stood. And when he came, I was frightened and fell on my face. But he said to me, “Understand, O son of man, that the vision is for the time of the end.” 18 And when he had spoken to me, I fell into a deep sleep with my face to the ground. But he touched me and made me stand up. &lt;br&gt;Dan 10:9-10,12,15 followed by Dan 10:19 And he said, “O man greatly loved, fear not, peace be with you; be strong and of good courage.” And as he spoke to me, I was strengthened and said, “Let my lord speak, for you have strengthened me.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18. the Living One. I was dead, but look!—I am alive forever and ever! And I hold the keys to Death and Sh&amp;rsquo;ol.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 25:8 He will swallow up death forever; and the Lord GOD will wipe away tears from all faces, and the reproach of his people he will take away from all the earth, for the LORD has spoken.  &lt;br&gt;Hos 13:14 I shall ransom them from the power of Sheol; I shall redeem them from Death. O Death, where are your plagues? O Sheol, where is your sting?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19. So write down what you see, both what is now, and what will happen afterward.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 30:8; Jer 30:2; Hab 2:2 (see Rev 1:11)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20. Here is the secret meaning of the seven stars you saw in my right hand, and of the seven gold menorahs: the seven stars are the angels of the seven Messianic communities, and the seven menorahs are the seven Messianic communities.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Zech 4:2 And he said to me, “What do you see?” I said, “I see, and behold, a lampstand all of gold, with a bowl on the top of it, and seven lamps on it, with seven lips on each of the lamps that are on the top of it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VrImdKWK4dU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/one-like-a-son-of-man&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revelation 1 Part 1 (1:1-11): Greetings</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/revelation-1-1-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/revelation-1-1-11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This third lesson is titled, &amp;ldquo;Greetings&amp;rdquo; because John includes an introduction and salutation very much in the style of correspondence of that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John will give us the sequence of the delivery:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From God to Yeshua/Jesus, from Yeshua to an angel, from an angel to John, and from John to Yeshua&amp;rsquo;s servants.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus had to learn of this from the Father.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is important to note that &lt;em&gt;it is the ANGEL who is speaking to John&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What makes this challenging is that the angel speaks of members of the Godhead in the 1st person.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Old Testament, we often see &amp;ldquo;the Angel of the LORD&amp;rdquo; also speaking of God the Father in the 1st person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have often assumed that the Angel of the LORD was a pre-incarnate appearance of Jesus.  We call this a &amp;ldquo;theophany.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now after studying the context of chapter 1, it may not be that simple.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The immediate recipients were His servants at the seven churches in Asia.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As we work through the book, begin to notice when things are out of place and how God sets things in their proper order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These Jewish congregations are outside of the land of Israel
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The promise made by God to their ancestors was to inherit the Land.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the end of Revelation, God will set this right and they will be back inside the Land.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then the document would have spread to all believers at the end of the first century.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then, indirectly, Revelation is written for all believers since, including you and me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/greek_letter_101ce.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;30%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John frequently uses the terms &amp;ldquo;testimony,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;witness.&amp;rdquo;  The picture to the right is a Dead Sea Scroll fragment (4Q175) called &lt;em&gt;Testimonia&lt;/em&gt; (“Messianic Anthology”), 1st century BC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He employs courtroom terminology in all his writings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Gospel of John, he is providing evidence that Jesus is the promised Messiah for all Israel in addition to evidence that the corrupt Jerusalem Temple establishment is usurping their power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Revelation, he testifies that not only is Jesus the coming king, this time it&amp;rsquo;s not just the corrupt Temple establishment but the corrupt world system that is on trial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation is unique because it is the only book in the Bible that promises a blessing for those who read, hear and obey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In chapter 1 we see the first of several patterns of seven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The commentary section of &lt;em&gt;talmidimway.org&lt;/em&gt; will list many of these.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example &amp;ldquo;Messiah&amp;rdquo; (v.1) and &amp;ldquo;Amen&amp;rdquo; (v.7) each occur exactly seven times throughout the book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are seven &amp;ldquo;blessings&amp;rdquo;, beginning with v.3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The description of Jesus in vs. 5-6 has seven attributes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the lesson, we will also unpack what John may have meant by, &amp;ldquo;I was in the Spirit on the Day of the Lord.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to read the cross-references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revelation 1:1-11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:1. This is the revelation which God gave to Yeshua the Messiah, so that he could show his servants what must happen very soon. He communicated it by sending his angel to his servant Yochanan,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Daniel 2:28 but there is a God in heaven who reveals mysteries, and he has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar what will be in the latter days. Your dream and the visions of your head as you lay in bed are these: 29 To you, O king, as you lay in bed came thoughts of what would be after this, and he who reveals mysteries made known to you what is to be.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:2. who bore witness to the Word of God and to the testimony of Yeshua the Messiah, as much as he saw&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:3. Blessed are the reader and hearers of the words of this prophecy, provided they obey the things written in it! For the time is near!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:4. From: Yochanan To: The seven Messianic communities in the province of Asia: Grace and shalom to you from the One who is, who was and who is coming; from the sevenfold Spirit before his throne;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 11:2 And the Spirit of the LORD shall rest upon him, the Spirit of wisdom and understanding, the Spirit of counsel and might, the Spirit of knowledge and the fear of the LORD.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:5. and from Yeshua the Messiah, the faithful witness, the firstborn from the dead and the ruler of the earth&amp;rsquo;s kings. To him, the one who loves us, who has freed us from our sins at the cost of his blood,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gen 49:11 Binding his foal to the vine and his donkey’s colt to the choice vine, he has washed his garments in wine and his vesture in the blood of grapes.&lt;br&gt; Psa 89:27 And I will make him the firstborn, the highest of the kings of the earth.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:6. who has caused us to be a kingdom, that is, Cohanim for God, his Father—to him be the glory and the rulership forever and ever. Amen.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ex 19:5-6 Now therefore, if you will indeed obey my voice and keep my covenant, you shall be my treasured possession among all peoples, for all the earth is mine; 6 and you shall be to me a kingdom of priests and a holy nation.’ These are the words that you shall speak to the people of Israel.” &lt;br&gt;Isa 61:6 but you shall be called the priests of the LORD; they shall speak of you as the ministers of our God; you shall eat the wealth of the nations, and in their glory you shall boast.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:7. Look! He is coming with the clouds! Every eye will see him, including those who pierced him; and all the tribes of the Land will mourn him. Yes! Amen!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:13-14 “I saw in the night visions, and behold, with the clouds of heaven there came one like a son of man, and he came to the Ancient of Days and was presented before him. 14 And to him was given dominion and glory and a kingdom, that all peoples, nations, and languages should serve him; his dominion is an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass away, and his kingdom one that shall not be destroyed.  &lt;br&gt;Isa 52:8 The voice of your watchmen—they lift up their voice; together they sing for joy; for eye to eye they see the return of the LORD to Zion.  &lt;br&gt;Zech 12:10-12 “And I will pour out on the house of David and the inhabitants of Jerusalem a spirit of grace and pleas for mercy, so that, when they look on me, on him whom they have pierced, they shall mourn for him, as one mourns for an only child, and weep bitterly over him, as one weeps over a firstborn. 11 On that day the mourning in Jerusalem will be as great as the mourning for Hadad-rimmon in the plain of Megiddo. 12 The land shall mourn, each family by itself:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:8. &amp;ldquo;I am the &amp;lsquo;A&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;lsquo;Z,&amp;rsquo; &amp;quot; says Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, the One who is, who was and who is coming.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 41:4 Who has performed and done this, calling the generations from the beginning? I, the LORD, the first, and with the last; I am he.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:9. I, Yochanan, am a brother of yours and a fellow-sharer in the suffering, kingship and perseverance that come from being united with Yeshua. I had been exiled to the island called Patmos for having proclaimed the message of God and borne witness to Yeshua.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 10:2-4 In those days I, Daniel, was mourning for three weeks. 3 I ate no delicacies, no meat or wine entered my mouth, nor did I anoint myself at all, for the full three weeks. 4 On the twenty-fourth day of the first month, as I was standing on the bank of the great river (that is, the Tigris)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:10. I came to be, in the Spirit, on the Day of the Lord; and I heard behind me a loud voice, like a trumpet,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 2:12 For the LORD of hosts has a day against all that is proud and lofty, against all that is lifted up—and it shall be brought low; &lt;br&gt; Joe 1:15 Alas for the day! For the day of the LORD is near, and as destruction from the Almighty it comes. &lt;br&gt; Oba 1:15 For the day of the LORD is near upon all the nations. As you have done, it shall be done to you; your deeds shall return on your own head.  &lt;br&gt;Mal 4:5-6 “Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the great and awesome day of the LORD comes. (6) And he will turn the hearts of fathers to their children and the hearts of children to their fathers, lest I come and strike the land with a decree of utter destruction.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rev 1:11. saying, &amp;ldquo;Write down what you see on a scroll, and send it to the seven Messianic communities—Ephesus, Smyrna, Pergamum, Thyatira, Sardis, Philadelphia and Laodicea!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 30:8 And now, go, write it before them on a tablet and inscribe it in a book, that it may be for the time to come as a witness forever.&lt;br&gt;Jer 30:2 “Thus says the LORD, the God of Israel: Write in a book all the words that I have spoken to you.&lt;br&gt;Hab 2:2 And the LORD answered me: “Write the vision;  make it plain on tablets, so he may run who reads it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HDLBhn4p3mQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;listen-to-the-podcast&#34;&gt;Listen to the Podcast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/2-greetings-rev-1-1-11&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Next Gospel Backgrounds Lesson: Triumphal Entry Part I</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/next-gospel-backgrounds-lesson-triumphal-entry-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/next-gospel-backgrounds-lesson-triumphal-entry-part-i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This lesson is titled “The Triumphal Entry” because we have finally arrived at the most significant week in all human history. The next seven days are a roller coaster of emotions, ending on the highest peak of all, the Resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lesson 39 will be in two parts. Part I will review the Ascent of Adummim, which connects Jericho to Jerusalem. We’ll meet up with Jesus and the recently resurrected Lazarus in Bethany, look at how Jesus procures a donkey for his entry into Jerusalem, and examine the crowd’s reaction as they welcomed Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/2bafbd3f9ccec62efdf0eaf9ce825b36.png&#34; alt=&#34;Elevation from Jericho to Jerusalem&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson begins with Jesus and His talmidim leaving Jericho to make the 18-mile journey to Jerusalem. We can recreate this journey when we go to Israel (albeit from an air-conditioned bus with wi-fi). Although 18 miles is not that far, the elevation gain is steep, so one had to be in excellent physical shape to do it on foot. As the “Following the Messiah” hosts point out, it would be challenging to do that strenuous hike and carry on a conversation simultaneously. What was going through Jesus&amp;rsquo; mind, knowing what would happen? What was going through the disciples&amp;rsquo; minds, wondering what would happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, in John, we have the &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt; wondering whether Jesus would come to the feast? This is an odd thought, as attendance at the feast was compulsory for all able-bodied Jewish men. In John 11:56-57, John distinguishes the “Ioudaioi” and the “chief priests and the Pharisees.” Not all “Jews” (&lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt;) were in on the plot, and we also know that not all Pharisees were in on the plot either (Nicodemus, for one). If we keep reading in John 12:9-11, we see that many &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt; were “believing in Jesus.” This was because of Lazarus&amp;rsquo; testimony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/9aed9aa5c1d2045b2e8c5dbbf23fc17c.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;a donkey in Bethany Israel&#34; width=&#34;33%&#34; style=&#34;float:left&#34;/&gt;
We assume Jesus spends Shabbat (Friday sundown to Saturday sundown) with Mary, Martha, and Lazarus (John may be indicating this in John 12:2-8). Then on Sunday morning, Jesus gives instructions to procure a donkey. We briefly discuss whether this represents a prophecy or whether Jesus was taking advantage of the hospitality system of that day (perhaps combined with His familiarity with the area). Just as with the beggars in Jericho, Matthew says “a colt and his mother,” whereas Mark and Luke focus only on the “colt.” Matthew occasionally says there were two of something when Luke/Mark focuses on the more significant one (perhaps this is a result of his former job as a tax collector!).
&lt;p&gt;The Triumphal entry is a big deal for one primary reason. Every other time before this, when the people wanted to anoint Jesus as their leader, He said, “my hour has not yet come.” Now, Jesus not only permits it, but He also arranges it in a way that has direct parallels to Solomon, another “son of David.” He would ride a donkey into Jerusalem, indicating that he comes not as a conqueror but in peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crowds shout “Hosanna” (Hebrew for “save us now” or “save us please!&amp;quot;) and wave palm branches, which was a direct allusion to the days of the Maccabees, who defeated the Seleucid Greeks in 166 BCE. In other words, they were encouraging Jesus to take over politically. They also chant Psalms 118, another messianic reference. It was unmistakable that they were crowning Jesus as the messiah, which Jesus is Ok with (Luke 19:40) .  The problem is (to borrow a quote), “this is not the messiah you’re looking for.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/IMG_1037.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;33%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
To close the lesson, we look at the “cheapest souvenir in Israel.” When the Pharisees heard the people chanting that Psalm in THAT circumstance, they feared reprisal from the leadership, this is one indication that these Pharisees were not against Jesus but were on his side. They simply feared for his safety.
&lt;p&gt;Jesus said, “If these kept quiet, the very stones would cry out.” So the cheapest souvenir is to bring home one of the stones that didn’t cry out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part II will continue with Jesus weeping over Jerusalem, a precise prophecy that would be fulfilled around 40 years later, and other activities in the Temple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew 21:1-17&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark 11:1-11&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luke 19:28-40&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John 11:55-12:1, John 12:9-16&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Note: There is a known textual problem with John 12:2-8, which we will discuss when we get to Matthew 26.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-videos&#34;&gt;Watch the videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gospel Backgrounds Lesson Video:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6YKiE6NzcV0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beginning of the Following the Messiah episode 8 has an excellent segment about the Triumphal Entry. Watch through 8:55.

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8UaThqyEBzc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb4/39-triumphal-entry-i&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to study the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historical Prelude to Revelation</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/historical-prelude-to-revelation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/historical-prelude-to-revelation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a supplement to our Revelation background series. We’re going to take a look at significant events in the period between the Jewish Revolt of 66CE, including the destruction of the Jewish Temple in 70, through the mid-90s that resulted in John’s exile on Patmos, where he received the Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This interval history is surprisingly relevant if we wish to better understand the context for Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if history wasn’t your best subject in school, I believe you’ll find this background helpful as we prepare to study Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b5iQBoBvy_0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/historical-prelude&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New series! Revelation Backgrounds</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/new-series-revelation-backgrounds/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/new-series-revelation-backgrounds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;images/e45914e26cc0be101f69fd4d54a746be.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to our series on the book of Revelation we call &amp;ldquo;Revelation Backgrounds.&amp;rdquo;  In this introductory episode, we will provide an introduction to the book, some background into Jewish Apocalyptic literature, and we&amp;rsquo;ll provide what we see are Seven Keys to Interpretation.  Revelation can be a complex book, but these keys will help assure we get started on the right path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many commentators focus on what Revelation may mean to us living in the 21st Century, very few Protestant commentators take the time to understand the historical, first-century context.  Revelation, as it turns out, is the &lt;em&gt;most Jewish book&lt;/em&gt; in the New Testament. There are over 800 allusions to the Old Testament in the book&amp;rsquo;s 404 verses.  The reasons many people struggle with the book is because we ignore its Jewishness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have developed &amp;ldquo;Seven Keys to Interpretation,&amp;rdquo; which we will discuss in the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow the &amp;ldquo;Talmidim Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; -  We want to learn to walk in the dust of Yeshua our Rabbi just as His original Talmidim, His disciples such as John did.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be open to the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s leading&lt;/strong&gt; - Understanding what God wants us to learn is way more important that making sure others know our beliefs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be a Berean&lt;/strong&gt; - Check everything out against scripture.  If our interpretation doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit, it might be something we need to discard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand the intended audience&lt;/strong&gt; - They were Jewish, or if they were gentiles, they were worshipping in a Jewish setting, which would have almost nothing in common with our western protestant churches today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revelation is a Jewish Book&lt;/strong&gt; - For every verse in Revelation there is a 2:1 ratio of Old Testament illusions.  If we try to understand Revelation without this background, we&amp;rsquo;ll be lost.  With it, we&amp;rsquo;ll be much better off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be suspicious if an interpretation does not fit the original context&lt;/strong&gt; - that is to say, if it could not have been within the realm of possibility for John or the original audience.  This is not to say that the book can&amp;rsquo;t have multiple layers of interpretation, but for our historical and cultural approach, we want to start by making sure it&amp;rsquo;s something that would have made sense to the original audience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No fear allowed&lt;/strong&gt; -  While books and websites present the events of Revelation as something that should scare an unbeliever (and they probably should be scared), fear has no place in a believer&amp;rsquo;s heart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will also look at who wrote the book and some other details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who wrote Revelation?  &lt;strong&gt;John the Apostle&lt;/strong&gt;.  We don&amp;rsquo;t have 100% concrete proof, but the earliest and best evidence suggests it was none other than John, the author of the Gospel and three letters that bear his name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where was it written?  &lt;strong&gt;Patmos&lt;/strong&gt;, which is an island some 35 miles off the coast of Turkey. Revelation 1:9 is our source for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When was it written?  Most conservative scholars land on &lt;strong&gt;90-95 of the Common Era&lt;/strong&gt;.  Iraneus is the earliest source for this information.  He was a disciple of Polycarp, who was a disciple of John.  Iraneus states John received the relevation during the time of Emperor Domitian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How was Revelation given?  &lt;strong&gt;Signs and Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;! Revelation 1:1 contains the Greek word σημαίνω, which literally means &amp;ldquo;rendered into signs.&amp;rdquo; Every sign in the Bible points to something.  Every sign in Revelation points to a verse (sometimes more than one) in the Old Testament.  The pattern of the number seven is also quite conspicuous.  Sevens are everywhere in Revelation.  Since sevens are also conspicuous throughout the entire Bible, this is often seen as the &amp;ldquo;fingerprints of the Holy Spirit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To whom was Revelation written? &lt;strong&gt;The seven messianic congregations in Asia Minor.&lt;/strong&gt;.  We are told this in Revelation 1:4.  Note that although your Bible may say &amp;ldquo;seven churches,&amp;rdquo; the &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; either as a building or an organization did not exist when Revelation was given.  We need to avoid what is called an &lt;em&gt;anachronistic fallacy&lt;/em&gt;.  See the lesson detail for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why was Revelation written? &lt;strong&gt;The Hope of HIS RETURN and the Restoration of all things!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to beginning this study!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation 1:1-9&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SfuWhCybaYU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;audio-only&#34;&gt;Audio only&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe title=&#34;Introduction - Revelation Backgrounds #1&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; style=&#34;border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; data-name=&#34;pb-iframe-player&#34; src=&#34;https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=txkgm-11a4bf1-pb&amp;from=pb6admin&amp;share=1&amp;download=1&amp;rtl=0&amp;fonts=Arial&amp;skin=1&amp;font-color=auto&amp;btn-skin=3&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/revelation-introduction&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zacchaeus and Bartimaeus</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/38-zaccheaus-and-bartimaus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/38-zaccheaus-and-bartimaus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This lesson is titled &amp;ldquo;Zacchaeus and Bartimaeus&amp;rdquo; because of the healings, one physical and one spiritual of Blind Bartimaeus and Zacchaeus, the wealthy tax collector. In Luke, Jesus also gives the double-parable of the Minas (Pounds) and the King&amp;rsquo;s Return. The lesson begins with Jesus passing through Jericho on His way up to Jerusalem for the Passover, where we are presented with two potential textual problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew says they were leaving Jericho, while Mark/Luke says they drew near to Jericho.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew says there were two beggars, while Mark/Luke list only one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both tensions are easily reconciled and need not distract us from the core teachings of the passage.  There are several lessons for us with the healing of Bartimaeus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/ad09ca3fccdb82076f4cf3d075fcbe64.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Sycamore tree in Jericho&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Luke alone tells the story of Zacchaeus, the repentant tax collector.  Zacchaeus would have been extremely wealthy, but mainstream Jewish society viewed tax collectors as outcasts.  To his credit, he wanted to see Jesus, and, as it turns out, Jesus wanted to see him. Zacchaeus was likely less than five feet tall, so he decided to climb a Sycamore tree to get a better view. Jesus notices the man in the tree, then says He &amp;ldquo;must&amp;rdquo; stay with him.  Apparently, without any prompting from Jesus, Zacchaeus pledges to give half his goods to the poor. To the extent he defrauded anyone (which he did), he promised to repay with 4x damages.  Jesus tells him, “Today salvation has come.” Jesus chose to honor an outcast, and he repented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke concludes this section with Jesus telling (but not explaining) two parables. Both fall into the category of “Journey parables.” With these parables in Luke 19, Luke makes it a point to tell us that Jesus told the parables “BECAUSE they supposed that the kingdom of God was to appear immediately.” So whatever interpretation and application we come up with, it must connect somehow to the fact that (as we, the readers, know) the Messianic Kingdom did NOT appear immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is curious about these parables is that Jesus deliberately compares the King-on-a-journey to the hated and wicked Herod Archelaus. Archelaus was so bad even the Romans got rid of him.  So, the reader is presented with a curious question: if Jesus is allegorically speaking of Himself as the King in the parables, why would He so obviously compare Himself to the wicked Archelaus?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video and lesson detail will explore some plausible interpretations and applications of these parables, including one that we might say goes against the grain of our typical expectations. We’ll don our “Acts 17:11 thinking caps” to work through these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson concludes with Luke writing, “when He had said these things, he went on ahead, going up to Jerusalem.” In the next lesson, we will examine the Triumphal Entry, which is the first of the most significant seven days in all human history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readhear-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/hear the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew 20:29-34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark 10:46-52&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luke 18:35-19:38 (Primary)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6o6Y8OogPgw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/38-zacchaeus-and-bartimaeus/&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Jordan Part II</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/beyond-the-jordan-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/beyond-the-jordan-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part II of the Gospel Backgrounds lesson titled, &amp;ldquo;Beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin the lesson, Jesus receives a question from a &amp;ldquo;rich, young ruler&amp;rdquo; about what must be done to inherit eternal life. We often think that the young man has a &amp;ldquo;works righteousness&amp;rdquo; mindset - in other words, if a person has enough good deeds, he or she will merit eternal salvation. This is true to some degree, but notice Jesus&amp;rsquo; answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t say &amp;ldquo;to get eternal life, all you need to do is accept Me into your heart.&amp;rdquo; In response to the immediate question, Jesus says first &amp;ldquo;keep the commandments&amp;rdquo;.  Then when pressed further, He says, &amp;ldquo;one thing you lack: sell everything, give it to the poor, then follow Me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that Jesus doesn&amp;rsquo;t rebuke the young man about being self-righteous, nor does Jesus correct the man&amp;rsquo;s errant theology. The man had a heart issue, not a head issue. There is a lot more going on with this exchange than it may first appear.  We will take a peek under the hood to get at some of the lessons for our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/mat05686.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exchange befuddles the disciples.  They &amp;ldquo;remind&amp;rdquo; Jesus that they HAVE left everything and followed their Rabbi as His talmidim.  Jesus assures them that their sacrifices will not go unrewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 20 begins with one of my favorite parables, the parable of the workers.  A man needs workers for his vineyard.  He finds some early in the day, but also at various points throughout the day, including at the &amp;ldquo;11th hour&amp;rdquo; right before the work is to end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the work is done, the owner calls the workers from last to first and, to the surprise of those hired early, everyone is paid a denarious, a full day&amp;rsquo;s wage.  Those hired early in the day gripe that this is unfair.  Is is right that someone who did 1/12 of the work get paid the same as those who did a full day&amp;rsquo;s work?  The owner replies that the first group agreed to the wage, and besides what He does with his money is his business and no one else&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parable is rich with meaning and has several practical and spiritual applications.  We will discuss a few of these in the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The section concludes with Jesus receiving a request from James and John to sit at Jesus&amp;rsquo; right and left hands during the millennial kingdom, which is often portrayed as a great banquet.  Instead of rebuking their pride, Jesus explains what it means to sit by his side and &amp;ldquo;drink His cup&amp;rdquo;.  This act of presumption, naturally, irks the other ten disciples.  Jesus explains that our mission as disciples is not to be serve but to serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew 19:16-20:28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark 10:17-45&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luke 18:18-34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MNGvRWEF5PU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/37b-beyond-the-jordan-ii&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Jordan Part I </title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/across-the-jordan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/across-the-jordan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;images/37.map.png&#34; title=&#34;map&#34; width=&#34;65%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel Backgrounds&lt;/em&gt; Lesson 37 is titled &amp;ldquo;Beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo;  We will do this in two parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After leaving the Harod Valley [#7 on the map], Jesus makes His way to the Jordan, just south of where it exits the Sea of Galilee.  The north-south path along the river in this vicinity was along the eastern shore, which the Gospel writers call &amp;ldquo;Judea beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo; [8]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus will engage a group of inquisitive (but not necessarily trecharous) Pharisees who want to know the Master&amp;rsquo;s position on divorce.  As it is today, divorce was a critical and controversial topic because of its impact on family and society.  The Pharisees themselves were divided on when divorce was permissible.  The majority view held that a man could divorce his wife for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; reason, including not liking her cooking or even finding another woman more attractive.  The minority view held that the Torah had in view sexual misconduct as the only permissible reason.  Jesus sided with the minority.  The disciples are so taken-aback by Jesus&amp;rsquo; response that they exclaim &amp;ldquo;in that case, it is better not to marry!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus also teaches about the role of children and we will understand what it means to &amp;ldquo;become like a child&amp;rdquo; in order to enter heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IxJTLlEQlp4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/beyond-the-jordan&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds commentary&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Between Samaria and Galilee</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/between-samaria-and-galilee/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/between-samaria-and-galilee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel Backgrounds&lt;/em&gt; Lesson 36 is titled &amp;ldquo;Between Samaria and Galilee,&amp;rdquo; and is taken from Luke 17:11 where we are told Jesus is making his way up to Jerusalem for His final passover and passes between Samaria and Galilee.  The video will explore the geography of the region know as the Harod Valley, where many scholars believe this episode took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/36.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central story is that of Jesus healing ten lepers.  While all ten were healed, only one, a Samaritan, returned to give thanks and praise to Jesus.  In that day, most Jews had a dim view of Samaritans as evidenced by the three stories where Samaritans are featured prominently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Woman at the Well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The parable of the Good Samaritan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Ten Lepers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson for us is if even a Samaritan has enough heart to give thanks, how much more should we, as followers/disciples/talmidim of Yeshua have a humble and thankful heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TKbltCM2Hus&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
