<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu59ba181d12b9f86a6b06fa85c0a2a62a_406614_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Jordan Part II</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/beyond-the-jordan-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/beyond-the-jordan-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part II of the Gospel Backgrounds lesson titled, &amp;ldquo;Beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin the lesson, Jesus receives a question from a &amp;ldquo;rich, young ruler&amp;rdquo; about what must be done to inherit eternal life. Jesus responds &amp;ldquo;Keep the Commandments.&amp;rdquo; When the man says that he&amp;rsquo;s done this, Jesus then tells him to sell everything.  We often think that the young man has a &amp;ldquo;works righteousness&amp;rdquo; mindset. This is true to some degree, but notice Jesus&#39; answer.  He doesn&amp;rsquo;t say &amp;ldquo;to get eternal life, all you need to do is accept Me into your heart.&amp;rdquo;  He says first &amp;ldquo;keep the commandments,&amp;rdquo;.  Then when pressed further, He says, &amp;ldquo;sell everything, give it to the poor, then follow Me.&amp;rdquo;  There is a lot more going on then it may first appear.  We will take a peek under the hood to get at some of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/mat05686.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exchange befuddles the disciples.  They &amp;ldquo;remind&amp;rdquo; Jesus that they HAVE left everything and followed their Rabbi.  Jesus assures them that their sacrifices will not go unrewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 20 begins with one of my favorite parables, the parable of the workers.  A man needs workers for his vineyard.  He finds some early in the day, but also at various points throughout the day, including the &amp;ldquo;11th hour&amp;rdquo; right before the work is to end.  This is possibly where our &amp;ldquo;at the 11th hour&amp;rdquo; idiom originates from.  When the work is done, the owner calls the workers from last to first and, to the surprise of those hired early, everyone is paid a denarious, a full day&amp;rsquo;s wage.  Those hired early in the day express their belief that this is unfair.  How can people who did 1/12 of the work get paid the same as those who did a full day&amp;rsquo;s work?  The owner replies that the first group agreed to the wage, and besides what He does with his money is his business and no one else&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parable is rich with meaning and has several applications.  We will discuss a few of these in the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The section concludes with Jesus receiving a request from James and John to sit at Jesus&#39; right and left hands during the millenial kingdom, which is often portrayed as a great banquet.  Instead of rebuking their pride, Jesus explains what it means to sit by his side and &amp;ldquo;drink His cup&amp;rdquo;.  This act of presumption, naturally, irks the other ten disciples.  Jesus explains that our mission as disciples is not to be serve but to serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MNGvRWEF5PU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/37b-beyond-the-jordan-ii&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Jordan Part I </title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/across-the-jordan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/across-the-jordan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;images/37.map.png&#34; title=&#34;map&#34; width=&#34;65%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel Backgrounds&lt;/em&gt; Lesson 37 is titled &amp;ldquo;Beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo;  We will do this in two parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After leaving the Harod Valley [#7 on the map], Jesus makes His way to the Jordan, just south of where it exits the Sea of Galilee.  The north-south path along the river in this vicinity was along the eastern shore, which the Gospel writers call &amp;ldquo;Judea beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo; [8]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus will engage a group of inquisitive (but not necessarily trecharous) Pharisees who want to know the Master&amp;rsquo;s position on divorce.  As it is today, divorce was a critical and controversial topic because of its impact on family and society.  The Pharisees themselves were divided on when divorce was permissible.  The majority view held that a man could divorce his wife for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; reason, including not liking her cooking or even finding another woman more attractive.  The minority view held that the Torah had in view sexual misconduct as the only permissible reason.  Jesus sided with the minority.  The disciples are so taken-aback by Jesus&#39; response that they exclaim &amp;ldquo;in that case, it is better not to marry!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus also teaches about the role of children and we will understand what it means to &amp;ldquo;become like a child&amp;rdquo; in order to enter heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IxJTLlEQlp4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/beyond-the-jordan&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds commentary&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Between Samaria and Galilee</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/between-samaria-and-galilee/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/between-samaria-and-galilee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel Backgrounds&lt;/em&gt; Lesson 36 is titled &amp;ldquo;Between Samaria and Galilee,&amp;rdquo; and is taken from Luke 17:11 where we are told Jesus is making his way up to Jerusalem for His final passover and passes between Samaria and Galilee.  The video will explore the geography of the region know as the Harod Valley, where many scholars believe this episode took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/36.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central story is that of Jesus healing ten lepers.  While all ten were healed, only one, a Samaritan, returned to give thanks and praise to Jesus.  In that day, most Jews had a dim view of Samaritans as evidenced by the three stories where Samaritans are featured prominently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Woman at the Well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The parable of the Good Samaritan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Ten Lepers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson for us is if even a Samaritan has enough heart to give thanks, how much more should we, as followers/disciples/talmidim of Yeshua have a humble and thankful heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TKbltCM2Hus&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
