<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu53652e90a6e4e4f125f22da2a993ec10_403021_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historical Prelude to Revelation</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/historical-prelude-to-revelation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/historical-prelude-to-revelation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a supplement to our Revelation background series. We’re going to take a look at significant events in the period between the Jewish Revolt of 66CE, including the destruction of the Jewish Temple in 70, through the mid-90s that resulted in John’s exile on Patmos, where he received the Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This interval history is surprisingly relevant if we wish to better understand the context for Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if history wasn’t your best subject in school, I believe you’ll find this background helpful as we prepare to study Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b5iQBoBvy_0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/historical-prelude&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New series! Revelation Backgrounds</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/new-series-revelation-backgrounds/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/new-series-revelation-backgrounds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;images/e45914e26cc0be101f69fd4d54a746be.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to our series on the book of Revelation we call &amp;ldquo;Revelation Backgrounds.&amp;rdquo;  In this introductory episode, we will provide an introduction to the book, some background into Jewish Apocalyptic literature, and we&amp;rsquo;ll provide what we see are Seven Keys to Interpretation.  Revelation can be a complex book, but these keys will help assure we get started on the right path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many commentators focus on what Revelation may mean to us living in the 21st Century, very few Protestant commentators take the time to understand the historical, first-century context.  Revelation, as it turns out, is the &lt;em&gt;most Jewish book&lt;/em&gt; in the New Testament. There are over 800 allusions to the Old Testament in the book&amp;rsquo;s 404 verses.  The reasons many people struggle with the book is because we ignore its Jewishness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have developed &amp;ldquo;Seven Keys to Interpretation,&amp;rdquo; which we will discuss in the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow the &amp;ldquo;Talmidim Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; -  We want to learn to walk in the dust of Yeshua our Rabbi just as His original Talmidim, His disciples such as John did.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be open to the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s leading&lt;/strong&gt; - Understanding what God wants us to learn is way more important that making sure others know our beliefs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be a Berean&lt;/strong&gt; - Check everything out against scripture.  If our interpretation doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit, it might be something we need to discard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand the intended audience&lt;/strong&gt; - They were Jewish, or if they were gentiles, they were worshipping in a Jewish setting, which would have almost nothing in common with our western protestant churches today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revelation is a Jewish Book&lt;/strong&gt; - For every verse in Revelation there is a 2:1 ratio of Old Testament illusions.  If we try to understand Revelation without this background, we&amp;rsquo;ll be lost.  With it, we&amp;rsquo;ll be much better off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be suspicious if an interpretation does not fit the original context&lt;/strong&gt; - that is to say, if it could not have been within the realm of possibility for John or the original audience.  This is not to say that the book can&amp;rsquo;t have multiple layers of interpretation, but for our historical and cultural approach, we want to start by making sure it&amp;rsquo;s something that would have made sense to the original audience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No fear allowed&lt;/strong&gt; -  While books and websites present the events of Revelation as something that should scare an unbeliever (and they probably should be scared), fear has no place in a believer&amp;rsquo;s heart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will also look at who wrote the book and some other details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who wrote Revelation?  &lt;strong&gt;John the Apostle&lt;/strong&gt;.  We don&amp;rsquo;t have 100% concrete proof, but the earliest and best evidence suggests it was none other than John, the author of the Gospel and three letters that bear his name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where was it written?  &lt;strong&gt;Patmos&lt;/strong&gt;, which is an island some 35 miles off the coast of Turkey. Revelation 1:9 is our source for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When was it written?  Most conservative scholars land on &lt;strong&gt;90-95 of the Common Era&lt;/strong&gt;.  Iraneus is the earliest source for this information.  He was a disciple of Polycarp, who was a disciple of John.  Iraneus states John received the relevation during the time of Emperor Domitian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How was Revelation given?  &lt;strong&gt;Signs and Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;! Revelation 1:1 contains the Greek word σημαίνω, which literally means &amp;ldquo;rendered into signs.&amp;rdquo; Every sign in the Bible points to something.  Every sign in Revelation points to a verse (sometimes more than one) in the Old Testament.  The pattern of the number seven is also quite conspicuous.  Sevens are everywhere in Revelation.  Since sevens are also conspicuous throughout the entire Bible, this is often seen as the &amp;ldquo;fingerprints of the Holy Spirit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To whom was Revelation written? &lt;strong&gt;The seven messianic congregations in Asia Minor.&lt;/strong&gt;.  We are told this in Revelation 1:4.  Note that although your Bible may say &amp;ldquo;seven churches,&amp;rdquo; the &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; either as a building or an organization did not exist when Revelation was given.  We need to avoid what is called an &lt;em&gt;anachronistic fallacy&lt;/em&gt;.  See the lesson detail for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why was Revelation written? &lt;strong&gt;The Hope of HIS RETURN and the Restoration of all things!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to beginning this study!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation 1:1-9&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SfuWhCybaYU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/revelation-introduction&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Revelation Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zacchaeus and Bartimaeus</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/38-zaccheaus-and-bartimaus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/38-zaccheaus-and-bartimaus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This lesson is titled &amp;ldquo;Zacchaeus and Bartimaeus&amp;rdquo; because of the healings, one physical and one spiritual of Blind Bartimaeus and Zacchaeus, the wealthy tax collector. In Luke, Jesus also gives the double-parable of the Minas (Pounds) and the King&amp;rsquo;s Return. The lesson begins with Jesus passing through Jericho on His way up to Jerusalem for the Passover, where we are presented with two potential textual problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew says they were leaving Jericho, while Mark/Luke says they drew near to Jericho.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew says there were two beggars, while Mark/Luke list only one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both tensions are easily reconciled and need not distract us from the core teachings of the passage.  There are several lessons for us with the healing of Bartimaeus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/ad09ca3fccdb82076f4cf3d075fcbe64.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Sycamore tree in Jericho&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Luke alone tells the story of Zacchaeus, the repentant tax collector.  Zacchaeus would have been extremely wealthy, but mainstream Jewish society viewed tax collectors as outcasts.  To his credit, he wanted to see Jesus, and, as it turns out, Jesus wanted to see him. Zacchaeus was likely less than five feet tall, so he decided to climb a Sycamore tree to get a better view. Jesus notices the man in the tree, then says He &amp;ldquo;must&amp;rdquo; stay with him.  Apparently, without any prompting from Jesus, Zacchaeus pledges to give half his goods to the poor. To the extent he defrauded anyone (which he did), he promised to repay with 4x damages.  Jesus tells him, “Today salvation has come.” Jesus chose to honor an outcast, and he repented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke concludes this section with Jesus telling (but not explaining) two parables. Both fall into the category of “Journey parables.” With these parables in Luke 19, Luke makes it a point to tell us that Jesus told the parables “BECAUSE they supposed that the kingdom of God was to appear immediately.” So whatever interpretation and application we come up with, it must connect somehow to the fact that (as we, the readers, know) the Messianic Kingdom did NOT appear immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is curious about these parables is that Jesus deliberately compares the King-on-a-journey to the hated and wicked Herod Archelaus. Archelaus was so bad even the Romans got rid of him.  So, the reader is presented with a curious question: if Jesus is allegorically speaking of Himself as the King in the parables, why would He so obviously compare Himself to the wicked Archelaus?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video and lesson detail will explore some plausible interpretations and applications of these parables, including one that we might say goes against the grain of our typical expectations. We’ll don our “Acts 17:11 thinking caps” to work through these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson concludes with Luke writing, “when He had said these things, he went on ahead, going up to Jerusalem.” In the next lesson, we will examine the Triumphal Entry, which is the first of the most significant seven days in all human history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readhear-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/hear the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew 20:29-34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark 10:46-52&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luke 18:35-19:38 (Primary)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6o6Y8OogPgw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/38-zacchaeus-and-bartimaeus/&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Jordan Part II</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/beyond-the-jordan-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/beyond-the-jordan-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part II of the Gospel Backgrounds lesson titled, &amp;ldquo;Beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin the lesson, Jesus receives a question from a &amp;ldquo;rich, young ruler&amp;rdquo; about what must be done to inherit eternal life. We often think that the young man has a &amp;ldquo;works righteousness&amp;rdquo; mindset - in other words, if a person has enough good deeds, he or she will merit eternal salvation. This is true to some degree, but notice Jesus&#39; answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t say &amp;ldquo;to get eternal life, all you need to do is accept Me into your heart.&amp;rdquo; In response to the immediate question, Jesus says first &amp;ldquo;keep the commandments&amp;rdquo;.  Then when pressed further, He says, &amp;ldquo;one thing you lack: sell everything, give it to the poor, then follow Me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that Jesus doesn&amp;rsquo;t rebuke the young man about being self-righteous, nor does Jesus correct the man&amp;rsquo;s errant theology. The man had a heart issue, not a head issue. There is a lot more going on with this exchange than it may first appear.  We will take a peek under the hood to get at some of the lessons for our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/mat05686.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exchange befuddles the disciples.  They &amp;ldquo;remind&amp;rdquo; Jesus that they HAVE left everything and followed their Rabbi as His talmidim.  Jesus assures them that their sacrifices will not go unrewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 20 begins with one of my favorite parables, the parable of the workers.  A man needs workers for his vineyard.  He finds some early in the day, but also at various points throughout the day, including at the &amp;ldquo;11th hour&amp;rdquo; right before the work is to end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the work is done, the owner calls the workers from last to first and, to the surprise of those hired early, everyone is paid a denarious, a full day&amp;rsquo;s wage.  Those hired early in the day gripe that this is unfair.  Is is right that someone who did 1/12 of the work get paid the same as those who did a full day&amp;rsquo;s work?  The owner replies that the first group agreed to the wage, and besides what He does with his money is his business and no one else&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parable is rich with meaning and has several practical and spiritual applications.  We will discuss a few of these in the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The section concludes with Jesus receiving a request from James and John to sit at Jesus&#39; right and left hands during the millennial kingdom, which is often portrayed as a great banquet.  Instead of rebuking their pride, Jesus explains what it means to sit by his side and &amp;ldquo;drink His cup&amp;rdquo;.  This act of presumption, naturally, irks the other ten disciples.  Jesus explains that our mission as disciples is not to be serve but to serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;readlisten-to-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/Listen to the portions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;, header_font_size: 10, body_font_size: 14, footer_font_size: 8, body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39; };&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew 19:16-20:28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark 10:17-45&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luke 18:18-34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MNGvRWEF5PU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-context&#34;&gt;Study the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/37b-beyond-the-jordan-ii&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Jordan Part I </title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/across-the-jordan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/across-the-jordan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;images/37.map.png&#34; title=&#34;map&#34; width=&#34;65%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel Backgrounds&lt;/em&gt; Lesson 37 is titled &amp;ldquo;Beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo;  We will do this in two parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After leaving the Harod Valley [#7 on the map], Jesus makes His way to the Jordan, just south of where it exits the Sea of Galilee.  The north-south path along the river in this vicinity was along the eastern shore, which the Gospel writers call &amp;ldquo;Judea beyond the Jordan.&amp;rdquo; [8]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus will engage a group of inquisitive (but not necessarily trecharous) Pharisees who want to know the Master&amp;rsquo;s position on divorce.  As it is today, divorce was a critical and controversial topic because of its impact on family and society.  The Pharisees themselves were divided on when divorce was permissible.  The majority view held that a man could divorce his wife for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; reason, including not liking her cooking or even finding another woman more attractive.  The minority view held that the Torah had in view sexual misconduct as the only permissible reason.  Jesus sided with the minority.  The disciples are so taken-aback by Jesus&#39; response that they exclaim &amp;ldquo;in that case, it is better not to marry!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus also teaches about the role of children and we will understand what it means to &amp;ldquo;become like a child&amp;rdquo; in order to enter heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IxJTLlEQlp4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/beyond-the-jordan&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the complete Gospel Backgrounds commentary&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Between Samaria and Galilee</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/post/between-samaria-and-galilee/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/post/between-samaria-and-galilee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel Backgrounds&lt;/em&gt; Lesson 36 is titled &amp;ldquo;Between Samaria and Galilee,&amp;rdquo; and is taken from Luke 17:11 where we are told Jesus is making his way up to Jerusalem for His final passover and passes between Samaria and Galilee.  The video will explore the geography of the region know as the Harod Valley, where many scholars believe this episode took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/36.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central story is that of Jesus healing ten lepers.  While all ten were healed, only one, a Samaritan, returned to give thanks and praise to Jesus.  In that day, most Jews had a dim view of Samaritans as evidenced by the three stories where Samaritans are featured prominently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Woman at the Well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The parable of the Good Samaritan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Ten Lepers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson for us is if even a Samaritan has enough heart to give thanks, how much more should we, as followers/disciples/talmidim of Yeshua have a humble and thankful heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TKbltCM2Hus&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
