<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gospel Backgrounds I: Beginnings | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Gospel Backgrounds I: Beginnings</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu9bdc4cc28a100eaa5c154301214e2807_480992_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Gospel Backgrounds I: Beginnings</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Logos</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb01/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In THE LOGOS We see the revelation of the Apostle John, a first-century Galilean Jew, of the Word becoming flesh. To understand his words, we need to understand them from a first-century Galilean Jewish perspective. Jesus brings the revelation and glory of God into the world of men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read/hear the portion: John 1:1-18&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-11&#34;&gt;John 1:1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-12-6&#34;&gt;John 1:2-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-17&#34;&gt;John 1:7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-18-13&#34;&gt;John 1:8-13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-114-15&#34;&gt;John 1:14-15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-11618&#34;&gt;John 1:16:18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#study-questions&#34;&gt;Study Questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fU4NFVS1Gbc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gospels are Jewish documents. 1st Century “Christianity” was a Jewish sect.
John is often viewed as contrasting the correct way of Christianity with the incorrect way of Judaism, but this represents what is called an anachronistic fallacy, often shortened to “Anachronism” - misappropriation of concepts and ideas in time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often see anachronisms in period piece movies.  Someone will be wearing a digital watch in a movie set in the 18th century.  at the 1955 enchantment under the sea dance, Marty McFly is playing a 1958 gibson guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a challenge to restrain our own presuppositions, our set of established beliefs, when we read the Bible.  It is natural to assume a biblical speaker to affirm our presuppositions in order to justify our positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An overarching anachronistic fallacy Many commentators commit is to take what is called “the parting of the ways” between Judaism and Christianity that occurred much later (2nd-4th centuries CE) and reading it back into this text in the 1st century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, since it had not occurred yet, there is absolutely no way John or any other biblical writer could have the split between Judaism and Christianity in view when they were writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is called eisegesis - reading into the text.  Modern conservative scholars would all agree that eisegesis is bad yet many of them do it almost automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we strive for is EXEGESIS, understanding the text IN CONTEXT to extract what the author was saying.  To do this, we must first realize the gospels are Jewish documents written within a historical context of 2nd Temple Judaism.  The audience were Jewish Christ followers together with many non-Jews who had joined a Jewish sect..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early church fathers affirmed John’s authorship of this Gospel strongly and unanimously. Some of the fathers claim to have personally known those who knew John in Ephesus in his later years, thus making a direct link to the tradition of Johannine authorship. The evangelist John is shown here with the symbol of an eagle, the one of the four living creatures which is traditionally associated with him (Ezekiel 1:5-10 and Revelation 4:6-7).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-11&#34;&gt;John 1:1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;1 In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logos in the normal sense means “word or speech”.  In this prologue, John uses it in the mystical sense.  He alludes directly to the beginning of the Torah and the beginning of creation.  He starts this with an intentional allusion to Genesis 1:1 “In the beginning”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-12-6&#34;&gt;John 1:2-6&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;2 He was in the beginning with God. 3 All things were made through him, and without him was not anything made that was made. 4 In him was life, and the life was the light of men. 5 The light shines in the darkness, and the darkness has not overcome it. 6 There was a man sent from God, whose name was John.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall the first act of Creation. “and God said Let there be Light, and there was light.”&lt;br&gt;
In verse 4  John declares that this life had always been available through God’s word, which is the same word that he identifies with Jesus (IVP).
In John 1:5, The divine light from the first day of creation shines once again into the dark world of man, signifying a new creation (COM)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There came a man, sent from God, whose name was John
Excavations in the early 2000s revealed this cave west of Jerusalem near Ein Kerem. Archaeologist Shimon Gibson identified it with the ministry of John the Baptist on the basis of a stick-figure drawing of a man inside the cave. Gibson’s theory was published in The Cave of John the Baptist (Doubleday, 2004).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For responses, see that by James F. Strange (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biblicalarchaeology.org/reviews/the-cave-of-john-the-baptist/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.biblicalarchaeology.org/reviews/the-cave-of-john-the-baptist/&lt;/a&gt;) and Todd Bolen (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bibleplaces.com/cave-of-john-the-baptist/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.bibleplaces.com/cave-of-john-the-baptist/)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the writing of the church father Origen (AD 185-254), the location of John’s baptizing at Bethany beyond the Jordan has been located at a point near the river opposite Jericho.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-17&#34;&gt;John 1:7&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;7  He came as a witness, to bear witness about the light, that all might believe through him&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some scholars note that John has a “legal” feel.  As you read John&amp;rsquo;s gospel, be on the lookout for the terms Witness, Testimony, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, John is interested not only in establishing Jesus’ credentials, he is also interested in “convicting” the corrupt Jerusalem establishment on the grounds of usurption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/01-the_logos_files/01.Picture7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;30%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discovered in Cave 4 of Qumran in the early 1950s, this text contains five biblical verses that focused on the coming of the Messiah. This artifact was photographed in the Amman Museum.&lt;br&gt;
A few scholars suspect John may have been part of the Essene sect, but in any case he was definitely influenced by them.  The Essenes believed that the forces controlling Jerusalem and the Temple were usurpers and priests of darkness.  They juxtaposed darkness and light just as John does throughout his writings.   “in the Dead Sea Scrolls, the forces of light and darkness were engaged in mortal combat, but light was predestined to triumph” (IVP)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-18-13&#34;&gt;John 1:8-13&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;8 He was not the light, but came to bear witness about the light. 9 The true light, which gives light to everyone, was coming into the world. 10 He was in the world, and the world was made through him, yet the world did not know him. 11 He came to his own, and his own people did not receive him. 12 But to all who did receive him, who believed in his name, he gave the right to become children of God, 13 who were born, not of blood nor of the will of the flesh nor of the will of man, but of God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal is spiritual rebirth, not ethnic descent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerusalem was the home of David and place where his greater Son was appointed to rule over the nation.  John uses a term Ioudaioi, which get’s translated as “jews” but many scholars believe this is too generic.  Think of the term “Americans” -The Americans won the Gold medal in 1980 (a group of 20 hockey players).  The Americans invaded Normandy (those members of the Army and the Navy in June 1944).  The Americans imposed Tariffs on China (specifically referring to the Government).  The Americans pay their taxes on April 15 (most Americans but not all - children don’t pay taxes).  The Americans are guaranteed freedoms under the Constitution (all Americans)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the term &amp;ldquo;Jews&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot; could be anywhere from All Jews - which we know is not in view here because the 1st Century church was nearly 100% Jewish.   Unfortunately many commentators, view it as exactly this: John is an early Christian Anti-Jewish document.  It is more likely that what is in view is not rejection by all-Israel, but rather rejection by a sub-group within Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What might some of these sub-groups be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could maybe refer those in Judea who generally rejected as opposed to those in Galilee where Jesus was largely accepted. But even here, not all Judeans rejected him.  Nicodemus for example.  Several scholars believe Ioudaoi specifically refers to the ruling establishment, which for the most part wanted Jesus out of the picture.  Again Nicodemus is an exception and there were probably others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many commentaries place the blame on all Israel, which could be painting with too broad of a brush.  It would be like holding all 300 million Americans responsible for something done by a small group of corrupt politicians in Washington DC.  With that said, a national guilt might also be in view- America is a sinful and unrepentant nation, even though many Americans do repent of their sin.  Deuteronomy 9:23 states, “You rebelled against the command of the LORD your God; you neither believed Him nor listened to His voice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, we must allow God to own the business of judgment.   it is wrong to use our holy book to specifically condemn a group of people (as the church as done to Jews for the last 2000 years).  We are to love our neighbors and pray for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Jewish thought of the day was that to be a true Child of God, one had to be a Child of Abraham, either through birth or conversion (even today, Ben Avraham is a common name a gentile takes when converting to Judaism).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John is setting the stage that it is not ethnic affiliation but spiritual rebirth that matters.  A topic that will be developed in John Chapter 3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-114-15&#34;&gt;John 1:14-15&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;14  And the Word became flesh and dwelt among us, and we have seen his glory, glory as of the only Son from the Father, full of grace and truth. 15  (John bore witness about him, and cried out, “This was he of whom I said, ‘He who comes after me ranks before me, because he was before me.’”)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A father’s only son” would remind readers of Genesis 22, where God instructed Abraham “take your son, your only son whom you love, Isaac&amp;hellip;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/01-the_logos_files/01.Picture8.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:left&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The star in the Church of Nativity in Bethlehem marks the spot where tradition says that Mary gave birth to Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the Greek mind, the invisible spiritual real is far superior to the earthly realm.  However, God created man spirit and flesh.  Our flesh only became corrupt AFTER the fall.  God intended there to be a union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The verb translated above as “dwelt” (skenoo) is related to the Greek word for “tabernacle” (skene). Just as God dwelt with his people in the tabernacle, so the Word tabernacled with his people in the incarnation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;john-11618&#34;&gt;John 1:16:18&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;John 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;16 For from his fullness we have all received, grace upon grace. 17 For (as) the (Torah) was given through Moses, grace and truth came through Jesus Christ. 18 No one has ever seen God; the only God, who is at the Father&amp;rsquo;s side, he has made him known.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verse 17 is often translated “for the law came through Moses &lt;em&gt;BUT&lt;/em&gt; Grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “BUT” is a mistranslation (possibly intentional) - it is not in the Greek.  John just got through saying that Jesus was there in the beginning.  This means Grace and Truth where there in the beginning.  The Law has a special role to play for the nation of Israel but it is not in any way antithetical to the Gospel of Jesus.  John sees Jesus as affirming the covenant promises God made in the Torah.  A better reading might be “for AS the Torah was given through Moses, Grace and Truth came through Jesus Christ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “but” originally occurred in the King James Version.  The anachronistic error here involves the 16th Century division between Protestants and Catholics regarding the function of the law in the life of the believer.  One of the Reformation cries was “Faith alone”.  It wasn’t until Luther that “Law” and “Grace” became opposites.  Superimposing this view on the Biblical Text is simply not correct.  The oppose of Law is lawlessness.  The oppose of grace is disgrace.  It is wrong to view any part of the Bible as lawless or disgraceful!  God’s Law is a good and beautiful thing.  Read Psalm 119!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;study-questions&#34;&gt;Study Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can anachronisms and eisegesis be a problem in my studies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In what ways does John 1:1-5 parallel Genesis 1 and how does that change my thinking of Genesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I think “His own” in verse 11 refers to all Jews?  Why or why not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did my opinionAs I reflect on the “tabernacle” discussion in John 1:14, how does (or how should) this affect my walk with Jesus?
change after this lesson?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did my understanding of the Law/Old Testament change after studying 1:17?  How can I apply this going forward?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/01-slides.pdf&#34;&gt;Lesson 1 Background slides (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/01-handout.pdf&#34;&gt;Lesson 1 Notes Worksheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bolen, Todd. “John 1.” PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keener, Craig S. The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament. 2nd edition. Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lancaster, Daniel T. “The Logos.” In Chronicles of the Messiah, edited by Boaz D. Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster. Second edition. Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lizorkin-Eyzenberg, Eli. The Jewish Gospel of John: Discovering Jesus, King of All Israel. CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform, 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schlegel, William. The Land and the Bible: A Historical Geographical Companion to the Satellite Bible Atlas. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.  2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;mdash;. Satellite Bible Atlas. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/satellite-bible-atlas-schlegel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/satellite-bible-atlas-schlegel/&lt;/a&gt;  2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images used are courtesy of the Photo Companion to the Bible or the Pictorial Library of Bible Lands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annunciations</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ANNUNCIATIONS, we visit the Holy Temple in Jerusalem to watch the priesthood conduct the morning sacrifice. We meet Zechariah and follow him into the Sanctuary for his encounter with the angel Gabriel. The story of Zechariah and Elizabeth and their struggle to conceive a child hearkens back to the patriarchs. The miraculous conception of John sets in motion a chain of events that will culminate in the messianic redemption. Then, six months later, the angel descends to appear before a simple Jewish girl in a rural Galilean village. Mary leaves Nazareth and travels to Ein Karem near Jerusalem to visit her cousin Elizabeth. The Holy Spirit stirs hearts and moves tongues to give utterance to the good news of redemption.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read/hear the portion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke 1:1-80&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#roadmap&#34;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-11-4&#34;&gt;Luke 1:1-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-15-7&#34;&gt;Luke 1:5-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-18-12&#34;&gt;Luke 1:8-12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#lukes-seven-oracles&#34;&gt;Luke&amp;rsquo;s Seven Oracles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-1-oracle-to-zechariah&#34;&gt;Luke 1: Oracle to Zechariah&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-118-20-zechariah-doubts&#34;&gt;Luke 1:18-20 Zechariah Doubts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-121-23&#34;&gt;Luke 1:21-23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-124-25&#34;&gt;Luke 1:24-25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-126-29-gabriel-visits-mary&#34;&gt;Luke 1:26-29 Gabriel visits Mary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-130-33-the-annunciation&#34;&gt;Luke 1:30-33 The Annunciation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-134-38&#34;&gt;Luke 1:34-38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-139-41&#34;&gt;Luke 1:39-41&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-142-45-elizabeths-blessing&#34;&gt;Luke 1:42-45 Elizabeth&amp;rsquo;s Blessing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-146-55----the-magnificat&#34;&gt;Luke 1:46-55 &amp;ndash; The &lt;em&gt;Magnificat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-156-58&#34;&gt;Luke 1:56-58&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-159&#34;&gt;Luke 1:59&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-160-66-his-name-is-yochanon&#34;&gt;Luke 1:60-66 His name is Yochanon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-167&#34;&gt;Luke 1:67&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-168-79-the-benedictus&#34;&gt;Luke 1:68-79 The &lt;em&gt;Benedictus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-180&#34;&gt;Luke 1:80&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I (1-12); 
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gzQWdaGn70g&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;II (13-38): 
 &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
   &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cjvZIhBuewQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;III (39-80): 
 &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
   &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mvUq3SWv-Dg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;roadmap&#34;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who is Theophilus?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;King Herod&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zechariah&amp;rsquo;s big day at the Altar of Incense&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke&amp;rsquo;s Seven Oracles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zechariah in the Penalty Box&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Annunciation at Nazareth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Magnificat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Benedictus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John in the Wilderness&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-11-4&#34;&gt;Luke 1:1-4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inasmuch as many have undertaken to compile a narrative of the things that have been accomplished among us,just as those who from the beginning were eyewitnesses and ministers of the word have delivered them to us, it seemed good to me also, having followed all things closely for some time past, to write an orderly account for you, most excellent Theophilus, that you may have certainty concerning the things you have been taught.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all one sentence in Greek as it is in English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is considered some of the highest academic/classical Greek in all of antiquity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this introduction belies the letter&amp;rsquo;s importance to whoever Theophilus was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This style will change abruptly in verse 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/image1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Ephesus Luke&amp;#39;s tomb with bull tb010501537&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the Gospel writers is associated with one of the Four Living Creatures in Ezekiel 1 and Revelation 4 (Lion, Man, Ox, and Eagle)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are also the standards for the camp of Israel (Numbers 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiously, the assignment of each has not remained constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We saw John as the Eagle in the last lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally Luke was associated with an Ox; today Mark gets the Ox because Mark portrays Jesus as the Servant of all, while Luke gets the Man because his gospel portrays Jesus as the Son of Man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The photo is of Luke&amp;rsquo;s tomb in Ephesus and, you can see the Ox or Bull underneath the cross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most scholars pin the date of the book to the 80s or early 90s CE; however, the fact that Luke (and all of the Gospels) omit mention of the destruction of the Jewish Temple in 70 CE might suggest an earlier date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who was Theophilus?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theo means God and Phileo means friendship love, so the name could mean &amp;ldquo;Lover of God.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potentially it is a code name. People who followed the God of Israel (including Yeshua following Jews and Gentiles) weren&amp;rsquo;t especially popular in the second-half of the first-century. Revelation speaks in code to avoid Roman censors; it&amp;rsquo;s possible the letter is addressed to the &amp;ldquo;Lover of God&amp;rdquo; who would have been known in Luke&amp;rsquo;s circle but not widely known elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is typically thought that Luke&amp;rsquo;s gospel was commissioned to provide an authoritative Greek gospel for the growing number of believers in the Gentile world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster notes that Josephus, a Jewish but pro-Roman historian, mentions (and archeology confirms) a high-priest by the name of Theophilus in the Apostolic Era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Missler believes Theophilus was a wealthy benefactor in one of Paul&amp;rsquo;s congregations who commissioned Luke and Acts for Paul&amp;rsquo;s trial in Rome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would be similar to a deposition or affidavit used in courts today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early date and formal first sentence would be consistent with such a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke notes that his gospel is not the only gospel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a trial lawyer, he reviewed other documents and interviewed witnesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke, who was a physician, was highly educated and credible; therefore, he could attest to the document&amp;rsquo;s authenticity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke makes the point that his is an &amp;ldquo;orderly account.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many commentators take this to mean Luke&amp;rsquo;s is the most chronologically accurate of the four gospels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-15-7&#34;&gt;Luke 1:5-7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the days of Herod, king of Judea, there was a priest named Zechariah, of the division of Abijah. And he had a wife from the daughters of Aaron, and her name was Elizabeth. And they were both righteous before God, walking blamelessly in all the commandments and statutes of the Lord. But they had no child, because Elizabeth was barren, and both were advanced in years.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference passages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genesis 15:6 And he believed the LORD, and he counted it to him as righteousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genesis 17:17 Then Abraham fell on his face and laughed and said to himself, &amp;ldquo;Shall a child be born to a man who is a hundred years old? Shall Sarah, who is ninety years old, bear a child?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the style abruptly changes from the lofty Greek to a Hebraic, Old Testament-style narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the many themes in the Bible is that of the righteous but barren woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Jewish sages wrote, &amp;ldquo;whenever it is written, &amp;lsquo;she had no child,&amp;rsquo; it means she would eventually bear one&amp;rdquo; (Genesis Rabbah 38:14).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, being barren was thought of as a type of curse; but here, Luke is going out of his way to let us know they were both righteous before God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He even points out that Elizabeth was from the daughters of Aaron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something a normal reader would likely pass over, but for those who dig, there is a nugget here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Levite like Zechariah was free to marry from any tribe, but it was considered especially righteous to marry another Levite from Aaron&amp;rsquo;s line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is Luke (or more specifically the Holy Spirit) underscoring how righteous Zechariah was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The childless was not a punishment for sin or because he was unworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that culture, Zechariah was also free to marry another who could have children; but he didn&amp;rsquo;t. He stayed with Elizabeth as they both advanced in years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herod















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image2_huae93d7b322f7700735e76c7b20ca7ba5_790034_314be0ab58ba4afe163fdaee8514bf27.webp 400w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image2_huae93d7b322f7700735e76c7b20ca7ba5_790034_a4128683d1abfcd427556a13421b43fd.webp 760w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image2_huae93d7b322f7700735e76c7b20ca7ba5_790034_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image2_huae93d7b322f7700735e76c7b20ca7ba5_790034_314be0ab58ba4afe163fdaee8514bf27.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;541&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any attempt to understand the political situation in Israel during the time of Jesus is going to be limited without a study of Herod the Great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Schlegel notes that Hollywood should make a movie because his life had all the elements Hollywood likes: war, violence, romance, sex, intrigue, assassinations, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one since Solomon controlled as much land in the region, and no one has since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His footprints are all over the Holy Land in terms of his many building projects, which the people liked because they give a sense of pride, and more immediately provided numerous jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These include the great palaces at Caesarea (labeled Strato&amp;rsquo;s Tower on this map), Jericho, Herodium by Bethlehem, and Masada, which has an incredible story as the last holdout for a band of rebels against Rome in AD72.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His most famous building was probably the Jewish Temple, which was one of the seven wonders of the ancient world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the old city walls are from the 16th century, the Western wall still contains a part of the Herodian wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, he was one of the most ruthless dictators who ever lived, so ultimately he was hated by the people he ruled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly suffering from some form of paranoia mixed with megalomania, he didn&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to eliminate anyone he saw as a threat including immediate family members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a quip that it was safer to be a pig in Herod&amp;rsquo;s house than one of his sons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He killed his wife Mariamne and then later wailed because of her death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he was dying, he gave an order to have some very popular Jewish leaders and rabbis arrested and executed&amp;hellip;all because he insisted that there be mourning on the day he died. Fortunately, that order was not carried out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was in the midst of this darkness that God became directly involved in Man&amp;rsquo;s affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-18-12&#34;&gt;Luke 1:8-12&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8 Now while he was serving as priest before God when his division was on duty, according to the custom of the priesthood, he was chosen by lot to enter the temple of the Lord and burn incense. And the whole multitude of the people were praying outside at the hour of incense. And there appeared to him an angel of the Lord standing on the right side of the altar of incense. And Zechariah was troubled when he saw him, and fear fell upon him.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Negev and the WildernessTabernacle ModelTabernacle model incense altar, tb052208365.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference passage: 1Ch 24:3,10 With the help of Zadok of the sons of Eleazar, and Ahimelech of the sons of Ithamar, David organized them according to the appointed duties in their service&amp;hellip;the seventh to Hakkoz, the eighth to Abijah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were as many as 18000 Levites who could serve as priests. This was likely a once-in-a-lifetime experience for Zechariah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His job was to kindle the incense and get it lit. The Jewish Mishnah records the day-to-day functions and service of the Temple. The photo is of the altar of incense as it may have looked like in the Tabernacle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Zechariah was doing this inside the Holy Place, the people were gathered. In their view, Zechariah was lifting their prayers up to God inside as they were praying outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Daniel 6, we see Daniel kept the appointed times of prayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He did this even though at the time, Jerusalem was in ruins. He still opened his window and prayed towards Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zechariah was likely praying too when he was interrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lukes-seven-oracles&#34;&gt;Luke&amp;rsquo;s Seven Oracles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Annunciation of John to Zechariah - 1:13-17&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Annunciation of Jesus to Mary - 1:30:37&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Blessings of Elizabeth - 1:42-45&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Magnificat&lt;/em&gt; - 1:46-55&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Benedictus&lt;/em&gt; - 1:68-80&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nunc Dimitis&lt;/em&gt; 2:29:32&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary&amp;rsquo;s Sword - 2:34-25&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke 1-2 continues the conspicuous pattern of sevens in the Bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most obvious is Revelation, where we have seven churches, seven bowls, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less obvious are the seven &amp;ldquo;I AM the &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; statements by Jesus in John&amp;rsquo;s gospel and the seven Kingdom parables in Matthew&amp;rsquo;s gospel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we exclude duplicates and letters written to pastors, we find that Paul also wrote to seven churches (Rome, Corinth, Galatia, Ephesus, Philippi, Colossae, and Thessaloniki).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep your eyes open for these as you study the Bible. Missler calls them &amp;ldquo;fingerprints of the Holy Spirit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost every verse in these oracles (also called &amp;ldquo;canticles&amp;rdquo; in some church traditions) has at least one allusion to an Old Testament verse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not have two books, a superior New Testament that replaces an inferior Old Testament. We have a single collection of 66 books that are intricately woven and interconnected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-1-oracle-to-zechariah&#34;&gt;Luke 1: Oracle to Zechariah&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;**13 But the angel said to him, &amp;ldquo;Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your prayer has been heard, and your wife Elizabeth will bear you a son, and you shall call his name John.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you will have joy and gladness, and many will rejoice at his birth, for he will be great before the Lord. And he must not drink wine or strong drink, and he will be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from his mother&amp;rsquo;s womb. And he will turn many of the children of Israel to the Lord their God, and he will go before him in the spirit and power of Elijah, to turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the disobedient to the wisdom of the just, to make ready for the Lord a people prepared.&amp;rdquo;**&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference passages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gen 21:6-7 And Sarah said, &amp;ldquo;God has made laughter for me; everyone who hears will laugh over me.&amp;rdquo; [7] And she said, &amp;ldquo;Who would have said to Abraham that Sarah would nurse children? Yet I have borne him a son in his old age.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Num 6:2-3 &amp;ldquo;Speak to the people of Israel and say to them, When either a man or a woman makes a special vow, the vow of a Nazirite, to separate himself to the LORD, [3] he shall separate himself from wine and strong drink. He shall drink no vinegar made from wine or strong drink and shall not drink any juice of grapes or eat grapes, fresh or dried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jdg 13:7 but he said to me, &amp;lsquo;Behold, you shall conceive and bear a son. So then drink no wine or strong drink, and eat nothing unclean, for the child shall be a Nazirite to God from the womb to the day of his death.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mal 4:5-6 &amp;ldquo;Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the great and awesome day of the LORD comes. [6] And he will turn the hearts of fathers to their children and the hearts of children to their fathers, lest I come and strike the land with a decree of utter destruction.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This annunciation echos the heavenly birth announcements found in Genesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many will rejoice &amp;ndash; not just the immediate circumstance at the news of Elizabeth&amp;rsquo;s delivery, but also those who repent and follow Jesus because of John&amp;rsquo;s message will celebrate John&amp;rsquo;s birth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No strong drink &amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is called a Nazirite vow from Numbers 6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul underwent a temporary Nazirite vow in Acts 18 (well after his Damascus Road experience, by the way. He REMAINED Jewish after his so-called &amp;ldquo;conversion.&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judges 13:7 states that when a child is to be a Nazirite from birth, there are restrictions placed on the mother as well. Elizabeth observed the Nazirite constraints. The passage references Samson, the most famous (and flawed) Nazirite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-118-20-zechariah-doubts&#34;&gt;Luke 1:18-20 Zechariah Doubts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And Zechariah said to the angel, &amp;ldquo;How shall I know this? For I am an old man, and my wife is advanced in years.&amp;rdquo; And the angel answered him, &amp;ldquo;I am Gabriel. I stand in the presence of God, and I was sent to speak to you and to bring you this good news. And behold, you will be silent and unable to speak until the day that these things take place, because you did not believe my words, which will be fulfilled in their time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The punishment for Zechariah&amp;rsquo;s disbelief seems harsh given that Abraham, Gideon, and even Mary asked similar questions when they received supernatural visions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, his being unable to speak was the sign from Gabriel. Be careful what you wish for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabriel comes from gibor, strong, mighty, warrior, hero, and El, the short name of God. So Gabriel is &amp;ldquo;hero of God,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;mighty man of God.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bible mentions two angels by name (besides The Angel of the Lord, which is a manifestation of God himself (and by extension Jesus preincarnate, since Jesus is God)), Michael and Gabriel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jewish and Catholic tradition adds a few more, notably Raphael and Uriel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One interesting speculation is that Zechariah was inside praying for a son, yet when that prayer was answered, he didn&amp;rsquo;t believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contrasts with Abraham, Gideon, and Mary where the appearance was unsolicited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, he was doubting God&amp;rsquo;s ability to answer his prayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How often are we like this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-121-23&#34;&gt;Luke 1:21-23&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And the people were waiting for Zechariah, and they were wondering at his delay in the temple. And when he came out, he was unable to speak to them, and they realized that he had seen a vision in the temple. And he kept making signs to them and remained mute. And when his time of service was ended, he went to his home.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Priestly Blessing: Numbers 6:24-26 | Bible pictures, Biblical art, Jewish art&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image4_huc79406d463f79a40e8a2a1237c82943a_24173_01d77558588cc5823d7e344f5c061aa6.webp 400w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image4_huc79406d463f79a40e8a2a1237c82943a_24173_e1b7de7c626b9d2eb301ddf2c33473ab.webp 760w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image4_huc79406d463f79a40e8a2a1237c82943a_24173_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image4_huc79406d463f79a40e8a2a1237c82943a_24173_01d77558588cc5823d7e344f5c061aa6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;273&#34;
               height=&#34;320&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Zechariah was inside, another priest outside the holy place ascended the ramp and sacrificed a lamb, and placed it onto the altar fires for the morning offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The priest who lit the incense was to emerge, and raise his hands in the sign of the priesthood (the &amp;ldquo;Spock&amp;rdquo; Vulcan hand gesture, which Lenord Neimoy, an observant Jew, intentionally incorporated into the original Star Trek). He then would give the priestly benediction: &amp;ldquo;the LORD Bless you and keep you; the LORD lift up his countenance on you and grant you shalom.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve got two immediate problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incense priest usually emerged immediately &amp;ndash; did Zechariah&amp;rsquo;s delay mean that the people&amp;rsquo;s prayers were not heard?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he did finally emerge, he was unable to give the benediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aren&amp;rsquo;t told how, but the people finally realized he&amp;rsquo;d seen a vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-124-25&#34;&gt;Luke 1:24-25&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After these days his wife Elizabeth conceived, and for five months she kept herself hidden, saying, &amp;ldquo;Thus the Lord has done for me in the days when he looked on me, to take away my reproach among people.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference passage: Gen 30:23 She conceived and bore a son and said, &amp;ldquo;God has taken away my reproach.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aren&amp;rsquo;t told exactly why she &amp;ldquo;kept herself hidden&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There might have been a custom of isolation during the early stages of pregnancy to guard against both natural and supernatural threats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-126-29-gabriel-visits-mary&#34;&gt;Luke 1:26-29 Gabriel visits Mary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the sixth month the angel Gabriel was sent from God to a city of Galilee named Nazareth, and he came to her and said, &amp;ldquo;Greetings, O favored one, the Lord is with you!&amp;rdquo; But she was greatly troubled at the saying, and tried to discern what sort of greeting this might be.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hail Mary, full of grace&amp;rdquo; is scriptural&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nazareth is about 70 miles north of Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some scholars speculate that the entire town of 200 or so folks might all be from David&amp;rsquo;s line (as Joseph and Mary were) who relocated north at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was nothing notable about Nazareth (except perhaps in a negative sense as used in John 1:46); the major center was Sephorris, which is likely where Joseph and Jesus found carpentry and masonry work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-130-33-the-annunciation&#34;&gt;Luke 1:30-33 The Annunciation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30 And the angel said to her, &amp;ldquo;Do not be afraid, Mary, for you have found favor with God. And behold, you will conceive in your womb and bear a son, and you shall call his name Jesus. He will be great and will be called the Son of the Most High. And the Lord God will give to him the throne of his father David, and he will reign over the house of Jacob forever, and of his kingdom there will be no end.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference verses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isa 7:14 Therefore the Lord himself will give you a sign. Behold, the virgin shall conceive and bear a son, and shall call his name Immanuel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im &amp;ndash; anu &amp;ndash; El = with us God&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hebrew word &lt;em&gt;alma&lt;/em&gt; could mean &amp;ldquo;maiden&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;young woman,&amp;rdquo; and this is a point that many antagonists of Christianity will point out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Old Testament was translated into Greek a couple of centuries before Jesus was born. The Greek word &lt;em&gt;Parthenos&lt;/em&gt; used in Isaiah 7:4 is unmistakably a virgin as we think of the word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the immediate context, this refers to King Ahaz&amp;rsquo;s son Hezekiah, but Christians see a double-fulfillment with Jesus. Often there is an immediate application and then a longer range application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The virgin birth, along with the resurrection are targets for critics who just can&amp;rsquo;t accept the supernatural nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gen 16:11 And the angel of the LORD said to her, &amp;ldquo;Behold, you are pregnant and shall bear a son. You shall call his name Ishmael, because the LORD has listened to your affliction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2Sa 7:9,14 And I have been with you wherever you went and have cut off all your enemies from before you. And I will make for you a great name, like the name of the great ones of the earth&amp;hellip; I will be to him a father, and he shall be to me a son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 2:7 I will tell of the decree: The LORD said to me, &amp;ldquo;You are my Son; today I have begotten you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 132:11 The LORD swore to David a sure oath from which he will not turn back: &amp;ldquo;One of the sons of your body I will set on your throne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2Sa 7:13 He shall build a house for my name, and I will establish the throne of his kingdom forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2Sa 7:16 And your house and your kingdom shall be made sure forever before me. Your throne shall be established forever.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isa 9:7 Of the increase of his government and of peace there will be no end, on the throne of David and over his kingdom, to establish it and to uphold it with justice and with righteousness from this time forth and forevermore. The zeal of the LORD of hosts will do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protestants tend to distance themselves from the Catholic veneration of Mary, but let&amp;rsquo;s not forget Mary was the chosen woman to bear the messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She truly was blessed among all women, so we owe her due credit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scripture does not say that she herself was immaculately conceived, nor does it say that she remained a virgin after Jesus was born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When discussing with people of different faith backgrounds, look for points of commonality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Catholics and Protestants would both agree that Mary is an incredible woman who was used by God, and the primary point of our focus should be on Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-134-38&#34;&gt;Luke 1:34-38&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And Mary said to the angel, &amp;ldquo;How will this be, since I am a virgin?&amp;rdquo; And the angel answered her, &amp;ldquo;The Holy Spirit will come upon you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow you; therefore the child to be born will be called holy&amp;mdash;the Son of God. And behold, your relative Elizabeth in her old age has also conceived a son, and this is the sixth month with her who was called barren. For nothing will be impossible with God.&amp;rdquo; And Mary said, &amp;ldquo;Behold, I am the servant of the Lord; let it be to me according to your word.&amp;rdquo; And the angel departed from her.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing about the Annunciation indicated that the conception would be supernatural, but perhaps Mary suspected or even physically felt something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strictly speaking, Mary was a barren woman just like Sarah and Elizabeth; she just was not advanced in age. Let us not overlook the fact that God, once again, supernaturally opens a closed womb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wonder if, at her young age, she truly realized she was about to become a social outcast and the subject of vicious small-town gossip for supposed illegitimate pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When we get to the &amp;ldquo;Genealogies&amp;rdquo; we&amp;rsquo;re going to study a guy by the name of Jeconiah in Jeremiah 22 and why the virgin birth may be particularly relevant to Jesus being of the &amp;ldquo;house and lineage of David.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Gideon and Zechariah, Mary does not ask for a sign. She just asks, how can these things be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She is given one anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her aged and heretofore barren relative Elizabeth has also conceived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her faithfulness here echos that of Ruth who places herself at the mercy of Naomi and then Boaz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we truly believe that &amp;ldquo;nothing is impossible with God&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-139-41&#34;&gt;Luke 1:39-41&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In those days Mary arose and went with haste into the hill country, to a town in Judah, and she entered the house of Zechariah and greeted Elizabeth. And when Elizabeth heard the greeting of Mary, the baby leaped in her womb. And Elizabeth was filled with the Holy Spirit,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke does not give a specific location for the home of Elizabeth and Zechariah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literary tradition from the 6th century identifies Elizabeth&amp;rsquo;s hometown with Ein Kerem (about 6 miles west of Jerusalem) and the presence of two 4th-century churches indicates that the tradition is even older.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today Ein Kerem has a population of about 2000; it is essentially a suburb of Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-142-45-elizabeths-blessing&#34;&gt;Luke 1:42-45 Elizabeth&amp;rsquo;s Blessing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;and she exclaimed with a loud cry, &amp;ldquo;Blessed are you among women, and blessed is the fruit of your womb! And why is this granted to me that the mother of my Lord should come to me? For behold, when the sound of your greeting came to my ears, the baby in my womb leaped for joy. And blessed is she who believed that there would be a fulfillment of what was spoken to her from the Lord.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-146-55----the-magnificat&#34;&gt;Luke 1:46-55 &amp;ndash; The &lt;em&gt;Magnificat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;C:PLBLsrluke01plusEin Kerem Church of Visitation Mary&amp;amp;rsquo;s Magnificat, tb031004838.jpg&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image5_hue050490ea814d3d429d75c354a8d9eba_242915_0f8bab00ca92ba3a05d9e53af35ba9c4.webp 400w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image5_hue050490ea814d3d429d75c354a8d9eba_242915_dd542efff055dd6ec986871e298e469b.webp 760w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image5_hue050490ea814d3d429d75c354a8d9eba_242915_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image5_hue050490ea814d3d429d75c354a8d9eba_242915_0f8bab00ca92ba3a05d9e53af35ba9c4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;500&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most beautiful expressions of glory and gratitude; it is very Psalm=like. The Holy Spirit was definitely present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The praise is similar to Hannah&amp;rsquo;s song in 1 Samuel 2 and has many allusions and themes from the Hebrew Bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It begins with her personal praise and expands to the hope and promise of the Messianic redemption (the redemption that has its fulfillment in Revelation 19)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;46 And Mary said, &amp;ldquo;My soul magnifies the Lord,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 Sam 2:1 And Hannah prayed and said, &amp;ldquo;My heart exults in the LORD; my horn is exalted in the LORD. My mouth derides my enemies, because I rejoice in your salvation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;47 and my spirit rejoices in God my Savior,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hab 3:18 yet I will rejoice in the LORD; I will take joy in the God of my salvation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word for salvation here is [יִשְׁעִֽי]{dir=&amp;ldquo;rtl&amp;rdquo;} &amp;ndash; Yesuha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;48 for he has looked on the humble estate of his servant. For behold, from now on all generations will call me blessed;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Sam 1:11 &amp;hellip;remember me and not forget your maidservant&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gen 29:32 And Leah conceived and bore a son, and she called his name Reuben, for she said, &amp;ldquo;Because the LORD has looked upon my affliction; for now my husband will love me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gen 30:13 And Leah said, &amp;ldquo;Happy am I! For women have called me happy.&amp;rdquo; So she called his name Asher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;49 for he who is mighty has done great things for me, and holy is his name.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Psa 126:3 The LORD has done great things for us; we are glad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;50 And his mercy is for those who fear him from generation to generation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Psa 103:17 But the steadfast love of the LORD is from everlasting to everlasting on those who fear him, and his righteousness to children&amp;rsquo;s children,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;51 He has shown strength with his arm; He has scattered the proud in the thoughts of their hearts;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 136:12 with a strong hand and an outstretched arm, for his steadfast love endures forever;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 89:13 You have a mighty arm; strong is your hand, high your right hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 89:10 &amp;hellip;you scattered your enemies with your mighty arm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;52 He has brought down the mighty from their thrones and exalted those of humble estate;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1Sa 2:7 The LORD makes poor and makes rich; He brings low and he exalts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 113:7 He raises the poor from the dust and lifts the needy from the ash heap,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;53 He has filled the hungry with good things, and the rich He has sent away empty.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 107:9 For he satisfies the longing soul, and the hungry soul he fills with good things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1Sa 2:5 Those who were full have hired themselves out for bread, but those who were hungry have ceased to hunger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;54 He has helped his servant Israel, in remembrance of His mercy,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isa 41:8 But you, Israel, my servant, Jacob, whom I have chosen, the offspring of Abraham, my friend&amp;hellip;Fear not&amp;hellip; you men of Israel! I am the one who helps you, declares the LORD; your Redeemer is the Holy One of Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 98:3 He has remembered his steadfast love and faithfulness to the house of Israel. All the ends of the earth have seen the salvation of our God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;55 as he spoke to our fathers, to Abraham and to his offspring forever.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exo 32:13 Remember Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, your servants, to whom you swore by your own self, and said to them, &amp;lsquo;I will multiply your offspring as the stars of heaven, and all this land that I have promised I will give to your offspring, and they shall inherit it forever.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mic 7:20 You will show faithfulness to Jacob and steadfast love to Abraham, as you have sworn to our fathers from the days of old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will you notice God is not done with Israel?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passages like this also demonstrate the interconnection between the Old and the New Testament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-156-58&#34;&gt;Luke 1:56-58&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And Mary remained with her about three months and returned to her home. Now the time came for Elizabeth to give birth, and she bore a son. And her neighbors and relatives heard that the Lord had shown great mercy to her, and they rejoiced with her.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-159&#34;&gt;Luke 1:59&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;C:PLBLsrluke01plus2Circumcision ceremony, tb092006640.jpg&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image6_hu4d144ff5f5ed70427a7d8d7e759be025_80489_abb7cd1781f47b7c1b716f1f6f661321.webp 400w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image6_hu4d144ff5f5ed70427a7d8d7e759be025_80489_031e41207667e0de51fb6c6e1af3a759.webp 760w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image6_hu4d144ff5f5ed70427a7d8d7e759be025_80489_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image6_hu4d144ff5f5ed70427a7d8d7e759be025_80489_abb7cd1781f47b7c1b716f1f6f661321.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;508&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And on the eighth day they came to circumcise the child. And they would have called him Zechariah after his father,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genesis 17:12 He who is eight days old among you shall be circumcised. Every male throughout your generations, whether born in your house or bought with your money from any foreigner who is not of your offspring,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lev 12:3 And on the eighth day the flesh of his foreskin shall be circumcised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-160-66-his-name-is-yochanon&#34;&gt;Luke 1:60-66 His name is Yochanon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;but his mother answered, &amp;ldquo;No; he shall be called John.&amp;rdquo; And they said to her, &amp;ldquo;None of your relatives is called by this name.&amp;rdquo; And they made signs to his father, inquiring what he wanted him to be called. And he asked for a writing tablet and wrote, &amp;ldquo;His name is John.&amp;rdquo; And they all wondered. And immediately his mouth was opened and his tongue loosed, and he spoke, blessing God. And fear came on all their neighbors. And all these things were talked about through all the hill country of Judea, and all who heard them laid them up in their hearts, saying, &amp;ldquo;What then will this child be?&amp;rdquo; For the hand of the Lord was with him.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-167&#34;&gt;Luke 1:67&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And his father Zechariah was filled with the Holy Spirit and prophesied, saying,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-168-79-the-benedictus&#34;&gt;Luke 1:68-79 The &lt;em&gt;Benedictus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;68 &amp;ldquo;Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, for he has visited and redeemed his people&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 41:13 Blessed be the LORD, the God of Israel, from everlasting to everlasting! Amen and Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 111:9 He sent redemption to his people; he has commanded his covenant forever. Holy and awesome is his name!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;69 and has raised up a horn of salvation for us in the house of his servant David,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1Sa 2:10 he will give strength to his king and exalt the horn of his anointed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 132:17 There I will make a horn to sprout for David; I have prepared a lamp for my anointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;70 as he spoke by the mouth of his holy prophets from of old,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zec 7:7 Were not these the words that the LORD proclaimed by the former prophets, when Jerusalem was inhabited and prosperous, with her cities around her, and the South and the lowland were inhabited?&#39;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;71 that we should be saved from our enemies and from the hand of all who hate us;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2Sa 22:18 He rescued me from my strong enemy, from those who hated me, for they were too mighty for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;72-73 to show the mercy promised to our fathers and to remember his holy covenant, the oath that he swore to our father Abraham, to grant us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exo 32:13 Remember Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, your servants, to whom you swore by your own self, and said to them, &amp;lsquo;I will multiply your offspring as the stars of heaven, and all this land that I have promised I will give to your offspring, and they shall inherit it forever.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lev 26:42 then I will remember my covenant with Jacob, and I will remember my covenant with Isaac and my covenant with Abraham, and I will remember the land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;74-75 that we, being delivered from the hand of our enemies, might serve him without fear, in holiness and righteousness before him all our days.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2Ki 17:39 but you shall fear the LORD your God, and he will deliver you out of the hand of all your enemies.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;76 And you, child, will be called the prophet of the Most High; for you will go before the Lord to prepare his ways,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isa 40:3 A voice cries: &amp;ldquo;In the wilderness prepare the way of the LORD; make straight in the desert a highway for our God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mal 3:1 &amp;ldquo;Behold, I send my messenger, and he will prepare the way before me. And the Lord whom you seek will suddenly come to his temple; and the messenger of the covenant in whom you delight, behold, he is coming, says the LORD of hosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;77 to give knowledge of salvation to his people in the forgiveness of their sins,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isa 53:11 Out of the anguish of his soul he shall see and be satisfied; by his knowledge shall the righteous one, my servant, make many to be accounted righteous, and he shall bear their iniquities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;78 because of the tender mercy of our God, whereby the sunrise shall visit us from on high&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mal 4:2 But for you who fear my name, the sun of righteousness shall rise with healing in its wings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isa 60:2 For behold, darkness shall cover the earth, and thick darkness the peoples; but the LORD will arise upon you, and his glory will be seen upon you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;79 to give light to those who sit in darkness and in the shadow of death, to guide our feet into the way of peace.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isa 9:2 The people who walked in darkness have seen a great light; those who dwelt in a land of deep darkness, on them has light shone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isa 42:6-7 &amp;ldquo;I am the LORD; I have called you in righteousness; I will take you by the hand and keep you; I will give you as a covenant for the people, a light for the nations, to open the eyes that are blind, to bring out the prisoners from the dungeon, from the prison those who sit in darkness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pro 3:17 Her ways are ways of pleasantness, and all her paths are peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-180&#34;&gt;Luke 1:80&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;80 And the child grew and became strong in spirit, and he was in the wilderness until the day of his public appearance to Israel.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;C:PLBLplbl3star4-804 Judah and the Dead SeaWilderness of Judah-NorthJudean wilderness, tb111603112.jpg&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image7_hu1d52ec6e487dac64b903fa7e206664cc_572566_5b1ef3655d17ec45117df156bee1d06d.webp 400w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image7_hu1d52ec6e487dac64b903fa7e206664cc_572566_2a6a82fb2534bc7dde3fc1f3a7770f70.webp 760w,
               /commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image7_hu1d52ec6e487dac64b903fa7e206664cc_572566_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb02/images/media/image7_hu1d52ec6e487dac64b903fa7e206664cc_572566_5b1ef3655d17ec45117df156bee1d06d.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bolen, Todd. (2012). “Judean Hill Country-North,” in Pictorial Library Vol. 4.: Judah and the Dead Sea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;_____. (2018). “Luke 1,” in Photo Companion to the Bible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keener, Craig S. (1993). The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lancaster, D. Thomas. (2014). “Annunciations,&amp;rdquo; in Chronicles of the Messiah. Boaz Michael, D. Thomas Lancaster, Steven Lancaster, eds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/gabriels_message_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/gabriels_message_1.html&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/annunciation_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/annunciation_1.html&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genealogies</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GENEALOGIES demonstrates to us that Jesus is of the &amp;ldquo;house and lineage&amp;rdquo; of King David. Once, when Jesus was passing through the streets, some blind men called out to Him, “Have mercy on us, Son of David!” Why did they call Him “Son of David”? What does that title mean, and what is Jesus’ relationship to King David? In this chapter we explore the family tree of the Messiah.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#roadmap&#34;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#gospels-snapshot&#34;&gt;Gospels Snapshot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-11&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-12-6--abraham-to-solomon--luke-3138-adam-to-nathan&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:2-6 – Abraham to Solomon &amp;amp; Luke 31:38 Adam to Nathan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#bad-girls-of-the-bible&#34;&gt;Bad Girls of the Bible&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#tamar&#34;&gt;Tamar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rahab&#34;&gt;Rahab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#ruth&#34;&gt;Ruth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#mary&#34;&gt;Mary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-wife-of-uriah-bathsheba&#34;&gt;The wife of Uriah (Bathsheba)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-17-16--solomon-to-jacob--luke-2331-nathan-to-heli&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:7-16 – Solomon to Jacob &amp;amp; Luke 23:31 Nathan to Heli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-deportation-to-babylon&#34;&gt;The deportation to Babylon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#jeconiah&#34;&gt;Jeconiah&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#other-reconciliation-theories&#34;&gt;Other Reconciliation theories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-112-17-jeconiah-to-jesus&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:12-17: Jeconiah to Jesus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-323-30&#34;&gt;Luke 3:23-30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#jeconiah-and-the-blood-curse&#34;&gt;Jeconiah and the blood curse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verse by verse lesson:&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/A0ghMk4_0jg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Women in Matthew&amp;rsquo;s Genealogy Supplement:&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hWzRZfkyTWk&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;roadmap&#34;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different accounts, yet both claim to be THE genealogy of Jesus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew genealogy (through Solomon) - Why 14?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke genealogy (through Nathan)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ενομιζετο – “as it was supposed”/“reckoned by law”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Babylonian deportation (Assyrian diversion)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Blood Curse on Jechoniah and the Royal Line (Jeremiah 22)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other genealogy reconciliation theories&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gospels-snapshot&#34;&gt;Gospels Snapshot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesus as&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jewish Messiah&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Servant of All&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Son of Man&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Son of God&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genealogy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Abraham&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Adam&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Preexistent One&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Jesus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Said&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Did&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Felt&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Who He Was&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Style&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Teachings&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Snapshots&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Narrative&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7 Miracles / 7 ”I AM the…” / 7 Discourses&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Miracle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Leper&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Demon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Demon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Water to Wine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symbol&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lion of Judah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ox&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Man&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eagle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-11&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matthew&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The book of the generations (genealogy) of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Gen 5:1&lt;/sup&gt; This is the book of the generations of Adam. When God created man, he made him in the likeness of God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Son of Abraham = means a Jew. Matthew wants us to know that Jesus is Jewish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Son of David is a clear Messianic title. Matthew wants us to know that Jesus is the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew presents his genealogy in the Hebraic style of Genesis 5:1, which reads “this (is the) book of the generations of Adam” (although it is Luke, not Matthew, who presents us the lineage back to Adam).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genealogies were important legal documents to demonstrate lineage for the purposes of inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically records were kept in the temple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it was destroyed in 70 CE so were most of the records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, ANYONE after 70 CE could claim to be descended from David and there would be no way to prove or disprove it. A few would-be messiahs in history even tried to fabricate their lineage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the claim for Jesus’ lineage was made when it could still have been checked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Gen 17:7&lt;/sup&gt; And I will establish my covenant between me and you and your offspring after you throughout their generations for an everlasting covenant, to be God to you and to your offspring after you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2Sa 7:16&lt;/sup&gt; And your house and your kingdom shall be made sure forever before me. Your throne shall be established forever.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a candidate for Messiah is not a descendant from David AND Abraham, he is to be rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God made eternal and unconditional covenants with both Abraham and David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 1:1 is the most important verse of the chapter as it establishes Jesus in both David’s line and Abraham’s line (with the remainder of the genealogy used to support the assertion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:2.60856in;height:1.95614in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Deu 17:15&lt;/sup&gt; you may indeed set a king over you whom the LORD your God will choose. &lt;strong&gt;One from among your brothers you shall set as king over you. You may not put a foreigner over you, who is not your brother&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any king, including, and especially the Messiah had to be Jewish by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have an interesting Juxtaposition between Jesus, the rightful king, and King Herod, the presently reigning king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dichotomy is accented by geography. Above is a picture of Herod’s palace called Herodium (of course he named it after himself). Herodium is about 3 miles from Bethlehem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To varying degrees, all of the gospels portray Jesus the rightful king, messiah, and Son battling against the usurping forces, be they Herod, the political/religious establishment or the forces of spiritual darkness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herod, was NOT BORN King of the Jews, in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. He’s wasn’t Jewish by birth. He was an Idumean, which is to say an edomite, descended from Esau not Jacob. If you know anything about the history, the Edomites and the Israelites didn’t get along at all. During the period of the Maccabees, Herod’s family was forced to convert. Forced conversions, whether done by the greeks under Antiochus IV, the Jews under the Maccabeans, or the Christians and Muslims in later years, never seem to work out very well for both the converted and those forcing the conversions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. He therefore was not qualified to be King. In fact, he approached the Roman Senate to grant him that title, which they did in 39 BC. And in an irony of History, Rome didn’t even control the area at the time. The Parthians did. Herod pushed them out and secured the area for Rome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adds some possible intrigue to &lt;sup&gt;Mat 2:1-2&lt;/sup&gt; Now after Jesus was born in Bethlehem of Judea in the days of Herod the king, behold, wise men from the east came to Jerusalem, [2] saying, “Where is he who has been &lt;strong&gt;born king of the Jews&lt;/strong&gt;? For we saw his star when it rose and have come to worship him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Magi approach Herod and ask, “where is he who has been BORN KING OF THE JEWS?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chuck Missler sees this as an intentional dig at Herod. In other words, “Not you, turkey. Where’s the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; king of the Jews?” Which of course sends Herod off in a fit of rage and we know from Matthew 2:4-5, Herod inquired of the birthplace of Messiah and was told it would be in Bethlehem. Eventually, he orders the execution of all males 2 years and younger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, before this episode, the Talmud records that Herod once approached his leaders for the qualifications of a Jewish leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Sanhedrin explained Deuteronomy 17:15 to Herod, telling him that one must be naturally born Jewish, Herod naturally, was not pleased with the explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He ordered the execution of all of the Sanhedrin except one (b. Bava Batra 3b), which tells you all about Herod. “don’t shoot the messenger” was not in his vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster notes that Herod then sought to destroy all such records and people of the Davidic Royal line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This likely forced any direct descendant of David to flee from Bethlehem, just a stone’s throw away from Herod’s palace at Herodium, to the relative obscurity in Nazareth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far from being a boring list of names, the fact that Matthew’s genealogy is preserved may be the first recorded miracle in his gospel!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image2.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.32569in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 1:1 establishes Jesus in David’s line and also in Abraham’s line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;אדם  &lt;/span&gt;= Abraham, David, Messiah according to the sages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-12-6--abraham-to-solomon--luke-3138-adam-to-nathan&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:2-6 – Abraham to Solomon &amp;amp; Luke 31:38 Adam to Nathan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew 1:2-6 ↓&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke 3:38-31 ↑&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, Judah and his brothers, Perez and Zerah by Tamar, Hezron, Ram, Amminadab, Nahshon, Salmon, Boaz by Rahab, Obed by Ruth, Jesse, David the king. And David was the father of &lt;strong&gt;Solomon&lt;/strong&gt; by the wife of Uriah…&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Adam the Son of God, Seth, Enosh, Cainan, Mahalalel, Jared, Enoch, Methuseleh, Lamech, Noah, Shem, Arphaxhad, &lt;em&gt;Cainan&lt;/em&gt;, Shelah, Eber, Peleg, Reu, Serug, Nahor, Terah, Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, Judah, Perez, Hezron, &lt;em&gt;Arni, Admin&lt;/em&gt;, Amminadab, Nashon, Sala, Boaz, Obed, Jesse, David, &lt;strong&gt;Nathan&lt;/strong&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is very much like an Old Testament genealogy that runs from oldest to newest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke follows the style of a Greco-Roman ancestry that runs from newest to oldest – Luke’s order is flipped above to make comparisons easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is interested in presenting Jesus as the Jewish Messiah, so his genealogy goes back to Abraham the first Jew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke is interested in presenting us the ancestry of the son of Man, so he’s going to go all the way back to Adam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to Abraham, EVERYONE was a “gentile” (if you’ll pardon the anachronism).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke, which was widely circulated in Gentile regions, wanted gentiles to know Jesus is their Messiah too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he stresses in Luke Volume II (the book we know as Acts), he wants us to know Gentiles are included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam to Noah is the same list as Genesis 5, and Shem to Terah, is roughly the same list as Genesis 11:10-25 (see discussion on potential discrepancies below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Gospels are basically the same from Abraham to David (see potential discrepancies).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will touch on the women in Matthew’s gospel in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potential discrepancies in this section:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew omits some names in this section and omits a LOT of names in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener notes this is not unusual for ancient genealogies, and we may have an element of the Holy Spirit blotting out certain names from the record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew conspicuously skips three kings of Judah: Ahaziah, Joash, and Amaziah (compare 1 Chronicles 3:10-16).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was interested in preserving 14 generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke inserts someone named “Cainan” inbetween Arphaxhad and Shelah in Abraham’s line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cainan is not mentioned in Genesis 11l&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this is the identical name to the Cainan in Noah’s line, this is possibly a copyist’s error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note this is why we say the Bible is inerrant &lt;strong&gt;in the original manuscripts&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several known copyist errors, most notably in John 5:3-4;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These do not detract from the overall inerrancy of Scripture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke inserts Arni and Admin, which are not included in the Old Testament accounts of David’s lineage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arni is potentially a variant spelling of Ram, we don’t know where Admin came from. Perhaps it’s an &lt;em&gt;admin&lt;/em&gt;istrative error.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big thing to note is that Matthew’s list runs through Solomon, the first surviving son of David and the wife of Uriah, while Luke’s runs through Nathan, the second surviving son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note also that Bathsheba is referred to only indirectly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In fact, she is never named in the Bible after she dies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nothing is accidental in the Bible. The Holy Spirit engineers and orchestrates every letter. For her not to be named is a “dis” from the Holy Spirit!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Far from being an innocent victim, perhaps she was the instigator of the entire episode. She did seem to relish her position as Queen Mother in 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Kings 2.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In contrast, Rahab repented, Tamar was declared righteous by Judah himself, and if you know anything about Ruth and Boaz, there was nothing inappropriate about their relationship.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bad-girls-of-the-bible&#34;&gt;Bad Girls of the Bible&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was highly unusual for an ancient genealogy to include women&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All five women listed, including Mary in verse 16, were tainted by scandal (real or suspected).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster posits that by including the first four women, Matthew sought to make any scandal regarding Mary irrelevant to Jesus’ claim to be the Messiah. The ancients held a much wider view of “mother” and “father” than we do today, so if David had a few less than reputable “mothers” in his line and is still regarded as the greatest King of Israel, how much more should Jesus be regarded as one greater than David even though there are some questions regarding His lineage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tamar&#34;&gt;Tamar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tamar relies on the Levirate Marriage law: &lt;sup&gt;Deu 25:5-6&lt;/sup&gt; If brothers dwell together, and one of them dies and has no son, the wife of the dead man shall not be married outside the family to a stranger. Her husband&amp;rsquo;s brother shall go in to her and take her as his wife and perform the duty of a husband&amp;rsquo;s brother to her. And the first son whom she bears shall succeed to the name of his dead brother, that his name may not be blotted out of Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tamar was the daughter in law of Judah. We can read the complete story in Genesis 38.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She married one of Judah’s sons a guy by the name of Er, but he was wicked and was struck down by the LORD before they had children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In accordance with the law of the Levirate marriage, Judah was REQUIRED to have Tamar marry the next available male, Onan, to marry Tamar and have a child in the name of the deceased son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judah did this but THAT son was also wicked and was struck down (a very R-rated story- the Bible tells it like it is).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re getting an idea that maybe Judah was a less than stellar father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judah had a third son, Shelah, but Judah feared He would die along the others, as if it was Tamar who was the bad news causing this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judah promised to give Shelah to Tamar but told her to wait until he was older.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Judah was likely hoping Tamar would go off and find someone else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember this is now the Royal line of Judah that is at stake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tamar realizes Judah is going to renege on his word so she takes matters into her own hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She KNOWS that Judah’s line must continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She dresses up as a harlot and entices none other than Judah, her father-in-law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judah doesn’t have cash on hand so he leaves his staff, cord and signet ring as a down payment. The next day he goes to collect but Tamar has vanished. He asks around but is told “there is no harlot here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three months later Tamar is showing. When Judah learns of it, he is incensed at the shame she has brough on the family (seriously?) and orders her burned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Gen 38:24-26&lt;/sup&gt; About three months later Judah was told, “Tamar your daughter-in-law has been immoral. Moreover, she is pregnant by immorality.” And Judah said, “Bring her out, and let her be burned.” As she was being brought out, she sent word to her father-in-law, “By the man to whom these belong, I am pregnant.” And she said, “Please identify whose these are, the signet and the cord and the staff.” Then Judah identified them and said, “She is more righteous than I, since I did not give her to my son Shelah.” And he did not know her again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He says “She is more righteous than I.” which is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tamar is untimately proclaimed righteous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She thwarted the attack on the Royal Line and had twins, Perez and Zerah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see how these seemingly obscure laws in the Torah like the Law of the Levirate Marriage are actually critical to the Lines of David and Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another interesting tidbit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Deu 23:2&lt;/sup&gt; “No one born of a forbidden union may enter the assembly of the LORD. Even to the tenth generation, none of his descendants may enter the assembly of the LORD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being “righteous” it was still a forbidden union according to the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God apparently means what He says when He says “10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; generation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perez by Tamar, Hezron, Ram, Amminadab, Nahshon, Salmon, Boaz, Obed, Jesse, David – 10 Generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rahab&#34;&gt;Rahab&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Jos 2:12-13&lt;/sup&gt; Now then, please swear to me by the LORD that, as I have dealt kindly with you, you also will deal kindly with my father&amp;rsquo;s house, and give me a sure sign that you will save alive my father and mother, my brothers and sisters, and all who belong to them, and deliver our lives from death.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rahab was an actual harlot in Jericho who ends up protecting Joshua’s men in exchange for protection. You can read the story in Joshua 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tradition holds that she repented and found grace and mercy by following the God of Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can’t say that Grace and Mercy are New Testament concepts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She is lauded in the Hebrews 11 Hall of faith:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Heb 11:31** **&lt;/sup&gt;By faith Rahab the prostitute did not perish with those who were disobedient, because she had given a friendly welcome to the spies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ruth&#34;&gt;Ruth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruth relies on the Kinsman Redeemer Law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Lev 25:25&lt;/sup&gt; “If your brother becomes poor and sells part of his property, then his nearest redeemer shall come and redeem what his brother has sold.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the passage that causes many to associate Ruth with scandal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Rth 3:7-9&lt;/sup&gt; And when Boaz had eaten and drunk, and his heart was merry, he went to lie down at the end of the heap of grain. Then she came softly and uncovered his feet and lay down. At midnight the man was startled and turned over, and behold, a woman lay at his feet! He said, “Who are you?” And she answered, “I am Ruth, your servant (handmaid). Spread your wings over your servant, for you are a redeemer.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you know anything about Ruth and Boaz, you know it was unlikely there was any mischief before marriage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Ruth 3, she “uncovers his feet”, which to be fair, in the Bible is often a euphemism for other things and then asks him to “spread your wing or hem/skirt over me (same wing and hem/corner are the same word in Hebrew). Her request was scandalous but not for the reason you may be thinking. As chuck Missler says, “she wasn’t propositioning him, it’s far worse than that. She was asking for his protection. In other words, she was asking him to make good on his duty to be a kinsman redeemer – another Old Testament law that turns out to be critically important to Jesus’ lineage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scandal part is that Moabites were the sworn enemies of Israel and Boaz was forbidden by law from marrying ruth, but he must make an exception (and I suspect he did so gladly) because of the overriding law of the Kinsman redeemer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that is important to know about the application of Jewish law. Whenever there is a negative commandment that conflicts with a positive one, the positive one wins out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is going to make use of this guideline frequently, particularly with the so-called Sabbath controversies. He’s not overriding the law; he’s following the law strictly and perfectly, much more perfectly than the prevailing attitudes of the day were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case the law said an Israelite was forbidden from marrying a moabitie but the positive command required the nearer kinsman to redeem.Ruth who earlier made the famous proclamation of “where you go I will go, and where you lodge I will lodge. Your people shall be my people, and your God my God.” (Ruth 1:16) now says “I am your servant or some translations say handmaid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Luk 1:38&lt;/sup&gt; And Mary said, “Behold, I am the servant (handmaid) of the Lord; let it be to me according to your word.” And the angel departed from her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mary’s words in Luke 1:38 echo ruth’s faithfulness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in Biblical typology Boaz is a type of Jesus and Ruth, a gentile is a picture of us, the gentile church. We are helpless and poor without our Redeemer. With Jesus we are royalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mary&#34;&gt;Mary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve talked and will talk a lot more about her righteousness but this doesn’t keep detractors from raising the appearance of scandal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Joseph appears initially ready to believe the scandal (not without reason of course)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Mat 1:18-19&lt;/sup&gt; Now the birth of Jesus Christ took place in this way. When his mother Mary had been betrothed to Joseph, before they came together she was found to be with child from the Holy Spirit. [19] And her husband Joseph, being a just man and &lt;strong&gt;unwilling to put her to shame, resolved to divorce her quietly&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that Jesus’ questionable lineage was used by His detractors in John 8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Joh 8:18-19&lt;/sup&gt; I am the one who bears witness about myself, and the Father who sent me bears witness about me.” [19] They said to him therefore, &lt;strong&gt;“Where is your Father?”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although I just said to give others the benefit of the doubt, we can tell by the context of the passage that they are being absolutely nasty here!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The psalms appear to speak of Jesus’ childhood struggles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Psa 69:8-12&lt;/sup&gt; I have become a &lt;strong&gt;stranger to my brothers, an alien to my mother&amp;rsquo;s sons&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;For zeal for your house has consumed me&lt;/em&gt;, and the reproaches of those who reproach you have fallen on me. When I wept and humbled my soul with fasting, it became my reproach. When I made sackcloth my clothing, I became a byword to them. &lt;strong&gt;I am the talk of those who sit in the gate, and the drunkards make songs about me&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s hard to imagine growing up and having Jesus as a half-brother. I’m sure James, Jude and the others were none too thrilled at being told “why can’t you be more like Yeshua?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-wife-of-uriah-bathsheba&#34;&gt;The wife of Uriah (Bathsheba)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:3.77014in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a familiar story but 2 Samuel 11 says it was the time when the Kings should have been on the battlefield but David stayed back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He eyes Bathsheba bathing and the rest as they say his history&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2Sa 11:4-5&lt;/sup&gt; So David sent messengers and took her, and she came to him, and he lay with her. (Now she had been purifying herself from her uncleanness.) Then she returned to her house. And the woman conceived, and she sent and told David, “I am pregnant.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He next tries to cover up by having Uriah lay with his wife, which he refused to do&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The army (again, where David SHOULD have been) was supposed to be in a state of ritual purity, specifically abstaining from marital relations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David then has Uriah eliminated so he can openly marry his wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a great example of the difference between the “vertical” and the “horizontal” realms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the vertical- our relationship with God– David repented and was forgiven. In acts 13, David is still referred to as a man after God’s own heart and Psalm 51 is a beautiful expression of repentence and forgiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horizontally – our relationship with others - there are still consequences when we sin. This episode resulted in David’s family life becoming an absolute train-wreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture above is inside the same archaeological park we talked about with David’s harp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists think David’s palace was at the top, and you can see how steep the incline is with the houses below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would have been quite easy for the king to walk out and look down into the houses below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some speculation as to whether this was a sexual assault by David. I tend not to see this and we get a clue why in Matthew 1:6. Notice Bathsheba is not named.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact she is NEVER named in the Bible after she dies, and only once during the episode in question is she named as “Bathsheba”, otherwise it’s the “wife of Uriah” or some other pronoun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some scholars see this as a “dis” from the Holy Spirit which to me suggests she knew exactly what she was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew continues this trend of not uttering her name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the other four women who are named either engaged in or had the appearance of scandal only without doing anything wrong. The contrast suggests to some commentators that Bathsheba never repented of her role in all of the drama. That is a speculation but we can see in 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Kings 2, Bathsheba seems to relish her power and position as the Queen Mother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet through it all, God orchestrated the messianic line through the sons of David and Bathsheba.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-17-16--solomon-to-jacob--luke-2331-nathan-to-heli&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:7-16 – Solomon to Jacob &amp;amp; Luke 23:31 Nathan to Heli&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 44%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 55%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew 1:7:16 ↓&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke 1:31-23 ↑&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solomon&lt;/strong&gt;, Rehoboam, Abijah, Asa, Jehoshaphat, Jehoram, Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, Hezekiah, Manasseh, Amon, Josiah, Jeconiah (&lt;em&gt;Jehoiakim&lt;/em&gt;?) at the time of the deportation to Babylon. After the deportation, Jeconiah, Shealtiel, Zerubbabel, Abiud, Eliakim, Azor, Zadok, Achim, Eliud, Eleazar, Matthan, &lt;strong&gt;Jacob&lt;/strong&gt; the father of Joseph the &lt;strong&gt;husband&lt;/strong&gt; of Mary, of whom Jesus was born, who is called Messiah.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nathan&lt;/strong&gt;, Mattatha, Menan, Melea, Eliakim, Jonam, Joseph, Judah, Simeon, Levi, Matthat, Jorim, Eliezer, Jose, Er, Elmodam, Cosam, Addi, Melchi, Neri, Salathiel, Zorobabel, Rhesa, Joannan, Juda, Joseph, Semei, Mattathias, Maath, Nagge, Esli, Naum, Amos, Mattathias, Joseph, Jannai, Melchi, Levi, Matthat, &lt;strong&gt;Heli&lt;/strong&gt;, Joseph, (ενομιζετο – &lt;strong&gt;so it was thought&lt;/strong&gt;/reckoned by law), Jesus, when He began his ministry was about 30 years of age&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;↓ &lt;sup&gt;Luke 3:23&lt;/sup&gt; Jesus, when he began his ministry, was about thirty years of age, being &lt;del&gt;the&lt;/del&gt; son (as was supposed) of Joseph, the son of Heli…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew goes from Solomon through Jacob&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He clearly says Joseph is the husband of Mary of whom Jesus was born; he does not say Joseph is the father of Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke goes from Nathan through Heli&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In everyday language, the fact that Luke adds, “as was supposed” implies that Jesus is not actually the son of Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the original Greek, there is no “the” before “son (supposed) of Joseph”, which further distinguishes Joseph from Jesus’ direct ancestors. “By the omission of the article, Joseph’s name is separated from the genealogical chain and accorded a place of its own” (&lt;em&gt;Rienecker&lt;/em&gt; as cited in Stern’s commentary).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Missler and other commentators see far more going on with the word ενομιζετο, which has as its root &lt;em&gt;nomos&lt;/em&gt;, meaning “law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They speculate that there was a legal adoption (relying completely on the Torah’s rulings) of Jesus by Joseph which gives Jesus claim to the Davidic line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other potential discrepancies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall Luke has 76 names while Matthew has 41 names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew omits Ahaziah, Joash and Amaziah (compare 1 Chronicles 3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thought is they were so bad they were blotted out according to Deuteronomy 29:20 -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deu 29:20 The LORD will not be willing to forgive him, and the LORD will blot out his name from under heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, Keener notes that omitting some names is not unexpected with ancient genealogies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said before, of all the Gospel writers Luke is the one most interested in chronology. Matthew is more interested in symbolism and the number 14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew’s math doesn’t add up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t get from 586, the main deportation to Babylon and the destruction of Jerusalm to 5 BC and the birth of Jesus with only 14 generations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew lists Jeconiah twice and counts him in both groups of 14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Missler suggests a copyists error with the second Jeconiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last two kings before the deportation were Jehoakim, the direct descendant of Josiah and Jehoiachin, called Jeconiah or Coniah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke and Matthew apparently have some overlap in the lines with Shealtiel and Zerubabbel or it could be just a coincidence with the same names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-deportation-to-babylon&#34;&gt;The deportation to Babylon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image4.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:3.92857in;height:2.84318in&#34; alt=&#34;C:\Pictorial Library of Bible Lands\Israel Museums\Tower of David Museum, Jerusalem\Babylonian exile imaginative depiction, tb042403502.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Babylon” is a recurring theme in the Bible, particularly the Babylonian destruction of Jerusalem in 586 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern mural depicts Israel’s deportation to Babylon. The words in the upper right say “Galut Bavel,” Exile (to) Babylon&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to place ourselves in the shoes of the Jews of that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve been promised that you’re God’s people through the Mosaic Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve been promised the land forever through the Abrahamic Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve been promised that David’s throne will endure forever through the Davidic Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerusalem was thought to be impregnable, particularly after the Assyrians failed (2 Kings 19:31-36).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet all that is lost on the 9&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of Av in -586.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had God’s promises failed? Maybe He’s not really all-powerful or all-good. Maybe we sinned. bad that we’re now beyond His reach. Maybe we misread the promises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the question many ask today in the face of tragedy or evil is, “How could a good God let this happen?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then what do you do next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sing the blues (Lamentations)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn your back on God&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reinvent/reapply/spiritualize the Bible passages pertaining to the promises&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fall on your knees in repentance and draw near to God&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we do today, the people back then did all those things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as Gettysburg, Pearl Harbor, the JFK assassination, or 9/11 is are those critical moments in history for Americans, the Babylonian captivity is such a moment for Jews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And a few years later in 70 CE, another such moment will occur: the Roman destruction of Jerusalem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;jeconiah&#34;&gt;Jeconiah&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew includes Jeconiah in the Royal Line of Messiah, but there’s a big problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jeremiah 22, God is so fed up with Jeconiah, he puts a curse on him AND his offspring, saying no offspring of his will ever rule in Judah&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet Jeconiah is in the Line of Jesus. So how can Jesus rule as King Messiah if that very same Royal Line is cursed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Chuck Missler says, we can imagine Satan and his demons rejoicing in the halls of hell – they finally polluted the royal line and prevented Messiah. All those attacks on the royal line from Adam and Eve, to Cain and Abel, to Judah and Tamar to David and Bathsheba, to the countless other times Satan tried to wipe out the line, finally worked! We’ve finally prevented the Messiah from ruling!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we need to imagine God turning to the Angels and saying “Watch what I do next!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the fine print! No OFFSPRING of Jeconiah’s shall sit on the Throne of David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image5.png&#34; style=&#34;width:3.95053in;height:3.9826in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s put this all together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we note that this is only a speculation, but it’s the one that appears to be held by most (but not all) Protestant commentators, though it’s not without its complications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion is Matthew is presenting Joseph’s Genealogy and Luke is giving us Mary’s line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presents Jesus as the Jewish King/Messiah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genealogy begins with Abraham, the father of the Jewish people,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;presents the Legal/Royal Line through Joseph&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his gospel, Matthew focuses much more on Joseph than on Mary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THE VIRGIN BIRTH directly circumvents the blood curse on Jeconiah, yet through an adoption procedure (hinted at by the word enomiZETo), Jesus has every right to David’s Royal Line JUST AS IF he were Joseph’s natural son&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the “HOUSE OF DAVID”, the Royal line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the virgin birth also avoids the original sin that happens anytime a human x and a human y chromosome merge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presents Jesus as the perfect man/last Adam/savior of all humanity,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genealogy begins with Adam, the first man,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;enomiZETO suggests Joseph adopted Jesus (or potentially some other similar adoption leveraging either the Daughters of Zelophehad (Numbers 27) or the Levirate Marriage (Deut 25) rulings in the Torah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presents the Blood line through Mary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his gospel, Luke focuses much more on Mary than on Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the LINEAGE OF DAVID, the blood line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Joseph is both of the House and Lineage of David (Luke 2:4), he contains the curse of Jeconiah and can never rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is also both of the House and Lineage of David, but He does NOT contain the curse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why the Virgin Birth is more than a simple sign of the Messiah, it is critical to Jesus’ claim to be the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-reconciliation-theories&#34;&gt;Other Reconciliation theories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as Stern points out “The Genealogies of both Matthew and Luke employ unusual language in connection with Yeshua/Jesus and with good reason. Both assert Yeshua had no human father in the ordinary sense of the word but that the virgin Mary was caused to bear Him by the holy spirit in a supernatural way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other suggestions over the years (some with very strong traditional support) include the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jewish tradition holds that Jeconiah repented so the need to circumvent the blood curse is null and void.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commentaries note that Jeconiah was NOT “Childless” as the Bible records his offspring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a counter-argument, we would say that none of those children reigned as KING of Judah. Some were lower-level administrators of the region but that’s not the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, the line of David continued, but his descendants no longer possessed the throne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is Mary’s line by birth through Solomon and Luke is Joseph’s through Nathan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew directly mentions Mary and the other women, while Luke does not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph’s father Jacob died, and Heli was his adopted father prior to Mary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heli died and his widow remarried Jacob&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew and Luke recorded the same genealogy differently because they had different sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes either Matthew or Luke in error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This commentator would reject that premise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The skeptic would say, “See? The Bible is full of contradictions and can’t be trusted.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our opinion this is an intellectually dishonest answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless a witness gives us a reason to think they are lying or delusional, we give them the benefit of the doubt that what they are recounting is the truth as they see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOWEVER God choose to authenticate Jesus’ claim to be the Messiah, we’re very thankful He did!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Heb 11:6&lt;/sup&gt; And without faith it is impossible to please him, for whoever would draw near to God must believe that he exists and that &lt;strong&gt;He rewards those who (diligently) seek Him.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Tit 3:9&lt;/sup&gt; But &lt;strong&gt;avoid foolish controversies, genealogies&lt;/strong&gt;, dissensions, and quarrels about the law, for they are &lt;strong&gt;unprofitable and worthless&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us strive to be diligent seekers but not engage in foolish and worthless controversies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-112-17-jeconiah-to-jesus&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:12-17: Jeconiah to Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And after the deportation to Babylon: Jechoniah was the father of Shealtiel, and Shealtiel the father of Zerubbabel, and Zerubbabel the father of Abiud, and Abiud the father of Eliakim, and Eliakim the father of Azor, and Azor the father of Zadok, and Zadok the father of Achim, and Achim the father of Eliud, and Eliud the father of Eleazar, and Eleazar the father of Matthan, and Matthan the father of Jacob, and Jacob the father of Joseph the husband of Mary, of whom Jesus was born, who is called Christ. . all the generations from Abraham to David were fourteen generations, and from David to the deportation to Babylon fourteen generations, and from the deportation to Babylon to the Christ fourteen generations.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a problem with Jeconiah, which we’ll discuss after we look at Luke’s genealogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew demonstrates that the line of David continued through Jesus even though David’s descendants no longer possessed the throne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The math doesn’t work – you can’t get 14 generations from -586 to -5, the time of Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more puzzling is Matthew has to count Jeconiah twice to get 14 from David to Babylon and also from Babylon to Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous theories have emerged such as counting Joseph and Mary separately, but these are all speculation and not really pertinent to our purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is more interested in the pattern of 14, which someone with a Hebraic mindset would have noticed right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hebrew spelling of David adds up to 14:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;ד&lt;/span&gt; = D = 4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;ו&lt;/span&gt; = V = 6&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;ד&lt;/span&gt; = D = 4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4+6+4 = 14&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another prominent theory is based on the moon phases and their connection to the House of David:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 89:35-37 Once for all I have sworn by my holiness; I will not lie to David. His offspring shall endure forever, his throne as long as the sun before me. &lt;strong&gt;Like the moon, it shall be established forever, a faithful witness in the skies&lt;/strong&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aaron Eby speculates that the original audience would have noted the roughly 14 days from New Moon to Full Moon, darkness to light (Abraham to David) and then the roughly 14 days from Full Moon to New Moon, light to darkness (David to Jeconiah and the deportation), with the dark to light pattern repeated from Jeconiah to Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is clearly establishing a link to David and that Yeshua is the rightful descendant of David’s royal line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-323-30&#34;&gt;Luke 3:23-30&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesus, when he began his ministry, was about thirty years of age, being the son (as was supposed) of Joseph, the son of Heli, the son of Matthat, the son of Levi, the son of Melchi, the son of Jannai, the son of Joseph, the son of Mattathias, the son of Amos, the son of Nahum, the son of Esli, the son of Naggai, the son of Maath, the son of Mattathias, the son of Semein, the son of Josech, the son of Joda, the son of Joanan, the son of Rhesa, the son of Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, the son of Neri, the son of Melchi, the son of Addi, the son of Cosam, the son of Elmadam, the son of Er, the son of Joshua, the son of Eliezer, the son of Jorim, the son of Matthat, the son of Levi, the son of Simeon, the son of Judah, the son of Joseph, the son of Jonam, the son of Eliakim, the son of Melea, the son of Menna, the son of Mattatha,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greek genealogies were often reverse chronological&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phrase “as was supposed” has puzzled scholars&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Greek word is a variation of nomitzo, which can mean “reckoned as by law” (&lt;em&gt;nomos&lt;/em&gt; = law).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One theory is that Luke is communicating Jesus is not the natural son of Joseph but an adopted son, just like adoptive parents go through a legal process today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we would call Eli the “father in law” of Joseph, but that type of terminology likely didn’t exist in 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century Judaism. According to this interpretation, Eli is Mary’s father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus a common interpretation is that Matthew is giving us the &lt;strong&gt;royal&lt;/strong&gt; line of Jesus through David and Solomon, while Luke is giving us the &lt;strong&gt;blood&lt;/strong&gt; line of Jesus through David and Nathan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus can be said that Jesus is of the house** (royal) and &lt;strong&gt;lineage&lt;/strong&gt; (blood) of David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does this matter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about Jeconiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;jeconiah-and-the-blood-curse&#34;&gt;Jeconiah and the blood curse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jer 22:24-30 “As I live, declares the LORD, though Coniah (i.e. Jeconiah) the son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, were the signet ring on my right hand, yet I would tear you off [25] and give you into the hand of those who seek your life, into the hand of those of whom you are afraid, even into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon and into the hand of the Chaldeans. [26] I will hurl you and the mother who bore you into another country, where you were not born, and there you shall die. [27] But to the land to which they will long to return, there they shall not return.” [28] Is this man Coniah a despised, broken pot, a vessel no one cares for? Why are he and his children hurled and cast into a land that they do not know? [29] O land, land, land, hear the word of the LORD! [30] Thus says the LORD: “Write this man down as childless, a man who shall not succeed in his days, for none of his offspring shall succeed in sitting on the throne of David and ruling again in Judah.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the promise made to David, Jeconiah was apparently so evil that God pronounced a curse on his line in verse 30: “none of his offspring shall succeed in sitting on the throne of David and ruling again in Judah.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have a problem. The Messiah is supposed to come from David’s royal line yet God just pronounced a blood curse on that line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can imagine Satan and his demons rejoicing, thinking God boxed Himself into a corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we can imagine God saying, “watch what I do next!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leading conjecture is that Matthew establishes Joseph as the &lt;strong&gt;legal father&lt;/strong&gt; through his marriage to Mary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, Jesus is legally entitled to be in David’s Royal line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because Jesus is not Joseph’s biological son, Jesus does not carry the blood curse of Jeconiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke establishes Jesus as being from the non-cursed blood line to David through Nathan and Mary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In other words, The ONLY way around the curse is through a virgin birth and adoption.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that doesn’t make you go “wow” you’ve either heard the story before, or you weren’t paying attention!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other conjectures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some scholars reverse this and say Matthew is Mary’s and Luke’s is Joseph. If so, a problem is that Mary is in Jeconiah’s line and would carry the blood curse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jewish tradition holds that Jeconiah repented and God accepted his contrition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus it is later written that Jeconiah had offspring who ruled Judea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The counter argument to this is they were local govenors of Judah under Persian rule, they were not monarchs. &lt;em&gt;The line of David may have continued, continued but his descendants no longer possessed the throne.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/son_of_david_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/son_of_david_1.html&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo tb042403502&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nativity</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb04/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In NATIVITY, Mary leaves Ein Karem in the hills of Judea and returns to Nazareth in Galilee. She will take this path many times to travel back and forth to Jerusalem. We journey with Mary as she ponders the great miracle she carries and how the revelation of it will practically affect her relationships. Joseph learns a lesson about how the light of Messiah can shine unexpectedly out of personal disappointments.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Then, we join the magi from the east bearing gifts and tribute for a newborn king. We visit Herod’s palace in Jerusalem, but the King of the Jews is not there. Instead, we find Him still in Bethlehem with His mother and father, and the star that led us hence appears again. Fleeing from Herod, Joseph takes the family to Alexandria, Egypt, where they remain hidden until the death of the tyrant.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-118-19-marys-condition-and-josephs-dilemma&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:18-19 Mary&amp;rsquo;s Condition and Joseph&amp;rsquo;s Dilemma&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-120-21-josephs-course-correction&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:20-21 Joseph&amp;rsquo;s Course Correction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-122-23-jesus-fulfills-isaiah-714&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:22-23 Jesus Fulfills Isaiah 7:14&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#answering-common-challenges-to-matthew-123&#34;&gt;Answering Common Challenges to Matthew 1:23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-124-25-josephs-revised-decision&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:24-25 Joseph&amp;rsquo;s Revised Decision&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 1:18-25:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JjSlTTnqKKg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke 2:1-38 (coming soon!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-118-19-marys-condition-and-josephs-dilemma&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:18-19 Mary&amp;rsquo;s Condition and Joseph&amp;rsquo;s Dilemma&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matthew 1:18&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Now the birth of Jesus Christ took place in this way. When his mother Mary had been betrothed to Joseph, before they came together, she was found to be with child from the Holy Spirit&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Heb 7:26&lt;/sup&gt; For it was indeed fitting that we should have such a high priest, holy, innocent, unstained, separated from sinners, and exalted above the heavens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Gen 3:15&lt;/sup&gt; I will put enmity between you and the woman, and between your seed and her seed; he shall bruise your head, and you shall bruise his heel.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until now, miraculous births in the Bible still required a male/female union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greek traditions (as well as Genesis 6) speak of gods impregnating women but nothing about the text indicates Mary’s conception was in any way sexual.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God spoke the universe into existence. He created Eve from Adam’s rib.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He could have achieved Mary’s pregnancy by speaking it or any number of other “contactless” ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a minimum, The Virgin Birth removes the stain of sin (often called original sin) that occurs whenever a human x and human y chromosome merge. Hebrews 7 reminds us that Jesus is “holy, innocent, unstained and separated from sinners.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another tidbit about the Virgin Birth. In Genesis 3:15 God says to the serpent, “I will put enmity between your seed and HER seed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “seed of the woman” is one of the many names of the Jewish Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a seemingly biological contradiction. The seed is in the man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Way back in Genesis, many scholars believe we have a hint of the virgin birth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wells and Caves&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:3.29028in;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eastern tradition (Greek, Russian orthodox, etc.) holds that the annunciation occurred at this well, in keeping with the rich tradition of momentous events happening at wells or springs throughout scripture. Abraham, Jacob, Gideon, and even Jesus in John 4 has the famous meeting with the Samaritan woman at the well.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Western (Roman Catholic) tradition holds that the annunciation was in a cave that today is venerated at the Catholic Church of the Annunciation in Nazareth.
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image2.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:3.29028in;float:right&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Caves are also prominent in the Bible with Abraham purchasing the cave at Machpelah in Hebron as a burial place, David establishing his superiority over Saul in a cave (though he later regretted it), Elijah, before he killed the priests of Baal, he found them hiding in caves,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John the Baptist traditionally lived in caves, and it is widely believed that both the birth of Jesus and the events described in the Garden of Gethsemane both took place in caves. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;large&gt;Matthew 1:19&lt;/large&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;And her husband Joseph, &lt;u&gt;being a just man&lt;/u&gt; and unwilling to put her to shame, resolved to divorce her quietly.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tzadik – &lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;צַדִּיק&lt;/span&gt; – righteous one; not sinless but in the sense of Michah 6:8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Micah 6:8&lt;/sup&gt; He has told you, O man, what is good; and what does the LORD require of you? but to do justice, and to love kindness (mercy), and to walk humbly with your God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Deu 22:23-24&lt;/sup&gt; “If there is a betrothed virgin, and a man meets her in the city and lies with her, then you shall bring them both out to the gate of that city, and you shall stone them to death with stones, the young woman because she did not cry for help though she was in the city, and the man because he violated his neighbor&#39;s wife. So you shall purge the evil from your midst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Mat 5:32&lt;/sup&gt; But I say to you that everyone who divorces his wife, except on the ground of sexual immorality, makes her commit adultery, and whoever marries a divorced woman commits adultery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Rom 12:7&lt;/sup&gt; Repay no one evil for evil, but give thought to do what is honorable in the sight of all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as the Spirit wanted us to know that Zechariah was righteous, He wants us to know that Joseph was righteous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the Hebrew word for a righteous one is tzadik. Abraham was a tzadik, Boaz was a Tsadik and here Joseph is a Tzadik&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you read proverbs and it says the righteous do such and such but the wicked do such and such, the word for righteous is almost always tsadik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be a tzadik does not require sinless perfection, but it essentially means the person is living out Deuteronomy 6:5, love the Lord your God with all your heart, soul, might and Leviticus 19:18 Love your neighbor as yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these are restated in Micah 6:8, He has told you, O man, what is good; and what does the LORD require of you? but to do justice, and to love kindness (mercy), and to walk humbly with your God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus gives us all the power to be tzadikim (pl), just like Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we weren’t acting like a tsaddik yesterday, today is a new day in the Lord who makes each of us a new creation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calling Joseph a Tzadik rules out Joseph being the biological father (at least not in the usual sense – see speculation below); a just man wouldn’t have had relations before marriage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The angelic visitation is confirmation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph did have a decision to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Joseph&amp;rsquo;s No Good Options&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike today, the engaged couple entered into a marriage covenant upon the announcement of the betrothal (today we only enter into such a contract after the wedding ceremony).
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:4.41111in;float:right&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contract is called a Ketubah and today at Jewish weddings, they are often done as beautiful artwork such as the one pictured.[^6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To break an agreement of betrothal required a legal divorce&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources indicate divorce in this situation was REQUIRED (if the child was not his)[^7]; Jesus even affirms that divorce is appropriate in the scenario of adultery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;According to the Mishna, adultery during a betrothal period was &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; serious than that done after the wedding.[^8]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph, as the injured party, had full control over what happened to Mary in terms of judicial punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option 1&lt;/strong&gt;: She could have been subject to the death penalty for adultery, which is death by stoning (Deuteronomy 22)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that she was obviously pregnant probably would have been enough for such a conviction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way it worked, was the injured party (for example the next of kin in a murder case) would be the one to cast the first stone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember this nugget when we get to John 8 and the woman caught in adultery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commentators are split on whether Mary had a chance to plead her case to Joseph or whether Joseph assumed what to him was obvious. They would not have been allowed to be alone together but this does not exclude a conversation between Mary and Joseph with another adult present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can infer that Joseph loved her. If they had discussed if any part of him wanted to believe her; this would make it nearly impossible for him to be the one to cause her death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although some of the reasons the Bible gives for the death penalty may sound harsh by our standards, in practice the death penalty was rarely carried out. The Mishna records the following: “Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya says a Sanhedrin that executes a transgressor once in seventy years (is considered a bloodthirsty tribunal)”[^9]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on what we know about Joseph, he was very unlikely to consider this option, and Matthew confirms this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option 2&lt;/strong&gt;: public divorce followed by public shame followed by exile – she would not be welcome in the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Honor and Shame” was very strong in the ancient world&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have honor and shame too, but we get it backwards; we &lt;strong&gt;encourage&lt;/strong&gt; shame (Netflix, Reality TV) and &lt;strong&gt;discourage&lt;/strong&gt; honor. It’s supposed to be the other way around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She and her child would have to fend for themselves in a society that did not take kindly to single mothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tzadik doesn’t seek revenge or seek to cause harm to another, even when he is wronged; therefore, #2 is also an unlikely option for Joseph&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Romans 12:17 reminds us that we should never repay evil for evil. This is a verse we must consider carefully whenever we are considering a legal remedy in response to a financial or physical injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though it wasn’t written in Romans yet, Joseph modeled this behavior. He took door #3, which was the only option left to him (so he thought).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option 3&lt;/strong&gt;: “Divorce her quietly” likely means Joseph was prepared to pay the fee to the father of the bride to break the engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is somewhat like a legal settlement where neither side admits any wrongdoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph is not going to press the issue of infidelity, and in so doing, HE would not directly bring any shame on Mary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, her condition would eventually be obvious and Mary would suffer the consequences of her actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without an accuser, there would be no judicial punishment, but she and her newborn would likely have been exiled from the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option 4?&lt;/strong&gt;: As we mentioned above, the one thing he did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have the option to do was to marry her. At least not prior to verse 20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law forbade it, so he would be sinning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing so would be an admission that He fathered the child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such an admission would be (and as best we can tell, ultimately WAS) treated accordingly by the small, tight-night, and religiously observant community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes the sacrifice Joseph is about to make even MORE remarkable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Since Joseph didn&amp;rsquo;t divorce Mary, why bother mentioning that he was thinking about it? Could there be a significant truth?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of being a disciple is asking questions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original &lt;em&gt;talmidim&lt;/em&gt; were frequently asking questions to make sure they understood what was happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 Timothy 3:16-17 tells us that all scripture is profitable…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we read the text, we want to begin to question everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At various points, we want to ask, “why does the Spirit want me to know this?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically in this case, given that Joseph ultimately did NOT divorce Mary, why is it “profitable” for us to know that he was considering it even though he didn’t go through with it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes all we can do is speculate, but as long as our loosely held theory doesn’t contradict Scripture or is refuted by historical facts we can continue to pursue it. We are very likely to learn something (or at least understand why our theory is false); either way, we grow!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given what we discussed in the last lesson about the apparent extraordinary lengths God went to assure Jesus had the right credentials to be the Messiah, verse 19 potentially represents a momentary crisis point in the narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had Satan enticed Joseph to follow through with the divorce, is it possible Jesus would have no connection or claim to the Royal line of David, and the whole messianic plan would have fallen apart?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put this another way, Jesus would have gone on to be the sinless Son of God with or without Joseph’s parenting. Why was Joseph’s NOT divorcing Mary worthy of mention?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can infer &lt;strong&gt;having Joseph involved must be extremely significant&lt;/strong&gt; somehow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence the very reasonable theory that the adoption by Joseph as the legal father is a required precondition to Jesus’ Messiahship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, with God&amp;rsquo;s plan momentarily in jeopardy, God must directly intervene once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-120-21-josephs-course-correction&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:20-21 Joseph&amp;rsquo;s Course Correction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matthew 1:20&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;But as he considered these things, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream, saying, “Joseph, son of David, do not fear to take Mary as your wife, for that which is conceived in her is from the Holy Spirit.&#34;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is 51:7 “Listen to me, you who know righteousness, the people in whose heart is my law; fear not the reproach of man, nor be dismayed at their revilings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“conceived” = γεννάω, literally “begotten”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isa 49:5 And now the LORD says, he who formed me from the womb to be his servant…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given all we’ve discussed, the command to take Mary as his wife is staggering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The angel reminded Joseph that he is a Son of David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joseph is not just in the bloodline of King David, he’s in the much more exclusive royal line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph then receives supernatural confirmation that Mary is not an adulteress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As noted previously, in any other circumstance, Joseph would be sinning if he married Mary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The angel tells him that he’s not sinning by marrying her&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this introduces another problem. By proceeding with the wedding, Joseph was communicating that the child was his &lt;em&gt;and that he had acted less than honorably before marriage. No one at the time was going to believe their story about an immaculate conception&lt;/em&gt;. Not very many believe it today for that matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory, we have a contradiction –&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The baby’s not his, so he can’t marry her; he’s a tsadik and a tsadik doesn’t willfully break the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, he DOES marry her even though the baby’s not his (or is it?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster speculates that among the infinite number of ways God could have engineered the pregnancy, we can’t rule out that Joseph’s DNA was not &lt;em&gt;somehow, someway,&lt;/em&gt; a part of the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this is speculation, but such a move resolves any legal quandaries, namely the requirement for Joseph to divorce Mary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This move would also assure the royal Davidic line continued to be blood-based but would (again, somehow, some way) not have the stain of the curse.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, think about the ramifications for Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us not overlook his sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph, Mary, and Jesus all had to live with the stigma of a crime they didn’t commit (and back then it was a crime) and for which the folks in a small town would have presumed their guilt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This perhaps adds new context to the angel’s encouragement to “do not fear”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isaiah 51:7 says “do not fear the reproach of men.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Greek word &lt;em&gt;genneas&lt;/em&gt; does not imply sexual conception;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is more along the lines of being miraculously formed in the womb as with Isaiah 49:5&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more, it could be understood as miraculously placed in the womb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nicene Creed attempts to deal with this by saying Jesus is “begotten not made, of one essence with the father by whom all things were made.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew 1:21&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;She will bear a son, and you shall call his name Jesus, for he will save his people from their sins.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Mat 1:21 (DD)&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;אֶת־שְׁמוֹ &lt;strong&gt;יֵשׁוּעַ&lt;/strong&gt; כִּי הוּא &lt;strong&gt;יוֹשִׁיעַ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus’ Hebrew/Aramaic name is Yeshua, which means salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is wordplay, albeit highly significant wordplay&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;אֶת־שְׁמוֹ יֵשׁוּעַ כִּי הוּא יוֹשִׁיעַ&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew likely meant “His people” denotatively (literally). His people were the Jewish people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Jews are His natural born people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gentiles that are His are His by adoption (Romans 8:15, Galatians 4:5) and grafting (Romans 11)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-122-23-jesus-fulfills-isaiah-714&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:22-23 Jesus Fulfills Isaiah 7:14&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matthew 1:22-23&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;All this took place to fulfill what the Lord had spoken by the prophet: “Behold, the virgin shall conceive and bear a son, and they shall call his name Immanuel” (which means, God with us).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Isa 7:13-&lt;/sup&gt;14 And he said, “Hear then, O house of David! Is it too little for you to weary men, that you weary my God also? [14] Therefore the Lord himself will give you a sign. Behold, the virgin shall conceive and bear a son, and shall call his name Immanuel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1Pe 3:15&lt;/sup&gt; but in your hearts honor Christ the Lord as holy, always being prepared to make a defense to anyone who asks you for a reason for the hope that is in you; yet do it with gentleness and respect&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Mat 28:20&lt;/sup&gt; And behold, I am with you always, to the end of the age.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is using a literary device called &lt;em&gt;inclusio.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inclusio&lt;/em&gt; is using the same or similar wording at both the beginning and the ending of a paragraph, passage, or in this case an entire book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we consider the genealogy a preamble, he’s essentially beginning his gospel with “God with us”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew ends his gospel with “I AM with you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the first of the statements on fulfilled prophecy cited by Matthew.
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image4.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:5.68403in;float:right&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The photo is from the “Great Isaiah Scroll” one of the Dead Sea scrolls which dates to the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; century BC that was discovered in 1947.  The bottom two lines are Isaiah 7:14.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;answering-common-challenges-to-matthew-123&#34;&gt;Answering Common Challenges to Matthew 1:23&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those with more conservative theological beliefs would contend Matthew was inspired by the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Through this lens, we contend Matthew supernaturally saw that Isaiah’s prophecy regarding the birth of &lt;code&gt;Immanuel&lt;/code&gt; had messianic fulfillment by the virgin birth of Yeshua.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, theological conservatives have less of a problem taking Matthew (and indeed the entire Bible) at face value than do those with a more liberal Christian worldview or a non-Christian worldview.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anti-missionaries&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and other critics/skeptics often cite several problems with Matthew’s hermaneutical methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the most part, these arguments &lt;em&gt;do have some validity&lt;/em&gt;; therefore, we believe such exploration is a worthwhile exercise, even though those of us reading this commentary may be firm in our beliefs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is to our benefit to know and understand common so-called &amp;ldquo;problems&amp;rdquo; with the Bible to have a ready response if asked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Peter 3:15 tells us to be prepared to give every man an answer for the hope that is within us doing so with gentleness and respect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of discipleship is having that initial conversation with a non-believer, whether that person is a skeptic or has never heard Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are called to provide reasons, and sound, logical arguments, for the hope we have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, if not checked, seeds of doubt can grow into weeds that impede our own discipleship.  We must be absolutely confident that God&amp;rsquo;s word is true, and we must live like we are confident in it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Chuck Missler used to say, &amp;ldquo;if you think you&amp;rsquo;ve found an error in the Bible, rejoice!  There are no errors in the Bible, and the journey you take to confirm that for yourself will result in a blessing.&amp;rdquo;  AMEN!&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times, such a defense may require us to provide refutations to arguments that attack the core fundamentals of the faith (in this case, the inerrancy of the Apostolic writings).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of doing so with gentleness and respect, I would say rebutting an argument is ONLY worthwhile if the other person is making a legitimate academic inquiry and seeking an answer in good faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should not pick fights or try to win points in a social media discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spending your time and energy answering someone who doesn’t really want to listen to you is an example of “casting your pearls before swine.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, let’s look at some of the common challenges, and then we’ll provide some rebuttals and rationales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Challenge #1: Matthew takes the passages out of context. This passage in Isaiah was a sign given to King Ahaz about King Hezekiah’s birth (who many had hoped would be the messiah).&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Response: Yes, he does ignore the original context for the most part. In context, we agree the prophecy was given to King Ahaz 700 years before Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew follows Jewish methods of Scripture interpretation and application of his day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such methods leverage word-play, gematria, and hyper-literal application called &lt;em&gt;Midrash&lt;/em&gt; related to &lt;em&gt;drosh&lt;/em&gt;, to seek out).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apostolic era midrash involves the transposition of a biblical text to a different application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no way my professors at Liberty University would let me get away with such methods of hermeneutics today, but they were common and accepted in the first century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many prophecies Matthew will cite have a dual application – one immediate to the time and another to the days of Messiah (and from a Christian perspective, this could either be the first coming or the second).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isaac Troki&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, one of the earliest published books that today’s anti-missionary groups rely on is called “Faith Strengthened” written in the mid 1500’s by Isaac Troki. Troki first documented most of the arguments we are discussing here in this section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Troki is from the Karaite branch of Judaism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an estimated 40,000 followers today (that is to say fairly small), Karaites break with most of traditional Judaism in rejecting the Oral Torah including the midrashic methods of interpretation used by almost every other branch of modern Judaism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, it’s easy for him to attack Matthew’s methods of Judaic interpretation because Troki himself didn’t agree with them according to his lens of Judaism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also wouldn’t agree with the hermeneutic traditions of most other traditional Jewish sects, including the beliefs of those today who cite his book to attack Christians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Challenge #2: Matthew takes the passages &amp;lsquo;hyper-literally.&amp;rsquo; He&amp;rsquo;s reading things into the text that aren&amp;rsquo;t there.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;-   Challenge: **He takes the passage hyper-literally.** Nothing about the passage implies a Virgin will still be a virgin when she conceives. It only requires that she be a virgin when the prophecy was given.
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;-   Response: Also true; but Matthew was also saying the most supernatural part of the prophecy remained unfulfilled in Ahaz’s day: the fact that the virgin will be a virgin when she conceives.

-   While the prophecy was most directly to King Ahaz (who lived 700 years before Jesus), Isaiah also said, “hear then, HOUSE OF DAVID…” – the prophecy can apply to the entire line; not just one man.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Challenge #3: The Hebrew word Matthew says means &lt;code&gt;virgin&lt;/code&gt; could also mean &lt;code&gt;a young woman&lt;/code&gt;, who is not necessarily a virgin.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Response: This complaint is more flawed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same people just got through arguing that the person need only be a virgin at the time the prophecy was written. For the woman to NOT be a virgin, would be a curse, not a prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six other times the word &lt;em&gt;alma&lt;/em&gt; is used in the Bible; most of the time it is unambiguously a virgin as we think of the word. The other couple of times, it could be ambiguous potentially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not much of a sign when a young woman gets pregnant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably the nail in the coffin of this complaint is when the Jewish scholars translated the Hebrew Bible into the Greek Septuagint, they used the unambiguous Greek word for virgin, Parthenos, παρθένος&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, 200 years before the birth of Jesus, the Jewish sages believed Isaiah meant “virgin” as we think of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Challenge #4: Judaism never teaches a virgin birth. The Christian concept of the &lt;code&gt;Immaculate Conception&lt;/code&gt; is straight out of Greco-Roman paganism.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Response: as we noted at the beginning of this lesson, pagan conceptions between gods and virgin females were ALWAYS sexual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened to Mary was in NO WAY sexual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, we acknowledge that two of the four gospels don’t mention the virgin birth and several apostolic writers including Paul never mentions it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;-   An argument as to why this could be that they didn’t find it all that surprising because they knew Jewish tradition, which DOES in fact have several TRADITIONS and LEGENDS of supernatural conceptions and births.[^13]
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bible recounts several “closed wombs” that were supernaturally opened by God, making all of those conceptions miraculous works of God. By definition, a virgin’s womb is closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not from the Bible, Jewish legend holds that Isaac, Moses, and David also were supernaturally conceived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dead Sea Scrolls written around the time of Jesus contain a fragment of a legend that holds Noah was supernaturally conceived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aren’t saying these non-biblical legends are true, and that is not the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is that a Jewish supernatural conception of a person God used mightily would have resonated with the early apostles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While they may have initially had their doubts, once they heard the story as authenticated by Matthew and Luke (of whom we have no reason to believe they were being deceitful or delusional), the other Jewish apostles had no reason to doubt any longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The virgin birth has nothing to do with pagan mythology that anti-missionaries object to.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-124-25-josephs-revised-decision&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:24-25 Joseph&amp;rsquo;s Revised Decision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matthew 1:24-25&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Reference&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When Joseph woke from sleep, he did as the angel of the Lord commanded him: he took his wife, but knew her not until she had given birth to a son. And he called his name Jesus.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Mishnah Bava Batra 8:6, 134a&lt;/sup&gt; If one says: &amp;ldquo;This is my son,&amp;rdquo; he is believed, as regards the right of inheritance”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern notes, “Joseph’s behavior indicated that he accepted Yeshua as his son.” The Mishnah states, “he is to be believed; thus Yeshua, as a legally acknowledged son, is entitled to inherit the throne of King David from Joseph.” &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps this supports the speculation that (somehow, someway) Jesus WAS Joseph’s son.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a minimum, it appears Joseph married Mary &lt;strong&gt;immediately&lt;/strong&gt; to attempt to minimize her (and now their) shame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By doing so, he also created the impression among the 200 or so other townsfolk of Nazareth that he faltered and fathered the child. They probably knew the timing didn’t line up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, to see both sides, there is another line of thought that says the folk in Nazareth, which means “branch town,” i.e., branch of David, believed the messiah would eventually come from their midst, so maybe the situation isn’t as dire as we might imagine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we go through the gospels, where it may be of value to our own discipleship, we will try to learn to critically question many of the standard conclusions made and passed down by commentators over the years to see if there might not be another equally plausible explanation for what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, we will look for examples that allow us to exhibit Leviticus 19:18 better and give others the benefit of the doubt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somehow, word got out, and Jesus’ detractors learned about Jesus’ seemingly inappropriate conception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several examples of ancient anti-Christian literature claim that Jesus resulted from an affair Mary had with a Roman soldier named Pantera (yes, children of the 80s, you heard that right).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We only have the one event from Jesus’ childhood where he visits the Temple, so nothing is recorded of any trauma or struggles in His childhood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 8, Psalm 69 and others might indicate the family was subjected to abuse because of the apparent scandal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew skips over the birth narrative with the shepherds, which we find in Luke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jewish boys were not named until the 8&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; day, at their circumcision&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another subtle hint that the Magi were not there the night of Jesus’ birth but came later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll spoil this and many other of your favorite Christmas traditions when we get to Luke 2!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, Todd. “Matthew 1.” PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———. “Matthew 21.” PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener, Craig S. &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;. 2nd edition (E-Sword). Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, Daniel T. “Nativity.” In &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Boaz D. Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster. Second. Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern, David H. &lt;em&gt;Jewish New Testament Commentary: A Companion Volume to the Jewish New Testament&lt;/em&gt;. E-Sword edition. Clarksville, Md.: Lederer Messianic Publications, 1992.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Mishnah Makkot 1:10.” Accessed August 27, 2022. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sefaria.org/Mishnah_Makkot.1.10?lang=bi&amp;amp;with=all&amp;amp;lang2=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.sefaria.org/Mishnah_Makkot.1.10?lang=bi&amp;with=all&amp;lang2=en&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Out of Egypt&lt;/em&gt;. Jesus, My Rabbi, 2020. Accessed August 31, 2022. &lt;a href=&#34;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/out_of_egypt_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/out_of_egypt_1.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Nativity&lt;/em&gt;. Jesus, My Rabbi, 2020. Accessed August 31, 2022. &lt;a href=&#34;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_nativity_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_nativity_1.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Virgin&lt;/em&gt;. Video. Vol. 1. 2 vols. Jesus, My Rabbi, 2020. Accessed August 29, 2022. &lt;a href=&#34;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_virgin_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_virgin_1.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Nativity&lt;/em&gt;, Jesus, My Rabbi, 2020, accessed August 31, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_nativity_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_nativity_1.html&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Out of Egypt&lt;/em&gt;, Jesus, My Rabbi, 2020, accessed August 31, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/out_of_egypt_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/out_of_egypt_1.html&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig S. Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition (E-Sword). (Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014), loc. Mt. 1:18.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, “Matthew 1” (PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), fig. tb041003218.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ibid., drra3g03452.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, “Nativity.”&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, “Matthew 1” (PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), fol. isax3y0.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anti-missionaries are traditional Jews who believe Christianity is a dangerous anti-Jewish cult and work to prevent, refute, and undo any Christian missionary efforts among Jews. “Jews for Jesus” is a messianic missionary group. “Jews for Judaism” is an anti-missionary group.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This author can attest that Chuck not only saved me countless hours of doubt, and probably saved me from a lot of bad theology.  On the flip side, prior to encountering solid teaching, I heard things in college religion courses (including elements of the &amp;ldquo;Documentary Hypothesis,&amp;rdquo; that were not taught as a hypothesis, but were taught as truth) that derailed parts of my faith for years.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern, &lt;em&gt;Jewish New Testament Commentary&lt;/em&gt;, loc. Mt 1:24.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5. The Nazarene</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/5-the-nazarene/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/5-the-nazarene/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In THE NAZARENE, Joseph and Mary return to the remote village of Nazareth overlooking the Jezreel Valley and Mount Tabor. The transition from cosmopolitan Alexandria to backwater Nazareth allows them to live out their own personal exodus from Egypt. Every year at Passover, the family joins other Galileans to make the pilgrimage to Jerusalem for the festival. Twelve-year-old Yeshua is reluctant to leave His Father’s house in the holy city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3uaVNrYBB0Q&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_nazarene_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_nazarene_1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6. John the Immerser</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/6-john-the-immerser/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/6-john-the-immerser/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In JOHN THE IMMERSER, Herod the Great’s sons have divided up the holy land, and the Holy Temple has fallen into the hands of a corrupt and Romanized priesthood. We turn our attention away from palaces and politics to seek a prophet, the voice of one calling in the wilderness. We find John the Immerser preaching on the other side of the Jordan River, near Bethany. John prepares the way through immersion and repentance. The waters of the Jordan River run with history and spiritual significance. Those waters have served as a place of renewal for the people of Israel more than once. The people seeking the prophet and his immersion must cross over its waters again to re-enter the land with a new heart and new commitment to God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C63y8Qq--lc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/john_the_immerser.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/john_the_immerser.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_voice_in_the_wilderness_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_voice_in_the_wilderness_1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
