<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Luke 3 | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/luke-3/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/tag/luke-3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Luke 3</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu9bdc4cc28a100eaa5c154301214e2807_480992_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Luke 3</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/luke-3/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genealogies - Matthew 1:1-17; Luke 3:23-38</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GENEALOGIES demonstrates to us that Jesus is of the &amp;ldquo;house and lineage&amp;rdquo; of King David. Once, when Jesus was passing through the streets, some blind men called out to Him, “Have mercy on us, Son of David!” Why did they call Him “Son of David”? What does that title mean, and what is Jesus’ relationship to King David? In this chapter we explore the family tree of the Messiah.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#roadmap&#34;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#gospels-snapshot&#34;&gt;Gospels Snapshot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-11&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-12-6--abraham-to-solomon--luke-3138-adam-to-nathan&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:2-6 – Abraham to Solomon &amp;amp; Luke 31:38 Adam to Nathan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#bad-girls-of-the-bible&#34;&gt;Bad Girls of the Bible&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#tamar&#34;&gt;Tamar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rahab&#34;&gt;Rahab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#ruth&#34;&gt;Ruth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#mary&#34;&gt;Mary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-wife-of-uriah-bathsheba&#34;&gt;The wife of Uriah (Bathsheba)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-17-16--solomon-to-jacob--luke-2331-nathan-to-heli&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:7-16 – Solomon to Jacob &amp;amp; Luke 23:31 Nathan to Heli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-deportation-to-babylon&#34;&gt;The deportation to Babylon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#jeconiah&#34;&gt;Jeconiah&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#other-reconciliation-theories&#34;&gt;Other Reconciliation theories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matthew-112-17-jeconiah-to-jesus&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:12-17: Jeconiah to Jesus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-323-30&#34;&gt;Luke 3:23-30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#jeconiah-and-the-blood-curse&#34;&gt;Jeconiah and the blood curse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verse by verse lesson:&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/A0ghMk4_0jg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Women in Matthew&amp;rsquo;s Genealogy Supplement:&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hWzRZfkyTWk&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;roadmap&#34;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different accounts, yet both claim to be THE genealogy of Jesus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew genealogy (through Solomon) - Why 14?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke genealogy (through Nathan)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ενομιζετο – “as it was supposed”/“reckoned by law”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Babylonian deportation (Assyrian diversion)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Blood Curse on Jechoniah and the Royal Line (Jeremiah 22)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other genealogy reconciliation theories&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gospels-snapshot&#34;&gt;Gospels Snapshot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesus as&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jewish Messiah&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Servant of All&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Son of Man&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Son of God&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genealogy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Abraham&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Adam&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Preexistent One&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Jesus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Said&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Did&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Felt&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Who He Was&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Style&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Teachings&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Snapshots&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Narrative&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7 Miracles / 7 ”I AM the…” / 7 Discourses&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Miracle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Leper&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Demon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Demon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Water to Wine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symbol&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lion of Judah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ox&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Man&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eagle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-11&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matthew&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The book of the generations (genealogy) of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Gen 5:1&lt;/sup&gt; This is the book of the generations of Adam. When God created man, he made him in the likeness of God.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Son of Abraham = means a Jew. Matthew wants us to know that Jesus is Jewish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Son of David is a clear Messianic title. Matthew wants us to know that Jesus is the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew presents his genealogy in the Hebraic style of Genesis 5:1, which reads “this (is the) book of the generations of Adam” (although it is Luke, not Matthew, who presents us the lineage back to Adam).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genealogies were important legal documents to demonstrate lineage for the purposes of inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically records were kept in the temple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it was destroyed in 70 CE so were most of the records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, ANYONE after 70 CE could claim to be descended from David and there would be no way to prove or disprove it. A few would-be messiahs in history even tried to fabricate their lineage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the claim for Jesus’ lineage was made when it could still have been checked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Gen 17:7&lt;/sup&gt; And I will establish my covenant between me and you and your offspring after you throughout their generations for an everlasting covenant, to be God to you and to your offspring after you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2Sa 7:16&lt;/sup&gt; And your house and your kingdom shall be made sure forever before me. Your throne shall be established forever.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a candidate for Messiah is not a descendant from David AND Abraham, he is to be rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God made eternal and unconditional covenants with both Abraham and David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 1:1 is the most important verse of the chapter as it establishes Jesus in both David’s line and Abraham’s line (with the remainder of the genealogy used to support the assertion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:2.60856in;height:1.95614in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Deu 17:15&lt;/sup&gt; you may indeed set a king over you whom the LORD your God will choose. &lt;strong&gt;One from among your brothers you shall set as king over you. You may not put a foreigner over you, who is not your brother&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any king, including, and especially the Messiah had to be Jewish by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have an interesting Juxtaposition between Jesus, the rightful king, and King Herod, the presently reigning king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dichotomy is accented by geography. Above is a picture of Herod’s palace called Herodium (of course he named it after himself). Herodium is about 3 miles from Bethlehem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To varying degrees, all of the gospels portray Jesus the rightful king, messiah, and Son battling against the usurping forces, be they Herod, the political/religious establishment or the forces of spiritual darkness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herod, was NOT BORN King of the Jews, in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. He’s wasn’t Jewish by birth. He was an Idumean, which is to say an edomite, descended from Esau not Jacob. If you know anything about the history, the Edomites and the Israelites didn’t get along at all. During the period of the Maccabees, Herod’s family was forced to convert. Forced conversions, whether done by the greeks under Antiochus IV, the Jews under the Maccabeans, or the Christians and Muslims in later years, never seem to work out very well for both the converted and those forcing the conversions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. He therefore was not qualified to be King. In fact, he approached the Roman Senate to grant him that title, which they did in 39 BC. And in an irony of History, Rome didn’t even control the area at the time. The Parthians did. Herod pushed them out and secured the area for Rome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adds some possible intrigue to &lt;sup&gt;Mat 2:1-2&lt;/sup&gt; Now after Jesus was born in Bethlehem of Judea in the days of Herod the king, behold, wise men from the east came to Jerusalem, [2] saying, “Where is he who has been &lt;strong&gt;born king of the Jews&lt;/strong&gt;? For we saw his star when it rose and have come to worship him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Magi approach Herod and ask, “where is he who has been BORN KING OF THE JEWS?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chuck Missler sees this as an intentional dig at Herod. In other words, “Not you, turkey. Where’s the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; king of the Jews?” Which of course sends Herod off in a fit of rage and we know from Matthew 2:4-5, Herod inquired of the birthplace of Messiah and was told it would be in Bethlehem. Eventually, he orders the execution of all males 2 years and younger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, before this episode, the Talmud records that Herod once approached his leaders for the qualifications of a Jewish leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Sanhedrin explained Deuteronomy 17:15 to Herod, telling him that one must be naturally born Jewish, Herod naturally, was not pleased with the explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He ordered the execution of all of the Sanhedrin except one (b. Bava Batra 3b), which tells you all about Herod. “don’t shoot the messenger” was not in his vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster notes that Herod then sought to destroy all such records and people of the Davidic Royal line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This likely forced any direct descendant of David to flee from Bethlehem, just a stone’s throw away from Herod’s palace at Herodium, to the relative obscurity in Nazareth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far from being a boring list of names, the fact that Matthew’s genealogy is preserved may be the first recorded miracle in his gospel!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image2.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.32569in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 1:1 establishes Jesus in David’s line and also in Abraham’s line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;אדם  &lt;/span&gt;= Abraham, David, Messiah according to the sages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-12-6--abraham-to-solomon--luke-3138-adam-to-nathan&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:2-6 – Abraham to Solomon &amp;amp; Luke 31:38 Adam to Nathan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew 1:2-6 ↓&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke 3:38-31 ↑&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, Judah and his brothers, Perez and Zerah by Tamar, Hezron, Ram, Amminadab, Nahshon, Salmon, Boaz by Rahab, Obed by Ruth, Jesse, David the king. And David was the father of &lt;strong&gt;Solomon&lt;/strong&gt; by the wife of Uriah…&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Adam the Son of God, Seth, Enosh, Cainan, Mahalalel, Jared, Enoch, Methuseleh, Lamech, Noah, Shem, Arphaxhad, &lt;em&gt;Cainan&lt;/em&gt;, Shelah, Eber, Peleg, Reu, Serug, Nahor, Terah, Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, Judah, Perez, Hezron, &lt;em&gt;Arni, Admin&lt;/em&gt;, Amminadab, Nashon, Sala, Boaz, Obed, Jesse, David, &lt;strong&gt;Nathan&lt;/strong&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is very much like an Old Testament genealogy that runs from oldest to newest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke follows the style of a Greco-Roman ancestry that runs from newest to oldest – Luke’s order is flipped above to make comparisons easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is interested in presenting Jesus as the Jewish Messiah, so his genealogy goes back to Abraham the first Jew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke is interested in presenting us the ancestry of the son of Man, so he’s going to go all the way back to Adam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to Abraham, EVERYONE was a “gentile” (if you’ll pardon the anachronism).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke, which was widely circulated in Gentile regions, wanted gentiles to know Jesus is their Messiah too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he stresses in Luke Volume II (the book we know as Acts), he wants us to know Gentiles are included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam to Noah is the same list as Genesis 5, and Shem to Terah, is roughly the same list as Genesis 11:10-25 (see discussion on potential discrepancies below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Gospels are basically the same from Abraham to David (see potential discrepancies).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will touch on the women in Matthew’s gospel in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potential discrepancies in this section:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew omits some names in this section and omits a LOT of names in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener notes this is not unusual for ancient genealogies, and we may have an element of the Holy Spirit blotting out certain names from the record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew conspicuously skips three kings of Judah: Ahaziah, Joash, and Amaziah (compare 1 Chronicles 3:10-16).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was interested in preserving 14 generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke inserts someone named “Cainan” inbetween Arphaxhad and Shelah in Abraham’s line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cainan is not mentioned in Genesis 11l&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this is the identical name to the Cainan in Noah’s line, this is possibly a copyist’s error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note this is why we say the Bible is inerrant &lt;strong&gt;in the original manuscripts&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several known copyist errors, most notably in John 5:3-4;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These do not detract from the overall inerrancy of Scripture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke inserts Arni and Admin, which are not included in the Old Testament accounts of David’s lineage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arni is potentially a variant spelling of Ram, we don’t know where Admin came from. Perhaps it’s an &lt;em&gt;admin&lt;/em&gt;istrative error.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big thing to note is that Matthew’s list runs through Solomon, the first surviving son of David and the wife of Uriah, while Luke’s runs through Nathan, the second surviving son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note also that Bathsheba is referred to only indirectly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In fact, she is never named in the Bible after she dies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nothing is accidental in the Bible. The Holy Spirit engineers and orchestrates every letter. For her not to be named is a “dis” from the Holy Spirit!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Far from being an innocent victim, perhaps she was the instigator of the entire episode. She did seem to relish her position as Queen Mother in 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Kings 2.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In contrast, Rahab repented, Tamar was declared righteous by Judah himself, and if you know anything about Ruth and Boaz, there was nothing inappropriate about their relationship.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bad-girls-of-the-bible&#34;&gt;Bad Girls of the Bible&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was highly unusual for an ancient genealogy to include women&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All five women listed, including Mary in verse 16, were tainted by scandal (real or suspected).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster posits that by including the first four women, Matthew sought to make any scandal regarding Mary irrelevant to Jesus’ claim to be the Messiah. The ancients held a much wider view of “mother” and “father” than we do today, so if David had a few less than reputable “mothers” in his line and is still regarded as the greatest King of Israel, how much more should Jesus be regarded as one greater than David even though there are some questions regarding His lineage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tamar&#34;&gt;Tamar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tamar relies on the Levirate Marriage law: &lt;sup&gt;Deu 25:5-6&lt;/sup&gt; If brothers dwell together, and one of them dies and has no son, the wife of the dead man shall not be married outside the family to a stranger. Her husband&amp;rsquo;s brother shall go in to her and take her as his wife and perform the duty of a husband&amp;rsquo;s brother to her. And the first son whom she bears shall succeed to the name of his dead brother, that his name may not be blotted out of Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tamar was the daughter in law of Judah. We can read the complete story in Genesis 38.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She married one of Judah’s sons a guy by the name of Er, but he was wicked and was struck down by the LORD before they had children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In accordance with the law of the Levirate marriage, Judah was REQUIRED to have Tamar marry the next available male, Onan, to marry Tamar and have a child in the name of the deceased son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judah did this but THAT son was also wicked and was struck down (a very R-rated story- the Bible tells it like it is).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re getting an idea that maybe Judah was a less than stellar father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judah had a third son, Shelah, but Judah feared He would die along the others, as if it was Tamar who was the bad news causing this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judah promised to give Shelah to Tamar but told her to wait until he was older.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Judah was likely hoping Tamar would go off and find someone else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember this is now the Royal line of Judah that is at stake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tamar realizes Judah is going to renege on his word so she takes matters into her own hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She KNOWS that Judah’s line must continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She dresses up as a harlot and entices none other than Judah, her father-in-law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judah doesn’t have cash on hand so he leaves his staff, cord and signet ring as a down payment. The next day he goes to collect but Tamar has vanished. He asks around but is told “there is no harlot here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three months later Tamar is showing. When Judah learns of it, he is incensed at the shame she has brough on the family (seriously?) and orders her burned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Gen 38:24-26&lt;/sup&gt; About three months later Judah was told, “Tamar your daughter-in-law has been immoral. Moreover, she is pregnant by immorality.” And Judah said, “Bring her out, and let her be burned.” As she was being brought out, she sent word to her father-in-law, “By the man to whom these belong, I am pregnant.” And she said, “Please identify whose these are, the signet and the cord and the staff.” Then Judah identified them and said, “She is more righteous than I, since I did not give her to my son Shelah.” And he did not know her again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He says “She is more righteous than I.” which is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tamar is untimately proclaimed righteous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She thwarted the attack on the Royal Line and had twins, Perez and Zerah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see how these seemingly obscure laws in the Torah like the Law of the Levirate Marriage are actually critical to the Lines of David and Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another interesting tidbit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Deu 23:2&lt;/sup&gt; “No one born of a forbidden union may enter the assembly of the LORD. Even to the tenth generation, none of his descendants may enter the assembly of the LORD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being “righteous” it was still a forbidden union according to the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God apparently means what He says when He says “10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; generation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perez by Tamar, Hezron, Ram, Amminadab, Nahshon, Salmon, Boaz, Obed, Jesse, David – 10 Generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rahab&#34;&gt;Rahab&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Jos 2:12-13&lt;/sup&gt; Now then, please swear to me by the LORD that, as I have dealt kindly with you, you also will deal kindly with my father&amp;rsquo;s house, and give me a sure sign that you will save alive my father and mother, my brothers and sisters, and all who belong to them, and deliver our lives from death.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rahab was an actual harlot in Jericho who ends up protecting Joshua’s men in exchange for protection. You can read the story in Joshua 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tradition holds that she repented and found grace and mercy by following the God of Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can’t say that Grace and Mercy are New Testament concepts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She is lauded in the Hebrews 11 Hall of faith:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Heb 11:31** **&lt;/sup&gt;By faith Rahab the prostitute did not perish with those who were disobedient, because she had given a friendly welcome to the spies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ruth&#34;&gt;Ruth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruth relies on the Kinsman Redeemer Law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Lev 25:25&lt;/sup&gt; “If your brother becomes poor and sells part of his property, then his nearest redeemer shall come and redeem what his brother has sold.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the passage that causes many to associate Ruth with scandal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Rth 3:7-9&lt;/sup&gt; And when Boaz had eaten and drunk, and his heart was merry, he went to lie down at the end of the heap of grain. Then she came softly and uncovered his feet and lay down. At midnight the man was startled and turned over, and behold, a woman lay at his feet! He said, “Who are you?” And she answered, “I am Ruth, your servant (handmaid). Spread your wings over your servant, for you are a redeemer.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you know anything about Ruth and Boaz, you know it was unlikely there was any mischief before marriage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Ruth 3, she “uncovers his feet”, which to be fair, in the Bible is often a euphemism for other things and then asks him to “spread your wing or hem/skirt over me (same wing and hem/corner are the same word in Hebrew). Her request was scandalous but not for the reason you may be thinking. As chuck Missler says, “she wasn’t propositioning him, it’s far worse than that. She was asking for his protection. In other words, she was asking him to make good on his duty to be a kinsman redeemer – another Old Testament law that turns out to be critically important to Jesus’ lineage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scandal part is that Moabites were the sworn enemies of Israel and Boaz was forbidden by law from marrying ruth, but he must make an exception (and I suspect he did so gladly) because of the overriding law of the Kinsman redeemer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that is important to know about the application of Jewish law. Whenever there is a negative commandment that conflicts with a positive one, the positive one wins out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is going to make use of this guideline frequently, particularly with the so-called Sabbath controversies. He’s not overriding the law; he’s following the law strictly and perfectly, much more perfectly than the prevailing attitudes of the day were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case the law said an Israelite was forbidden from marrying a moabitie but the positive command required the nearer kinsman to redeem.Ruth who earlier made the famous proclamation of “where you go I will go, and where you lodge I will lodge. Your people shall be my people, and your God my God.” (Ruth 1:16) now says “I am your servant or some translations say handmaid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Luk 1:38&lt;/sup&gt; And Mary said, “Behold, I am the servant (handmaid) of the Lord; let it be to me according to your word.” And the angel departed from her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mary’s words in Luke 1:38 echo ruth’s faithfulness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in Biblical typology Boaz is a type of Jesus and Ruth, a gentile is a picture of us, the gentile church. We are helpless and poor without our Redeemer. With Jesus we are royalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mary&#34;&gt;Mary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve talked and will talk a lot more about her righteousness but this doesn’t keep detractors from raising the appearance of scandal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Joseph appears initially ready to believe the scandal (not without reason of course)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Mat 1:18-19&lt;/sup&gt; Now the birth of Jesus Christ took place in this way. When his mother Mary had been betrothed to Joseph, before they came together she was found to be with child from the Holy Spirit. [19] And her husband Joseph, being a just man and &lt;strong&gt;unwilling to put her to shame, resolved to divorce her quietly&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that Jesus’ questionable lineage was used by His detractors in John 8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Joh 8:18-19&lt;/sup&gt; I am the one who bears witness about myself, and the Father who sent me bears witness about me.” [19] They said to him therefore, &lt;strong&gt;“Where is your Father?”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although I just said to give others the benefit of the doubt, we can tell by the context of the passage that they are being absolutely nasty here!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The psalms appear to speak of Jesus’ childhood struggles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Psa 69:8-12&lt;/sup&gt; I have become a &lt;strong&gt;stranger to my brothers, an alien to my mother&amp;rsquo;s sons&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;For zeal for your house has consumed me&lt;/em&gt;, and the reproaches of those who reproach you have fallen on me. When I wept and humbled my soul with fasting, it became my reproach. When I made sackcloth my clothing, I became a byword to them. &lt;strong&gt;I am the talk of those who sit in the gate, and the drunkards make songs about me&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s hard to imagine growing up and having Jesus as a half-brother. I’m sure James, Jude and the others were none too thrilled at being told “why can’t you be more like Yeshua?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-wife-of-uriah-bathsheba&#34;&gt;The wife of Uriah (Bathsheba)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:3.77014in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a familiar story but 2 Samuel 11 says it was the time when the Kings should have been on the battlefield but David stayed back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He eyes Bathsheba bathing and the rest as they say his history&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2Sa 11:4-5&lt;/sup&gt; So David sent messengers and took her, and she came to him, and he lay with her. (Now she had been purifying herself from her uncleanness.) Then she returned to her house. And the woman conceived, and she sent and told David, “I am pregnant.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He next tries to cover up by having Uriah lay with his wife, which he refused to do&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The army (again, where David SHOULD have been) was supposed to be in a state of ritual purity, specifically abstaining from marital relations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David then has Uriah eliminated so he can openly marry his wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a great example of the difference between the “vertical” and the “horizontal” realms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the vertical- our relationship with God– David repented and was forgiven. In acts 13, David is still referred to as a man after God’s own heart and Psalm 51 is a beautiful expression of repentence and forgiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horizontally – our relationship with others - there are still consequences when we sin. This episode resulted in David’s family life becoming an absolute train-wreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture above is inside the same archaeological park we talked about with David’s harp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists think David’s palace was at the top, and you can see how steep the incline is with the houses below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would have been quite easy for the king to walk out and look down into the houses below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some speculation as to whether this was a sexual assault by David. I tend not to see this and we get a clue why in Matthew 1:6. Notice Bathsheba is not named.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact she is NEVER named in the Bible after she dies, and only once during the episode in question is she named as “Bathsheba”, otherwise it’s the “wife of Uriah” or some other pronoun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some scholars see this as a “dis” from the Holy Spirit which to me suggests she knew exactly what she was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew continues this trend of not uttering her name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the other four women who are named either engaged in or had the appearance of scandal only without doing anything wrong. The contrast suggests to some commentators that Bathsheba never repented of her role in all of the drama. That is a speculation but we can see in 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Kings 2, Bathsheba seems to relish her power and position as the Queen Mother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet through it all, God orchestrated the messianic line through the sons of David and Bathsheba.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-17-16--solomon-to-jacob--luke-2331-nathan-to-heli&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:7-16 – Solomon to Jacob &amp;amp; Luke 23:31 Nathan to Heli&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 44%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 55%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew 1:7:16 ↓&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke 1:31-23 ↑&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solomon&lt;/strong&gt;, Rehoboam, Abijah, Asa, Jehoshaphat, Jehoram, Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, Hezekiah, Manasseh, Amon, Josiah, Jeconiah (&lt;em&gt;Jehoiakim&lt;/em&gt;?) at the time of the deportation to Babylon. After the deportation, Jeconiah, Shealtiel, Zerubbabel, Abiud, Eliakim, Azor, Zadok, Achim, Eliud, Eleazar, Matthan, &lt;strong&gt;Jacob&lt;/strong&gt; the father of Joseph the &lt;strong&gt;husband&lt;/strong&gt; of Mary, of whom Jesus was born, who is called Messiah.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nathan&lt;/strong&gt;, Mattatha, Menan, Melea, Eliakim, Jonam, Joseph, Judah, Simeon, Levi, Matthat, Jorim, Eliezer, Jose, Er, Elmodam, Cosam, Addi, Melchi, Neri, Salathiel, Zorobabel, Rhesa, Joannan, Juda, Joseph, Semei, Mattathias, Maath, Nagge, Esli, Naum, Amos, Mattathias, Joseph, Jannai, Melchi, Levi, Matthat, &lt;strong&gt;Heli&lt;/strong&gt;, Joseph, (ενομιζετο – &lt;strong&gt;so it was thought&lt;/strong&gt;/reckoned by law), Jesus, when He began his ministry was about 30 years of age&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;↓ &lt;sup&gt;Luke 3:23&lt;/sup&gt; Jesus, when he began his ministry, was about thirty years of age, being &lt;del&gt;the&lt;/del&gt; son (as was supposed) of Joseph, the son of Heli…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew goes from Solomon through Jacob&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He clearly says Joseph is the husband of Mary of whom Jesus was born; he does not say Joseph is the father of Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke goes from Nathan through Heli&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In everyday language, the fact that Luke adds, “as was supposed” implies that Jesus is not actually the son of Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the original Greek, there is no “the” before “son (supposed) of Joseph”, which further distinguishes Joseph from Jesus’ direct ancestors. “By the omission of the article, Joseph’s name is separated from the genealogical chain and accorded a place of its own” (&lt;em&gt;Rienecker&lt;/em&gt; as cited in Stern’s commentary).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Missler and other commentators see far more going on with the word ενομιζετο, which has as its root &lt;em&gt;nomos&lt;/em&gt;, meaning “law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They speculate that there was a legal adoption (relying completely on the Torah’s rulings) of Jesus by Joseph which gives Jesus claim to the Davidic line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other potential discrepancies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall Luke has 76 names while Matthew has 41 names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew omits Ahaziah, Joash and Amaziah (compare 1 Chronicles 3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thought is they were so bad they were blotted out according to Deuteronomy 29:20 -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deu 29:20 The LORD will not be willing to forgive him, and the LORD will blot out his name from under heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, Keener notes that omitting some names is not unexpected with ancient genealogies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said before, of all the Gospel writers Luke is the one most interested in chronology. Matthew is more interested in symbolism and the number 14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew’s math doesn’t add up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t get from 586, the main deportation to Babylon and the destruction of Jerusalm to 5 BC and the birth of Jesus with only 14 generations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew lists Jeconiah twice and counts him in both groups of 14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Missler suggests a copyists error with the second Jeconiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last two kings before the deportation were Jehoakim, the direct descendant of Josiah and Jehoiachin, called Jeconiah or Coniah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke and Matthew apparently have some overlap in the lines with Shealtiel and Zerubabbel or it could be just a coincidence with the same names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-deportation-to-babylon&#34;&gt;The deportation to Babylon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image4.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:3.92857in;height:2.84318in&#34; alt=&#34;C:\Pictorial Library of Bible Lands\Israel Museums\Tower of David Museum, Jerusalem\Babylonian exile imaginative depiction, tb042403502.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Babylon” is a recurring theme in the Bible, particularly the Babylonian destruction of Jerusalem in 586 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern mural depicts Israel’s deportation to Babylon. The words in the upper right say “Galut Bavel,” Exile (to) Babylon&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to place ourselves in the shoes of the Jews of that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve been promised that you’re God’s people through the Mosaic Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve been promised the land forever through the Abrahamic Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve been promised that David’s throne will endure forever through the Davidic Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerusalem was thought to be impregnable, particularly after the Assyrians failed (2 Kings 19:31-36).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet all that is lost on the 9&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of Av in -586.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had God’s promises failed? Maybe He’s not really all-powerful or all-good. Maybe we sinned. bad that we’re now beyond His reach. Maybe we misread the promises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the question many ask today in the face of tragedy or evil is, “How could a good God let this happen?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then what do you do next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sing the blues (Lamentations)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn your back on God&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reinvent/reapply/spiritualize the Bible passages pertaining to the promises&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fall on your knees in repentance and draw near to God&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we do today, the people back then did all those things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as Gettysburg, Pearl Harbor, the JFK assassination, or 9/11 is are those critical moments in history for Americans, the Babylonian captivity is such a moment for Jews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And a few years later in 70 CE, another such moment will occur: the Roman destruction of Jerusalem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;jeconiah&#34;&gt;Jeconiah&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew includes Jeconiah in the Royal Line of Messiah, but there’s a big problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jeremiah 22, God is so fed up with Jeconiah, he puts a curse on him AND his offspring, saying no offspring of his will ever rule in Judah&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet Jeconiah is in the Line of Jesus. So how can Jesus rule as King Messiah if that very same Royal Line is cursed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Chuck Missler says, we can imagine Satan and his demons rejoicing in the halls of hell – they finally polluted the royal line and prevented Messiah. All those attacks on the royal line from Adam and Eve, to Cain and Abel, to Judah and Tamar to David and Bathsheba, to the countless other times Satan tried to wipe out the line, finally worked! We’ve finally prevented the Messiah from ruling!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we need to imagine God turning to the Angels and saying “Watch what I do next!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the fine print! No OFFSPRING of Jeconiah’s shall sit on the Throne of David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image5.png&#34; style=&#34;width:3.95053in;height:3.9826in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s put this all together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we note that this is only a speculation, but it’s the one that appears to be held by most (but not all) Protestant commentators, though it’s not without its complications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion is Matthew is presenting Joseph’s Genealogy and Luke is giving us Mary’s line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presents Jesus as the Jewish King/Messiah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genealogy begins with Abraham, the father of the Jewish people,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;presents the Legal/Royal Line through Joseph&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his gospel, Matthew focuses much more on Joseph than on Mary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THE VIRGIN BIRTH directly circumvents the blood curse on Jeconiah, yet through an adoption procedure (hinted at by the word enomiZETo), Jesus has every right to David’s Royal Line JUST AS IF he were Joseph’s natural son&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the “HOUSE OF DAVID”, the Royal line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the virgin birth also avoids the original sin that happens anytime a human x and a human y chromosome merge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presents Jesus as the perfect man/last Adam/savior of all humanity,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genealogy begins with Adam, the first man,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;enomiZETO suggests Joseph adopted Jesus (or potentially some other similar adoption leveraging either the Daughters of Zelophehad (Numbers 27) or the Levirate Marriage (Deut 25) rulings in the Torah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presents the Blood line through Mary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his gospel, Luke focuses much more on Mary than on Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the LINEAGE OF DAVID, the blood line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Joseph is both of the House and Lineage of David (Luke 2:4), he contains the curse of Jeconiah and can never rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is also both of the House and Lineage of David, but He does NOT contain the curse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why the Virgin Birth is more than a simple sign of the Messiah, it is critical to Jesus’ claim to be the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-reconciliation-theories&#34;&gt;Other Reconciliation theories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as Stern points out “The Genealogies of both Matthew and Luke employ unusual language in connection with Yeshua/Jesus and with good reason. Both assert Yeshua had no human father in the ordinary sense of the word but that the virgin Mary was caused to bear Him by the holy spirit in a supernatural way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other suggestions over the years (some with very strong traditional support) include the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jewish tradition holds that Jeconiah repented so the need to circumvent the blood curse is null and void.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commentaries note that Jeconiah was NOT “Childless” as the Bible records his offspring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a counter-argument, we would say that none of those children reigned as KING of Judah. Some were lower-level administrators of the region but that’s not the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, the line of David continued, but his descendants no longer possessed the throne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is Mary’s line by birth through Solomon and Luke is Joseph’s through Nathan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew directly mentions Mary and the other women, while Luke does not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph’s father Jacob died, and Heli was his adopted father prior to Mary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heli died and his widow remarried Jacob&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew and Luke recorded the same genealogy differently because they had different sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes either Matthew or Luke in error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This commentator would reject that premise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The skeptic would say, “See? The Bible is full of contradictions and can’t be trusted.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our opinion this is an intellectually dishonest answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless a witness gives us a reason to think they are lying or delusional, we give them the benefit of the doubt that what they are recounting is the truth as they see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOWEVER God choose to authenticate Jesus’ claim to be the Messiah, we’re very thankful He did!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Heb 11:6&lt;/sup&gt; And without faith it is impossible to please him, for whoever would draw near to God must believe that he exists and that &lt;strong&gt;He rewards those who (diligently) seek Him.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Tit 3:9&lt;/sup&gt; But &lt;strong&gt;avoid foolish controversies, genealogies&lt;/strong&gt;, dissensions, and quarrels about the law, for they are &lt;strong&gt;unprofitable and worthless&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us strive to be diligent seekers but not engage in foolish and worthless controversies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;matthew-112-17-jeconiah-to-jesus&#34;&gt;Matthew 1:12-17: Jeconiah to Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And after the deportation to Babylon: Jechoniah was the father of Shealtiel, and Shealtiel the father of Zerubbabel, and Zerubbabel the father of Abiud, and Abiud the father of Eliakim, and Eliakim the father of Azor, and Azor the father of Zadok, and Zadok the father of Achim, and Achim the father of Eliud, and Eliud the father of Eleazar, and Eleazar the father of Matthan, and Matthan the father of Jacob, and Jacob the father of Joseph the husband of Mary, of whom Jesus was born, who is called Christ. . all the generations from Abraham to David were fourteen generations, and from David to the deportation to Babylon fourteen generations, and from the deportation to Babylon to the Christ fourteen generations.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a problem with Jeconiah, which we’ll discuss after we look at Luke’s genealogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew demonstrates that the line of David continued through Jesus even though David’s descendants no longer possessed the throne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The math doesn’t work – you can’t get 14 generations from -586 to -5, the time of Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more puzzling is Matthew has to count Jeconiah twice to get 14 from David to Babylon and also from Babylon to Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous theories have emerged such as counting Joseph and Mary separately, but these are all speculation and not really pertinent to our purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is more interested in the pattern of 14, which someone with a Hebraic mindset would have noticed right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hebrew spelling of David adds up to 14:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;ד&lt;/span&gt; = D = 4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;ו&lt;/span&gt; = V = 6&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;ד&lt;/span&gt; = D = 4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4+6+4 = 14&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another prominent theory is based on the moon phases and their connection to the House of David:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psa 89:35-37 Once for all I have sworn by my holiness; I will not lie to David. His offspring shall endure forever, his throne as long as the sun before me. &lt;strong&gt;Like the moon, it shall be established forever, a faithful witness in the skies&lt;/strong&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aaron Eby speculates that the original audience would have noted the roughly 14 days from New Moon to Full Moon, darkness to light (Abraham to David) and then the roughly 14 days from Full Moon to New Moon, light to darkness (David to Jeconiah and the deportation), with the dark to light pattern repeated from Jeconiah to Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is clearly establishing a link to David and that Yeshua is the rightful descendant of David’s royal line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-323-30&#34;&gt;Luke 3:23-30&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jesus, when he began his ministry, was about thirty years of age, being the son (as was supposed) of Joseph, the son of Heli, the son of Matthat, the son of Levi, the son of Melchi, the son of Jannai, the son of Joseph, the son of Mattathias, the son of Amos, the son of Nahum, the son of Esli, the son of Naggai, the son of Maath, the son of Mattathias, the son of Semein, the son of Josech, the son of Joda, the son of Joanan, the son of Rhesa, the son of Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, the son of Neri, the son of Melchi, the son of Addi, the son of Cosam, the son of Elmadam, the son of Er, the son of Joshua, the son of Eliezer, the son of Jorim, the son of Matthat, the son of Levi, the son of Simeon, the son of Judah, the son of Joseph, the son of Jonam, the son of Eliakim, the son of Melea, the son of Menna, the son of Mattatha,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greek genealogies were often reverse chronological&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phrase “as was supposed” has puzzled scholars&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Greek word is a variation of nomitzo, which can mean “reckoned as by law” (&lt;em&gt;nomos&lt;/em&gt; = law).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One theory is that Luke is communicating Jesus is not the natural son of Joseph but an adopted son, just like adoptive parents go through a legal process today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we would call Eli the “father in law” of Joseph, but that type of terminology likely didn’t exist in 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century Judaism. According to this interpretation, Eli is Mary’s father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus a common interpretation is that Matthew is giving us the &lt;strong&gt;royal&lt;/strong&gt; line of Jesus through David and Solomon, while Luke is giving us the &lt;strong&gt;blood&lt;/strong&gt; line of Jesus through David and Nathan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus can be said that Jesus is of the house** (royal) and &lt;strong&gt;lineage&lt;/strong&gt; (blood) of David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does this matter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about Jeconiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;jeconiah-and-the-blood-curse&#34;&gt;Jeconiah and the blood curse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jer 22:24-30 “As I live, declares the LORD, though Coniah (i.e. Jeconiah) the son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, were the signet ring on my right hand, yet I would tear you off [25] and give you into the hand of those who seek your life, into the hand of those of whom you are afraid, even into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon and into the hand of the Chaldeans. [26] I will hurl you and the mother who bore you into another country, where you were not born, and there you shall die. [27] But to the land to which they will long to return, there they shall not return.” [28] Is this man Coniah a despised, broken pot, a vessel no one cares for? Why are he and his children hurled and cast into a land that they do not know? [29] O land, land, land, hear the word of the LORD! [30] Thus says the LORD: “Write this man down as childless, a man who shall not succeed in his days, for none of his offspring shall succeed in sitting on the throne of David and ruling again in Judah.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the promise made to David, Jeconiah was apparently so evil that God pronounced a curse on his line in verse 30: “none of his offspring shall succeed in sitting on the throne of David and ruling again in Judah.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have a problem. The Messiah is supposed to come from David’s royal line yet God just pronounced a blood curse on that line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can imagine Satan and his demons rejoicing, thinking God boxed Himself into a corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we can imagine God saying, “watch what I do next!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leading conjecture is that Matthew establishes Joseph as the &lt;strong&gt;legal father&lt;/strong&gt; through his marriage to Mary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, Jesus is legally entitled to be in David’s Royal line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because Jesus is not Joseph’s biological son, Jesus does not carry the blood curse of Jeconiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke establishes Jesus as being from the non-cursed blood line to David through Nathan and Mary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In other words, The ONLY way around the curse is through a virgin birth and adoption.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that doesn’t make you go “wow” you’ve either heard the story before, or you weren’t paying attention!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other conjectures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some scholars reverse this and say Matthew is Mary’s and Luke’s is Joseph. If so, a problem is that Mary is in Jeconiah’s line and would carry the blood curse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jewish tradition holds that Jeconiah repented and God accepted his contrition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus it is later written that Jeconiah had offspring who ruled Judea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The counter argument to this is they were local govenors of Judah under Persian rule, they were not monarchs. &lt;em&gt;The line of David may have continued, continued but his descendants no longer possessed the throne.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/son_of_david_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/son_of_david_1.html&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo tb042403502&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6. John the Immerser</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb06/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/gb06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#a-word-on-the-lesson-title&#34;&gt;A word on the lesson title&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-time-of-the-beginning&#34;&gt;The time of the beginning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-message-and-the-messenger&#34;&gt;The message and the messenger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#a-specimen-of-johns-preaching&#34;&gt;A specimen of John’s preaching&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-forerunners-picture-of-the-messiah-before-seeing-him&#34;&gt;The forerunner&amp;rsquo;s picture of the Messiah before seeing Him&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#archived-video&#34;&gt;Archived Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portions&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke 3:1-18 / Matthew 3:1-12 / Mark 1:1-8 / John 1:19-28&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In JOHN THE IMMERSER, Herod the Great’s sons have divided up the holy land, and the Holy Temple has fallen into the hands of a corrupt and Romanized priesthood. We turn our attention away from palaces and politics to seek a prophet, the voice of one calling in the wilderness. We find John the Immerser preaching on the other side of the Jordan River, near Bethany. John prepares the way through immersion and repentance. The waters of the Jordan River run with history and spiritual significance. Those waters have served as a place of renewal for the people of Israel more than once. The people seeking the prophet and his immersion must cross over its waters again to re-enter the land with a new heart and new commitment to God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1k0IysiVqgk&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-word-on-the-lesson-title&#34;&gt;A word on the lesson title&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In messianic Jewish circles, John the Baptist is often referred to as “John the immerser.” The reason for this is the term “Baptist” has become somewhat of a charged term theologically (positively and negatively). Immersion reminds us that Christian baptism has its roots in Jewish ritual immersion in a pool of “living water” (either a spring-fed river or lake, or a cistern used to collect rainwater) and is not an entirely new practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-time-of-the-beginning&#34;&gt;The time of the beginning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mat 3:1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mar 1:1,4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Luk 3:1-2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In those days John the Baptist came preaching in the wilderness of Judea,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The beginning of the gospel of Jesus Christ, the Son of God…John appeared baptizing in the wilderness&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In the fifteenth year of the reign of Tiberius Caesar, Pontius Pilate being governor of Judea, and Herod being tetrarch of Galilee, and his brother Philip tetrarch of the region of Ituraea and Trachonitis, and Lysanias tetrarch of Abilene, during the high priesthood of Annas and Caiaphas, the word of God came to John the son of Zechariah in the wilderness.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Augustus was the Caesar at the time of Jesus’ birth; in 14 he was succeeded by Tiberius. If we assume Luke is counting from the beginning of Tiberius’ reign as Emperor (which is only an assumption) 15&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; year would place us in 27/28. Other commentators use other dates to come up with anywhere from 26-30 CE/AD. This results in a crucifixion date between 29-33 CE being defendable. Often the date one picks for the start of His ministry depends on the bias one holds regarding a Friday crucifixion and the Daniel 9 prophecy – we’ll get to both of those questions much later in our study. Unless you need a topic for a PhD thesis in seminary, I recommend we hold dates VERY loosely there’s a lot of ambiguity with calendar conversions and dating methods. Luke says Jesus was ”about thirty” when He started his ministry – if He started in the year 28, he would have been in his mid-30s (remember He had to be born prior to 4 BC when Herod the great died).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The region of Judea, Samaria and Idumea was first given to Archelaus, who as we mentioned last time fits the modern definition of a train wreck. He was deposed in 6 CE and was exiled. At this time Rome brought in Governors or Procurators, All Rome asked of its citizens was “pay your taxes and don’t revolt”. The procurators were tasked with seeing to both things. The procurators were headquartered at the palace in Caesarea but tended to visit Jerusalem during the feast days where large numbers of Jews &lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:2.45972in;height:2.39375in&#34; /&gt;(most of whom hated Rome) congregated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of Jesus, the procurator was Pontius Pilate. Some scholars doubted Pilate’s existence until a stone with an inscription referencing Pontius pilate prefect of Judea was found at Caesarea. The stone was found in the theater at Caesarea upside down. Even back then they were into recycling. Pontius Pilate was appointed governor of Judea in AD 26/27, and he held the post until March of AD 37. This inscription was found in secondary use in the theater of Caesarea. A suggested restoration reads: “Pontius Pilate, Prefect of Judea, made and dedicated the Tiberium to the Divine Augustus.” The stone is the first and only mention of Pilate from an archaeological source. Today a replica is on display at the national park in Caesarea and the original is in the Israel Museum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herod Philip had the northern districts including villages such as Bethsaida and Caesarea Philippi where Peter will later make his famous declaration. When asked “who do YOU say I am”, Peter answered, “you are the Messiah.” Jesus asks us that same question today and every day. In the Gospels, the scene at Caesarea Philippi is the high-water mark of sorts. Jesus would now begin to teach and repeat overtly that he would suffer and die. Both thematically as well as geographically, the rest of the gospels picture Jesus moving from Caesarea Philippi with Peter’s proclamation, which should have been EVERYONE’s proclamation, up to Jerusalem where he would be crucified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Herod that will give Jesus the most trouble is Antipas. Antipas was over galilee and the territory east of the Jordan called Perea. John the Baptist will accuse Antipas of adultery, and even the Jewish historian Josephus records that Antipas was politically threatened by John the Baptist. Jesus calls Antipas a “fox” in Luke 13 and they finally met face to face on the day Jesus was crucified. Jesus was before pilate being interrogated. When Pilate learned that Jesus was from Galilee, Pilate was concerned about a jurisdictional issue and had Jesus transferred to Antipas. Jesus said nothing to Antipas who mocked him and sent Jesus back to Pilate where he was given over to be crucified. Antipas would eventually be exiled just as his brother Archelaus was and replaced by Herod Agrippa I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Decapolis (which means “ten cities) were gentile territory where Jesus fed the 4000 and expelled the demons into the herd of pigs, which Chuck Missler affectionally labels, “the first case of deviled ham”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schlegel notes that “Jews were unhappy with this complicated arrangement of foreign roman domination.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In other words, Messianic hopes were high that God would correct this situation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster reports that between the time John’s father Zechariah served in the temple and the start of John’s ministry, the Romans began to sell the office of the high priest to the highest bidder, and of course, it only was awarded to those loyal to Rome. Annas was like a mafia godfather. Josephus records the political intrigue that resulted in Caiaphas being appointed High Priest, with Annas behind the scenes pulling the strings. The family controlled the high priesthood between 6 and 66. You know the saying about absolute power corrupting absolutely. These were the corrupt Sadducees and they virtually controlled the Sanhedrin in the days of Jesus and Paul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we get the idea that all of Jesus’ opponents were a single collective group – not so – the Pharisees tried to live their lives strictly by the word of God, so they detested the politically corrupt Sadducees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilderness&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Judean wilderness between Jerusalem and Jericho is virtually uninhabitable apart from a few isolated monasteries first built in the Byzantine period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saying “The word of God came to John” is linking John with the Old Testament prophets who received supernatural revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wilderness recalls the 40 years wilderness wanderings in Exodus. Lancaster: “Just as he led them into Canaan in the past, He will lead them from the wilderness into the Messianic Era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Lexham Geographic Commentary, Aubrey Taylor notes, “The wilderness paradoxically symbolizes chaos and distance from God, as well as a place for God to create new life and order. In the wilderness, God created a people and bound them to Himself, laying a foundation for the future nation. John likely believed he was initiating God’s return by enacting prophetic passages in a literal way within the wilderness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark begins his gospel narrative here, completely bypassing the birth and childhood events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark presents Jesus as the servant of all and focuses primarily on what Jesus did to serve mankind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is essentially Peter’s gospel, and it moves like Peter did. Quick fire hits. We can imagine Peter dictating to Mark in Hebrew, while Mark translated into Greek, trying to keep up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark does not have a genealogy because, as Missler says, “we aren’t interested in the pedigree of a servant.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-message-and-the-messenger&#34;&gt;The message and the messenger&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 25%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 27%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 23%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 23%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mat 3:2-6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mar 1:2-6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Luk 3:3-6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;John 1:22-23&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.2&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;2 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; “Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is at hand.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.3&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;3 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; For this is he who was spoken of by the prophet Isaiah when he said, “The voice of one crying in the wilderness: ‘Prepare the way of the Lord; make his paths straight.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.4&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;4 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Now John wore a garment of camel&#39;s hair and a leather belt around his waist, and his food was locusts and wild honey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.5&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;5 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Then Jerusalem and all Judea and all the region about the Jordan were going out to him,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.6&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;6 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and they were baptized by him in the river Jordan, confessing their sins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.2&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;2 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; As it is written in Isaiah the prophet, “Behold, I send my messenger before your face, who will prepare your way,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.3&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;3 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; the voice of one crying in the wilderness: ‘Prepare the way of the Lord, make his paths straight,’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.4&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;4 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; John appeared, baptizing in the wilderness and proclaiming a baptism of repentance for the forgiveness of sins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.5&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;5 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And all the country of Judea and all Jerusalem were going out to him and were being baptized by him in the river Jordan, confessing their sins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.6&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;6 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Now John was clothed with camel&#39;s hair and wore a leather belt around his waist and ate locusts and wild honey.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.3&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;3 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And he went into all the region around the Jordan, proclaiming a baptism of repentance for the forgiveness of sins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.4&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;4 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; As it is written in the book of the words of Isaiah the prophet, “The voice of one crying in the wilderness: ‘Prepare the way of the Lord, make his paths straight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.5&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;5 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Every valley shall be filled, and every mountain and hill shall be made low, and the crooked shall become straight, and the rough places shall become level ways,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.6&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;6 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and all flesh shall see the salvation of God.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;What do you say about yourself?” [23] He said, “I am the voice of one crying out in the wilderness, ‘Make straight the way of the Lord,’ as the prophet Isaiah said.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 3:2 says, “repent for the kingdom of heaven is at hand.” This is John’s gospel message. It is also Jesus’ gospel message (Matthew 4:17) and it is also the disciples’ Gospel message (Matthew 10:2). Note the gospel message is not “believe in me so you can live however you want and still go to heaven when you die”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repent means return to God, literally it means to turn around and go the other direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kingdom of heaven, as interpreted by Rabbi Lichtenstein is “both the external state where Messiah reigns over the whole earth and the internal state of the individual who is forgiven and spiritually regenerated by the LORD.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is at hand – the kingdom messianic age is about to begin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All four gospels say that John’s ministry fulfills Isaiah 40:3. The Isaiah passage begins with “comfort, comfort my people” (40:1) and then goes into the voice of one crying in the wilderness (40:3). God’s Comfort is here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism and its Jewish predecessor immersion in a Mikveh carries a tie to ritual cleanliness and confession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the firstborn son of a priest, John should have been serving in the temple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was either disenfranchised and pushed out by the corruption, or he voluntarily withdrew because he wanted nothing to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bible does not tell us that he abandoned his priestly obligations, so we need to be cautious with inferring this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do have some suggestion that John affiliated with another group of disaffected priests known as the Essenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Essenes lived at Qumron and are presumed to be the authors of the dead sea scrolls. Qumron is located in the Judean Wilderness on the Northwestern shore of the Dead Sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They opposed the sold-out, corrupted, Rome-loving, Hasmonean and Sadducean priesthood of Jerusalem.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholars debate whether he was formally an Essene, merely was familiar with the Essenes and shared some similarities, or was not affiliated with them in any way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster writes, “John and his disciples are associated with, and at points, endorsed by the Pharisees; this would not have happened if John were a known Essene.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His attire alludes to Elijah&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2Ki 1:8 They answered him, “He wore a garment of hair, with a belt of leather about his waist.” And he said, “It is Elijah the Tishbite.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Jordan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is the area of, and perhaps the exact location where Moses called the nation to make a covenant with the LORD and Joshua crossed the river and lead Israel into the promised land.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Locusts &amp;amp; wild honey&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke 7:33 reminds us John was a Nazirite from birth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“John entrusted himself solely to God for his daily needs,”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which is reminiscent of the Israelites in the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deu 29:5-6 I have led you forty years in the wilderness. Your clothes have not worn out on you, and your sandals have not worn off your feet. [6] You have not eaten bread, and you have not drunk wine or strong drink, that you may know that I am the LORD your God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Locusts could be insects or it could be carob pods from the locust tree, a tree that would have been available in parts of the Judean wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honey could refer to the syrup of dates and figs in addition to bee honey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John exemplified Jesus’ teaching on “do not be worried about what you will eat or drink” (Matthew 6:25)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His attire alludes to Elijah&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John wore clothing that was not purchased in the markets of Jerusalem. John’s dress reminded the people of the prophet Elijah, who wore a garment of hair (2 Kgs Mark 1:8). Indeed, John came in the spirit and power of Elijah to warn of impending judgment before the Lord’s appearance (Mal 3:1-6; 4:5-6).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-specimen-of-johns-preaching&#34;&gt;A specimen of John’s preaching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 34%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 65%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mat 3:7-10&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Luk 3:7-14&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.7&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;7 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But when he saw many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming to his baptism, he said to them, “You brood of vipers! Who warned you to flee from the wrath to come?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.8&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;8 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Bear fruit in keeping with repentance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.9&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;9 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And do not presume to say to yourselves, ‘We have Abraham as our father,’ for I tell you, God is able from these stones to raise up children for Abraham.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.10&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;10 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Even now the axe is laid to the root of the trees. Every tree therefore that does not bear good fruit is cut down and thrown into the fire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.7&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;7 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; He said therefore to the crowds that came out to be baptized by him, “You brood of vipers! Who warned you to flee from the wrath to come?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.8&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;8 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Bear fruits in keeping with repentance. And do not begin to say to yourselves, ‘We have Abraham as our father.’ For I tell you, God is able from these stones to raise up children for Abraham.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.9&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;9 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Even now the axe is laid to the root of the trees. Every tree therefore that does not bear good fruit is cut down and thrown into the fire.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.10&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;10 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And the crowds asked him, “What then shall we do?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.11&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;11 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And he answered them, “Whoever has two tunics is to share with him who has none, and whoever has food is to do likewise.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.12&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;12 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Tax collectors also came to be baptized and said to him, “Teacher, what shall we do?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.13&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;13 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And he said to them, “Collect no more than you are authorized to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.14&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;14 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Soldiers also asked him, “And we, what shall we do?” And he said to them, “Do not extort money from anyone by threats or by false accusation, and be content with your wages.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the seeker-friendly message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus will have a lot to say about bearing fruit during His ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We say it often, but our works matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t do good works to get saved; we do good works because we already are saved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A healthy fruit tree will bear fruit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are saved, there should be evidence of good works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By saying “Bear fruit in keeping with repentance” John is confirming that immersion must be an outward expression of an inward change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He didn’t see any fruit of an inward change, so he refused to permit the outward expression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Matthew mentioning Pharisees and Sadducees we might get the impression that John is rejecting the religious and allowing sinners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why there is value of comparing passages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke makes it clear that John rejected ANYONE who was unrepentant, whether they were in vocational ministry or everyday folk such as soldiers and common folk, or vocational sinners such as tax-collectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 21:32 also references John ministering to prostitutes, which can include “fallen women” for any reason not limited to sex for hire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He did not single out just the religious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What he is likely railing against here is what we might call “cheap grace.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back when the golden calf incident happened, God was ready to wipe the people out, Moses ”reminded” God of his promises to Abraham and God relented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this, it became fashionable to rely on their familial connection to righteous Abraham to cover up sins in much the same way that Christians invoke the atoning sacrifice of Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is when they invoke Abraham, or we invoke Jesus to exonerate us from personal responsibility.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing we will note is the old adage whenever you point a finger at someone, there are three fingers pointing back at you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we do this today? Do we ever say “well, I’m saved by Jesus so I’m forgiven”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we say that from a posture of contrition and repentance it’s absolutely true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we say it as an excuse to keep on sinning WITHOUT repenting, then it’s a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What shall we do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After shooting painfully straight with his audience the faithful asked “what then shall we do?” There’s hope in this. None of us are beyond the father’s reach&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John prescribes acts of lovingkindness, called chesed in Hebrew; these deeds achieve the spirit of the commandment to love one’s neighbor as one’s self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of note, John allowed them to stay in their occupations provided they conduct their lives with the highest standards of ethics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The soldiers here are unlikely to be Roman soldiers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John’s ministry did not extend to gentiles and Romans would have had no interest in anything Jewish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given where he was (Perea), the soldiers were likely employed by Herod Antipas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These stones&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Joshua 4, God commanded stones of rememberance be placed to mark the moment where Israel was consecrated and crossed in to inherit the promised land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hebrew, the words for “stones” and “sons” only differ by one letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A possible point could be a warning for them to not rely on cheap grace. In other words, “don’t fool yourselves. There are plenty of genuinely repentant righteous people who produce good fruit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also a sense could be “be like the original generation who crossed at this location by faith.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Judaism, a gentile convert receives the title “Son of Abraham.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-forerunners-picture-of-the-messiah-before-seeing-him&#34;&gt;The forerunner&amp;rsquo;s picture of the Messiah before seeing Him&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 17%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 12%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 26%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 43%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mat 3:11-12&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mar 1:7-8&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Luk 3:15-18&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Joh 1:19-28&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.11&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;11 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; “I baptize you with water for repentance, but he who is coming after me is mightier than I, whose sandals I am not worthy to carry. He will baptize you with the Holy Spirit and fire.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.7&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;7 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And he preached, saying, “After me comes he who is mightier than I, the strap of whose sandals I am not worthy to stoop down and untie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.8&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;8 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I have baptized you with water, but he will baptize you with the Holy Spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.15&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;15 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; As the people were in expectation, and all were questioning in their hearts concerning John, whether he might be the Christ,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.16&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;16 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; John answered them all, saying, “I baptize you with water, but he who is mightier than I is coming, the strap of whose sandals I am not worthy to untie. He will baptize you with the Holy Spirit and fire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joh 1:19-28 And this is the testimony of John, when the Jews sent priests and Levites from Jerusalem to ask him, “Who are you?” [20] He confessed, and did not deny, but confessed, “I am not the Christ.” [21] And they asked him, “What then? Are you Elijah?” He said, “I am not.” “Are you the Prophet?” And he answered, “No.” [22] So they said to him, “Who are you? We need to give an answer to those who sent us. What do you say about yourself?” [23] He said, “I am the voice of one crying out in the wilderness, ‘Make straight the way of the Lord,’ as the prophet Isaiah said.” [24] (Now they had been sent from the Pharisees.) [25] They asked him, “Then why are you baptizing, if you are neither the Christ, nor Elijah, nor the Prophet?” [26] John answered them, “I baptize with water, but among you stands one you do not know, [27] even he who comes after me, the strap of whose sandal I am not worthy to untie.” [28] These things took place in Bethany across the Jordan, where John was baptizing.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John’s message was that the Messianic Age was about to commence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This naturally led some to wonder whether John was the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In John 1:20, he says that he is not the messiah but is the forerunner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shoes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Talmud records, “a disciple must render to his teacher all the service that a slave renders to his master except that of loosening his shoe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John is saying “I’m not even worthy to be regarded as Jesus’ slave.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water vs Holy Spirit and fire&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrival of Messiah has two different implications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the believers who repent and bear fruit (the righteous), Jesus brings an immersion in the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the unbelievers who don’t repent and don’t bear fruit (the wicked), the coming of Messiah brings judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book of Proverbs is our go-to reference when we study the righteous versus the wicked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the righteous, as it is today with Christian baptism, water is an outward sign that symbolizes spiritual regeneration in the Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus Jesus says in John 3:5, “Truly, truly, I say to you, unless one is born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter the kingdom of God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 29%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 35%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 34%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matthew 3:12&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Luke 3:17-18&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Reference&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.12&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;12 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; His winnowing fork is in his hand, and he will clear his threshing floor and gather his wheat into the barn, but the chaff he will burn with unquenchable fire.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.17&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;17 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; His winnowing fork is in his hand, to clear his threshing floor and to gather the wheat into his barn, but the chaff he will burn with unquenchable fire.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.18&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;18 &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; So with many other exhortations he preached good news to the people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Mal 4:1&lt;/sup&gt; “For behold, the day is coming, burning like an oven, when all the arrogant and all evildoers will be stubble. The day that is coming shall set them ablaze, says the LORD of hosts, so that it will leave them neither root nor branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Mal 4:5-6&lt;/sup&gt; “Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the great and awesome day of the LORD comes. [6] And he will turn the hearts of fathers to their children and the hearts of children to their fathers, lest I come and strike the land with a decree of utter destruction.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that day they would take a tool like a pitchfork and toss the kernels up into the air. The heavier seed would drop into one pile and the lighter chaff would be carried downwind into a separate pile. This was usually done on a plateau called a threshing floor. At the end the seeds would be gathered into a barn or a storehouse, and the chaff would be burned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew and Luke develop this theme of spirit vs fire with a quick one-verse parable, which we may call “the winnower, the wheat, and the chaff.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winnowing fork = instrument of Messiah’s judgment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winnower’s hand = Messiah&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Threshing floor = Land of Israel/or the world&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barn = the Kingdom of Heaven&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wheat = repentant righteous&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chaff = unrepentant wicked - The image of the wicked as chaff is common in the Old Testament (Ps 1:4; Isa 40:24; Dan 2:35).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meaning: Messiah is coming to punish the wicked and reward the righteous. I, John, am bringing you this good news and therefore begging each of you to repent and do works of righteousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, John is the fulfillment (at least partially) of Malachi 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many believe Elijah himself is one of the two witnesses in Revelation 11, at which time Malachi’s prophecy would be completely fulfilled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John’s mission was to call God’s people to repentance and right behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, it’s as if John is saying, “you can &lt;em&gt;tell&lt;/em&gt; me you’re repentant, but you need to prove it to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When things are going well it&amp;rsquo;s easy to trick ourselves into thinking that God must be really proud of our piety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all must turn to God for our provision. Again we don’t do good works to get saved, we do good works and bear good fruit because we are saved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fruit of repentance is a life of good deeds that reflect our love for God and our love for our neighbors, just as Jesus instructs his disciples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bibliography&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, Todd. “Matthew 3.” PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, D. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by Boaz Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster. 2nd ed. Vol. 3. 6 vols. Torah Club. Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schlegel, William. “The Land and the Bible: A Historical Geographical Companion to the Satellite Bible Atlas,” September 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, Todd. “Luke 3.” PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener, Craig S. The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament. 2nd edition. Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, D. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by Boaz Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster. 2nd ed. Vol. 3. 6 vols. Torah Club. Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schlegel, William. “The Land and the Bible: A Historical Geographical Companion to the Satellite Bible Atlas,” September 2015. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———. The Satellite Bible Atlas by William Schlegel. Israel: William Schlegel, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern, David H. Jewish New Testament Commentary: A Companion Volume to the Jewish New Testament. Reprint edition. Clarksville, Md.: Lederer Messianic Publications, 1992.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor, Aubrey L. “Ministry in the Wilderness.” In Lexham Geographic Commentary on the Gospels, edited by Barry J. Beitzel. Bellingham, WA: Lexham Press, 2017&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;archived-video&#34;&gt;Archived Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C63y8Qq--lc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/john_the_immerser.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/john_the_immerser.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_voice_in_the_wilderness_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_voice_in_the_wilderness_1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William Schlegel, “The Land and the Bible: A Historical Geographical Companion to the Satellite Bible Atlas,” September 2013, 159, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. Thomas Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Boaz Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster, 2nd ed., vol. 3, Torah Club (Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014), 151.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 3:152.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 3:149.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 3:162–63.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 3:167.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, “Matthew 3” (PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), 82.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7. Immersion and Temptation</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb07/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In IMMERSION AND TEMPTATION, we briefly return to &lt;strong&gt;Nazareth&lt;/strong&gt;. More than two decades have elapsed since we last visited. Yeshua is no longer a precocious twelve-year-old boy; he is a grown man who has taken over His father Joseph’s carpenter trade. From Nazareth, we follow Yeshua’s family to the plains of the &lt;strong&gt;Jordan&lt;/strong&gt;, across from Jericho, where John the Immerser is at work, proclaiming the good news and immersing for repentance&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. After His immersion, we follow Yeshua out into the dry and waterless &lt;strong&gt;Judean&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Wilderness&lt;/strong&gt; between &lt;strong&gt;Jerusalem&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Jericho&lt;/strong&gt; where He spends forty days in prayer and fasting, concluding with His three temptations.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passages&lt;/strong&gt;: Matthew 3:13-4:11 (Mark 1:9-13, Luke 3:21-23, 4:1-13; John 1:29-34)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QMquTSUkTGE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#geography&#34;&gt;Geography:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#jesus-baptized-by-john-in-the-jordan&#34;&gt;Jesus baptized by John in the Jordan&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fulfill-all-righteousness&#34;&gt;Fulfill all Righteousness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-spirit-like-a-dove&#34;&gt;The Spirit like a Dove&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-three-temptations-of-jesus&#34;&gt;The three temptations of Jesus&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#into-the-wilderness&#34;&gt;Into the wilderness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#first-temptation-stone-to-bread&#34;&gt;First temptation: stone to bread&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#second-temptation-throw-yourself-down&#34;&gt;Second temptation: throw yourself down&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#third-temptation-all-the-kingdoms-of-the-world-if-you-bow&#34;&gt;Third temptation: all the kingdoms of the world if you bow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#worship-me&#34;&gt;Worship me&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion-the-devil-departs&#34;&gt;Conclusion: the devil departs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#lessons-from-the-temptations&#34;&gt;Lessons from the Temptations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#following-the-messiah-link&#34;&gt;Following the Messiah link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;geography&#34;&gt;Geography:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.png&#34; style=&#34;width:90%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This map&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; traces Jesus’ early ministry, including leaving Nazareth to be baptized by John (Mark 1:9) leading to His baptism in the Jordan (box 1), followed by His temptation in the Judean wilderness (box 2). We don’t know exactly where (or when) Jesus was baptized. Because of a few references, including the apparent proximity to Jerusalem (Mark 1:5) and the reference to “these stones” in the Luke and Matthew accounts suggest opposite Jericho near (or quite probably at) the location where Joshua led the Israelites across in Joshua 4. This site is marked by a traditional holy site today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not disputing a southern location for Jesus’ baptism, some scholars, including William Schlegel the publisher of this map, contend “Bethany beyond the Jordan” is not located across from Jericho but much further north in the Golan Heights (marked by box 3 on the map). They point out that it does not say that Jesus was baptized at Bethany; but in John’s gospel, it appears as if John is recollecting Jesus’ baptism which occurred at least 40 days earlier and in a different location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aubrey Taylor has noted that in the same region where Moses commissioned Joshua, and Elijah commissioned Elisha, Jesus receives a similar commission from John.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image2.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:75%&#34; alt=&#34;J:\Bethany\Matson15k1\Jordan River\Jordan River, mat23194.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:75%&#34; alt=&#34;Jordan River by Bethany beyond Jordan, tb060303267&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The photo on the top&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is a colorized version of an American Colony photograph taken between 1896 and 1946. The photo on the bottom&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is the same area today. The most significant issue in that part of the world, since ancient times and continues today is water rights. Before 1948 the area was sparsely populated. After 1948 with the founding of both the modern states of Israel as well as Jordan, the area began to grow, and all those new people needed food and food requires water from the Jordan river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;jesus-baptized-by-john-in-the-jordan&#34;&gt;Jesus baptized by John in the Jordan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 3:13-15&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mar 1:9&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John 1:29-31&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Then Jesus came from Galilee to the Jordan to John, to be baptized by him. John would have prevented him, saying, “I need to be baptized by you, and do you come to me?” But Jesus answered him, “Let it be so now, for thus it is fitting for us to fulfill all righteousness.” Then he consented.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In those days Jesus came from Nazareth of Galilee and was baptized by John in the Jordan.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The next day he saw Jesus coming toward him, and said, “Behold, the Lamb of God, who takes away the sin of the world! This is he of whom I said, ‘After me comes a man who ranks before me, because he was before me.’ I myself did not know him, but for this purpose I came baptizing with water, that he might be revealed to Israel.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it’s only a few verses in our Bibles, we need to remember that John and Jesus had probably never met until this day (and unlikely that John would remember doing a somersault in his mother Elizabeth’s womb over 30 years earlier); however, John 1:31 could also be interpreted that John initially did not recognize that Jesus was the Messiah, not that they were entirely unfamiliar with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, by now, we presume Joseph has died and Jesus has been left in charge of Mary and Jesus’ many siblings. John apparently recognized Jesus as soon as they saw each other and makes a Passover allusion to the sacrificial lamb and Isaiah 53:7: He was oppressed, and he was afflicted, yet he opened not his mouth; like a lamb that is led to the slaughter, and like a sheep that before its shearers is silent, so he opened not his mouth. John is certainly foreshadowing Jesus’ suffering and crucifixion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster paraphrases Matthew 3:14 as, “I need to be baptized by you WITH THE HOLY SPIRIT, yet you come to me to be baptized with water?”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fulfill-all-righteousness&#34;&gt;Fulfill all Righteousness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, Jesus Himself did not need to be baptized for his sins, so what does Jesus mean by “fulfilling all righteousness?” Keener notes that Jesus’ response indicates his identification with Israel in obedience to the Law and by extension, larger humanity who DID need purification&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. To fulfill all righteousness means it’s the proper way of doing things in the proper order. A prophet in the spirit and power of Elijah must arise, identify, declare, and anoint the Messiah (who must of course allow Himself to be anointed). By being baptized by John, Jeremy Dehut in Following the Messiah Jesus “testified to the authenticity and authority of John’s message and continued providing an example of faithful submission.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few lessons back we looked at how the verse “out of Egypt I have called my son” exemplifies how Jesus mirrors the nation. As we will see in the next section, Jesus’ 40-day fast recalls Israel’s 40 years in the wilderness. Just as God sustained Israel in the wilderness so He sustained Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we get to the question of why a Sinless Jesus would need a baptism of repentance, we must remember that Jesus is a perfect representative of the nation, just as He is a perfect and sinless representative of humankind. As a representative of Israel, Jesus “passes through the waters of the Jordan” just like the Nation did. His “repentance” (so to speak) represented the “corporate guilt and confession”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of His people. Taylor goes on to say that Jesus’ temptations can also be viewed in light of this representative role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-spirit-like-a-dove&#34;&gt;The Spirit like a Dove&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 17%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 16%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 25%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 17%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 23%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 3:16-17&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mar 1:9-11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luk 3:21-23&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John 1:32-34&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.16&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And when Jesus was baptized, immediately he went up from the water, and behold, the heavens were opened to him, and he saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove and coming to rest on him;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.17&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;17&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; and behold, a voice from heaven said, “This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.10&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And when he came up out of the water, immediately he saw the heavens being torn open and the Spirit descending on him like a dove.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.11&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And a voice came from heaven, “You are my beloved Son; with you I am well pleased.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.21&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;21&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Now when all the people were baptized, and when Jesus also had been baptized and was praying, the heavens were opened,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.22&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;22&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; and the Holy Spirit descended on him in bodily form, like a dove; and a voice came from heaven, “You are my beloved Son; with you I am well pleased.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.23&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;23&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Jesus, when he began his ministry, was about thirty years of age, being the son (as was supposed) of Joseph, the son of Heli,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;And John bore witness: “I saw the Spirit descend from heaven like a dove, and it remained on him. I myself did not know him, but he who sent me to baptize with water said to me, ‘He on whom you see the Spirit descend and remain, this is he who baptizes with the Holy Spirit.’ And I have seen and have borne witness that this is the Son of God.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Psalm 2:7&lt;/sup&gt; I will tell of the decree: The LORD said to me, “You are my Son; today I have begotten you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Gen 22:2&lt;/sup&gt; He said, “Take your son, your only son Isaac, whom you love, and go to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering on one of the mountains of which I shall tell you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Isa 11:2&lt;/sup&gt; And the Spirit of the LORD shall rest upon him, the Spirit of wisdom and understanding, the Spirit of counsel and might, the Spirit of knowledge and the fear of the LORD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Isa 42:1&lt;/sup&gt; Behold my servant, whom I uphold, my chosen, in whom my soul delights; I have put my Spirit upon him; he will bring forth justice to the nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image4.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:60%; float:right&#34; /&gt;When I visited Israel in February 2013, I took this picture of a pair of doves at Jesus’ traditional baptism site. I wonder if they were only there for the tourists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that day many believed that God had gone silent. So, the heavens opening and the spirit poured out indicated that the Messianic era had arrived. John earlier proclaimed, “the kingdom of heaven is at hand” (Mat 3:1). “A kingdom needs a king and a messianic era needs a messiah.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God’s voice and John’s prophetic testimony are the two witnesses required to establish a matter; in this case, the stamp of approval on Jesus as Messiah. The Spirit would signify that the Messianic era is at hand. The spirit resting on Jesus could be an allusion to Genesis 1, where the Spirit of God moved over the surface of the waters, and Genesis 8, where the dove flew out over the waters and, finding no other place to land, came to “rest” on Noah (noach means rest in Hebrew). Despite our impression of doves as docile and peaceful, they are notoriously territorial. Lancaster writes, “His disciples probably understood Him to mean a sudden, startling rush of wind – only slightly less jarring than being struck by lightning.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My beloved son” could also be read as “my son, the beloved” or even “my son, whom I love” which also recalls Genesis 22 when Abraham is told “take your son, your only son Isaac, whom you love and go to the land of Moriah and offer him there as a burnt offering”. Isaac is a type or a foreshadow of Jesus who would be sacrificed, thus Lancaster notes in apostolic theology, the “beloved one” becomes a title for the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this seems to highlight the messianic prophecy of Isaiah 11:2 “And the spirit of the LORD shall rest upon Him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke 3:23 says Jesus was “about 30” when He began His ministry. We should not take this to mean exactly 30. The precise date of one’s birth was not especially relevant in the ancient world. Lancaster supposes that this is 28 CE, which if he was born in 5 or 6 BCE makes Jesus 34 years old here and then 36 years old when he died. According to Jewish tradition, Isaac was also 36 at the time of his binding on the altar in Genesis 22.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-three-temptations-of-jesus&#34;&gt;The three temptations of Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;into-the-wilderness&#34;&gt;Into the wilderness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 35%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 4:1-2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mar 1:12-13a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luk 4:1-2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.1&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4:1&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Then Jesus was led up by the Spirit into the wilderness to be tempted by the devil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.2&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And after fasting forty days and forty nights, he was hungry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.12&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; The Spirit immediately drove him out into the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.13&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And he was in the wilderness forty days, being tempted by Satan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.4.1&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4:1&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And Jesus, full of the Holy Spirit, returned from the Jordan and was led by the Spirit in the wilderness&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.4.2&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; for forty days, being tempted by the devil. And he ate nothing during those days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image5.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:80%&#34; /&gt;Bolen writes, “Because of its lack of water and good routes, the Judean wilderness&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; has been (mostly) uninhabited throughout history. Consequently, it was an ideal place for those seeking refuge from enemies or retreat from the world. John the Baptist preached here, and it seems likely that this was the wilderness where Jesus was tempted.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener writes, “Jesus was led into the wilderness just as Israel was led. Just as Moses fasted for 40/40, so did Jesus.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In fact, Mark 1:12 emphatically says the spirit forcibly drove Jesus out into the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is a shadow of both Moses and Israel. They were tested and God sustained them all. Jesus passed the test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Christian traditions observe lent, where we abstain from certain pleasures, if not do a partial fast for 40 days between Ash Wednesday and Resurrection story. We do this in honor of Jesus’ 40 days in the wilderness. Jewish people similarly observe 40 days of Teshuva (“repentance”) which recalls the 40 years wandering in the wilderness (which is said to be one year for every day the spies were in the land). This concludes with Yom Kippur (Day of Atonement) which is a day of national fasting. Lancaster says, “Jewish liturgy treats the Day of Atonement as a day for dealing with Satan and his accusations. The liturgies of the day are filled with references to a legal showdown between Israel and the devil, which concludes with the scape goat being led out into the wilderness, symbolizing the defeat of evil.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-temptation-stone-to-bread&#34;&gt;First temptation: stone to bread&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 35%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 4:3-4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luk 4:3-4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.3&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And the tempter came and said to him, “If you are the Son of God, command these stones to become loaves of bread.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.4&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; But he answered, “It is written, “‘Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that comes from the mouth of God.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3 The devil said to him, “If you are the Son of God, command this stone to become bread.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 And Jesus answered him, “It is written, ‘Man shall not live by bread alone.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Deu 8:3&lt;/sup&gt; And he humbled you and let you hunger and fed you with manna, which you did not know, nor did your fathers know, that he might make you know that man does not live by bread alone, but man lives by every word that comes from the mouth of the LORD.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.34792in&#34; alt=&#34;C:\Users\Todd\Desktop\Files\sr pics\photobiblesr\Ascent of Adumim Roman road remains, tb113006722.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This photograph was taken in the Judean Wilderness, along the Ascent of Adummim, between Jericho and Jerusalem.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholars debate the moment in time when Jesus came to the full realization of His mission and destiny. Many speculate that it was at His baptism that the spirit descended. Lancaster speculates that the Satan’s temptations were an attempt to force Yeshua to question the revelation He just received. Maybe like in some movie where a normal person is given some superhuman ability, the Satan believes Jesus has the desire to try out His new superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three temptations will involve shortcuts to revealing His messianic identity and plan. Remember the phrase Jesus uses frequently between now and the triumphal entry: “My hour is not net come”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the first temptation is declaring that Jesus indeed trusts that revelation that He heard come from the mouth of the LORD. He did not need to prove it. Let’s break it down some more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Satan begins with “If you are the son of God.” One of the main limitations of the written word is that we have to use our imaginations with respect to voice inflection and body language. Did the Satan say this scoffingly, inquisitively, or matter-of-factly? Since the Satan is the accuser, it’s not too difficult to imagine him taunting Jesus with this challenge. “Since we know God made manna from heaven in the wilderness if you are that God, you should be able to do the same thing in this wilderness. And by the way, I know you are hungry. Why don’t you just go ahead and fix yourself something to eat.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus declines the invitation to demonstrate His messianic power. He will do it on His terms and in His timing. Jesus WILL provide bread, but it will be food for the people, not for Himself. He will serve others, not Himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is the Word and the Bread of Life who has come down from heaven. He quotes Deuteronomy 8:3, which is a passage about how “God tested Israel in the wilderness by causing them to hunger and feeding them with manna.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Physical bread will temporarily relieve hunger but the Bread of Life, the very Words of God will cure spiritual hunger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first temptation is declaring that Jesus indeed trusts that revelation that He heard come from the mouth of the LORD. He did not need to prove it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-temptation-throw-yourself-down&#34;&gt;Second temptation: throw yourself down&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 23%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 26%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 4:5-7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luk 4:9-12&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.5&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Then the devil took him to the holy city and set him on the pinnacle of the temple&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.6&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; and said to him, “If you are the Son of God, throw yourself down, for it is written, “‘He will command his angels concerning you,’ and “‘On their hands they will bear you up, lest you strike your foot against a stone.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.7&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Jesus said to him, “Again it is written, ‘You shall not put the Lord your God to the test.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;9 And he took him to Jerusalem and set him on the pinnacle of the temple and said to him, “If you are the Son of God, throw yourself down from here,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 for it is written, “‘He will command his angels concerning you, to guard you,’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 and “‘On their hands they will bear you up, lest you strike your foot against a stone.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12 And Jesus answered him, “It is said, ‘You shall not put the Lord your God to the test.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Psa 91:11-14 For he will command his angels concerning you to guard you in all your ways. [12] On their hands they will bear you up, lest you strike your foot against a stone. [13] You will tread on the lion and the adder; the young lion and the serpent you will trample underfoot. [14] “Because he holds fast to me in love, I will deliver him; I will protect him, because he knows my name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deu 6:13-16 It is the LORD your God you shall fear. Him you shall serve and by his name you shall swear. [14] You shall not go after other gods, the gods of the peoples who are around you— [15] for the LORD your God in your midst is a jealous God—lest the anger of the LORD your God be kindled against you, and he destroy you from off the face of the earth. [16] “You shall not put the LORD your God to the test, as you tested him at Massah.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we compare Matthew and Luke side-by-side we see that Luke reverses the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; and 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; temptations. Some may view this as the Gospel authors being unable to keep their stories straight, but another way of looking at it is that this demonstrates a lack of coordination and collusion among the authors. If one witness in a trial recalls she heard a dog bark and then a car horn, but another witness recalls she heard a car horn then a dog bark, we don’t typically assume one or the other is lying. It’s just a different recollection. The differences between Matthew and Luke are not significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is more significant is that leaping from a tall building is not typically a temptation to most people. The next matter is that before they were in the wilderness and now all of a sudden they are in Jerusalem. Scholars debate as to whether this is a vision, or whether they were supernaturally transported. I tend to vote against the vision. The leap has to be potentially fatal for the miracle the Satan is proposing to actually be miraculous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a photo of the southeastern corner of the Temple Mount.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The drop today is likely fatal but 2000 years ago, the Kidron valley below was much steeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image7.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:60%&#34; alt=&#34;C:\Users\Todd\Desktop\Files\sr pics\photobiblesr\Temple Mount southeastern corner, pinnacle, tb051908162.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a reminder that the Satan knows Scripture and he is an expert at making arguments. We need to be like Jesus and know the “whole council” of God so we don’t take Bible passages out of context, and don’t fall for it when others try to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Satan says, “look here. God says He will send His Psalm 91 angels to protect you.” Psalm 91 is a messianic passage (and the Satan knows this). Psalm 91 is a great passage and one we all would do well to memorize and rely on. However, a Tzaddiq (a righteous one) such as Jesus would have known that angelic protection is for ills that befall God’s servants, not for those who foolishly seek out danger. Therefore, we must know our Bible, and therefore we are going through the Gospels verse by verse in this series!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus counters with another passage from Deuteronomy. Note the context of “you shall not test the Lord” is not merely doing something foolish/sinful and asking God to make it right. The context is following after other gods spiritually. When we listen to the lies of the Satan, we are following after a false god. (ouch).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The testing at Massah refers to Exodus 17:7: And he called the name of the place Massah and Meribah, because of the quarreling of the people of Israel, and because they tested the LORD by saying, “Is the LORD among us or not?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-temptation-all-the-kingdoms-of-the-world-if-you-bow&#34;&gt;Third temptation: all the kingdoms of the world if you bow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 35%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 4:8-10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke 4:5-8&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.8&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Again, the devil took him to a very high mountain and showed him all the kingdoms of the world and their glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.9&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And he said to him, “All these I will give you, if you will fall down and worship me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.10&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Then Jesus said to him, “Be gone, Satan! For it is written, “‘You shall worship the Lord your God and him only shall you serve.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5 And the devil took him up and showed him all the kingdoms of the world in a moment of time,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 and said to him, “To you I will give all this authority and their glory, for it has been delivered to me, and I give it to whom I will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 If you, then, will worship me, it will all be yours.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 And Jesus answered him, “It is written, “‘You shall worship the Lord your God, and him only shall you serve.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 6:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Satan apparently is now convinced of Jesus’ messianic credentials, now offers Him a shortcut to usher in the Messianic Kingdom. Satan also likely knew the people were hoping for a conquering, military messiah. Here was a chance for Jesus to be this and skip all of that cross business. This might also be the Satan’s plea bargain; we make a deal here and I don’t go to the lake of fire later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writer to Hebrews reminds us that Jesus “has been tempted in all things as we are, yet without sin” (Hebrews 4:15). As Missler used to quip, “If I offer to sell you the Brooklyn Bridge, are you tempted to buy it from me? Probably not, because you are relatively certain that I don’t own it. For this to be a valid temptation, that means Jesus is acknowledging that Satan has ownership of these things, and they truly are his to give away. Jesus doesn’t challenge Satan’s ownership.” One of the many subthemes in the Bible is what I might call “things out of place.” We opened the Gospels with King Herod ruling over the land, who was neither born king nor born Jewish. Herod’s power and riches were juxtaposed against the rightful king who came lowly in a cave surrounded by deplorable shepherds. In the last lesson, we saw John the Baptist, the son of Zechariah who officiated in the temple in Jerusalem. John, a Levite, should have been in Jerusalem at the temple but instead, we find him “exiled” to the wilderness, while the usurping Sadducees are running the Temple. Here, the world that rightly belongs to God is under the authority of the Satan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t know which mountain. Mt. Nebo would have been nearby in the wilderness. Mt. Nebo is where Moses surveyed the land. Others have suggested Mt. Hermon in the far north of Israel and is the highest peak in the land of Israel. Mt. Hermon is intriguing because of its association with demonic activity in antiquity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;worship-me&#34;&gt;Worship me&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Satan said, “worship me,” he wasn’t necessarily asking Jesus to change His mind and start following Satan with His whole heart (although he certainly could have been). During the days of the seven churches in Revelation, Rome generally let people, particularly Jews, practice their religion without interference (depending on who was in charge). But often what they had to do was, one day a year, offer a sacrifice to the emperor. In the seven letters, Jesus sternly chides those who are compromising in this way. This is still idolatry, no matter how seemingly insignificant the idolatrous act is. Conversely, Jesus lavishly praises those in Smyrna and other cities who kept themselves pure from idolatry. In fact, the Bible uses an interesting metaphor for idolatry: adultery. Idolatry is spiritual fornication and unfaithfulness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a story of a mother who caught her child doing something and the response was “mom, I only did it once and it was only a little. I’m ok.” A few days later the mom made a batch of brownies and the son of course got very excited. He took one bite and the happiness immediately gagged. “What’s wrong honey,” said the mom. “These taste awful,” said the son. “What happened?” “Hmm that’s strange,” said the mom. “I only put a little bit of dog poo in the brownies. Not even a teaspoon. They should be ok.” Point made. Jesus demands complete purity. There will come a day when Jesus will take proper possession of the things of the earth that are currently in the hands of the usurper. There will be no shortcuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion-the-devil-departs&#34;&gt;Conclusion: the devil departs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 4:11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mar 1:13b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luk 4:13&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.11&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Then the devil left him, and behold, angels came and were ministering to him.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13 And he was with the wild animals, and the angels were ministering to him.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13 And when the devil had ended every temptation, he departed from him until an opportune time.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark and Luke give us interesting tidbits. Mark says he was with the wild animals and Luke says the devil departed until “an opportune time.” We infer that opportune time was at the Garden of Gethsemane. The animals underscore the point that Jesus was completely isolated. Satan often likes to attack us when we are isolated from other believers. The photo shows the Ibex, a type of wild goat that is common in the Judean wilderness.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image8.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.32222in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-from-the-temptations&#34;&gt;Lessons from the Temptations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus concludes each test the way any good rabbi would; He makes an appeal to Scripture. “As it is written…” should be a phrase we as Talmidim begin to use frequently as we continue to learn to be imitators of Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three temptations parallel the warning given in 1 John 2:15-17: Do not love the world or the things in the world. If anyone loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him. For all that is in the world—the desires of the flesh and the desires of the eyes and pride of life—is not from the Father but is from the world. And the world is passing away along with its desires, but whoever does the will of God abides forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bread – desire of the flesh&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kingdoms – desire of the eyes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw yourself down and angels will save – pride of life&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Satan is basically recycling the approach he used in the Garden: “So when the woman saw that the tree was good for food (flesh), and that it was a delight to the eyes (eyes), and that the tree was to be desired to make one wise (pride of life), she took of its fruit and ate, and she also gave some to her husband who was with her, and he ate” (Gen 3:6).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first Adam couldn’t resist the temptation, but the Last Adam did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;following-the-messiah-link&#34;&gt;Following the Messiah link&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Episode 3 of the “Following the Messiah” series covers the Baptism and Temptation of Jesus. It is very much worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ytb4DkglxRc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Immersion&lt;/em&gt;, accessed October 21, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_immersion_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_immersion_1.html&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Three Temptations&lt;/em&gt;, accessed October 21, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/three_temptations_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/three_temptations_1.html&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William Schlegel, &lt;em&gt;The Satellite Bible Atlas&lt;/em&gt; (Israel: William Schlegel, 2013), 119.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aubrey L. Taylor, “Wilderness Events: The Baptism and Temptations of Jesus,” in &lt;em&gt;Lexham Geographic Commentary on the Gospels&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Barry J Beitzel (Bellingham, WA: Lexham Press, 2017), 56.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo: Todd Bolen, “Mark 1” (PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), fig. mat23194.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo: Bolen, fig. tb060303267.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. Thomas Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Boaz Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster, 2nd ed., vol. 3, Torah Club (Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014), 183.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig S. Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition (E-Sword) (Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014), loc. Mat 3:15.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jesus’ Was Tempted by the Devil! Following the Messiah: Ep 3&lt;/em&gt;, 2017, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ytb4DkglxRc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ytb4DkglxRc&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor, “Wilderness Events: The Baptism and Temptations of Jesus,” 58.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, 3:183.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 3:185.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, “Luke 4” (PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), fig. tb010703286.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, “Luke 4.”&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary&lt;/em&gt;, loc. Luk 4:1.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, 3:192.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, “Luke 4,” fig. tb113006722.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, 3:195.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, “Matthew 4” (PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), fig. tb051908162.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, “Mark 1,” fig. tb021906258.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
