<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Revelation Backgrounds | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Revelation Backgrounds</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu53652e90a6e4e4f125f22da2a993ec10_403021_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Revelation Backgrounds</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>1. Revelation Introduction</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/revelation-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/revelation-introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#revelation-not-revelations&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Revelation&amp;rdquo; (not &amp;ldquo;Revelations&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-apocalyptic-literature&#34;&gt;What is &amp;ldquo;Apocalyptic Literature&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#seven-keys-to-interpretation&#34;&gt;Seven Keys to Interpretation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1-follow-the-talmidim-way&#34;&gt;#1 Follow the &amp;ldquo;Talmidim Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#2-be-open-to-the-spirits-leading&#34;&gt;#2 Be open to the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s leading&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#3-be-a-berean-acts-1711&#34;&gt;#3 be a Berean (Acts 17:11)!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#4-understand-the-intended-audience&#34;&gt;#4 Understand the intended audience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#5-understand-revelation-is-a-jewish-book&#34;&gt;#5 Understand Revelation is a Jewish book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#6-be-suspicious-if-an-interpretation-could-not-have-occurred-to-the-original-audience&#34;&gt;#6 Be suspicious if an interpretation could not have occurred to the original audience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#7-acknowledge-that-fear-is-not-from-god&#34;&gt;#7 Acknowledge that fear is not from God&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#revelation-metadata&#34;&gt;Revelation &amp;ldquo;metadata&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 14,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read/hear the portions&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Revelation 1:1-9 (CJB)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;This is the revelation which God gave to Yeshua the Messiah, so that he could show his servants what must happen very soon. He communicated it by sending his angel to his servant Yochanan,  2.  who bore witness to the Word of God and to the testimony of Yeshua the Messiah, as much as he saw.  3.  Blessed are the reader and hearers of the words of this prophecy, provided they obey the things written in it! For the time is near!  4.  From: Yochanan To: The seven Messianic communities in the province of Asia: Grace and shalom to you from the One who is, who was and who is coming; from the sevenfold Spirit before his throne;  5.  and from Yeshua the Messiah, the faithful witness, the firstborn from the dead and the ruler of the earth&amp;rsquo;s kings. To him, the one who loves us, who has freed us from our sins at the cost of his blood,  6.  who has caused us to be a kingdom, that is, cohanim for God, his Father—to him be the glory and the rulership forever and ever. Amen.  7.  Look! He is coming with the clouds! Every eye will see him, including those who pierced him; and all the tribes of the Land will mourn him. Yes! Amen!  8.  &amp;ldquo;I am the &amp;lsquo;A&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;lsquo;Z,&amp;rsquo; &amp;quot; says Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, the One who is, who was and who is coming.  9.  I, Yochanan, am a brother of yours and a fellow-sharer in the suffering, kingship and perseverance that come from being united with Yeshua. I had been exiled to the island called Patmos for having proclaimed the message of God and borne witness to Yeshua.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to our series on the book of Revelation we call &amp;ldquo;Revelation Backgrounds.&amp;rdquo;  In this introductory episode, we will provide an introduction to the book, some background into Jewish Apocalyptic literature, and we&amp;rsquo;ll provide what we see are Seven Keys to Interpretation.  Revelation can be a complex book, but these keys will help assure we get started on the right path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SfuWhCybaYU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;revelation-not-revelations&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Revelation&amp;rdquo; (not &amp;ldquo;Revelations&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In his course on Jerusalem, Dr. Cargill said, &amp;ldquo;the name of the book is &amp;lsquo;RevelationnnnnnNUH,&#39;&amp;rdquo; he said to emphasize the singular&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He continued, &amp;ldquo;This is a pet peeve of mine. If you call it &amp;lsquo;RevelationS,&amp;rsquo; it means you have never read the 1st verse, and I will flunk you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of course, we won&amp;rsquo;t flunk anybody, but this is a good reminder that the correct name of the book is not &amp;ldquo;Revelation&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;,&amp;rdquo; but &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Revelation.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-apocalyptic-literature&#34;&gt;What is &amp;ldquo;Apocalyptic Literature&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We often think of an apocalypse as some cataclysmic event involving worldwide destruction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the Greek word &lt;em&gt;apokalupsis&lt;/em&gt;, apocalypse means &amp;ldquo;revealing&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;unveiling.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specifically, we would say an unveiling of something not previously known, which wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be known were it not for divine intervention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the days of John, there was a significant body of Jewish apocalyptic literature that he and much of his audience would have known&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The general flow of apocalyptic literature:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A person in a &amp;ldquo;spiritual state,&amp;rdquo; such as fasting and praying, is caught up to a realm usually unseen by mortals (possibly physically or possibly by way of a vision).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He is given a tour, usually guided by an angel, where he sees heavenly worship services, God&amp;rsquo;s throne, and various hallowed chambers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He also sometimes sees &amp;ldquo;the war behind the war.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In other words, when there is a physical war on earth, the person gets to witness a corresponding unseen spiritual warfare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then he gets to witness a final climactic battle between the forces of good and evil and resulting judgments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often, the things the person with the vision sees are nearly impossible to put into words
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best he can do is use the best words he can,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because the human is trying to explain the inexplicable, we end up with the extreme symbolism, such as beasts doing strange things (Daniel 7:5-6) and objects that seem to defy the laws of physics (Ezekiel 1:16-20)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The general purpose of an Apocalypse is for God to reassure His people to remain faithful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lancaster summarizes a biblical apocalypse like this:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Although things on earth seem terribly unjust, with the righteous suffering and the wicked prospering, a day is coming where God will pour out his wrath upon the wicked and reward the righteous.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In other words, &amp;ldquo;your faith and suffering are not in vain.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;The Apocalypse of Paul?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Did you know Paul (or a man he knew) had an Apocalypse?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 Corinthians 12:2-4: &amp;ldquo;I know a man in Messiah (whether in the body I don&amp;rsquo;t know, or whether out of the body I don&amp;rsquo;t know—God knows)—fourteen years ago, he was caught up to the third heaven. I know such a man (whether in the body or outside of the body I don&amp;rsquo;t know—God knows)— he was caught up into Paradise and heard words too sacred to tell, which a human is not permitted to utter.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a classic apocalyptic vision. Were it not for the &amp;ldquo;gag order,&amp;rdquo; we might have had not one but two Books titled &amp;ldquo;Revelation&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;seven-keys-to-interpretation&#34;&gt;Seven Keys to Interpretation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Revelation is perhaps the most studied but least understood book in the New Testament.&amp;rdquo; – Daniel Lancaster&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our primary challenge with understanding Revelation, or just about any other book of the Bible, is that we are separated from the original intended audience in three critical areas: time, distance, and most importantly, culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/49f033022fe7e954bd6946926032fbc0.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;66%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time – John recorded these events nearly 2000 years ago, and he often references writings written hundreds of years before that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distance – Turkey, the geographic setting for Revelation 2-3, is over 6000 nautical miles away from the central United States.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Culture
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setting is a Jewish author writing to Jews and gentile God-fearers in the diaspora (Jews living outside the Land of Israel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These early believers knew their Scriptures, what we would call the &amp;ldquo;Old Testament,&amp;rdquo; much better than we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These believers brought a very different set of experiences, assumptions, and expectations than we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These areas may be less familiar to us if our context is western Protestant Christianity and we have never traveled to these lands. To bridge these gaps, our study in Revelation Backgrounds synthesizes several published commentaries that focus on the historical, geographic, and cultural (specifically Jewish) aspects of the Bible. We also consult Bible atlases, travel videos, and occasionally extra-biblical documents and pertinent archeologic findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with the pattern of &amp;ldquo;sevens&amp;rdquo; in Revelation, we have seven &amp;ldquo;Keys to Interpretation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-follow-the-talmidim-way&#34;&gt;#1 Follow the &amp;ldquo;Talmidim Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Talmidim&lt;/em&gt; is the Hebrew word for &amp;ldquo;disciples.&amp;rdquo; I am a &lt;em&gt;talmid&lt;/em&gt;. You are a &lt;em&gt;talmid&lt;/em&gt;. We are all &lt;em&gt;Talmidim&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talmidim was one of the first Hebrew words I ever learned, so it has a special place in my heart. The word is symbolic of a journey I&amp;rsquo;ve been on for over ten years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an expression that ancient Jewish disciples would follow their rabbi so closely that they would be &amp;ldquo;covered in his dust.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/547b202d55681e683cc9dab7b8528db4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;33%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For these reasons, I call the ministry the &lt;em&gt;Talmidim Way&lt;/em&gt;. Our logo contains a drawing of an ancient stone footpath to remind us that our faith is founded on old ways, and we should walk in the dust of our Rabbi Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig Keener is one of my go-to commentators for historical context. He says much more eloquently, &amp;ldquo;Shedding light on the original provides modern readers better access to the message of the book when they seek to apply it today.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-be-open-to-the-spirits-leading&#34;&gt;#2 Be open to the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s leading&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us not cling too tightly to any presupposed interpretation or application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My positions on Revelation have changed over the years (see &amp;ldquo;we reserve the right to get smarter&amp;rdquo; callout)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to dive into the text, leverage the wisdom of trustworthy commentators who have gone before us, check everything out against Scripture&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and let the Spirit pour into us.
&lt;img src=&#34;images/dove.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may mean we need to leave behind a previously held position&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider yourself lucky if you do not already have a firm position on &amp;ldquo;pretribulation,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;preterist,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;postmillennial.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More division than edification occurs over these subjects, in my opinion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s ok to hold firm views, but remember we are all brothers and sisters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can and should debate and challenge; Proverbs 27:17 says, &amp;ldquo;As iron sharpens iron, so one person sharpens another.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let us never divide over these types of matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;We reserve the right to get smarter.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I admittedly am looking at myself when I say not to cling too tightly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other times I&amp;rsquo;ve studied Revelation from end to end, I&amp;rsquo;ve been rather staunchly in the &amp;ldquo;futurist, pre-tribulation&amp;rdquo; camp. That means that my view of Revelation tended to be that after chapter 4, everything that happened was yet future (futurist). Before this happened, all the faithful believers would be raptured before the tribulation (pretribulation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, particularly after digging into the Gospels context and other things, I&amp;rsquo;m no longer 100% sold on that approach. Also, if we look at Jesus&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;one will be taken and the other left&amp;rdquo; statements and in the parables where all the fish are hauled in, but then some are removed, it&amp;rsquo;s not the good who are removed. It&amp;rsquo;s the wicked who are removed. It&amp;rsquo;s the rotten fish that are thrown back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not saying definitively that the pretribulation view is wrong. Only that now, my opinions are more flexible after further review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to have a colleague who liked to say, &amp;ldquo;we always reserve the right to get smarter.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-be-a-berean-acts-1711&#34;&gt;#3 be a Berean (Acts 17:11)!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will begin every study with Acts 17:11&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These (Bereans) were more noble than those in Thessalonica in that they received the word with all readiness of mind and searched the scriptures daily, whether those things were so. (Acts 17:11 KJV)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acts 17:11 is paramount for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every other commentator and I are human. I will, of course, make every attempt to be faithful and reliable. Still, we all have our biases, blind spots, and mistaken conclusions.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I assert a fact, I will try to back it up with a citation. When I offer an opinion or speculation, I will try to disclose that also. After each lesson, I will include a list of works cited. I encourage everyone to never take my word for it but validate what I say.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acts 17:11 tells us the Biblical model is to &amp;ldquo;trust but verify.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is up to the reader to do your research and verify that any facts and conclusions are scriptural.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are all called to &amp;ldquo;be Bereans.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-understand-the-intended-audience&#34;&gt;#4 Understand the intended audience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Bible, including the Book of Revelation, was written FOR us but not TO us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are operating under the assumption that the Apostle John wrote Revelation, likely between 90-95 CE&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He was instructed to share it with seven specific Messianic communities/congregations.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note we should not say &amp;ldquo;seven churches&amp;rdquo; because no such thing as a &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; existed in 95.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The reason for the apocalypse was to provide hope for the faithful during the intense persecution of the Roman Emperor Domitian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Bible is written &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; us in the sense of 2 Timothy 3:16-17. All Scripture is inspired by God and useful &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; teaching, &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; reproof, &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; restoration, and &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; training in righteousness, 17. so that the person belonging to God may be capable, fully equipped &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; every good deed.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teaching/doctrine = what &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reproof = what is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restoration/correction = how to &lt;strong&gt;get&lt;/strong&gt; right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Training in righteousness/instruction = how to &lt;strong&gt;stay&lt;/strong&gt; right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-understand-revelation-is-a-jewish-book&#34;&gt;#5 Understand Revelation is a Jewish book&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revelation is a Jewish book. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s really Jewish. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s the most Jewish book in our New Testament&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This fact is why we as Gentiles often have trouble understanding Revelation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The symbolism can be baffling since we likely won&amp;rsquo;t have the background in the Hebrew Scriptures that John&amp;rsquo;s original audience had.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are 404 verses in Revelation, but there are allusions to over 800 Old Testament verses. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interestingly, John never directly quotes any other verse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniel, Isaiah, Ezekiel, Psalms, and Deuteronomy are frequently alluded to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation 1:3 promises a blessing for those who hear and obey what has been written.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While the exact nature of the blessing is not stated, a thorough study of Revelation will take us into nearly every other book of the Bible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a blessing when we study God&amp;rsquo;s word. The Jewish sages see Bible study as worship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proverbs 3:13-14: Happy (blessed) is the man who finds wisdom and the man who gains understanding. For her trade-value is better than silver, and her yield better than fine gold.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will call attention to many of these references as we go verse-by-verse through Revelation Backgrounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jewish imagery is everywhere: Jewish prophecy, Rosh Hashanah, Yom Kippur, Sukkot, Palm Branches, Shofars, Menorahs, books of judgment, the Book of Life, liturgical functions and ceremonies about the Temple in Jerusalem, etc.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We assume that John wrote this between 90-95 CE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is significant as it would have been &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the Roman destruction of the Second Temple in Jerusalem in 70 CE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John drew from a time in Israel&amp;rsquo;s history where a nearly identical event happened: the destruction of the First Temple in 586 BCE by the Babylonians.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowing this allows us to frame John&amp;rsquo;s references to Babylon in their proper context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we approach Revelation and ignore its Jewishness, we will find it difficult, if not impossible, to understand.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But if we are Bereans and search the Scriptures, we will discover Revelation significantly demystified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For this reason, we will be presenting verses from Revelation and other books from the &amp;ldquo;Complete Jewish Bible&amp;rdquo; (CJB).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CJB is a translation by Dr. David H. Stern that seeks to &amp;ldquo;present the Bible (Old and New Testaments) as a complete Jewish book and connect readers with the Jewishness of the Messiah.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It also seeks to correct anachronisms, such as the label &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; in the New Testament before such an entity ever existed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-be-suspicious-if-an-interpretation-could-not-have-occurred-to-the-original-audience&#34;&gt;#6 Be suspicious if an interpretation could not have occurred to the original audience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If an interpretation would not or could not have occurred to John or his audience, we will treat it with a degree of healthy suspicion.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The historical aspect tends to get the least attention from other Protestant-based commentators.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, how the events described in Revelation relate to what was happening in John&amp;rsquo;s Day will be our primary focus with Revelation Backgrounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many interpretations may appear to &amp;ldquo;fit&amp;rdquo;; they just may not fit within our scope. We want to stay focused on the 1st-century context as much as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Healthy suspicion doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean we reject it outright just because it was beyond the scope of the original audience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;God is perfectly capable of delivering a message that is just as relevant for us as it was to the original audience.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, the &amp;ldquo;seven letters&amp;rdquo; have many layers of understanding and application (admittedly, some are concrete while others are speculative).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no reason why multiple layers of interpretation can&amp;rsquo;t be correct.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-acknowledge-that-fear-is-not-from-god&#34;&gt;#7 Acknowledge that fear is not from God&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear is not from God&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fear not,&amp;rdquo; or an equivalent, is one of the most frequently repeated commands in the Bible.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Mathew 10:28, Jesus said the only fear we should have is the fear of God, a healthy fear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Far too many approach Revelation with a spirit of fear; may it not be so with us!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We must always apply &amp;ldquo;Acts 17:11 logic&amp;rdquo; to any potential interpretation.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the given interpretation consistent with the rest of the Scriptures?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does it magnify Yeshua (Jesus) the Messiah?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does it give us a spirit of peace?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we are left fearful of anyone or anything besides God, then the interpretation/application is not from God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;no-fear-means-avoiding-frontpage-exegesis&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;No Fear&amp;rdquo; means avoiding &amp;ldquo;Frontpage Exegesis&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The media loves fear. Fear sells. If it bleeds, it leads. Yet we just said that fear is not from God. Fear should not be a factor in our attempts to understand Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Exegesis&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extracting concepts from the biblical text while applying reasonable academic inquiry techniques&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&amp;ldquo;Frontpage&amp;rdquo; Exegesis&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing every sensational headline or significant current as a fulfillment of biblical prophecy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation is NOT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A crystal ball to predict the future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A description of current events in the 21st century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A chronological, linear sequence of end-time events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A literal narrative, but neither is it an allegory
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember this: &lt;strong&gt;Revelation is not an allegory.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frontpage exegesis intentionally or unintentionally allegorizes Scripture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem with an allegory is that we can twist it to mean anything we want it to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For context, if we were to study Christian writings during WWI, a large segment of Christians believed they were living in the days of Revelation. Some even quit their jobs, stopped having children, and even committed suicide.
&lt;img src=&#34;images/frontpage_exegesis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;20%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During WWII, many thought Hitler was the Antichrist (not entirely without reason).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 1988, one person was &lt;em&gt;so sure&lt;/em&gt; the rapture was going to occur that year, he published a book, &amp;ldquo;88 Reasons Why the Rapture will be in 1988,&amp;rdquo; and then had the audacity to say &amp;ldquo;if I&amp;rsquo;m wrong, the Bible is wrong.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over the last decade, the Beast was &amp;ldquo;obviously&amp;rdquo; Donald Trump or Barack Obama, depending on your political viewpoint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone throughout history who has claimed that he or she was living out the events prophesied by Revelation has been wrong. That&amp;rsquo;s the problem with Frontpage Exegesis. It&amp;rsquo;s always been wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; fair to say, &amp;ldquo;Revelation describes literal events using signs/symbolic language.&amp;rdquo; We&amp;rsquo;ll talk more about some of these signs below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;revelation-metadata&#34;&gt;Revelation &amp;ldquo;metadata&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s look at the &amp;ldquo;who, what, when, where&amp;rdquo; of Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;who-wrote-revelation&#34;&gt;Who wrote Revelation?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation 1:1-2 This is the Revelation which God gave to Yeshua the Messiah so that he could show his servants what must happen very soon. He communicated it by sending his angel to his servant &lt;mark&gt;Yochanan (John)&lt;/mark&gt;, 2. who bore witness to the Word of God and to the testimony of Yeshua the Messiah, as much as he saw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note the progression of transmission: God → Jesus → His angel/messenger → John → Jesus&amp;rsquo; servants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ultimate Author is God
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation is not just &amp;ldquo;divinely inspired&amp;rdquo; but is &amp;ldquo;divinely given.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Divinely inspired – the Holy Spirit guided the words, but the structure, choice of words, what aspects to include, what to omit, and other stylistic details were at the discretion of the human author&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Divinely given – the words, what to include/omit, and so forth came directly from God. The human author was primarily a transcriber and copy editor
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation is the only New Testament book that is divinely given; all others are divinely-inspired&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the Torah, the first five books of Moses, are divinely given (The phrase, &amp;ldquo;The LORD spoke to Moses and said, &amp;lsquo;Thus shall you say to the Children of Israel…&#39;&amp;rdquo; appears frequently.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John wrote down the words of the angel/messenger unless he was told not to (Revelation 10:4)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While we can&amp;rsquo;t prove it beyond all doubt, the evidence is convincing that Revelation&amp;rsquo;s (human) author is John the Apostle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In other words, the author is John, the &lt;em&gt;talmid&lt;/em&gt; (disciple) of Yeshua, the author of the Gospel of John, and the three epistles that bear his name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One additional piece of evidence is the phrase &amp;ldquo;bore witness.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This type of legal/courtroom terminology is all over the Gospel of John.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John presents evidence that Yeshua/Jesus is the rightful authority for Israel and the good shepherd. In addition, John also bears witness that the Jerusalem religious establishment is unauthorized and its leaders are the &amp;ldquo;bad shepherds&amp;rdquo; over Israel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;when-and-where-was-revelation-written&#34;&gt;When and where was Revelation written?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation 1:9 I, John, your brother and fellow partaker with you in the tribulation and kingdom and patient endurance that are in Yeshua, was on &lt;mark&gt;the island called Patmos because of the word of God and the testimony of Yeshua&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/e45914e26cc0be101f69fd4d54a746be.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iraneus, the earliest source who cited the Apostle John as the author, also stated that he wrote during the worldwide persecution of Jews and Christians of Emperor Domitian. Domitian was also responsible for exiling John to Patmos.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The small island of Patmos is about 7.5 miles (12 km) long from north to south and at its widest is 6 miles (10 km) from east to west.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domitian was the Roman Emperor from 81-96.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most conservative scholars believe Revelation was written between 90-95.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    For information on exactly how John ended up in Patmos &amp;ldquo;because of the Word of God and Testimony of Yeshua,&amp;rdquo; see our Revelation Backgrounds Supplement &amp;ldquo;Historical Background of John&amp;rsquo;s Exile.&amp;rdquo;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-was-revelation-written&#34;&gt;How was Revelation written?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation 1:1b: He &lt;mark&gt;communicated it&lt;/mark&gt; by sending His angel to His servant Yochanan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Greek word for &amp;ldquo;communicated it&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;made it known&amp;rdquo; is &lt;em&gt;σημαίνω&lt;/em&gt; to signify, literally &amp;ldquo;render into signs.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We might say &amp;ldquo;encoded.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Missler writes, &amp;ldquo;Revelation is in code, but every code is explained elsewhere in Scripture!&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every sign in the Bible points to something – in the case of Revelation, the signs point to the climax of God&amp;rsquo;s plan for Man.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Readers familiar with the Old Testament would have understood what these signs represented.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will get more comfortable with John&amp;rsquo;s communication as we dig into the Hebrew Scriptures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sevens&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another way Revelation is &amp;ldquo;signified&amp;rdquo; is through repetitive patterns, specifically the number seven.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sevens are conspicuous in Revelation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In biblical thought, seven is the number that denotes &amp;quot; completion,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;finality,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;perfection.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Shabbat (7th day) is a day of peace, joy, and rest; the Messianic Kingdom is often described as entering into the (Sabbath) peace/joy/rest of God&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This comes from Genesis 2:1-3
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So the heavens and the earth were completed along with their entire array. 2. God completed—on the seventh day—His work that He made, and He ceased—on the seventh day—from all His work that He made. 3. Then God blessed the seventh day and sanctified it, for on it He ceased from all His work that God created.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some of the seven patterns are obvious (congregations, seals, trumpets, bowls), while others are less noticeable.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The depiction of Messiah in chapter 1 has seven features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each letter to a congregation in chapters 2-3 contains seven components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are seven &amp;ldquo;blessings&amp;rdquo; (or beatitudes) scattered throughout the book, beginning with the blessing to the one who reads and obeys the words at Revelation 1:3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;to-whom-was-revelation-written&#34;&gt;To whom was Revelation written?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation 1:4: From: Yochanan To: The seven Messianic communities in the province of Asia:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John, at the time, was over the congregation in Ephesus and had responsibility for the other six nearby assemblies: Smyrna, Pergamos, Thyatira, Sardis, Philadelphia, and Laodicea.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These are circled on the map, along with John&amp;rsquo;s location on Patmos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John was tasked with shepherding his flocks through this tumultuous time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    The term &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; is an anachronism
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;images/seven_congregations.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;66%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At this point, you may be asking, &amp;ldquo;why aren&amp;rsquo;t you using the word &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo;? I thought they were the &amp;ldquo;seven churches of Revelation?&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can say with reasonable certainty that the name of the building where 1st-century believers in Asia met was called a synagogue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These communities or congregations were predominately Jewish but had their share of gentile believers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t recommend calling them &amp;ldquo;churches&amp;rdquo; because the &amp;ldquo;church,&amp;rdquo; either a building or an organizational structure, did not exist in the first century.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anachronism&lt;/strong&gt;: the misappropriation of concepts and ideas in time.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When an actor in a movie set in the Middle Ages is wearing a digital watch, or there&amp;rsquo;s a car visible on a street that is supposed to occur during the civil war, that&amp;rsquo;s an anachronism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anachronistic fallacy&lt;/strong&gt;: when one purposely or inadvertently &lt;strong&gt;asserts or infers a concept&lt;/strong&gt; based on an anachronism.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; didn&amp;rsquo;t exist yet in the first century, every time we translate &amp;ldquo;ecclesia&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; in the New Testament, that&amp;rsquo;s an anachronistic fallacy.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In fact, the word &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; in any form or language doesn&amp;rsquo;t appear until around the mid-5th Century CE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Greek word &lt;em&gt;ecclesia&lt;/em&gt;, later translated as &amp;ldquo;church,&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;called out assembly,&amp;rdquo; or in a religious context, &amp;ldquo;congregation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;ecclesia&lt;/em&gt; is about people, not an institution, yet this is not what usually comes to our mind when we see the word &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; in our Bibles. We tend to associate &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;a building or collection of (non-Jewish) worshippers.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John, a Jew, wrote to Jewish congregations attended by Jews and gentiles. In the early to mid 90s, they assembled in synagogues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;To whom was the revelation &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; given?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jesus! This has some interesting theological implications, as there were apparently things Jesus didn&amp;rsquo;t know even after his Resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation 1:1 The Revelation of Yeshua the Messiah, which God gave &lt;strong&gt;Him&lt;/strong&gt; to show to His servants the things that must soon take place. He made it known by sending His angel to His servant John,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;why-was-revelation-written&#34;&gt;Why was Revelation written?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revelation 1:7 &lt;mark&gt;Look! He is coming with the clouds! Every eye will see him&lt;/mark&gt;, including those who pierced Him, and all the tribes of the Land will mourn him. Yes! Amen!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We mentioned above how the purpose of apocalyptic literature was to give the faithful hope during times of tribulation. No matter what happens here on earth, we always have the hope of his return.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zechariah 14:4 reminds us that when he returns, His &amp;ldquo;feet will stand on the Mount of Olives.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the end of the day, Revelation is about God fixing what man and Satan have messed up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whereas we saw the entrance of sin, the curse, and death in Genesis, we will see the end of sin (chapter 21), no more condemnation (chapter 22), and no more death (chapter 21).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like Steven Covey says, &amp;ldquo;Begin with the end in mind.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No matter how murky or mysterious Revelation may be, ultimately, it is about the Glory of God and restoration of Man to the state that God originally intended for us in Eden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation reminds us, &amp;ldquo;victory depends on Christ&amp;rsquo;s finished work, not on human circumstances (and) that the imminent hope of His return is worth more than all the world&amp;rsquo;s goods.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amen!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am excited to dig into this book. I&amp;rsquo;ve studied it many times, but this will be the first time diving into using messianic and other cultural background commentaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we begin, remember the &amp;ldquo;Seven Keys to Interpretation&amp;rdquo; we listed above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will have a separate segment to review the relevant history before John receives the Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if history wasn&amp;rsquo;t your best subject, I encourage you to view this supplement. Understanding this extra-biblical background turns out to be highly relevant to our studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, we&amp;rsquo;ll see you for Revelation chapter 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert R. Cargill, &lt;em&gt;Jerusalem in Rebellion&lt;/em&gt;, Jerusalem: The Holy City (Spring 2010): A History of Jerusalem from Ancient Canaan to Modern Israel, 2010, &lt;a href=&#34;https://itunes.apple.com/itunes-u/jerusalem-holy-city-spring/id434136076?mt=10&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://itunes.apple.com/itunes-u/jerusalem-holy-city-spring/id434136076?mt=10&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically Jewish apocalyptic literature fall into a category called pseudopigrapha – writings falsely ascribed to someone else describing a vision that person had. For example, the Book of (First) Enoch probably dates to 200-100 BCE (long after the Biblical Enoch was taken by God in Genesis 5). Revelation follows the genre of 1 Enoch, but it is also different because we are confident it came directly from God through John the Apostle.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel T. Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse of Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, Apocalypse of John, 2015, accessed January 19, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bethimmanuel.org/audio-series/apocalypse-of-john&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bethimmanuel.org/audio-series/apocalypse-of-john&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ibid.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig S. Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition (E-Sword). (Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014), chap. Revelation Introduction.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I like to refer to as &amp;ldquo;putting on our Acts 17:11 thinking caps.&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believers need not be bothered by the &amp;ldquo;BCE/CE&amp;rdquo; (Before Common Era/Common Era) designations in place of &amp;ldquo;BC&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;AD&amp;rdquo;. They mean the same things. Saying BCE/CE is less offensive particularly to Jewish people. It is a chance to love our neighbors and live out Romans 12:18 (&amp;ldquo;If possible, so far as it depends on you, live in &lt;em&gt;shalom&lt;/em&gt; with all people&amp;rdquo;). Besides, when the Catholic Church established the BC/AD system in the Middle Ages, they made a math error. We now know that Yeshua was most likely born 5 or 4 BCE. Saying &amp;ldquo;Jesus Christ was born in the year 5 Before Christ&amp;rdquo; is non-sensical when you think about it!&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chuck Missler, &lt;em&gt;Cosmic Codes: Hidden Messages From The Edge Of Eternity&lt;/em&gt; (Koinonia House, 2013). Missler has categorized these references in Appendix C.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse of Messiah&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Complete Jewish Bible (CJB) - Version Information - BibleGateway.Com,&amp;rdquo; accessed January 22, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biblegateway.com/versions/Complete-Jewish-Bible-CJB/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.biblegateway.com/versions/Complete-Jewish-Bible-CJB/&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A piece of Christian internet folklore says, &amp;ldquo;there are 365 &amp;ldquo;fear not&amp;rdquo; commands; one for every day of the year!&amp;rdquo; While this isn&amp;rsquo;t entirely accurate, there are well over 100, so the point is still valid. Fear is not from God.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel T. Lancaster, &amp;ldquo;Patmos,&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Apostles&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Boaz D. Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster, vol. 5, Torah Club (Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2018), 1309.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, &amp;ldquo;Patmos (BiblePlaces.Com) – BiblePlaces.Com,&amp;rdquo; n.d., accessed January 19, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/patmos/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/patmos/&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chuck Missler, &lt;em&gt;The Book of Revelation Handbook&lt;/em&gt; (Koinonia House, 2020), 6.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is some cause to conclude the fallacy in our Bible translations was &lt;em&gt;deliberate&lt;/em&gt; as the church became increasingly anti-semetic and distanced itself from its Jewish heritage.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary&lt;/em&gt;, chap. Revelation Introduction.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2. Revelation Historical Prelude</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/historical-prelude/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/historical-prelude/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-jewish-revolt-nero-vespasian-and-josephus&#34;&gt;The Jewish Revolt: Nero, Vespasian, and Josephus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#2nd-temple-destruction-fulfills-prophecy&#34;&gt;2nd Temple Destruction Fulfills Prophecy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#roman-aftermath-vespasian-and-titus&#34;&gt;Roman aftermath: Vespasian and Titus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#domitian&#34;&gt;Domitian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#domitian-john-and-patmos16&#34;&gt;Domitian, John, and Patmos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion-relevance-to-revelation&#34;&gt;Conclusion: Relevance to Revelation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 14,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is going to be a supplement to our Revelation background series. We&amp;rsquo;re essentially going to take a look at significant events in the period between the Jewish Revolt of 66CE, including the destruction of the Jewish Temple in 70, through the mid-90s that resulted in John&amp;rsquo;s exile on Patmos, where he received the Revelation. Even if history wasn&amp;rsquo;t your best subject in school, I think you&amp;rsquo;ll find this helpful as we prepare to study Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b5iQBoBvy_0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/12dbc6729425b0146e399d1142ecde75.png&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than Jesus predicting the temple&amp;rsquo;s destruction in Luke 21, all of this is drawn from extra-biblical sources. Much of it is verifiable from historical documents. Still, some of it is based on church tradition that was likely passed on orally before it was written down several centuries later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The church father, Iraneus, was only one generation removed from John the Apostle. Iraneus in &lt;em&gt;ecclesiastical history¸&lt;/em&gt;is the earliest source that tells us that John the Apostle wrote Revelation and did so from Patmos because the Roman Emperor Domitian exiled him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Domitian&amp;rsquo;s persecution turns out to be critically important if we are to put Revelation in context. The following is summarized mainly from Cargill&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Jerusalem the Holy City&lt;/em&gt; course&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Lancaster&amp;rsquo;s series &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse of John&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Apostles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The years following Jesus&#39; Resurrection and Ascension were a tumultuous time for Israel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The governors that followed Pontius Pilate went from bad to worse, as did the Herods that took over for Antipas and Phillip, notably Agrippa I and Agrippa II&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With this came increased talk of rebellion and hopes for a Messianic deliverer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In many Jew&amp;rsquo;s minds, the Messiah will deliver the people from captivity and establish a literal political kingdom, just like Moses did during the Exodus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since Jesus didn&amp;rsquo;t do that, He couldn&amp;rsquo;t be the promised deliverer&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;False messiahs were abundant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This led to what is known as the &amp;ldquo;First Jewish Revolt&amp;rdquo; in 66 CE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-jewish-revolt-nero-vespasian-and-josephus&#34;&gt;The Jewish Revolt: Nero, Vespasian, and Josephus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/3feaa830cafd78dd620f3f1cbab7887f.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;25%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 66 CE, during the time of Emperor Nero (famous for his own persecutions and insanity), there was open rebellion; a Roman General named Vespasian (pictured at right) was sent with Roman Legions V, X, and XV to quash it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Josephus predicts greatness for Vespasian.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During one battle in the north of Israel, Vespasian captured a Jewish general named Yosef ben Mattiyahu, who later became known as Flavius Josephus.&lt;img src=&#34;images/408d47525f6d48efcea99f82468abd74.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;25%&#34; style=&#34;float:left&#34; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As he was about to be executed, Josephus said to Vespasian something along the lines of, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not really a general. I&amp;rsquo;m a prophet, and one day you&amp;rsquo;re going to be the emperor.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most Roman leaders were extraordinarily superstitious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naturally, what this man said was pleasing to Vespasian&amp;rsquo;s ears; therefore, Josephus was allowed to live as an enslaved person. He authored two large volumes of Jewish history up to that point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 69, while dealing with the Jewish rebellion, Vespasian was recalled to Rome, where he was indeed named emperor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Josephus also told Vespasian that amid all this Jewish messianic enthusiasm, it was &lt;em&gt;Vespasian and his line&lt;/em&gt; who fulfilled the Jewish prophecies about the coming Messiah, not some Jewish person from the house of David.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After Vespasian became emperor, they took Jewish prophecies very seriously!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Josephus was still very much in the picture some 10-20 years later, when Vespasian&amp;rsquo;s son Domitian took over the Roman Empire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Josephus is viewed as a traitor to the Jews for his actions.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;According to legend, a group of generals entered into a suicide pact rather than be captured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Josephus conveniently drew the proverbial last straw and was tasked with killing the last man and then himself. He obviously took another way when he presented himself to Vespasian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vespasian&amp;rsquo;s son Titus ultimately was successful in putting down the rebellion.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 70, he besieged and sacked Jerusalem and destroyed the Temple stone-by-stone, just as Jesus had predicted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 72, he rooted out the last Jewish holdouts at a place called Masada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those Jews who were not slaughtered were forced into exile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Jews would not have a homeland to call their own until 1948.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2nd-temple-destruction-fulfills-prophecy&#34;&gt;2nd Temple Destruction Fulfills Prophecy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/60576df31e34f2c3e4538d7811953bdc.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;
Luke 19:41-44 As He drew near and saw Jerusalem, He wept over her, 42. saying, &#34;If only you had recognized this day the things that lead to shalom! But now they are hidden from your eyes. 43. For the days will come upon you when your enemies will surround you with barricades and hem you in on all sides. 44. And they will smash you to the ground—you and your children within you. And they won&#39;t leave within you one stone upon another because you did not recognize the time of your visitation.
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus&#39; words about the destruction of Jerusalem and the Temple were fulfilled in 70 CE
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indeed, not one stone was left upon another.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A visit to the Temple Mount area in Jerusalem today reveals these massive stones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Based on the indentations in the surrounding pavement, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to conclude that they fell from the top of the temple mount above (note the person in the upper left corner for a sense of the size of the stones!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Archaeologists date these stones to the 1st century and the destruction of Jerusalem by the Roman army.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The destruction of the &amp;ldquo;2nd Temple&amp;rdquo; is critical in Jewish history.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The destruction of the 1st Temple in 586 BCE was another such moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In one of those quirks of history, both destructions happened on the same day on the Jewish Calendar, the 9th day of the Jewish month of Av.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since then, several calamities have happened on that date, and to this day, the 9th of Av is a day of mourning and fasting for the Jewish People.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;roman-aftermath-vespasian-and-titus&#34;&gt;Roman aftermath: Vespasian and Titus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The destruction of the Temple was a severe blow to the hopes and aspirations of Jews
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the second time in their history, God&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;chosen people&amp;rdquo; had been decimated, exiled, and seen God&amp;rsquo;s house overrun by a pagan empire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;How could an all-powerful, all-loving God let this happen? What will we do next?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first time it happened was in 586 BCE at the hands of the Babylonians.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After the fall of Jerusalem in 70 CE, Emperor Vespasian did two things to teach a lesson to this rebellious people.
&lt;img src=&#34;images/41894ca448ddd5df916ab6bc1f1e5491.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
-   This tax only applied to Jews.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He imposed a &lt;em&gt;fiscus Iudaicus&lt;/em&gt; (a Jewish Tax).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a further insult, the tax went to the upkeep of the pagan Temple of Jupiter/Zeus, which stood where the Jewish Temple once did.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In ancient cultures, putting your holy site over someone else&amp;rsquo;s holy site was the ultimate in &amp;ldquo;smack talk&amp;rdquo;; it communicates, &amp;ldquo;your God is vanquished.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some Jews (both followers and non-followers of Yeshua) &amp;ldquo;renounced&amp;rdquo; their faith to avoid the tax.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He &amp;ldquo;gave orders that everyone who belonged to the lineage of David should be sought out that none of the royal race might be left among the Jews.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Titus succeeded Vespasian in 79 but only reigned two years before he died of a fever.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Arch of Titus&amp;rdquo; stands in Rome today as a tribute to his victory over the Jews&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/61a7daa2ad04e35e37a8668a756e01d0.png&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empathy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to put ourselves in the Jew&amp;rsquo;s shoes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our God is supposed to be all-powerful with a special place in His heart for His people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yet not once but twice, God&amp;rsquo;s house, the holiest place on earth, has been overrun by idol-worshipping pagans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moreover, in the case of the first temple, God made an unconditional covenant with David that appears to have been broken. What do you do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is your God not who He says He is? Maybe he&amp;rsquo;s not that powerful. Perhaps He doesn&amp;rsquo;t love us. Maybe we sinned so severely he had no choice but to break his promise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you do when what you believe to be true is so blatantly contradicted by the evidence?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you walk away from your faith? A lot did, I&amp;rsquo;m sure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you say God would have protected us, but our people were so bad they deserved it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you say that maybe we misread or misunderstood the promises?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of people did a combination of these things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Psychologists use the term &amp;ldquo;cognitive dissonance&amp;rdquo; for those times when what you believe, what you have been taught all your life doesn&amp;rsquo;t match your reality. According to Cargill, this is what the Jews in exile after the destruction of the First Temple were experiencing.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And let us not be so glib as to say, &amp;ldquo;Jesus did away with the temple.&amp;rdquo; Or &amp;ldquo;the Jews rejected Jesus, so they got what was coming.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not that simple.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first apostles met in the Temple every day, and the temple was also important to Paul.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Temple was a big deal to all Jews, including those who accepted Jesus as their Messiah&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of all, they mourned.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After the First Temple was destroyed, we get passages like Psalms 137.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When God&amp;rsquo;s people mourn, God listens.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After the first temple destruction and the people were scattered to a foreign land, the Babylon Empire, God, sent apocalyptic visions to prophets like Ezekiel and Daniel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It should not surprise us that we get a similar apocalyptic vision after the second temple was destroyed and God&amp;rsquo;s people were scattered throughout the Roman empire. This time God would make it through John the Apostle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But first, we need to talk about another Nero figure named Domitian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;domitian&#34;&gt;Domitian&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the short time Titus was emperor, he softened his father&amp;rsquo;s hard-line positions, particularly concerning political prisoners. Presumably, this also included an easing of enforcement efforts on the two anti-Jewish programs instituted by his father.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All that would change under Domitian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domitian (emperor from 81-96) reinstituted the two programs of Vespasian &amp;ldquo;with the utmost rigor&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Additionally, In Rome, worship of the imperial cult was viewed as a symbol of loyalty to the Roman state. This included worshipping a statue or image of the emperor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whereas Vespasian and Titus weren&amp;rsquo;t significantly &amp;ldquo;religious,&amp;rdquo; Domitian, by the Josephus prophecy, believed himself to be the promised one sent by the gods. He thus demanded worship while he was still alive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He set up a temple to himself and demanded to be addressed as &amp;ldquo;my master, my lord, my god, Domitian.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is in addition to Rome&amp;rsquo;s general paranoia about foreign religions, particularly those like Judaism, whose proponents denounced Rome&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lancaster says something significant here: &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;this fantasy made him all the more worthy of the title of antichrist.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now add to the mix that numerous gentiles throughout the empire were coming to faith in Yeshua.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul and the early leadership decided that gentiles should not be required to convert to Judaism as a condition of being accepted into the assembly (see Acts 15).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The unintended consequence meant that these converts were not Jewish and didn&amp;rsquo;t have to pay the tax&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the eyes of Domitian, they had exploited what we might call &amp;ldquo;a tax loophole.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They could worship the Jewish Messiah in a Jewish congregation but still not pay the Jewish tax.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domitian expected to find Jewish tax evaders and deal with them accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He was not expecting to find the amounts of non-Jews throughout the empire who had forsaken Roman gods to drift into Jewish ways&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The conversions, in combination with the &amp;ldquo;tax loophole&amp;rdquo; problem, sent Domitian into a rage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People in his household were even part of this strange new religion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although Judaism was a recognized religion in the empire, it was only legal for Jews to practice it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domitian initially turned his wrath on the Jews for aiding and abetting these non-Jews.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;According to him, it was their fault for spreading and proselytizing to non-Jews.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He started by banishing all Jews from the city of Rome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some of them naturally protested, saying, &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;s not all Jews! It&amp;rsquo;s this strange sect called the &amp;lsquo;Nazarenes.&amp;rsquo; Blame them!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domitian next initiated a system to weed out these &amp;ldquo;secret Jews&amp;rdquo; - being a &amp;ldquo;Christian&amp;rdquo; was now punishable by death&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-believing Jews were required to become informants on their messianic brethren&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specifically, Keener notes that synagogues in Asia (modern Turkey) expelled Jewish Christians.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They &lt;strong&gt;accused&lt;/strong&gt; the gentiles in messianic fellowships of &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;saying they were Jews, but were not&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From a religious standpoint, these people were violating the Torah&amp;rsquo;s requirement to &amp;ldquo;Love your neighbor as yourself&amp;rdquo; (Leviticus 19:18), as even the narrowest interpretation of &amp;ldquo;neighbor&amp;rdquo; would have included Gentiles who have attached themselves as &amp;ldquo;god fearers&amp;rdquo; and worshipped in synagogues alongside Jews.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Nazis were not the first to do this. The Church led the Spanish Inquisition, which also required people to inform each other.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domitian had the same problem Torquemada and Hitler did. Who exactly was a Jew?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domitian&amp;rsquo;s answer was &amp;ldquo;anyone who lived like a Jew,&amp;rdquo; which included gentile followers of Yeshua.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was the first large-scale persecutions of Christian believers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The captives had one opportunity to dispel the charges.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They had to reject their Jewish ways, then bow and worship an image of the emperor and acknowledge that Domitian was &amp;ldquo;Lord of all.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roman citizens who refused or were believed to be insincere were &amp;ldquo;mercifully&amp;rdquo; beheaded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-citizens suffered a worse fate, up to and including crucifixion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He offered compassion to the wealthy: they could have their lives spared but would be exiled to an Island in the Mediterranean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;domitian-john-and-patmos16&#34;&gt;Domitian, John, and Patmos&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In many ways, it is not surprising that Domitian and John crossed paths since John was the last of the original &lt;em&gt;Talmidim&lt;/em&gt; of Yeshua.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domitian ordered the arrest and extradition of John back to Rome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are several traditions associated with John&amp;rsquo;s arrest and trial before Domitian.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When it was time to execute John, Domitian first made him drink a cup of poison, but true to Jesus&amp;rsquo;s words (Mark 16:18), the poison did not harm him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, the ancient historian Tertullian records the deaths of Peter and Paul and the attempted death of John in Rome: &amp;ldquo;John was plunged unhurt into burning oil.&amp;rdquo; Another legend was that he was shaved from head to toe first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To bring us up to the time of Revelation, &amp;ldquo;When even the cauldron did not deter John from preaching Christ, by order of Domitian, he was relegated to the Island of Patmos.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /commentary/revelation/historical-prelude/images/e45914e26cc0be101f69fd4d54a746be_hud55e7a17541709dd003bd5e981afddcf_219964_85f90fe504f57a87d4565cb71f71850a.webp 400w,
               /commentary/revelation/historical-prelude/images/e45914e26cc0be101f69fd4d54a746be_hud55e7a17541709dd003bd5e981afddcf_219964_288a6d7de5b5bbb915b8818f6b753a2a.webp 760w,
               /commentary/revelation/historical-prelude/images/e45914e26cc0be101f69fd4d54a746be_hud55e7a17541709dd003bd5e981afddcf_219964_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/historical-prelude/images/e45914e26cc0be101f69fd4d54a746be_hud55e7a17541709dd003bd5e981afddcf_219964_85f90fe504f57a87d4565cb71f71850a.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;508&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because John wouldn&amp;rsquo;t die, Domitian exercised his last legal option to exile John to Patmos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At Patmos, John received the famous Revelation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This fulfilled Jesus&#39; prophecy that &amp;ldquo;some of you here will not taste death until you see the Son of Man coming in Glory.&amp;rdquo; (Matthew 16:21)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Additionally, we can see that the world intended martyrdom for John, fulfilling Jesus&#39; prediction that James and John would indeed drink Jesus&#39; Cup of Suffering. (Matthew 20:23)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a post-script, the next emperor, Nerva, is recorded as being &amp;ldquo;wise and moderate.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nerva released all the political prisoners, and John returned to Ephesus for the remainder of his days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion-relevance-to-revelation&#34;&gt;Conclusion: Relevance to Revelation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this background, keep the following in mind as we work through Revelation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suppose one wanted to indirectly refer to Rome (the people who destroyed the 2nd Temple).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In that case, he/she might compare them to the people who destroyed the 1st Temple: &lt;strong&gt;Babylon.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suppose one wanted to refer to Domitian indirectly.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In that case, he/she might compare to an emperor who had a similar style: &lt;strong&gt;Nero&lt;/strong&gt; (whose name has a mathematical equivalent of &amp;ldquo;666&amp;rdquo; – we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss when we get to Revelation 13).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suppose one wanted to indirectly refer to a false messiah who demanded to be worshipped as &amp;ldquo;my master, my lord, my god.&amp;rdquo; In other words, this person required people to use titles rightly reserved for Jesus.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In that case, he/she might use the term &lt;strong&gt;Antichrist.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suppose one wanted to indirectly refer to non-believing Jewish informants, who accused believing gentiles of &amp;ldquo;saying they were Jews when they were not.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In that case, we might say they were from the &amp;ldquo;synagogue of the accuser,&amp;rdquo; or since the Hebrew word for &amp;ldquo;accuser&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;satan,&amp;rdquo; we could say they are from the &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;synagogue of Satan&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; (&lt;em&gt;Satan&lt;/em&gt; is Hebrew for &amp;ldquo;accuser&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This does not mean that they were worshipping Satan the way we might think of it with satanic rituals and such.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We could say that they were doing Satan&amp;rsquo;s bidding.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When we accuse another believer, either directly or through gossip, guess what?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are acting as an &amp;ldquo;accuser of the brethren.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Further, one who claimed to be Jewish but informed against his neighbor is not upholding the high ethical standards of Judaism. He is a hypocrite. He is saying he is a Jew but is not acting like one. Thus we can apply the phrase &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;those who say they are Jews but are not.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Please note this is spoken ONLY against those Jews who failed to uphold the high ethical standards expected of Jews by denouncing their neighbors to the authorities. This is not an indictment against all Jews.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus, as a Jew, obviously would not label Himself as one &amp;ldquo;who said He was a Jew but was not.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If one were going to praise believers who stood up to the authorities, we might say they &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Held fast to His Name&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When John was arrested and taken to Rome, he had little hope for survival.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To a Jewish mind, John was &amp;ldquo;dead&amp;rdquo; as soon as the order for extradition came. See Hebrews 11:19.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Revelation 11, when John writes of two witnesses martyred for their testimony but who God raises from the dead, John&amp;rsquo;s audience could have thought, &amp;ldquo;oh, just like He raised John from the dead.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get the idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So much of Revelation is unlocked when we understand the context. We will open more as we progress through the study.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Primarily Robert R. Cargill, &lt;em&gt;Jerusalem in Rebellion&lt;/em&gt;, Jerusalem: The Holy City (Spring 2010): A History of Jerusalem from Ancient Canaan to Modern Israel, 2010, &lt;a href=&#34;https://itunes.apple.com/itunes-u/jerusalem-holy-city-spring/id434136076?mt=10&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://itunes.apple.com/itunes-u/jerusalem-holy-city-spring/id434136076?mt=10&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Exilic Jerusalem.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Primarily Daniel T. Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Boiled in Oil&lt;/em&gt;, Apocalypse of John, 2015, accessed January 19, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bethimmanuel.org/audio-series/apocalypse-of-john&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bethimmanuel.org/audio-series/apocalypse-of-john&lt;/a&gt; but other lectures as well.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel T. Lancaster, “Patmos,” in &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Apostles&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Boaz D. Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster, vol. 5, Torah Club (Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2016), 1299–1310.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the primary reason why traditional Jews today can’t accept Jesus as their messiah. The deplorable treatment of Jews by the Church over the centuries has cemented this position in their minds.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Fiscus Judaicus&lt;/em&gt;,” &lt;em&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/em&gt;, April 21, 2021, accessed January 24, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Fiscus_Judaicus&amp;amp;oldid=1019171147&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Fiscus_Judaicus&amp;oldid=1019171147&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eusebius, Ecclesiastical History 3.12.1, as cited in Lancaster, “Patmos,” 1300.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Gottheil and Samuel Krauss, “Vespasian,” &lt;em&gt;Jewish Encyclopedia&lt;/em&gt;, n.d., accessed January 24, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/14687-vespasian&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/14687-vespasian&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert R. Cargill, &lt;em&gt;Exilic Jerusalem&lt;/em&gt;, Jerusalem: The Holy City (Spring 2010): A History of Jerusalem from Ancient Canaan to Modern Israel, 2010, &lt;a href=&#34;https://itunes.apple.com/itunes-u/jerusalem-holy-city-spring/id434136076?mt=10&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://itunes.apple.com/itunes-u/jerusalem-holy-city-spring/id434136076?mt=10&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eusebius, Ecclesiastical History 3.19.1, as cited in Lancaster, “Patmos,” 1300.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall the “no friend of Caesar” exchange in John 19:12.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are differing views on this. Lancaster suggests that non-Jewish believers were not liable to pay the tax. When Domitian learned of this, enforcement became the cover story for Domitian&amp;rsquo;s intense persecutions of Christians. However, the Wikipedia article, &amp;ldquo;Fiscus Judaecus,&amp;rdquo; references scholars who suggest that since neither the Romans nor the Christians themselves viewed Christianity as a separate religion, non-Jewish believers in the first century were equally subject to the tax. I&amp;rsquo;m sympathetic to both views. Perhaps it was not as big of an issue under Vespasian as it was under Domitian, which is Lancaster&amp;rsquo;s frame of reference.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Boiled in Oil&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ibid.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel T. Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Synagogue of Satan&lt;/em&gt;, Apocalypse of John, 2016, accessed January 19, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bethimmanuel.org/audio-series/apocalypse-of-john&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bethimmanuel.org/audio-series/apocalypse-of-john&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig S. Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition (E-Sword). (Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014), chap. Revelation Introduction.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entire section summarized from Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Boiled in Oil&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jacobus de Varagine, The Golden Legend, as cited in Lancaster, “Patmos,” 1307.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nerva,” &lt;em&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/em&gt;, January 14, 2022, accessed January 25, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nerva&amp;amp;oldid=1065614709&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nerva&amp;oldid=1065614709&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Hebrews 11:19, in Abraham&amp;rsquo;s mind, Isaac was &amp;ldquo;dead&amp;rdquo; as soon as God gave the command to sacrifice. The journey from Beersheva to Jerusalem took three days. Therefore, figuratively and typologically, Isaac rose from the dead on the third day.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3. Greetings (Rev 1:1-11)</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/2-greetings-rev-1-1-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/2-greetings-rev-1-1-11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-11-the-revelation-to-yeshua&#34;&gt;Rev 1:1: The Revelation to Yeshua&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-12-bore-witness&#34;&gt;Rev 1:2: Bore Witness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-13-the-blessing&#34;&gt;Rev 1:3: The Blessing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-14-grace-and-shalom&#34;&gt;Rev 1:4: Grace and Shalom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-15-6-sevenfold-description-of-yeshua&#34;&gt;Rev 1:5-6: Sevenfold Description of Yeshua&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-17-he-comes-in-the-clouds&#34;&gt;Rev 1:7: He Comes In The Clouds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-18-the-aleph-and-the-tav&#34;&gt;Rev 1:8: The Aleph and the Tav&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-19-patmos&#34;&gt;Rev 1:9: Patmos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-110-in-the-spirit-on-the-day-of-the-lord&#34;&gt;Rev 1:10: In the Spirit on the Day of the Lord&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-111-write&#34;&gt;Rev 1:11: Write!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 12,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;h4 id=&#34;readhear-the-portions&#34;&gt;Read/hear the portions:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;This is the revelation which God gave to Yeshua the Messiah, so that he could show his servants what must happen very soon. He communicated it by sending his angel to his servant Yochanan, 2. who bore witness to the Word of God and to the testimony of Yeshua the Messiah, as much as he saw. 3. Blessed are the reader and hearers of the words of this prophecy, provided they obey the things written in it! For the time is near! 4. From: Yochanan To: The seven Messianic communities in the province of Asia: Grace and shalom to you from the One who is, who was and who is coming; from the sevenfold Spirit before his throne; 5. and from Yeshua the Messiah, the faithful witness, the firstborn from the dead and the ruler of the earth&amp;rsquo;s kings. To him, the one who loves us, who has freed us from our sins at the cost of his blood, 6. who has caused us to be a kingdom, that is, cohanim for God, his Father—to him be the glory and the rulership forever and ever. Amen. 7. Look! He is coming with the clouds! Every eye will see him, including those who pierced him; and all the tribes of the Land will mourn him. Yes! Amen! 8. &amp;ldquo;I am the &amp;lsquo;A&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;lsquo;Z,&amp;rsquo; &amp;quot; says Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, the One who is, who was and who is coming. 9. I, Yochanan, am a brother of yours and a fellow-sharer in the suffering, kingship and perseverance that come from being united with Yeshua. I had been exiled to the island called Patmos for having proclaimed the message of God and borne witness to Yeshua. 10. I came to be, in the Spirit, on the Day of the Lord; and I heard behind me a loud voice, like a trumpet, 11. saying, &amp;ldquo;Write down what you see on a scroll, and send it to the seven Messianic communities—Ephesus, Smyrna, Pergamum, Thyatira, Sardis, Philadelphia and Laodicea!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;watch-the-video&#34;&gt;Watch the video&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HDLBhn4p3mQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re short on time, you can speed up the video in YouTube.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-11-the-revelation-to-yeshua&#34;&gt;Rev 1:1: The Revelation to Yeshua&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;OT Allusions&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1. This is the revelation which God gave to Yeshua the Messiah, so that he could show his servants what must happen very soon. He communicated it by sending his angel to his servant Yochanan,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1:1 Daniel 2:28 but there is a God in heaven who reveals mysteries, and he has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar what will be in the latter days. Your dream and the visions of your head as you lay in bed are these: 29 To you, O king, as you lay in bed came thoughts of what would be after this, and he who reveals mysteries made known to you what is to be.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Allusions and Cross-References&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
We believe your study of this amazing book will be greatly enhanced if you read and meditate on the allusions listed. A comprehensive listing for all 22 chapters, including cross-references from the Treasury of Scripture Knowledge, is in Appendix A1.
&lt;p&gt;As you hover over (or tap) on each verse, the text of the English Standard Version will appear.
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-is-the-revelation&#34;&gt;This is the Revelation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have several questions answered immediately in verse 1.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who wrote: John&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is it for: servants of Yeshua (not for unbelievers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is it about: Yeshua&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When should we study: immediately for the time is near&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As we noted in the introduction, this is &lt;strong&gt;one&lt;/strong&gt; revelation, so the book&amp;rsquo;s name is Revelation, not &amp;ldquo;revelations.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John&amp;rsquo;s Hebrew name, Yochanan, means something like &amp;ldquo;blessed by God.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although the original record we have is in Greek and John was multilingual, Jesus very likely communicated this in Hebrew, John&amp;rsquo;s primary language.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interestingly, Hebrew words for &amp;ldquo;revelation&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;exile&amp;rdquo; are linguistically related.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;גָלָה is the verb for &amp;ldquo;to reveal, uncover&amp;rdquo; and is pronounced &amp;ldquo;ga-LAH&amp;rdquo;; גָלוּת, &amp;ldquo;ga-LOOT,&amp;rdquo; is the word for exile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jewish apocryphal writings, of which Revelation is included, tend to occur when the people were exiled by God, living outside the land when they were vulnerable to abuses by the pagan nations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As we mentioned in the introduction, one of the purposes of Jewish apocalyptic literature was for God to communicate to His people that He is still in control. Although things seem unfair now, a day is coming when God will set everything straight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To help capture the &amp;ldquo;Jewishness&amp;rdquo; of the book, we will be using the Complete Jewish Bible (CJB) paraphrase translation.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No translation is perfect, and the CJB is not without problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can hover over any Bible reference and compare the English Standard Version (ESV). Often the King James Version does the best job at capturing the meaning of the Greek.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;godyeshuaangelyochanan&#34;&gt;God/Yeshua/Angel/Yochanan&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note that we receive Revelation, &amp;ldquo;4th hand.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;God gave it to Jesus, who gave it to an angel/messenger, who gave it to John, who wrote it down and communicated to the servants of Messiah.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John is not receiving all of this directly from Jesus but through an angel who bears witness to Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the end of the chapter, we will be practically unable to distinguish who is speaking, even though we know from verse 1 that it must be the angel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This concept is very similar to the &amp;ldquo;Angel of the LORD&amp;rdquo; that we see in the Old Testament.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We often presume this angel is a pre-incarnate version of Jesus, but it may not be that simple.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There appears to be an &amp;ldquo;Angel of the Messiah,&amp;rdquo; just like an &amp;ldquo;Angel of the LORD.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This angel has the full authority to speak to John, just as if it were Jesus Himself speaking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lizorkin and Shir discuss the challenges of figuring out who is speaking in Revelation:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;As in any complex composition, such a rich polyphony of heavenly sound will demand careful and attentive listening to clearly distinguish between the voices and appreciate both their choir-like message and the voice of the individual performers.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chapter one reveals that John&amp;rsquo;s concept of the &amp;ldquo;Trinity&amp;rdquo; may not be fully in keeping with the traditional Protestant view
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protestants see the Trinity as three co-equal persons. Still, throughout Revelation and even in the Gospel of John, Jesus is subordinate to the Father.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In verse 1, we see that Jesus had to learn about Revelation from the Father.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While the doctrine of the Trinity is undoubtedly biblical, we must remember it is a man-made concept – the word &amp;ldquo;trinity&amp;rdquo; never appears in the Bible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We would be wise to loosely hold any man-made ideas (including views on Eschatology) as we work through Revelation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the Spirit pour into us as we check everything out against Scripture!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;servants&#34;&gt;Servants&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Greek word for servants is &lt;em&gt;doulos&lt;/em&gt; which we can translate as &amp;ldquo;bondservants.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A bondservant is one who freely and willingly attaches himself to the household of his master, &amp;ldquo;because he loves you and your household since he is well-off with you.&amp;rdquo; (Deut 15:16-17)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As talmidim of Jesus, we are called to be His bondservants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This book is for us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we go through the book, we will highlight some of the patterns of seven that may not be obvious. The callout box below lists the seven instances of &amp;ldquo;Messiah&amp;rdquo; in Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Seven Messiah verses in Revelation&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;ldquo;Messiah&amp;rdquo; (Christ) appears seven times, starting with 1:1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is the revelation which God gave to Yeshua the &lt;strong&gt;Messiah&lt;/strong&gt;, so that he could show his servants what must happen very soon. He communicated it by sending his angel to his servant Yochanan (Rev 1:1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who bore witness to the Word of God and to the testimony of Yeshua the &lt;strong&gt;Messiah&lt;/strong&gt;, as much as he saw. (Rev 1:2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and from Yeshua the &lt;strong&gt;Messiah&lt;/strong&gt;, the faithful witness, the firstborn from the dead, and the ruler of the earth&amp;rsquo;s kings. To him, the one who loves us, who has freed us from our sins at the cost of his blood, (Rev 1:5)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The seventh angel sounded his shofar; and there were loud voices in heaven, saying, &amp;ldquo;The kingdom of the world has become the Kingdom of our Lord and his &lt;strong&gt;Messiah&lt;/strong&gt;, and he will rule forever and ever!&amp;rdquo; (Rev 11:15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then I heard a loud voice in heaven saying, &amp;ldquo;Now have come God&amp;rsquo;s victory, power and kingship, and the authority of his &lt;strong&gt;Messiah&lt;/strong&gt;; because the Accuser of our brothers, who accuses them day and night before God, has been thrown out! (Rev 12:10)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then I saw thrones, and those seated on them received authority to judge. And I saw the souls of those who had been beheaded for testifying about Yeshua and proclaiming the Word of God, also those who had not worshipped the beast or its image and had not received the mark on their foreheads and on their hands. They came to life and ruled with the &lt;strong&gt;Messiah&lt;/strong&gt; for a thousand years. (Rev 20:4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blessed and holy is anyone who has a part in the first resurrection; over him the second death has no power. On the contrary, they will be cohanim of God and of the &lt;strong&gt;Messiah&lt;/strong&gt;, and they will rule with him for the thousand years. (Rev 20:6)
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-12-bore-witness&#34;&gt;Rev 1:2: Bore Witness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;who &lt;mark&gt;bore witness&lt;/mark&gt; to the Word of God and to the &lt;mark&gt;testimony&lt;/mark&gt; of Yeshua the Messiah, as much as he saw.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;bore-witnesstestimony&#34;&gt;Bore witness/testimony&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John loves courtroom language (witness, testimony, testify, judge, judgment, authority (in the sense of legal standing), etc.). There are over 100 examples of this in John&amp;rsquo;s writings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John uses nearly the identical language in John 3:32-33 as he does in Revelation 1:2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Gospel, John portrayed evidence that Jesus was the proper authority. At the same time, the Jerusalem religious establishment were the usurpers, &amp;ldquo;bad shepherds,&amp;rdquo; an illegitimate regime.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Revelation, he&amp;rsquo;s going to magnify that. The entire corrupt world system, not just the corrupt Jerusalem establishment, will be put on trial by God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, remember the context: believers in Asia were being betrayed to Roman courts. God grants true justice and righteous judgment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Seven Testimony verses&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
There are seven &#34;**Testimony**&#34; verses starting with 1:2. We can look at this list in a couple of ways.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are seven verses with &amp;ldquo;testimony&amp;rdquo; appearing twice in 19:10.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seven &amp;ldquo;Testimony of Jesus&amp;rdquo; references
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can remove 11:7 where &amp;ldquo;testimony &lt;strong&gt;of Jesus&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; is not directly implied – the two witnesses are testifying of God&amp;rsquo;s judgment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:11 is directly implied as being martyred for their testimony of Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We count 19:10 twice for a total of seven&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who bore witness to the word of God and to the &lt;strong&gt;testimony of Jesus&lt;/strong&gt; Christ, even to all that he saw. (Rev 1:2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I, John, your brother and partner in the tribulation and the kingdom and the patient endurance that are in Jesus, was on the island called Patmos on account of the word of God and the &lt;strong&gt;testimony of Jesus.&lt;/strong&gt; (Rev 1:9)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;And when they have finished their&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;testimony&lt;/strong&gt;*, the beast that rises from the bottomless pit will make war on them and conquer them and kill them, (Rev 11:7)*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And they have conquered him by the blood of the Lamb and by the word of their &lt;strong&gt;testimony (of Jesus)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; for they loved not their lives even unto death. (Rev 12:11)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then the dragon became furious with the woman and went off to make war on the rest of her offspring, on those who keep the commandments of God and hold to the &lt;strong&gt;testimony of Jesus&lt;/strong&gt;. And he stood on the sand of the sea. (Rev 12:17)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then I fell down at his feet to worship him, but he said to me, &amp;ldquo;You must not do that! I am a fellow servant with you and your brothers who hold to the &lt;strong&gt;testimony of Jesus&lt;/strong&gt;. Worship God.&amp;rdquo; For the &lt;strong&gt;testimony of Jesus&lt;/strong&gt; is the Spirit of prophecy. (Rev 19:10)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then I saw thrones, and seated on them were those to whom the authority to judge was committed. Also I saw the souls of those who had been beheaded for the &lt;strong&gt;testimony of Jesus&lt;/strong&gt; and for the word of God, and those who had not worshiped the beast or its image and had not received its mark on their foreheads or their hands. They came to life and reigned with Christ for a thousand years. (Rev 20:4)
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-13-the-blessing&#34;&gt;Rev 1:3: The Blessing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blessed are the reader and hearers of the words of this prophecy, provided they obey the things written in it! For the time is near!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-blessing&#34;&gt;The blessing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is the first of seven such blessings in the book (see callout below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation is the only book with such an explicit promise.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s no wonder the enemy tries to tell us it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to understand, and many have a spirit of fear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conversely, when believers wonder how they can be blessed by God, a biblical answer is &amp;ldquo;study Revelation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We aren&amp;rsquo;t told what form the blessing will be, but ANY gift from God will be great.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One such blessing may be that approaching Revelation as a Jewish book means you will read nearly 1000 verses from the Old Testament.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another blessing is that we will walk away with a much more complete picture of our Savior&amp;rsquo;s person, mission, and destiny than we may have had previously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Greek carries the sense of read-aloud. Most people did not have their own copies of the Bible, so they would have had to hear it read aloud by the reader in the synagogue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note that the blessing is conditional upon the reader understanding and obeying
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is very Hebraic. In Hebrew, verbs are action-oriented.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In English, we can listen, but we don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily equate hearing with obedience. In other words, we can listen passively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no such thought in Hebrew. If you don&amp;rsquo;t obey, you aren&amp;rsquo;t listening.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stern writes, &amp;ldquo;in Judaism, learning is supposed to lead to doing.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the 18th century, a Christian Hebraist named Franz Delitzsch translated the New Testament from Greek back into Biblical Hebrew, using forms and idioms the Old Testament uses. It is a highly educated guess on what the original Jewish authors might have said had their works recorded in their original Hebrew.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For Revelation 1:3, he used a verb that frequently appears in the Torah of Moses – hear/obey (Shema) – שָׁמַע. This beautiful Hebrew word is rich with meaning and application. Talmidim hear and obey the words of Yeshua. Most notably, the word appears in Deut 6:4, which is the famous &amp;ldquo;Shema Israel&amp;rdquo; passage, which Jesus quotes in Mark 12:29.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;שְׁמַ֖ע&lt;/em&gt; יִשְׂרָאֵ֑ל יְהוָ֥ה אֱלֹהֵ֖ינוּ יְהוָ֥ה ׀ אֶחָֽד׃&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Hear, O Israel: The LORD our God, the LORD is one.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then Deuteronomy verse 5 continues, &amp;ldquo;You shall love the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your might.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &amp;ldquo;hear&amp;rdquo; is followed by a list of behaviors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s in a Name?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also contained within the word שָׁמַע are the letters שׁ and מ. When we put those together, we get שֶׁם (shem), which is the Hebrew word for name (Hebrew has five letters that are spelled differently when at the end of a word. The mem (מ/ם) is one of those).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your name is not just a string of letters. In Hebraic thought, your name is your reputation and your character. Being an obedient listener and one who diligently keeps/guards God&amp;rsquo;s word reflects on our reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, when we take on the name of Yeshua, we must positively reflect His character. We do that by keeping and guarding His words. In a sense this could be the third commandment. When we fail to keep and guard his name, we could be said to be taking on his name in vain. Conversely, there is a blessing to be had when we keep obey and guard His reputation.
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;very-soon-and-for-the-time-is-near&#34;&gt;Very soon and for the time is near!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John believed the fulfillment of all things was very near.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He did not mean merely within a few years and certainly did not mean two thousand years! He is writing with a sense of urgency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In fact, we can defend from Scripture that the New Testament authors didn&amp;rsquo;t just believe the &amp;ldquo;end times&amp;rdquo; were near; they thought the end times were upon them.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See 1 Corinthians 10:11 and note that Paul directly connects the Old Testament with the &amp;ldquo;end times.&amp;rdquo; Further, the &amp;ldquo;end times&amp;rdquo; IS the fulfillment of Old Testament Prophecies.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The above point is critically important to keep in mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul and John weren&amp;rsquo;t looking to events occurring in the world around them; they were looking to the &amp;ldquo;fulfillment of the purposes and prophecies of the Old Testament.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An alternate sense could be once the events commence, they will unfold rapidly;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 Peter 3:3-4 seems to imply Peter at least suspected there would be some delay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yet, at the end of the passage (2 Peter 3:10), Peter says every believer should be alert.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Seven Blessings&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are seven &lt;em&gt;berachot&lt;/em&gt; (blessings) starting with 1:3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blessed&lt;/strong&gt; are the reader and hearers of the words of this prophecy, provided they obey the things written in it! For the time is near! (Rev 1:3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blessed&lt;/strong&gt; are the dead who die in the Lord (Rev 14:13).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blessed&lt;/strong&gt; is he that watches and keeps his garments (Rev 16:15).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blessed&lt;/strong&gt; are they who are called unto the marriage supper of the Lamb (Rev 19:9).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blessed&lt;/strong&gt; and holy is he that hath part in the first resurrection (Rev 20:6).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blessed&lt;/strong&gt; is he that keeps the words of the prophecy of this book (Rev 22:7)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blessed&lt;/strong&gt; are they that wash their robes (Rev 22:14).
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-14-grace-and-shalom&#34;&gt;Rev 1:4: Grace and Shalom&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;OT Allusions&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4. From: Yochanan To: The seven Messianic communities in the province of Asia:  Grace and shalom to you from the One who is, who was and who is coming; from the sevenfold Spirit before his throne;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1:4 Isa 11: 2 And the Spirit of the LORD shall rest upon him, the Spirit of wisdom and understanding, the Spirit of counsel and might, the Spirit of knowledge and the fear of the LORD.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;from-yochananjohn&#34;&gt;From Yochanan/John&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While we can&amp;rsquo;t be 100% certain, most conservative scholars believe this is John the Apostle (see the introductory lesson for more background)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whichever John this was, we might say &amp;ldquo;he needed no introduction.&amp;rdquo; We are given no further background than &amp;ldquo;John,&amp;rdquo; indicating that he was well-known to his audience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several early church writers believed the letter was a forgery and argued that the book should not become part of the New Testament canon.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They based this view partly because the Greek of Revelation is borderline substandard quality, particularly compared to the Gospel of John.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This may be explained. The Gospel was composed with a translator, someone learned in Greek, which John was not. On Patmos, John was left with his limited Greek skills.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;seven-communitieschurches&#34;&gt;Seven communities/&amp;ldquo;churches&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/49f033022fe7e954bd6946926032fbc0.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;66%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immediately there is underlying tension we might miss.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are in Asia. Modern Turkey.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jews aren&amp;rsquo;t supposed to be outside Eretz Israel (the land of Israel)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a big clue that things are out of order&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the end of the book, they will be back in the Land&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We talked about this anachronism of the word &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo; during the introduction.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The church, either an institution or a gathering of people, did not exist when John wrote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is hard not to call them &amp;ldquo;the seven churches.&amp;rdquo; If we do, we need to be aware of the anachronism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number &amp;ldquo;seven&amp;rdquo; is a fingerprint of the Holy Spirit and speaks of completeness and fulfillment. It can also carry a sense of holiness/set apartness-the Shabbat (7th day) is a time to be set apart from the other six days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whatever other interpretations of Revelation may be plausible, we must remember first and foremost it was written to actual first-century congregations with real struggles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we look at a map&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the seven cities are in relative proximity. We can easily imagine the letter starting in Ephesus and traveling clockwise to Smyrna, using the Roman road system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of course, there were many more than seven congregations in Asia (one received a letter from Paul, Colossians).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t exactly know why these seven were called out
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indeed, these seven had real problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problems are likely typical of what other fellowships were going through at the time.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each letter will end with &amp;ldquo;hear what the Spirit says to the church&lt;em&gt;es&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; (i.e., the words are directed to all fellowships, not just the specific one addressed).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lancaster speculates that many fellowships likely existed in each town. In other words, there was probably not merely one assembly in Ephesus.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He says that although it is unlikely there were separate fellowships for Gentiles (as the Jew/Gentile split in Christianity had not yet occurred, or at best was only in its infancy), there may have been separate meetings for Believers in Messiah that were distinct from other Jewish fellowships.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This could explain why some believers had been arrested and martyred, but others in the same town had not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;grace-and-shalom-peace&#34;&gt;Grace and Shalom (Peace)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This could be a combination of the Greek &lt;em&gt;Charis&lt;/em&gt; (grace) and the Hebrew &lt;em&gt;shalom&lt;/em&gt; (peace)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr Bolen writes: &amp;ldquo;the greeting seems to combine a common formulaic openings in Greco-Roman and Semitic letters.&amp;rdquo; Grace&amp;rdquo; (Gk. charis, χάρις) is related to the common Greek word &amp;ldquo;greetings&amp;rdquo; (Gk. chairein, χαίρειν) as seen in Acts 15:23, 23:26, and James 1:1 (cf. Matt 26:49, Mark 15:18, Luke 1:28, and John 19:3). &amp;ldquo;Peace&amp;rdquo; (Gk. eirēnē, εἰρήνη; Heb. shalōm, שָׁלוֹם) is a common Semitic greeting as seen in Luke 10:5, 24:36, and John 20:19.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potentially, both meanings are encompassed by the rich Hebrew word &lt;em&gt;shalom.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dan Stolebarger says that when we wish someone &amp;ldquo;shalom,&amp;rdquo; we are wishing them &amp;ldquo;peace as it was before the Fall.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;True Shalom comes when God makes everything right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-trinity&#34;&gt;The Trinity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verses 4-5 are widely and correctly viewed as &lt;strong&gt;the Trinity.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In this case, the order is Father, Spirit, Son, which is consistent with John&amp;rsquo;s overall view that Jesus is (somehow) subordinate to the Father. It is the Spirit who empowers the Son.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Father – John uses an identical phrase as the Septuagint translation of Exodus 3:14.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Hebrew, this is unmistakable. “I am who I am” אֶֽהְיֶ֖ה אֲשֶׁ֣ר אֶֽהְיֶ֑ה (ehyeh asher eheyh).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In general terms, God is transcendent. Missler says, &amp;ldquo;Time is a physical property subject to mass acceleration and gravity. God&amp;rsquo;s not subject to those. God is not someone with lots of time. He&amp;rsquo;s outside our time domain altogether. He knows the end from the beginning.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note that the &amp;ldquo;Father&amp;rdquo; is also described as One who…&amp;rdquo; is coming&amp;rdquo; – we usually think of Jesus, the Son, as the One who is coming again. Still, in some sense, the Father is also coming.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Zechariah 14:4, Adonai will set His foot upon the Mount of Olives. The text doesn&amp;rsquo;t say, &amp;ldquo;Messiah will set foot upon the Mount of Olives.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In some places in Scripture, we see some distinction among the roles.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus sits at the right hand of the Father (Acts 2:33)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus doesn&amp;rsquo;t pray to Himself or the Spirit, but to the Father, and says His job is to glorify the Father. (John 17:1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In others, we see a blurring of roles.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both Adonai, whom we usually view as &amp;ldquo;The Father,&amp;rdquo; and Jesus say, &amp;ldquo;I am the first and the last.&amp;rdquo; (Father in Rev 1:8, Son in Rev 1:17).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul says the Spirit caused Jesus to rise from the Dead (Rom 8:11), and he also says it was the Father (Gal 1:1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In several locations, Jesus says He is the &amp;ldquo;I AM&amp;rdquo; of our Old Testament.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lizorkin and Shir phrase it like this: &amp;ldquo;The Son and the Father are distinct, but somehow so connected that they cannot always be distinguished.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the better comparisons I&amp;rsquo;ve heard to describe the Trinity is as three partners in a corporation. Each partner may act independently, but legally the corporation is one unit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All models are clumsy because we are trying to describe the infiniteness of God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bottom line is the more we can remain flexible in our concepts of the Trinity, the less befuddling Revelation will be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;sevenfold-spirit&#34;&gt;Sevenfold Spirit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This could also be rendered &amp;ldquo;seven spirits.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number seven represents completeness. Therefore &amp;ldquo;sevenfold Spirit&amp;rdquo; is likely simply describing the Spirit as the complete and perfect Spirit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jewish tradition sees seven archangels.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lancaster and Lizorkin/Shir dive into this in their commentaries and believe this is potentially in John&amp;rsquo;s view, given his Jewish background. They connect this verse with the seven angels that repeatedly appear in the book.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lancaster notes the parallel in the description of the person giving the revelation between Revelation 1:9-18 and Daniel 10.  In Daniel 10, the messenger is clearly a supernatural angel, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a member of the Trinity.  We will discuss this further in the next lesson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lizorkin and Shir are also skeptical of the connection to Isaiah 11:2, which is often cited as a parallel passage. &amp;ldquo;This does not explain why there are seven spirits mentioned in Revelation.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They caution that we may be force-reading our view of the trinity into this passage when that may not be what John intended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Seven angels&amp;rdquo; appear repeatedly in Revelation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-15-6-sevenfold-description-of-yeshua&#34;&gt;Rev 1:5-6: Sevenfold Description of Yeshua&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;OT Allusions&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5. and from Yeshua the Messiah, the faithful witness, the firstborn from the dead and the ruler of the earth&amp;rsquo;s kings. To him, the one who loves us, who has freed us from our sins at the cost of his blood,  6. who has caused us to be a kingdom, that is, Cohanim for God, his Father—to him be the glory and the rulership forever and ever. Amen.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1:5 Gen 49: 11 Binding his foal to the vine and his donkey&amp;rsquo;s colt to the choice vine, he has washed his garments in wine and his vesture in the blood of grapes. Psa 89:27 And I will make him the firstborn, the highest of the kings of the earth.   1:6 Ex 19:5-6 Now therefore, if you will indeed obey my voice and keep my covenant, you shall be my treasured possession among all peoples, for all the earth is mine; 6 and you shall be to me a kingdom of priests and a holy nation.&#39; These are the words that you shall speak to the people of Israel.&amp;rdquo; Isa 61:6 but you shall be called the priests of the LORD; they shall speak of you as the ministers of our God; you shall eat the wealth of the nations, and in their glory you shall boast.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;firstborn-of-the-dead&#34;&gt;Firstborn of the dead&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not to say that Jesus was the first ever to be raised from the dead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Judaism, &amp;ldquo;firstborn&amp;rdquo; is a title of inheritance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The firstborn would receive a double-portion.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While usually, this was the eldest son, the eldest son could forfeit the title of firstborn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joseph was the 11th of Jacob&amp;rsquo;s 12 sons, yet was the titular Firstborn who received a double portion of Jacob&amp;rsquo;s inheritance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Jewish feast of firstfruits is also in view (always on Sunday after Passover).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This title is synonymous with victory .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because Jesus conquered death, we can (and will!) too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;ruler-of-the-earths-kingsone-who-loves-usfreed-uscaused-us-to-be-cohanim-priests&#34;&gt;Ruler of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s Kings/One who loves us/Freed us/Caused us to be Cohanim (priests)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/be7a878b3dea1900acab133304ac1516.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34;/&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 1 Corinthians 15 (the &amp;ldquo;resurrection chapter&amp;rdquo;), Paul connects the dots – since Jesus is the firstborn of the dead, He will come again and &amp;ldquo;hand over the Kingdom to God the Father, after having put an end to every rulership, yes, to every authority and power.&amp;rdquo; (1Co 15:24)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To an audience fearful of persecution, these words remind them who is truly in charge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conversely, the challenge for us is whether we have indeed submitted to his kingship, or are we still telling Him, &amp;ldquo;I got this&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When we submit to Him, it&amp;rsquo;s good to know that He loves us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation tells the outcome for those who tell God, &amp;ldquo;I got this.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exodus 19:5-6: Now therefore, if you will indeed obey my voice and keep my covenant, you shall be my treasured possession among all peoples, for all the earth is mine; and you shall be to me a kingdom of priests and a holy nation.&#39; These are the words that you shall speak to the people of Israel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All of this has to do with how we spend our time in this life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Seven components to the description of Messiah&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He is the faithful witness (or &amp;ldquo;the faithful martyr&amp;rdquo;; see Rev_2:13).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He is the firstborn (or &amp;ldquo;foremost, chief&amp;rdquo;) of those who get raised from the dead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He is the ruler of the earth&amp;rsquo;s kings, the &amp;ldquo;King of Kings&amp;rdquo; (Rev_17:14, Rev_19:16) who will one day subject to himself even the most unbridled and oppressive governments (1Co_15:24-25).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He loves us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He causes us to be freed from our sins at the cost of his blood (that is, by his bloody, sacrificial death; see Rom_3:24).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He causes us to be a kingdom, a community subject to him who loves us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He causes us to be cohanim (&amp;ldquo;priests&amp;rdquo;) for God, his Father.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern notes that the first three attributes would have brought immediate comfort to the faithful. Because He loves us, we gain the final three &amp;ldquo;benefits&amp;rdquo; as we might call them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern, &lt;em&gt;Jewish New Testament Commentary&lt;/em&gt;, v. 1:5-6.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Sevens: &amp;lsquo;Amen!&amp;rsquo;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amen is a Hebrew word that connotes &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;may it be so.&amp;rdquo; Every time you say &amp;ldquo;amen,&amp;rdquo; you&amp;rsquo;re speaking Hebrew! Yay you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who has caused us to be a kingdom, that is, cohanim for God, his Father—to him be the glory and the rulership forever and ever. &lt;strong&gt;Amen&lt;/strong&gt;. (Rev 1:6)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look! He is coming with the clouds! Every eye will see him, including those who pierced him; and all the tribes of the Land will mourn him. Yes! &lt;strong&gt;Amen&lt;/strong&gt;! (Rev 1:7)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;To the angel of the Messianic Community in Laodicea, write: &amp;lsquo;Here is the message from the &lt;strong&gt;Amen&lt;/strong&gt;, the faithful and true witness, the Ruler of God&amp;rsquo;s creation: (Rev 3:14)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The four living beings said, &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Amen&lt;/strong&gt;!&amp;rdquo; and the elders fell down and worshipped. (Rev 5:14)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Amen! &amp;ldquo;Praise and glory, wisdom and thanks, honor and power and strength belong to our God forever and ever! &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Amen&lt;/strong&gt;!&amp;rdquo; (Rev 7:12)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The twenty-four elders and the four living beings fell down and worshipped God, sitting on the throne, and said, &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Amen&lt;/strong&gt;! Halleluyah!&amp;rdquo; (Rev 19:4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The one who is testifying to these things says, &amp;lsquo;Yes, I am coming soon!&amp;rsquo; &amp;quot; &lt;strong&gt;Amen&lt;/strong&gt;! Come, Lord Yeshua! (Rev 22:20)
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-17-he-comes-in-the-clouds&#34;&gt;Rev 1:7: He Comes In The Clouds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;OT Allusions&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7. Look! He is coming with the clouds! Every eye will see him, including those who pierced him; and all the tribes of the Land will mourn him. Yes! Amen!  8. &amp;ldquo;I am the &amp;lsquo;A&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;lsquo;Z,&amp;rsquo; &amp;quot; says Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, the One who is, who was and who is coming.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1:7 Dan 7:13-14 &amp;ldquo;I saw in the night visions, and behold, with the clouds of heaven there came one like a son of man, and he came to the Ancient of Days and was presented before him. &lt;br&gt;Zech 12:10-14 &amp;ldquo;And I will pour out on the house of David and the inhabitants of Jerusalem a spirit of grace and pleas for mercy, so that, when they look on me, on him whom they have pierced, they shall mourn for him, as one mourns for an only child, and weep bitterly over him, as one weeps over a firstborn. 11 On that day the mourning in Jerusalem will be as great as the mourning for Hadad-rimmon in the plain of Megiddo. 12 The land shall mourn, each family by itself: the family of the house of David by itself, and their wives by themselves; the family of the house of Nathan by itself, and their wives by themselves; 13 the family of the house of Levi by itself, and their wives by themselves; the family of the Shimeites by itself, and their wives by themselves; 14 and all the families that are left, each by itself, and their wives by themselves. &lt;br&gt; 1:8 Isa 41:4 Who has performed and done this, calling the generations from the beginning? I, the LORD, the first, and with the last; I am he.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;look-behold-he-comes&#34;&gt;Look! Behold He comes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Hebrew word for &amp;ldquo;behold&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;hinei&amp;rdquo; and it frequently appears in the Old Testament
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You may have learned that the word &amp;ldquo;therefore&amp;rdquo; is a clue, particularly in Paul&amp;rsquo;s writings. The saying goes, &amp;ldquo;whenever you see a &amp;lsquo;therefore,&amp;rsquo; you always want to ask, &amp;lsquo;what is it there for?&#39;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conceptually the same is true for &amp;ldquo;behold&amp;rdquo; in the Old Testament. The author is calling something to our attention in the narrative. We want to make sure we know what is we are beholding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Hineini!  הִנֵנִי&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Closely related to the word &amp;ldquo;hinei&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;heneini.&amp;rdquo; In Genesis 22, when God calls out,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Avraham! Avraham!&amp;rdquo; Abraham answers in Hebrew, &amp;ldquo;Hineini!&amp;rdquo; – translated as &amp;ldquo;here am I&amp;rdquo; but also the purpose of Behold, me! In the sense of &amp;ldquo;I am available, pick me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isaiah also says &amp;ldquo;Hineini&amp;rdquo; in Isaiah 6:8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an expression that God values your &lt;em&gt;avail&lt;/em&gt;ability more than he values your ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a great Hebrew prayer, just tell God, &amp;ldquo;Hineini!&amp;rdquo; Look! I&amp;rsquo;m available!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;clouds&#34;&gt;Clouds&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compare Acts 1:11 – He will return very similar to how He ascended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniel 7 talks about the Messiah emerging from clouds and going before the Ancient of Days. There the Father gives the Son all things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A minor note that whoever is speaking switches to the 3rd person in verse seven, and then God will take over in Verse 8. Figuring out who is speaking is not nearly as important as the truth of the words spoken. Still, it&amp;rsquo;s interesting to notice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-tribes-will-mourn&#34;&gt;The tribes will mourn&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protestant/Pre-tribulation theology holds that once these events happen, there may be little, if any, hope for any unbeliever to repent, least of all traditional Jews who are cursed for rejecting their Messiah and forfeited all of their promises to the Church. This view stems from Replacement Theology. See the callout note below for additional information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zechariah 13:11 tells a different story. They will mourn him but that not the end of the story.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The people specifically from the House of David will be cleansed from their sins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore a &amp;ldquo;terminal&amp;rdquo; judgment may not be what John is communicating in verse 7.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The mourning may be that of a repentant heart; the same heart we should have when we ponder the price He truly paid for us. Through his sacrifice, all the families of the Earth shall be blessed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Replacement Theology&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a personal note, ever since my first trip to Israel in 2010, my eyes have been more open to the fact that we hold in our hands a single book, which in the hands of gentile church leaders all but stripped it of its Jewishness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, come to find our Messiah/Christ is Jewish. All the writers of the New Testament were Jewish. As best we can tell, Luke was a gentile convert to Judaism. The Bible, first and foremost, is about the redemption of Israel and the coming Messianic Kingdom; Revelation is the culmination of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roman 11 says the Gentiles have been grafted in and should not boast about our superiority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a nasty theory that goes by the name of Replacement Theology, which says that because Israel rejected and crucified her Messiah, all the promises meant for Israel in the Old Testament now have their spiritual fulfillment in the Church. Other components include the beliefs that Jesus and Paul forsook their Judaism and founded a gentile religion. It is said that Jesus was a sabbath breaker and Paul disregarded the dietary laws. All of these are provable as false if we do Acts 17:11 research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with this general theory is it makes God an untrustworthy liar, the Old Testament irrelevant, the law as opposite of grace, and causes us to see Jews as enemies. Replacement Theology is a tare that the enemy has planted, which has grown up alongside the nutritious kernels of solid doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must guard against Replacement Theology as this violates the two great commandments. If we view God as able to break His promises, how can we say we &amp;ldquo;love the Lord our God with our whole hearts, minds, and strengths?&amp;rdquo; If we ascribe the evil deeds of what may have been less than 20 corrupt religious leaders and blame an entire race of people, how can we say we &amp;ldquo;love our neighbors as ourselves?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Replacement Theology is a lie that has been repeated so often for the last 1500 years that it seeps into otherwise educated and insightful men writing contemporary commentaries. I may agree with 90% of everything else a given commentator says but if there is even a hint of Replacement Theology, I&amp;rsquo;m going to do my best to call it out and correct the errant conclusion.
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-18-the-aleph-and-the-tav&#34;&gt;Rev 1:8: The Aleph and the Tav&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;OT Allusions&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8. &amp;ldquo;I am the &amp;lsquo;A&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;lsquo;Z,&amp;rsquo; &amp;quot; says Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, the One who is, who was and who is coming.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1:8 Isa 41:4 Who has performed and done this, calling the generations from the beginning? I, the LORD, the first, and with the last; I am he.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;alpha-and-omegaa-and-zaleph-and-tav&#34;&gt;Alpha and Omega/A and Z/Aleph and Tav&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We typically think of Jesus as saying He is the Alpha and the Omega, but note here, we would say it is &amp;ldquo;God the Father&amp;rdquo; speaking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The phrase also appears in Rev 21:6 and Rev 22:13.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Hebrew, the first and last letters are Aleph א and Tav ת.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The word אֵת (et) has a unique function in Hebrew. See the callout box if you are interested in learning more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note again that the Father says He &amp;ldquo;is coming.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another one of God&amp;rsquo;s names in the Hebrew Bible is El Shaddai - which is God almighty in the sense of the protector.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;The Aleph and the Tav&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hebrew word אֵת is most often used as a grammatical marker in the Bible. It is used to indicate a definite direct object. When used this way, it has no direct translational value. It is spelled with Aleph (א) and tav (ת).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional Jewish exegesis (a fancy word for &amp;ldquo;Bible study&amp;rdquo;) sees four layers of meaning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The literal surface meaning – we always start here, and the deeper interpretations must never contradict the base meaning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is called a &amp;ldquo;hint of something deeper.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A comparative meaning often drawn from the conclusion of similar words/phrases among passages.
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, Deuteronomy 6:5 and Leviticus 19:18 contain the exact phrase, &amp;ldquo;and you shall love.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus was employing this level of interpretation when He linked these two verses as &amp;ldquo;the greatest commandment&amp;rdquo; – &amp;ldquo;and you shall love the Lord your God…&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;and you shall love your neighbor…&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An esoteric mystical meaning (obviously, we use this one with caution).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a &amp;ldquo;hint of something deeper,&amp;rdquo; several verses in Hebrew can take on an added deeper meaning when we consider that Jesus called Himself the &amp;ldquo;Aleph and the Tav.&amp;rdquo; Let&amp;rsquo;s look at just three of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genesis 1:1 – the very first verse in the Bible:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;בְּרֵאשִׁית בָּרָא אֱלֹהִים &lt;strong&gt;אֵת&lt;/strong&gt; הַשָּׁמַיִם &lt;strong&gt;וְאֵת&lt;/strong&gt; הָאָרֶץ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curiously there are also precisely seven Hebrew words. In the beginning (all one word) created God (et) the heaven (et) the earth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could we also say that in the beginning, God, &lt;strong&gt;the Aleph, and Tav&lt;/strong&gt;, created the heavens, and &lt;strong&gt;the Aleph and Tav&lt;/strong&gt; created the world? I believe we could.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genesis 1:4
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;וַיַּ֧רְא אֱלֹהִ֛ים &lt;strong&gt;אֶת&lt;/strong&gt;־הָא֖וֹר כִּי־ט֑וֹב&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And God saw the light, and it was good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And God saw &lt;strong&gt;the Aleph and Tav&lt;/strong&gt;, the Light, and it was good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zechariah 12:10
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;והביטו אלי &lt;strong&gt;את&lt;/strong&gt; אשׁר־דקרו&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They will look upon me whom they have pierced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They will look upon me, &lt;strong&gt;the Aleph and Tav,&lt;/strong&gt; whom they have pierced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Seven &amp;lsquo;LORD, God Almighty&amp;rsquo;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the literal phrase used in the Old Testament (אֱלֹהֵֽי־צְבָא֖וֹת which sometimes gets translated as &amp;ldquo;God of Hosts&amp;rdquo;, and commonly, but &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; poorly transliterated as &amp;ldquo;Jehovah Sabaoth&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I am the &amp;lsquo;A&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;lsquo;Z,&amp;rsquo; &amp;quot; says Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, the One who is, who was and who is coming. (Rev 1:8)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each of the four living beings had six wings and was covered with eyes inside and out; and day and night they never stop saying, &amp;ldquo;Holy, holy, holy is Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies the One who was, who is and who is coming!&amp;rdquo; (Rev 4:8)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;saying, &amp;ldquo;We thank you, Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, the One who is and was, that you have taken your power and have begun to rule. (Rev 11:17)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They were singing the song of Moshe, the servant of God, and the song of the Lamb: &amp;ldquo;Great and wonderful are the things you have done, Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies! Just and true are your ways, king of the nations! (Rev 15:3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then I heard the altar say, &amp;ldquo;Yes, Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, your judgments are true and just!&amp;rdquo; (Rev 16:7)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then I heard what sounded like the roar of a huge crowd, like the sound of rushing waters, like loud peals of thunder, saying, &amp;ldquo;Halleluyah! Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, has begun his reign! (Rev 19:6)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I saw no Temple in the city, for Adonai, God of heaven&amp;rsquo;s armies, is its Temple, as is the Lamb. (Rev 21:22)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why &amp;ldquo;Adonai&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many of our English Bibles, when translators came across what is called the &amp;ldquo;Tetragrammaton&amp;rdquo; (The Hebrew word for God&amp;rsquo;s name spelled yod-hei-vav-hei), they typically render it as &lt;small&gt;LORD&lt;/small&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, they are preserving a Jewish custom that was in place during the time of Jesus&#39; ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observant Jews will never attempt to pronounce this name. Instead, they will say &amp;ldquo;Adonai&amp;rdquo; if in a formal/religious setting or &amp;ldquo;Hashem,&amp;rdquo; Hebrew for &amp;ldquo;The Name,&amp;rdquo; if in a less formal setting. This purposeful avoidance of using God&amp;rsquo;s sacred Name is called a &amp;ldquo;circumlocution.&amp;rdquo; Jesus used circumlocutions many times and NEVER pronounced the Name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We encourage our students to use a circumlocution such as &amp;ldquo;Lord&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Adonai.&amp;rdquo;. It shows similar honor as not calling your parents by their first name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, &amp;ldquo;Jehovah&amp;rdquo; is a made-up word. Some Hebrew Bibles add the vowels from &amp;ldquo;Adonai&amp;rdquo; to the Tetragrammaton. This is to remind readers to say &amp;ldquo;Adonai.&amp;rdquo; When some non-Hebrew speaker mistakenly tried to pronounce this non-word, he came up with &amp;ldquo;Jehovah.&amp;rdquo; Don&amp;rsquo;t call God &amp;ldquo;Jehovah.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s not a real word!
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;El Shaddai&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever been to a Jewish home, you may have noticed something long and narrow attached to an outer door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/e5d1e7831cd11a6b9ef323c77f8d1a18.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;33%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is called a Mezuzah and it comes from a command in Deu 6:9 You shall write them on the doorposts of your house and on your gates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Referring to the Shema, you shall love the Lord with all your heart, all your soul and all your might.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inside the Mezuzah will be a scroll with the Shema and other passages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the outside of the Mezuzah will be the Hebrew letter Shin, the W looking character you can see on this mezuzah. The shin is short for Shaddai.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mezuzah serves as a reminder that God almighty is the great protector and in return He asks for our love and obedience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll say this a lot but remember John&amp;rsquo;s original audience was under a death sentence for practicing their faith. They neeed to be reminded of God&amp;rsquo;s almighty-ness and His protection and provision. God&amp;rsquo;s army is WAAAAY more powerful than the Roman army.
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-19-patmos&#34;&gt;Rev 1:9: Patmos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revelation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OT Allusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I, Yochanan, am a brother of yours and a fellow-sharer in the suffering, kingship, and perseverance that come from being united with Yeshua. I had been exiled to the island called Patmos for having proclaimed the message of God and borne witness to Yeshua.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 10:2-4 In those days I, Daniel, was mourning for three weeks. 3 I ate no delicacies, no meat or wine entered my mouth, nor did I anoint myself at all, for the full three weeks. 4 On the twenty-fourth day of the first month, as I was standing on the bank of the great river (that is, the Tigris)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;exiled-to-patmos&#34;&gt;Exiled to Patmos&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/4ba61b20eea37afb7fb8d31162fcbb1a.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John is positioning himself as an equal, not a superior; an empathizer not a sympathizer.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We discussed how John came to be at Patmos during our background lesson.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patmos is a relatively small Greek island (17.5 sq mi) about 35 miles off the coast of Turkey.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were two levels of Roman exile&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first was actual deportation (&lt;em&gt;deportatio in insulaim&lt;/em&gt;), in which the prisoner lost all rights; this was permanent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second was what we might call a relegation (&lt;em&gt;relegation ad insulam&lt;/em&gt;), which was a temporary banishment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It appears John fell into the second group. In any case, the Romans did not want the Gospel going out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surrounded by water, it is no surprise that the sea is a dominant image throughout the book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the fifth century, the &amp;ldquo;Cave of the Apocalypse&amp;rdquo; has been venerated to mark the site where John received visitation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo credit:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;proclaimed-the-message-of-god&#34;&gt;Proclaimed the message of God&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This will be a recurring theme as many believers will be martyred for this reason.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We believe John wasn&amp;rsquo;t directly martyred but died of natural causes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, if we believe the tradition, Domitian ordered John boiled in oil, yet John was spared.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Jewish mind would say that John &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; martyred, and then he was delivered by God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;daniel-10-as-parallel-passage&#34;&gt;Daniel 10 as parallel passage&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a parallel of Revelation 1:9-20 and Daniel 10, which we will explore next lesson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For now, note the similarities of 1:9 to Daniel 10:2-4.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They both have a &amp;ldquo;double&amp;rdquo; introduction for emphasis (&amp;ldquo;I, John&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;I, Daniel&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both can be said to be physically suffering for God (John externally and Daniel internally through a three-week fast).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both are in exile (John at Patmos, Daniel on the bank of the Tigres in Babylon).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-110-in-the-spirit-on-the-day-of-the-lord&#34;&gt;Rev 1:10: In the Spirit on the Day of the Lord&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;I came to be, in the Spirit, on the Day of the Lord; and I heard behind me a loud voice, like a trumpet&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-came-to-be-in-the-spirit&#34;&gt;I came to be in the Spirit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three primary options, each of which is a conjecture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John&amp;rsquo;s received a vision but was not physically transported anywhere, like a dream (and it was not uncommon for people to receive messages from God via dreams)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John had what we might call an &amp;ldquo;out of body experience&amp;rdquo;; his body remained on Patmos, but he was otherwise transported to the heavenly throne&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John was physically present&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2 Corinthians 12:2, Paul says, &amp;ldquo;whether in the body or out of the body, I do not know.&amp;rdquo;  Maybe John himself didn&amp;rsquo;t know either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;day-of-the-lordlords-day&#34;&gt;Day of the Lord/Lord&amp;rsquo;s Day&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was this a weekday or a moment in time? The possibilities discussed below are conjecture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Sunday
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While this is the day we honor the resurrection, there is no biblical evidence that the first day of the week was ever referred to as &amp;ldquo;The Lord&amp;rsquo;s day.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Saturday
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;According to Genesis 2, Exodus 16, and Exodus 20, if there is one day of the week that God holds holy, it&amp;rsquo;s Saturday.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a direct connection between the Sabbath and the kingdom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, the Bible never refers to Shabbat as &amp;ldquo;the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Day&amp;rdquo; either.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This view is further rendered unlikely since John was told to write, a creative activity widely considered prohibited on Shabbat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John was not referencing a specific day of the week, but a particular moment in time: &lt;strong&gt;the fulfillment and restoration of all things.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are NUMEROUS biblical references for the &amp;ldquo;Day of the Lord&amp;rdquo; to support this view: (Is. 2:12; 13:6-9; Ezek. 13:5, 30:3; Joel 1:15; 2:1-31; 3:14; Amos 5:18-20; Obad. 15; Zeph 1:7-14; Zech 14:1; Mal 4:5).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is where I tend to land.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John wasn&amp;rsquo;t telling us the day of the week so much as he told us the moment in time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As Stern comments, for John to note the day of the week would be a minor if not an entirely insignificant detail. For John to say he was present for the final judgment is monumentally significant.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-loud-voice-like-a-trumpet&#34;&gt;A loud voice like a trumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hebrew for loud voice &lt;em&gt;kol gadol –&lt;/em&gt; this is also how the Bible describes thunder or a deafening noise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Daniel 10:6, &amp;ldquo;the sound of his words were like the sound of a multitude.&amp;rdquo; (photo credit&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). John hears the same sound, but it is &amp;ldquo;loud voice, like a trumpet&amp;rdquo; to him.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Greek does not indicate whether the trumpet is a &lt;em&gt;shofar&lt;/em&gt; (a ram&amp;rsquo;s horn made into a trumpet) or a brass trumpet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A brass trumpet would connote a call to battle, while a shofar would connote a call to worship. Either may be applicable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Later in chapter 1, John will more clearly describe a &lt;em&gt;menorah&lt;/em&gt;, so precisely, a &lt;em&gt;shofar&lt;/em&gt;, also used in the Jewish Temple service, looks likely here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In any case, when a Jew such as John heard a trumpet, he knew it was a call to assemble and prepare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-111-write&#34;&gt;Rev 1:11: Write!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;OT Allusions&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11. saying, &amp;ldquo;Write down what you see on a scroll, and send it to the seven Messianic communities—Ephesus, Smyrna, Pergamum, Thyatira, Sardis, Philadelphia, and Laodicea!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1:11 Isa 30:8 And now, go, write it before them on a tablet and inscribe it in a book, that it may be for the time to come as a witness forever.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;write-down-what-you-see&#34;&gt;Write down what you see&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/1407b53c7491ccf1e8715a718106bb21.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John wrote the vision down right away not just to remember it but also so it would function as a testimony.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The person receiving an apocalypse was often told to &amp;ldquo;seal up&amp;rdquo; the words. Not so with John. This is to be an &amp;ldquo;open&amp;rdquo; book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo credit: &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will discuss the background of the seven cities when we get to chapters 2-3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Seven First and Last?&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The KJV adds, &amp;ldquo;I am Alpha and Omega, the first and the last&amp;rdquo; before the instruction to write.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This phrase is not contained in the newer translations (NIV, ESV, NLT, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As familiar as the phrase &amp;ldquo;First and Last&amp;rdquo; is, it only occurs three times in Isaiah and then, according to KJV, four times in Revelation for a total of seven.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In this instance, it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t surprise me if the KJV is correct and the other translations were mistaken in omitting &amp;ldquo;I am the first and the last&amp;rdquo; from verse 11.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isaiah 41:4 Who has performed and done this, calling the generations from the beginning? I, the LORD, the first, and with the last; I am he.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isaiah 44:6 Thus says the LORD, the King of Israel and his Redeemer, the LORD of hosts: “I am the first and I am the last; besides me there is no god.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isaiah 48:12  “Listen to me, O Jacob, and Israel, whom I called! I am he; I am the first, and I am the last.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Revelation 1:11&lt;/em&gt; (disputed) Saying, &lt;em&gt;I am Alpha and Omega, the first and the last: and,&lt;/em&gt; What thou seest, write in a book, and send it unto the seven churches which are in Asia;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation 1:17 And he laid his right hand upon me, saying unto me, Fear not; I am the first and the last&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation 2:8 And unto the angel of the church in Smyrna write; These things saith the first and the last, which was dead, and is alive;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation 22:13  I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, the first and the last.
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verse 12 will begin a very unusual description of Jesus (or perhaps a blurring of the entire Godhead). We will pick this up next time, but there is one crucial point to make. The picture of Jesus in our minds may be quite different from the Jesus of Revelation. We must be conformed to his image and not force God to conform to our image. As we have been saying, we need not cling too tightly to any preconceptions. Revelation may challenge a lot of them. Part of the blessing from reading Revelation comes with our own unveiling; that is, when our biases and bloodspots are exposed and resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eli Lizorkin-Eyzenberg and Pinchas Shir, &lt;em&gt;Hebrew Insights from Revelation&lt;/em&gt;, Kindle., Jewish Studies for Christians, 2021, 32.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David H. Stern, &lt;em&gt;Jewish New Testament Commentary: A Companion Volume to the Jewish New Testament&lt;/em&gt;, E-Sword edition. (Clarksville, Md.: Lederer Messianic Publications, 1992), v. 1:3.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tom Bradford, “Lesson 2 - Revelation 1,” &lt;em&gt;Seed of Abraham Ministries, Inc&lt;/em&gt;, accessed January 31, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.torahclass.com/bible-studies/new-testament-studies/1917-new-testament-revelation/2864-lesson-2-revelation-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.torahclass.com/bible-studies/new-testament-studies/1917-new-testament-revelation/2864-lesson-2-revelation-1&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ibid.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lizorkin-Eyzenberg and Shir, &lt;em&gt;Hebrew Insights from Revelation&lt;/em&gt;, 24.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, &lt;em&gt;Smyrna-Izmir&lt;/em&gt;, vol. Western Turkey, Pictorial Library of Bible Lands, 2012, 2.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel T. Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;A Lamp in Ephesus&lt;/em&gt;, Apocalypse of John, 2015, accessed January 19, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bethimmanuel.org/audio-series/apocalypse-of-john&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bethimmanuel.org/audio-series/apocalypse-of-john&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, &lt;em&gt;Colossians 1&lt;/em&gt;, vol. Colossians, Photo Companion to the Bible (Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), 13.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One tell-tale sign of this in the Gospels is when people pick up stones to stone Jesus. We may miss what is going on, but in the people&amp;rsquo;s minds, Jesus had just committed blasphemy by equating Himself to God (or as Christians would say, &amp;ldquo;God the Father&amp;rdquo;). The penalty for blasphemy is death by stoning.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lizorkin-Eyzenberg and Shir, &lt;em&gt;Hebrew Insights from Revelation&lt;/em&gt;, 32.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 29.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Wilson, “Geography of the Island of Patmos,” in &lt;em&gt;Lexham Geographic Commentary on Acts through Revelation&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Barry J. Beitzel (Bellingham, WA: Lexham Press, 2019), 624.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, “Patmos (BiblePlaces.Com) – BiblePlaces.Com,” n.d., accessed January 19, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/patmos/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/patmos/&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern, &lt;em&gt;Jewish New Testament Commentary&lt;/em&gt;, v. 1:10.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, &lt;em&gt;Daniel 10&lt;/em&gt;, vol. Daniel, Photo Companion to the Bible (Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), 25.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, &lt;em&gt;Daniel 7&lt;/em&gt;, vol. Daniel, Photo Companion to the Bible (Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), 8.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4. One Like a Son of Man (Rev 1:12-20)</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/one-like-a-son-of-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/revelation/one-like-a-son-of-man/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#daniel-7-and-10&#34;&gt;Daniel 7 and 10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-112-gold-menorah&#34;&gt;Rev 1:12: Gold Menorah&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-113-one-like-a-son-of-man&#34;&gt;Rev 1:13: One Like a Son of Man&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-114-head-hair-and-eyes&#34;&gt;Rev 1:14: Head, Hair, and Eyes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-115-feet-and-voice&#34;&gt;Rev 1:15: Feet and Voice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-116-right-hand-mouth-and-face&#34;&gt;Rev 1:16: Right Hand, Mouth, and Face&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-117-fear-not&#34;&gt;Rev 1:17: Fear not!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-118-i-was-dead-but-behold-i-am-alive&#34;&gt;Rev 1:18: &amp;ldquo;I was dead but behold, I Am alive!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-119-μετα-ταυτα&#34;&gt;Rev 1:19: μετα ταυτα&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rev-120-the-meaning-of-the-starsmenorah&#34;&gt;Rev 1:20: The Meaning of the Stars/Menorah&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#postscript-rev-1-and-dan-10&#34;&gt;Postscript: Rev 1 and Dan 10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
  window.ESV_CROSSREF_OPTIONS = {
    body_background_color: &#39;D7E5F0&#39;,
    header_font_size: 10,
    body_font_size: 1,
    footer_font_size: 8,
    header_font_family: &#39;Arial&#39;,
    body_font_family: &#39;Times&#39;
  };
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://static.esvmedia.org/crossref/crossref.min.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read/hear the portions&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation 1:12-20&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12. I turned around to see who was speaking to me; and when I had turned, I saw seven gold menorahs; 13. and among the menorahs was someone like a Son of Man, wearing a robe down to his feet and a gold band around his chest. 14. His head and hair were as white as snow-white wool, his eyes like a fiery flame, 15. his feet like burnished brass refined in a furnace, and his voice like the sound of rushing waters. 16. In his right hand he held seven stars, out of his mouth went a sharp double-edged sword, and his face was like the sun shining in full strength. 17. When I saw him, I fell down at his feet like a dead man. He placed his right hand upon me and said, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid! I am the First and the Last, 18. the Living One. I was dead, but look!—I am alive forever and ever! And I hold the keys to Death and Sh&amp;rsquo;ol. 19. So write down what you see, both what is now, and what will happen afterward. 20. Here is the secret meaning of the seven stars you saw in my right hand, and of the seven gold menorahs: the seven stars are the angels of the seven Messianic communities, and the seven menorahs are the seven Messianic communities.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VrImdKWK4dU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;daniel-7-and-10&#34;&gt;Daniel 7 and 10&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The so-called &amp;ldquo;Vision of the Risen Christ&amp;rdquo; in Revelation 1:12-18 has several similarities (and key differences) with Daniel 7 and Daniel 10. It is beneficial to read the Daniel passages before we begin a verse-by-verse study of the remainder of Revelation 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Daniel passages, focus on the depictions of the &amp;ldquo;Ancient of Days&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;Son of Man&amp;rdquo; in Daniel 7:9-14, and then the description of the unnamed angel in Daniel 10:5-10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-2&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Daniel 7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1) In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon, Daniel saw a dream and visions of his head as he lay in his bed. Then he wrote down the dream and told the sum of the matter. (2) Daniel declared, &amp;ldquo;I saw in my vision by night, and behold, the four winds of heaven were stirring up the great sea. (3) And four great beasts came up out of the sea, different from one another. (4) The first was like a lion and had eagles&#39; wings. Then as I looked its wings were plucked off, and it was lifted up from the ground and made to stand on two feet like a man, and the mind of a man was given to it. (5) And behold, another beast, a second one, like a bear. It was raised up on one side. It had three ribs in its mouth between its teeth; and it was told, &amp;lsquo;Arise, devour much flesh.&amp;rsquo; (6) After this I looked, and behold, another, like a leopard, with four wings of a bird on its back. And the beast had four heads, and dominion was given to it. (7) After this I saw in the night visions, and behold, a fourth beast, terrifying and dreadful and exceedingly strong. It had great iron teeth; it devoured and broke in pieces and stamped what was left with its feet. It was different from all the beasts that were before it, and it had ten horns. (8) I considered the horns, and behold, there came up among them &lt;mark&gt;another horn, a little one, before which three of the first horns were plucked up by the roots. And behold, in this horn were eyes like the eyes of a man, and a mouth speaking great things&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(9) &amp;ldquo;As I looked, thrones were placed, and the &lt;mark&gt;Ancient of Days took his seat&lt;/mark&gt;; his &lt;mark&gt;clothing was white as snow, and the hair of his head like pure wool&lt;/mark&gt;; his throne was fiery flames; its wheels were burning fire. (10) A stream of fire issued and came out from before him; a thousand thousands served him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood before him; the court sat in judgment, and the books were opened. (11) &amp;ldquo;I looked then because of the sound of the great words that the horn was speaking. And as I looked, the beast was killed, and its body destroyed and given over to be burned with fire. (12) As for the rest of the beasts, their dominion was taken away, but their lives were prolonged for a season and a time. (13) &amp;ldquo;I saw in the night visions, and behold, &lt;mark&gt;with the clouds of heaven there came one like a son of man&lt;/mark&gt;, and he came to the Ancient of Days and was presented before him. (14) And to him was given dominion and glory and a kingdom, that all peoples, nations, and languages should serve him; his dominion is an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass away, and his kingdom one that shall not be destroyed. (15) &amp;ldquo;As for me, Daniel, my spirit within me was anxious, and the visions of my head alarmed me. (16) I approached one of those who stood there and asked him the truth concerning all this. So he told me and made known to me the interpretation of the things.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(17) &amp;lsquo;These four great beasts are four kings who shall arise out of the earth. (18) But the saints of the Most High shall receive the kingdom and possess the kingdom forever, forever and ever.&amp;rsquo; (19) &amp;ldquo;Then I desired to know the truth about the fourth beast, which was different from all the rest, exceedingly terrifying, with its teeth of iron and claws of bronze, and which devoured and broke in pieces and stamped what was left with its feet, (20) and about the ten horns that were on its head, and the other horn that came up and before which three of them fell, the horn that had eyes and a mouth that spoke great things, and that seemed greater than its companions. (21) As I looked, this horn made war with the saints and prevailed over them, (22) until the Ancient of Days came, and judgment was given for the saints of the Most High, and the time came when the saints possessed the kingdom. (23) &amp;ldquo;Thus he said: &amp;lsquo;As for the fourth beast, there shall be a fourth kingdom on earth, which shall be different from all the kingdoms, and it shall devour the whole earth, and trample it down, and break it to pieces. (24) As for the ten horns, out of this kingdom ten kings shall arise, and another shall arise after them; he shall be different from the former ones, and shall put down three kings. (25) He shall speak words against the Most High, and shall wear out the saints of the Most High, and shall think to change the times and the law; and they shall be given into his hand for a time, times, and half a time. (26) But the court shall sit in judgment, and his dominion shall be taken away, to be consumed and destroyed to the end. (27) And the kingdom and the dominion and the greatness of the kingdoms under the whole heaven shall be given to the people of the saints of the Most High; his kingdom shall be an everlasting kingdom, and all dominions shall serve and obey him.&amp;rsquo; (28) &amp;ldquo;Here is the end of the matter. As for me, Daniel, my thoughts greatly alarmed me, and my color changed, but I kept the matter in my heart.&amp;rdquo; &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One suggestion is that Daniel was alarmed in verse 15 because this was a paradigm shift.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the prevailing view of his day, Messiah was not necessarily a deity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yet in verse 13, Daniel sees the Ancient of Days (whom we might call &amp;ldquo;the Father&amp;rdquo;) giving the kingdom, the power, and the glory – where have we heard that phrase before? – to the one like a Son of Man, whom we might identify as Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walton (et al.) notes that Jewish writings from before Jesus viewed the &amp;ldquo;son of man&amp;rdquo; as the Jewish Messiah.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John would have been familiar with these documents, particularly &lt;em&gt;1 Enoch&lt;/em&gt;. Of course, the earliest Christians saw the &amp;ldquo;Son of Man&amp;rdquo; as Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John H. Walton, Victor H. Matthews, and Mark W. Chavalas, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: Old Testament&lt;/em&gt;, (E-Sword). (Downers Grove, Ill: IVP Academic, 2000), v. Dan 7:13-14.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-3&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Daniel 10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Walton estimates Daniel 7 was 552-549 BCE (Babylonian reign of Belshazzar), and Daniel 10 was 537-536 BCE (Persian reign of Cyrus). He notes Daniel 10 is &amp;ldquo;very close to the time when the first wave of Jews are returning from captivity and beginning the rebuilding of the (second) temple.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Again, note the description of the angelic messenger and Daniel&amp;rsquo;s reaction in verses 5-12 compared with Revelation 1:12-18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1) In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a word was revealed to Daniel, who was named Belteshazzar. And the word was true, and it was a great conflict. And he understood the word and had understanding of the vision. (2) In those days I, Daniel, was mourning for three weeks. (3) I ate no delicacies, no meat or wine entered my mouth, nor did I anoint myself at all, for the full three weeks. (4) On the twenty-fourth day of the first month, as I was standing on the bank of the great river (that is, the &lt;mark&gt;Tigris&lt;/mark&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(5) I lifted up my eyes and looked, and behold, &lt;mark&gt;a man clothed in linen, with a belt of fine gold from Uphaz around his waist. (6) His body was like beryl, his face like the appearance of lightning, his eyes like flaming torches, his arms and legs like the gleam of burnished bronze, and the sound of his words like the sound of a multitude&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; (7) And I, Daniel, alone saw the vision, for the men who were with me did not see the vision, but a great trembling fell upon them, and they fled to hide. (8) So I was left alone and saw this great vision, and no strength was left in me. My radiant appearance was fearfully changed, and I retained no strength. &lt;strong&gt;(9) Then I heard the sound of his words, and as I heard the sound of his words, I fell on my face in deep sleep with my face to the ground. (10) And behold, a hand touched me and set me trembling on my hands and knees. (11) And he said to me, &amp;ldquo;O Daniel, man greatly loved, understand the words that I speak to you, and stand upright, for now I have been sent to you.&amp;rdquo; And when he had spoken this word to me, I stood up trembling. (12) Then he said to me, &amp;ldquo;Fear not, Daniel, for from the first day that you set your heart to understand and humbled yourself before your God, your words have been heard, and I have come because of your words.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(13) The prince of the kingdom of Persia withstood me twenty-one days, but Michael, one of the chief princes, came to help me, for I was left there with the kings of Persia, (14) and came to make you understand what is to happen to your people in the latter days. For the vision is for days yet to come.&amp;rdquo; (15) When he had spoken to me according to these words, I turned my face toward the ground and was mute. (16) And behold, one in the &lt;mark&gt;likeness of the children of man&lt;/mark&gt; touched my lips. Then I opened my mouth and spoke. I said to him who stood before me, &amp;ldquo;O my lord, by reason of the vision pains have come upon me, and I retain no strength. (17) How can my lord&amp;rsquo;s servant talk with my lord? For now no strength remains in me, and no breath is left in me.&amp;rdquo; (18) Again one having the appearance of a man touched me and strengthened me. (19) And he said, &amp;ldquo;O man greatly loved, fear not, peace be with you; be strong and of good courage.&amp;rdquo; And as he spoke to me, I was strengthened and said, &amp;ldquo;Let my lord speak, for you have strengthened me.&amp;rdquo; (20) Then he said, &amp;ldquo;Do you know why I have come to you? But now I will return to fight against the prince of Persia; and when I go out, behold, the prince of Greece will come. (21) But I will tell you what is inscribed in the book of truth: there is none who contends by my side against these except Michael, your prince.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ibid., v. Dan 10:1.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-112-gold-menorah&#34;&gt;Rev 1:12: Gold Menorah&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12. I turned around to see who was speaking to me; and when I had turned, I saw seven gold menorahs;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exodus 37:23 And he made its seven lamps and its tongs and its trays of pure gold. Zec 4:2 And he said to me, &amp;ldquo;What do you see?&amp;rdquo; I said, &amp;ldquo;I see, and behold, a lampstand all of gold, with a bowl on the top of it, and seven lamps on it, with seven lips on each of the lamps that are on the top of it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember back in verse 10, John heard a great voice behind him. Here he turns to look.
&lt;img src=&#34;images/f37a1158a991a6a4d9acb4a8284cc1ff.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your Bible may say, &amp;ldquo;lampstands or candlesticks,&amp;rdquo; but what John sees is unquestionably a menorah, as Stern translated in the CJB.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He renders as &amp;ldquo;seven menorahs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A menorah has seven branches; this is one Menorah with seven lights. To the right is a photo I took of the Temple Institute Menorah in2013.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Later, we will find out that each &amp;ldquo;candlestick&amp;rdquo; is a congregation with Jesus in the midst.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Menorah is also reminiscent of a tree or a vine with branches.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus is the vine, and we are the branches (John 15).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus is also the light of the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, the tabernacle/temple menorah was made of gold, which fits with verse 12.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;According to Missler, this scene should remind us of the Tabernacle.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The robe and gold band in verse 13 may allude to the High Priest (Exodus 28:4).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The high priest was the one who tended the Menorah, including snuffing out and correcting if unsatisfactory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lizorkin says, &amp;ldquo;the presence of the Temple menorah would signal to John&amp;rsquo;s audience that his visionary experience took place in the vicinity of the Temple. And more precisely in the inner section of the Temple.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Temple/Tabernacle Menorah also testifies to God&amp;rsquo;s presence.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The seven fellowships are supposed to live in such a way that their communities see God&amp;rsquo;s light and presence.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Num 7:89 And when Moses went into the tent of meeting to speak with the LORD, he heard the voice speaking to him from above the mercy seat that was on the ark of the testimony, from between the two cherubim; and it spoke to him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-113-one-like-a-son-of-man&#34;&gt;Rev 1:13: One Like a Son of Man&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13. and among the menorahs was someone like a Son of Man, wearing a robe down to his feet and a gold band around his chest&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exo 28:4 These are the garments that they shall make: a breast piece, an ephod, a robe, a coat of checker work, a turban, and a sash. They shall make holy garments for Aaron your brother and his sons to serve me as priests.  &lt;br&gt;Dan 7:13 &amp;ldquo;I saw in the night visions, and behold, with the clouds of heaven there came &lt;mark&gt;one like a son of man&lt;/mark&gt;, and he came to the &lt;mark&gt;Ancient of Days&lt;/mark&gt; and was presented before him. Dan 10:5 I lifted up my eyes and looked, and behold, a man clothed in linen, with a belt of fine gold from Uphaz around his waist. &lt;br&gt;Dan 10:16 And behold, &lt;mark&gt;one in the likeness of the children of man&lt;/mark&gt; touched my lips. Then I opened my mouth and spoke. I said to him who stood before me, &amp;ldquo;O my lord, by reason of the vision pains have come upon me, and I retain no strength.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is often called the &amp;ldquo;vision of the Risen Christ.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fact that John noted one dressed as a priest in the &amp;ldquo;midst&amp;rdquo; of the Menorah may suggest he was witnessing Jesus as High Priest in heavenly Tabernacle (Heb 9).
&lt;img src=&#34;images/0fab3a7bee3b9b8d1fbc99ce645b1a4a.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The photo shows the &amp;ldquo;Holy Place,&amp;rdquo; where the Menorah was located. In the foreground is the Table of Showbread. By the curtain leading to the Holy of Holies is the Altar of Incense. (Ex 26:33)&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is from a Tabernacle replica that one can visit near Eilat, Israel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interestingly, John does NOT identify Jesus but says &amp;ldquo;one like a Son of Man.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John and Jesus were very close during Jesus&#39; earthly ministry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presumably, He would have said, &amp;ldquo;and among the Menorahs was Jesus wearing a robe…&amp;quot;…but he didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We know from 1:1 and 22:8 that John is not talking directly with Jesus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This angelic divine being is at the same time Jesus but not quite Jesus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As we saw from some of the parallel passages, the description of the one like a Son of Man is inherited from the Ancient of Days.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Baruch Korman writes, &amp;ldquo;This is a depiction of Messiah taking on the mantle of God the father.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Lizorkin writes, &amp;ldquo;The garments are highly symbolic, showing that Jesus is the heavenly priest, fully prepared and qualified to carry out His duties.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Keener writes, &amp;ldquo;the cumulative impact of these images is to present the risen Jesus as the greatest conceivable figure.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are numerous parallels among Revelation 1:12-18, Daniel 7, Daniel 10, and to a lesser extent, Ezekiel 1 and even Matthew 17 and the Transfiguration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will compare Revelation 1 and Daniel 10 towards the end of the lesson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus physically is seated at the Right Hand of the Father
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This may explain why it appears to be an Angel and not Jesus directly who speaks with John.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus is to remain seated at the Right Hand until the appointed time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In either case, Jesus is also spiritually amid our fellowships and us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember also that the earthly fellowships were undergoing intense persecution. Perhaps they felt abandoned by God, but here we see God is right in their midst.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-114-head-hair-and-eyes&#34;&gt;Rev 1:14: Head, Hair, and Eyes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14. His head and hair were as white as snow-white wool, his eyes like a fiery flame,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 7:9 &amp;ldquo;As I looked, thrones were placed, and the Ancient of Days took his seat; his clothing was white as snow, and the hair of his head like pure wool; his throne was fiery flames; its wheels were burning fire.  Dan 10:6 His body was like beryl, his face like the appearance of lightning, … Mat 17:2 And he was transfigured before them, and his face shone like the sun, and his clothes became white as light.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/e98a0edcc386a3d065dbf86ce29e5d25.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;center&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo caption: &amp;ldquo;Lambs in the Negev.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-115-feet-and-voice&#34;&gt;Rev 1:15: Feet and Voice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15. his feet like burnished brass refined in a furnace, and his voice like the sound of rushing waters.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 10:6 … his arms and legs like the gleam of burnished bronze, and the sound of his words like the sound of a multitude. Eze 1:&lt;strong&gt;7, 24&lt;/strong&gt; Their legs were straight, and the soles of their feet were like the sole of a calf&amp;rsquo;s foot. And they sparkled like burnished bronze. &lt;strong&gt;24&lt;/strong&gt; And when they went, I heard the sound of their wings like the sound of many waters, like the sound of the Almighty, a sound of tumult like the sound of an army. When they stood still, they let down their wings. &lt;strong&gt;Eze 43:2&lt;/strong&gt; And behold, the glory of the God of Israel was coming from the east. And the sound of his coming was like the sound of many waters, and the earth shone with his glory.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a biblical type, brass speaks of judgment
&lt;img src=&#34;images/e388ce01ad2053a59b63c79e169ab88f.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;center&#34; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo caption: &amp;ldquo;Bronze greaves (armor that protects the leg) from Derveni, 300 BC.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-116-right-hand-mouth-and-face&#34;&gt;Rev 1:16: Right Hand, Mouth, and Face&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16. In his right hand he held seven stars, out of his mouth went a sharp double-edged sword, and his face was like the sun shining in full strength.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jdg 5:31 &amp;ldquo;So may all your enemies perish, O LORD! But your friends be like the sun as he rises in his might.&amp;rdquo; Isa 49:2 He made my mouth like a sharp sword; in the shadow of his hand he hid me; he made me a polished arrow; in his quiver he hid me away. Heb 4:12 For the word of God is living and active, sharper than any two-edged sword, piercing to the division of soul and of spirit, of joints and of marrow, and discerning the thoughts and intentions of the heart.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/6b0fc0fc42ec66634448e646d3165042.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We occasionally see drawings, some quite grotesque in my opinion, of Jesus with a literal sword coming out of His mouth. This misses the point entirely. Obviously, the sword is symbolic. As Lizorkin says, &amp;ldquo;this being is powerful enough to destroy with his voice alone.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early Jewish believers saw the two edges as two aspects of the Word of God
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Either the &amp;ldquo;law and the prophets&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Moses and Jesus.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unfortunately, Reformation theology sees &amp;ldquo;Law&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Gospel&amp;rdquo; as opposites. They are not. The opposite of &amp;ldquo;law&amp;rdquo; is not &amp;ldquo;grace&amp;rdquo; but &amp;ldquo;lawlessness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If this is the model, here we see that Law and Gospel are not opposed to each other but are two sides of the same sword&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both bring judgment for the wicked and life for the righteous.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Baruch pointed out that a sword also divides and separates, in the sense that in Genesis 1:4, God divided the light from the darkness.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I saw a meme recently that the light never flees in the face of darkness. It is the darkness that runs when confronted by light. For darkness to prevail, the light source must be removed. John 3:19 has more about this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo caption: &amp;ldquo;Sunrise over the coastline at Assos&amp;rdquo; (western Turkey).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Assos is not too far from Pergamum.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-117-fear-not&#34;&gt;Rev 1:17: Fear not!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17. When I saw him, I fell down at his feet like a dead man. He placed his right hand upon me and said, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid! I am the First and the Last,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dan 8:17-18 So he came near where I stood. And when he came, I was frightened and fell on my face. But he said to me, &amp;ldquo;Understand, O son of man, that the vision is for the time of the end.&amp;rdquo; 18 And when he had spoken to me, I fell into a deep sleep with my face to the ground. But he touched me and made me stand up.  Dan 10:9-10,12,15 followed by Dan 10:19 And he said, &amp;ldquo;O man greatly loved, fear not, peace be with you; be strong and of good courage.&amp;rdquo; And as he spoke to me, I was strengthened and said, &amp;ldquo;Let my lord speak, for you have strengthened me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/0241949c6ca5d3a6f134f40c58195f1d.jpg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a common reaction when people in the Bible are given a glimpse of God – even if it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;just&amp;rdquo; an angel, they are terrified!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The drawing on the right illustrates Abraham bowing before angelic visitors, one of whom is the &amp;ldquo;Angel of the Lord.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of our Bibles have from 1:17 through the end of chapter 3 in red text; the translators assume Jesus is speaking. It&amp;rsquo;s a fair assumption; however, if we&amp;rsquo;re faithful to the text, John does not record who is speaking.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 1:1 and Rev 22:8 tell us John received the vision from an Angel, not from Jesus directly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assuming this is John the Apostle, he knew Jesus better than anyone. Was he afraid because this incredible and terrifying being wasn&amp;rsquo;t Jesus?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even if we assume it was Jesus, there is a lesson.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No matter how well you know Jesus, He&amp;rsquo;s still God. We can&amp;rsquo;t get too casual.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS Lewis captures this beautifully in &amp;ldquo;The Lion, the Witch, and the Wardrobe.&amp;rdquo; Susan Pevensie is talking to Mr. Beaver. &amp;ldquo;Aslan is a lion- the Lion, the great Lion.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Ooh,&amp;rdquo; said Susan. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;d thought he was a man. Is he-quite safe? I shall feel rather nervous about meeting a lion&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;&amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;Safe&lt;/strong&gt;?&amp;rdquo; said Mr. Beaver &lt;strong&gt;&amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo;Who said anything about safe? &amp;lsquo;Course he isn&amp;rsquo;t safe&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;But he&amp;rsquo;s good&lt;/strong&gt;. He&amp;rsquo;s the King, I tell you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In any case, the angel has the authority to speak for Jesus and God the Father in the 1st person.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we look back in Genesis, the &amp;ldquo;Angel of the LORD&amp;rdquo; in the Old Testament has the authority to speak for the Father in the first person. It&amp;rsquo;s as if Abraham is communicating with God Himself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe that is the case with John. The text tells us John is not speaking with Jesus directly, but he might as well be since He&amp;rsquo;s the only One who purchased our life with His death&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The safest avenue is to say John is speaking with an Angel of the God of Israel, acknowledging some elasticity in our definitions of the Father, Spirit, and Son.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-118-i-was-dead-but-behold-i-am-alive&#34;&gt;Rev 1:18: &amp;ldquo;I was dead but behold, I Am alive!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18. the Living One. I was dead, but look!—I am alive forever and ever! And I hold the keys to Death and Sh&amp;rsquo;ol.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 25:8 He will swallow up death forever; and the Lord GOD will wipe away tears from all faces, and the reproach of his people he will take away from all the earth, for the LORD has spoken.  Hos 13:14 I shall ransom them from the power of Sheol; I shall redeem them from death. O death, where are your plagues? O Sheol, where is your sting?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1 Corinthians 15:54, Paul says, &amp;ldquo;the saying will come about as it is written, &amp;ldquo;Death is swallowed up in victory!&amp;rdquo; He was quoting Isaiah 25:8. The words spoken to John appear linked to this passage also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/cc210d9fa2964a4ab7d252ee417dbf45.png&#34; width=&#34;66%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the great find of the Dead Sea Scrolls in 1948 in a cave by the Dead Sea: a complete and relatively intact scroll containing the book of Isaiah. Before this, the most recent full copy of the Hebrew Bible we had was from the 9th or 10th century CE. This scroll dates to 1000 years prior, the 1st Century before Christ, or before the Common Era. There are minor differences only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo caption: &amp;ldquo;Isaiah 25:8 on the great Isaiah Scroll.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-119-μετα-ταυτα&#34;&gt;Rev 1:19: μετα ταυτα&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19. So write down what you see, both what is now, and what will happen afterwards.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isa 30:8; Jer 30:2; Hab 2:2 (see Rev 1:11)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conservative scholars tend to see this as an Outline of the book, though this is debated:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What you see: the Vision of the Risen Christ – chapter 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The things which are: the seven assemblies/churches - chapters 2-3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The things that shall be after – chapters 4-22&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Greek phrase for &amp;ldquo;after these things&amp;rdquo; is μετα ταυτα meta tauta.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meta tauta acts as a signpost throughout Revelation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;There are 10 μετα ταυτα phrases in Revelation&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 1:19 Write therefore the things that you have seen, those that are and those that are to take place &lt;mark&gt;after this&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 4:1 &lt;mark&gt;After this&lt;/mark&gt; I looked, and behold, a door standing open in heaven!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 4:1 And the first voice, which I had heard speaking to me like a trumpet, said, “Come up here, and I will show you what must take place &lt;mark&gt;after this&lt;/mark&gt;.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 7:1 &lt;mark&gt;after this&lt;/mark&gt; I saw four angels standing at the four corners of the earth, holding back the four winds of the earth, that no wind might blow on earth or sea or against any tree.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 7:9 &lt;mark&gt;after this&lt;/mark&gt; I looked, and behold, a great multitude that no one could number, from every nation, from all tribes and peoples and languages, standing before the throne and before the Lamb, clothed in white robes, with palm branches in their hands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 9:12 The first woe has passed; behold, two woes are &lt;mark&gt;still to come&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 15:5 &lt;mark&gt;after this&lt;/mark&gt; I looked, and the sanctuary of the tent of witness in heaven was opened&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 18:1 &lt;mark&gt;after this&lt;/mark&gt; I saw another angel coming down from heaven, having great authority, and the earth was made bright with his glory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 19:1 &lt;mark&gt;after this&lt;/mark&gt; I heard what seemed to be the loud voice of a great multitude in heaven, crying out, “Hallelujah! Salvation and glory and power belong to our God&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rev 20:3 and threw him (Satan) into the pit, and shut it and sealed it over him, so that he might not deceive the nations any longer, until the thousand years were ended. &lt;mark&gt;After that&lt;/mark&gt; he must be released for a little while.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Tens in the Bible&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are not seven but 10 μετα ταυτα phrases in Revelation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Hebrew Gematria, specific numbers that reappear throughout the Bible are assigned concepts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gematria means that scholars, both ancient sages and modern academics, have studied these patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where they see seven, they notice a general theme of completion or perfection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using this method, 10 represents divine order or law,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The most obvious examples are the 10 commandments and the 10 plagues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were also 10 generations from Adam to Noah, where we saw the flood restoring order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were also 10 generations from Noah to Abraham where we received the Abrahamic covenant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Ruth 4, there is a strange prophecy given to Ruth and Boaz, followed by a list of 10 generations from Perez to King David.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ruth 4:12 and may your house be like the house of Perez, whom Tamar bore to Judah, because of the offspring that the LORD will give you by this young woman.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you know the story of Tamar and Judah, it&amp;rsquo;s sordid. If you received this &amp;ldquo;blessing,&amp;rdquo; you might be inclined to think &amp;ldquo;same to you, fella!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perez was the product of a &amp;ldquo;forbidden union&amp;rdquo; between Tamar and Judah, her father in-law.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deuteronomy 23:2 - &amp;ldquo;No one born of a forbidden union may enter the assembly of the LORD. Even to the &lt;em&gt;tenth&lt;/em&gt; generation, none of his descendants may enter the assembly of the LORD.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The backstory is Tamar&amp;rsquo;s previous husbands (Judah&amp;rsquo;s other sons) had died without issue, and it was Judah&amp;rsquo;s responsibility to see that his line continued.  He failed to do this, so Tamar posed as a prostitute and went into to Judah.  Of course, she became pregnant by him.  When Judah found out that his daughter in law had played the harlot, he was furious.  He was about to have her executed when she presented evidence that he was the father of the child.  Oops.  The son&amp;rsquo;s name was Perez.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The end of Ruth connects the dots for us by listing 10 generations from Perez to David the King.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From a spiritual perspective, this was yet another attempt by Satan to sabotage the lineage of Jesus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tamar perhaps unknowingly, saw to it that the line continued, and indeed she is one of the four women noted in Jesus&#39; genealogy (Matthew 1:3).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rev-120-the-meaning-of-the-starsmenorah&#34;&gt;Rev 1:20: The Meaning of the Stars/Menorah&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revelation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;References&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20. Here is the secret meaning of the seven stars you saw in my right hand, and of the seven gold menorahs: the seven stars are the angels of the seven Messianic communities, and the seven menorahs are the seven Messianic communities.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Zech 4: 2 And he said to me, &amp;ldquo;What do you see?&amp;rdquo; I said, &amp;ldquo;I see, and behold, a lampstand all of gold, with a bowl on the top of it, and seven lamps on it, with seven lips on each of the lamps that are on the top of it.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/06d103558029ba8fd995cd8e7e4bea39.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A topic of debate is whether the seven stars/angels are natural or supernatural&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About all the &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; camp has going for it is our western minds can understand it better.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In this view, the angels of each congregation are human.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More than likely, the messenger would be the pastor of each community or a designated reader in the synagogue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unfortunately, no church leadership position is ever called an angel or messenger anywhere else in the New Testament.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In favor of the supernatural angel view, the entire book of Revelation has angels everywhere, so why not in Chapters 2 and 3?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jewish texts often portray angels as stars.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In this view, churches/fellowships have designated angels just like nations do.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Daniel 10, the angelic messenger had to do battle with the spirit of Persia and then had to go back to do battle with the spirit of Greece.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In other words, there is a heavenly counterpart to an earthly reality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Admittedly it is foreign to think of a fellowship having a &amp;ldquo;guardian angel.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If our churches had such an angel, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it keep false teaching and division out of the church?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protestants tend to deemphasize angels, which is odd given that &amp;ldquo;angels&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;angel&amp;rdquo; appears over 180 times in the New Testament- about 80 times in Revelation and the other 100 in the rest of the New Testament.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is probably much more going on in the supernatural angelic community than most of us realize.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In both Hebrew and Greek, the meaning could be either a supernatural angel or a natural messenger. However, only about six times out of the 180 can we be certain that the word references only a human messenger.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This certainly raises several questions:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do churches today have designated angels?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was this a 1st-century phenomenon?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was it ONLY these seven specially designated congregations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who knows!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By having the stars in his right hand, the hand of power, John is possibly communicating, &amp;ldquo;Christ is Lord over the universe including Lord over the angels who guide the churches as well as the nations.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keener also notes given the tensions between non-messianic and messianic branches of Judaism in that day, &amp;ldquo;by identifying the churches as (a menorah), John claims that the Jesus movement is the true form of Judaism.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One thing we do know: a menorah&amp;rsquo;s purpose is to give off light in a dark place
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is what our churches should be doing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is what we as disciples should be doing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo caption: &amp;ldquo;Tabernacle Model Golden Menorah.&amp;quot;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;postscript-rev-1-and-dan-10&#34;&gt;Postscript: Rev 1 and Dan 10&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a postscript, let&amp;rsquo;s do a quick side-by-side of Revelation 1 and Daniel 10. In this way, we can see how the book we hold in our laps or in our smart devices is ONE book with one consistent message from beginning to end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Topic&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Dan 10&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Rev 1:9-18&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Double introduction&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2 In those days I, Daniel,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9&lt;/strong&gt; I, John, your brother and partner in the tribulation and the kingdom and the patient endurance that are in Jesus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Location – both surrounded by water&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4 was standing on the bank of the great river (that is, the Tigris)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9 was on the island called Patmos&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;State of preparation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2 In those days I, Daniel, was mourning for three weeks. 3 I ate no delicacies, no meat or wine entered my mouth, nor did I anoint myself at all, for the full three weeks.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt; I was in the Spirit on the Lord&amp;rsquo;s day,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The listener notices&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5 I lifted up my eyes and looked, and behold, a man&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12 I turned around to see who was speaking to me;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The being&amp;rsquo;s clothing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5 clothed in linen, with a belt of fine gold from Uphaz around his waist.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13 clothed with a long robe and with a golden sash around his chest.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Head/face&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6 his face like the appearance of lightning, (Dan 7:9 the hair of his head like pure wool)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14 The hairs of his head were white, like white wool, like snow.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eyes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6 his eyes like flaming torches&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14 His eyes were like a flame of fire,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Arms &amp;amp; Legs/Feet&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6 his arms and legs like the gleam of burnished bronze&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15 his feet were like burnished bronze, refined in a furnace,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Voice&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6 the sound of his words like the sound of a multitude.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15 and his voice was like the roar of many waters.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reaction&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9&lt;/strong&gt; as I heard the sound of his words, I fell on my face in deep sleep with my face to the ground.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17 When I saw him, I fell at his feet as though dead.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Commission&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt; And behold, a hand touched me&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17 But he laid his right hand on me,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Assurance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12&lt;/strong&gt; Then he said to me, &amp;ldquo;Fear not, Daniel,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17 saying, &amp;ldquo;Fear not, I am the first and the last, 18 and the living one. I died, and behold I am alive forevermore, and I have the keys of Death and Hades&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mission&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;14,19&lt;/strong&gt; and came to make you understand what is to happen to your people in the latter days. For the vision is for days yet to come….I will tell you what is inscribed in the book of truth.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19 Write therefore the things that you have seen, those that are and those that are to take place after this.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris Flanagan, &lt;em&gt;Jerusalem Temple Menorah at Night in 2013&lt;/em&gt;, Digital Photograph, February 2013.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chuck Missler, &lt;em&gt;The Book of Revelation Handbook&lt;/em&gt; (Koinonia House, 2020), 21.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eli Lizorkin-Eyzenberg and Pinchas Shir, &lt;em&gt;Hebrew Insights from Revelation&lt;/em&gt;, Kindle., Jewish Studies for Christians, 2021, 39–40.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, &lt;em&gt;Tabernacle Model&lt;/em&gt;, vol. Negev and the Wilderness, Pictorial Library of Bible Lands, 2012, 33.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baruch Korman, &lt;em&gt;Revelation Chapter 1 Part 3&lt;/em&gt;, 2015, accessed February 10, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/135168951&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://vimeo.com/135168951&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lizorkin-Eyzenberg and Shir, &lt;em&gt;Hebrew Insights from Revelation&lt;/em&gt;, 43–44.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig S. Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition (E-Sword). (Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014), v. Rev 1:13.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Korman, &lt;em&gt;Revelation Chapter 1 Part 3&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, &lt;em&gt;Daniel 7&lt;/em&gt;, vol. Daniel, Photo Companion to the Bible (Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), 70.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, &lt;em&gt;Daniel 10&lt;/em&gt;, vol. Daniel, Photo Companion to the Bible (Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), 24.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lizorkin-Eyzenberg and Shir, &lt;em&gt;Hebrew Insights from Revelation&lt;/em&gt;, 49.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Korman, &lt;em&gt;Revelation Chapter 1 Part 3&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, &lt;em&gt;Judges 5&lt;/em&gt;, vol. Judges, Photo Companion to the Bible (Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), 196.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, &lt;em&gt;Daniel 10&lt;/em&gt;, Daniel:34.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tom Bradford, “Lesson 4 - Revelation 1 Concl.,” &lt;em&gt;Seed of Abraham Ministries, Inc&lt;/em&gt;, accessed January 31, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.torahclass.com/bible-studies/new-testament-studies/1917-new-testament-revelation/2882-lesson-4-revelation-1-concl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.torahclass.com/bible-studies/new-testament-studies/1917-new-testament-revelation/2882-lesson-4-revelation-1-concl&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, &lt;em&gt;1 Corinthians 15&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 1st Corinthians, Photo Companion to the Bible (Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), 183.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary&lt;/em&gt;, v. Rev 1:20.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, &lt;em&gt;Tabernacle Model&lt;/em&gt;, Negev and the Wilderness:41.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
