<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>practical | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/practical/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/tag/practical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>practical</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu53652e90a6e4e4f125f22da2a993ec10_403021_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>practical</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/practical/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Passports, Customs, and Airport Security</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/practical/passport/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/practical/passport/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crossing a frontier can be an intimidating experience. Security, government, and airline officials speak English and are interested in moving things along, but there may be officials who were born to be suspicious, or who revel in their authority to search you or in their power to deny you entry to their country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, security reigns supreme in a country that can’t have it otherwise. The young men and women asking questions are usually polite, but they take their job very seriously – and passengers should be glad they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottom line: Be patient, expect questions, answer frankly, don&amp;rsquo;t volunteer information unless asked, don’t get uptight or confrontational. They’ve got time; you’ve got a country to see. In short, make it easy for yourself by making it easier for them. If they seem to be getting irritated with you, you keep your cool and keep smiling.  They are just doing their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t worry about memorizing all of these details, and there is no need to print this page (it is better if you didn&amp;rsquo;t).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will review the details once more immediately before we leave.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;passports&#34;&gt;Passports&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All travelers including minors must have a valid passport - valid at least six months AFTER the date you exit Israel
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In other words, if your passport expires on/before 11/15/2023, you MUST get it renewed before you leave home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, you will need your valid passport# and expiration date at the time you book your travel -&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information on &lt;a href=&#34;https://travel.state.gov/content/travel/en/passports/how-apply.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;obtaining a passport is here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you need to renew, do yourself a favor and &lt;a href=&#34;https://travel.state.gov/content/passports/en/passports/renew.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RENEW IT NOW!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No additional paperwork (e.g. visas) or shots are required for US citizens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are not a US citizen, please let Chris know and we can discuss specific requirements for your country&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before leaving home, make &lt;strong&gt;two&lt;/strong&gt; copies of the information page - leave one with someone you could easily contact while you are on your trip and put the other one in your suitcase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While in transit, &lt;strong&gt;keep your passport on your person at all times.&lt;/strong&gt;  You will need to produce it at all airports.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never pack your original passport in your suitcase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not stick it in the seat pocket in front of you (it&amp;rsquo;s too easy to leave behind)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A backpack is fine; just make sure it can&amp;rsquo;t fall out accidentally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neck pouches or waist belts are options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;secondary-security-screening-before-leaving-the-us&#34;&gt;Secondary Security Screening Before Leaving the Us&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will go through the usual TSA screening that all passengers have to do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is different is that before the direct flight to TLV there will usually be a &lt;em&gt;secondary&lt;/em&gt; security screening at the GATE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is almost EXACTLY like the airport security when you first departed from your home airport – coats off, shoes off, laptops out, etc.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ASK if you can bring unopened bottled water. This seems to vary from place to place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These checkpoints generally open two hours before takeoff
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not as bad as it seems - flights sometimes start boarding an hour &lt;em&gt;or more&lt;/em&gt; before departure time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are NO FOOD OR RESTROOMS on the other side of the checkpoint - if you leave the area you will need to be rescreened again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will need to show your Passport here, and then again when you board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;arriving-in-israel&#34;&gt;Arriving In Israel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before You Leave Your Seat:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have your Passport? Phone? Wallet? Camera? Glasses? Name Badge?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no other way to say this - you are likely to be &amp;ldquo;out of it&amp;rdquo; after the long flight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look around between seats, under the seat in front of you as well as under your own seat, etc; be eyes for others in our group as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you are now wearing your Name Badge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soak in the fact that you are now in a very special Land that God calls His own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;israeli-passport-control&#34;&gt;Israeli Passport Control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the level of tension in the region, it will be no surprise that security at Israel’s airports is stringent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As you walk through the terminal you will eventually come to passport control - get in the lines for non-Israeli citizens and have your passport ready&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Between the fatigue, slow-moving lines, and &amp;ldquo;guilty until proven innocent&amp;rdquo; stance from the guards, &lt;strong&gt;Passport Control can truly test a believer&amp;rsquo;s witness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be repeated questions about what you intend to do while in Israel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t know something just say, &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; (the name or address of someone in Israel, for example), and let them ask a follow-up question.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they ask where you are going, an acceptable first answer is that we are going primarily to Galilee and Jerusalem with our tour group
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t give them a day-by-day activity list. Let them follow up with questions if they need more specifics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The type of tour we are doing is probably the most common tour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone on our tour should be wearing their name badge, which may make it easier for the officers to determine who is with whom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes they may act like you&amp;rsquo;re in trouble when you really are not.  They do this to see how you respond. It&amp;rsquo;s OK!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will have our guide&amp;rsquo;s cell and contact information on the formal itinerary.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are stopped for questioning having this type of information can help, but again, it is not necessary to volunteer the itinerary unless they ask for it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be aware that passengers who have recently visited Arabic countries OR who are of Arab or Indian descent, or have an Arabic or Indian name, or in any other way arouse suspicion for any reason, may be subject to further questioning (including email and social media accounts)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are detained please kindly request that you be allowed to notify one of our leaders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once cleared, you will be given a paper receipt which is your 90-day entry visa (Israel does not stamp passports). &lt;strong&gt;Do not lose this.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Answer their questions and do not chat, make jokes, or volunteer information unless you are asked for it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MILLIONS of Americans come and go each year without incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With any luck, we&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;em&gt;over&lt;/em&gt;prepped you and you&amp;rsquo;ll sail through wondering what all the fuss was about!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;israeli-customs&#34;&gt;Israeli Customs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After the Passport Control process is concluded, walk around behind the kiosk and enter the huge baggage claim hall where you will pick up your bags.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure those traveling with you stay together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grab your bag and head through the green &amp;ldquo;nothing to declare&amp;rdquo; sign (unless of course, you have something to declare) - you likely will not be stopped here&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Representatives from our group will be in the waiting area and will be identifiable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You made it to the Promised Land! We&amp;rsquo;re going to have an amazing trip!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;departing-israel&#34;&gt;Departing Israel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Our guides will walk us through all of this again on the day of departure.  Feel free to ask any questions at any time.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After several amazing days it will sadly be time to head back home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certain larger purchases are eligible for Value Added Tax refund.  When you make such a purchase, the vendor may provide you with a form, or you can get one at the airport.  &lt;strong&gt;Complete and drop off any VAT forms before going through security&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep your passport accessible at all times. Just about everyone in the airport will want to see it at some point (at least that&amp;rsquo;s how it feels).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1st Stage-Baggage Screening and interview&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My personal experience is that these guards are always incredibly friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They want you to be relaxed; just follow the same advice as on entry: be honest but not overly chatty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Typical first questions are, “&lt;strong&gt;Did you pack your bag yourself?&lt;/strong&gt;” and “&lt;strong&gt;Where was it after you packed it?&lt;/strong&gt;” (was it standing for an hour in a hotel corridor, for instance, where someone could have tampered with it? In our case, the likely answer will be that our bags were on the bus in a locked compartment.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another question is likely to be, &lt;strong&gt;“Did anyone give you something to take with you?”&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While your mind may immediately go to something illicit and tempt you to answer &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo;, the &lt;strong&gt;answer to this question is almost always &amp;ldquo;yes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our guide may give us items such as maps, or olive wood communion cups as souvenirs. These count.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t let them find it on their own and then ask you why you didn’t mention it in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They may pull different members of our group (including husbands and wives) out of the queue for questioning. Don&amp;rsquo;t be alarmed. This is routine. They will then compare answers.  Since we were all at the same places doing the same things, there shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be any problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next step is a large scanner for your check-through luggage.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow instructions to load your bags&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait for the bags on the other side of the machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The checker on his/her monitor either clears a particular bag by putting a bar-coded paper strip on it, or sends you to another station a few steps away if there is some unidentifiable item or container that requires opening the bag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s on a bag-by-bag not passenger-by-passenger basis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This part is not too unlike TSA screening - if they can&amp;rsquo;t figure out what something is they will do a manual inspection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your bag is pulled, it&amp;rsquo;s not a big deal (unless you have something to hid, which you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t!). Don&amp;rsquo;t get alarmed (and definitely don&amp;rsquo;t get defensive or irritated!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2nd Stage&lt;/strong&gt; - Airline Check in; keep your passport out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3rd Stage&lt;/strong&gt; - usual passenger screening/carry on security and passport control exit.  If you&amp;rsquo;ve made it this far, there is unlikely to be any drama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if all went smoothly we may have an hour or two to chill in the beautiful terminal before boarding. Savor your memories!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;united-stated-re-entry&#34;&gt;United Stated Re-entry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who have never done it, returning into the USA is almost always a non-event for US citizens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check your app store for &amp;ldquo;Mobile Passport Control&amp;rdquo;, which advertises seamless reentry into the US  &lt;strong&gt;you will want to download this before you get on the plane in Israel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be given a customs and border form to complete; again keep this with your passport or they may direct you to use the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re using the app, answer the prompts and you should get a QR code to eventually show to an agent or a machine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who don&amp;rsquo;t want to use the app, there might RFID/biometric machines available to further expedite&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If not, queue up and wait your turn for a US immigration agent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are connecting within another airport in the US you will, go through the process above, then you will have to get your checked bags, clear customs and then re-check for the connecting flight to Dallas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The exact process will depend on your connecting airport and airline - some make it easier than others&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After you check in, the remainder of the process will be the same as if you were on a domestic flight&amp;hellip;because you are on a domestic flight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    If you are connecting to a US-bound flight from an airport outside the US, you likely will not have to go through passport control or customs in the connecting country, but you may have to rescreen for security.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clothing</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/practical/clothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/practical/clothing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comfort before fashion is the key to touring in Israel. Casual, travel-ready clothing is all you will need with a few specific guidelines (see &amp;ldquo;Holy sites&amp;rdquo; below). The weather in late spring will be warm, like Texas. You will want to pack lightly, wrinkle-free, and be ready to rewear outfits. Simplicity is the key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-can-you-bring&#34;&gt;What CAN you bring?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One checked bag up to 50 lbs, MAX (airline restriction), plus one personal carry-on, such as a backpack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-should-you-bring&#34;&gt;What SHOULD you bring?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; stuff a suitcase full of clothes doesn’t mean you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Less is more&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The simpler you can make your life on the road, the more time you will have for HIM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More options = more complexity - the more outfits you bring, the more time you will spend digging through your suitcase or closet choosing what to wear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For our type of tour, if your clothes for two weeks in Israel can&amp;rsquo;t fit in a 21&amp;quot; roll-aboard, you&amp;rsquo;ve overpacked.
&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note - Whatever size suitcase you bring, allow extra room to bring back items purchased while in Israel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;general-think-function-over-fashion&#34;&gt;General: think function over fashion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lightweight and wrinkle-free&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally SPF and moisture-wicking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Columbia (outlet store in Allen), REI (store in Plano), Magellan, North Face, Outdoor Research, LL Bean, and other &amp;ldquo;outdoorsy&amp;rdquo; stores have practical travel clothes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Function over fashion&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; - plan to wear and re-wear outfits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For dinners, you might consider bringing one &amp;ldquo;casual dressy&amp;rdquo; outfit - (something other than jeans) but this is your option. Wearing your touring clothes is just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO TIP: Do Laundry in hotel sinks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laundry availability is inconsistent. Bring powdered detergent, a 1-3/8&amp;quot; sink plug, a travel clothesline, and a few clothespins to wash/rinse your clothes in the hotel sink and leave them to dry the next day&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;footwear&#34;&gt;Footwear&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO TIP: Proper footwear is your #1 clothing priority&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short of forgetting or losing your passport, shoes need to be your #1 priority. They can make or break your trip. Blisters are no fun.  Break-in new shoes before arrival.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Links to examples are &lt;strong&gt;Bolded&lt;/strong&gt;, but we are not necessarily recommending these specific products)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/s?k=moisture&amp;#43;wicking&amp;#43;socks&amp;amp;crid=2VJTYNYFR9NSF&amp;amp;sprefix=moisture&amp;#43;wicking&amp;#43;socks%2Caps%2C526&amp;amp;ref=nb_sb_noss_2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moisture-wicking socks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are highly recommended. Recommend Smart Wool or something similar. Cotton is more susceptible to fostering blisters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoes should have solid ankle support – break in extremely well before arrival&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of folks love the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/gp/aw/s/ref=is_s?k=chaco&amp;#43;sandals&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chaco style&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; sandals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Otherwise good walking shoes or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss_2?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;amp;field-keywords=hiking&amp;#43;shoes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hiking shoes/sandals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water shoes are fine for Hezekiah&amp;rsquo;s tunnel or the dead sea but don&amp;rsquo;t use these for other walking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t recommend flip-flops for walking because of the chances of turning an ankle on uneven terrain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t forget sunscreen if the top of your foot is going to be exposed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sandals or other comfortable casual shoes for evenings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;shirts&#34;&gt;Shirts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss_1?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;amp;field-keywords=magellan&amp;#43;shirts&amp;amp;rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Amagellan&amp;#43;shirts&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lightweight, hiking/fishing, moisture-wicking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or knit shirts that dry quickly. You might want a long sleeve if you are sun-sensitive or prefer more coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women - as above or cotton or silk shirt or blouse (one that covers the shoulder down to the middle of your upper arm if you want to be good to go for Holy sites). Note - women and girls should not have exposed midriffs, bring tank tops, blouses with spaghetti straps, or short-shorts as they are too immodest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO TIP: Darker colors are best for photos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/28df0f7a78d822f7bfd69adda62b439d.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; &gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than the well-watered north, most of Israel&amp;rsquo;s terrain and buildings are this tan/sand color. Outdoor travel clothing also tends to be tan-colored. Notice how the dark colors stand out in this photo. Now, imagine if the man was also wearing a tan-colored shirt in addition to his tan pants. He would almost be invisible! Wear contrasting colors!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pantsskirtsshorts&#34;&gt;Pants/Skirts/shorts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lightweight fabric shorts which dry quickly (i.e. Nylon, hiking type)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skirts that cover the knees work as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given the time of year, long pants are likely to be uncomfortable. Suggest the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.columbia.com/search?q=convertible&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;convertible&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; variety for Holy sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modest swimming suit for the Dead Sea (and possible Baptism or other limited swimming opportunities).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;holy-site-special-requirements&#34;&gt;Holy Site Special Requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/a889d8572637de9949cda38927218467.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;30%&#34; style=&#34;float:right&#34; &gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capernaum and a few sites in Jerusalem (including the Temple Mount, Western Wall, and Holy Sepulcher) have dress codes enforced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bare legs (knees and above) and shoulders are inappropriate
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For women, a mid-calf lightweight elastic waist skirt, lightweight jumper or large cotton scarf to wrap around shorts plus a scarf or shawl to quickly cover bare shoulders. Capri pants are fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pair of pants with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Columbia-Mens-Convertible-Pant-Small/dp/B0089PWWZO/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1494461753&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=columbia&amp;#43;pfg&amp;#43;convertible&amp;#43;pants&amp;#43;mens&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;zip on/off legs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; would be helpful for an easy transition when legs must be covered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guides will let us know in advance when a modest dress code is required&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hat&#34;&gt;Hat&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Columbia-Bora-Booney-Hats-Sage/dp/B0058YU1OI/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1494461519&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=columbia&amp;#43;hat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wide-brimmed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a must!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ballcaps do not cover the ears &amp;amp; neck; visors cover even less.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dehydration is more common if the head is uncovered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We strongly recommend a hat with a strap as it can get windy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Head must be COVERED at Western Wall and other Jewish holy sites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Head must be UNCOVERED for the Holy Sepulcher
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the Pope wears a Jewish kippah; go figure&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;jackets&#34;&gt;Jackets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like to wear a jacket or sweatshirt in Texas in late spring, then you might want to bring one to Israel. Other than the airplane trip, most of us will not need one! The chance of rain between May and September is statistically zero, but with God, we never say never! This is up to you. We might advise a travel windbreaker as opposed to a bulky sweatshirt or jacket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-clothing-items&#34;&gt;Other Clothing items&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Durable high-quality sunglasses are a must! You may want a neck cord.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Ergodyne-Chill-Its-6602-Evaporative-Cooling/dp/B001B5I57I/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1494462214&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=ergodyne&amp;#43;chill&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaporative Cooling Towel&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(a&lt;/strong&gt; popular brand is Ergodyne) is becoming popular for participants to bring - even more practical is the &amp;ldquo;Buff&amp;rdquo; (like on Survivor) that convert from a neck-wrap to a beanie (you can also use it as a mask if Covid breaks out again)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are prone to calf swelling on a long flight, or if you think you might be prone, recommend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Kendall-T-E-D-Length-Embolism-Stockings/dp/B0015TGAVS/ref=sr_1_2_a_it?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1494462441&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=ted&amp;#43;hose&amp;#43;compression&amp;#43;stockings&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;compression stockings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the flight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;h3 id=&#34;clothing-not-to-bring&#34;&gt;Clothing NOT to bring&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excessive pairs of &lt;strong&gt;anything&lt;/strong&gt; (shoes, shorts, underwear) - just bring 2 or 3 outfits and wear them over and over again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clothing that is prone to wrinkling (unless you like that look)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember simplicity is the key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; bring an outfit that requires ironing, but then you&amp;rsquo;d have to bring a travel iron (irons are not standard in Israeli hotels), then you&amp;rsquo;d spend time ironing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is better to just bring wrinkle-free travel clothes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things that will not dry overnight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clothing with American, political, or Christian symbols/slogans is highly discouraged.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are not being ashamed or unpatriotic - you are loving your neighbors and being a gracious and polite guest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This type of shirt is definitely a no-go! The Crusades are still a sore subject with Muslims and Jews (ask me why sometimes)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/18f5a4b4bca68c715c291997b549134b.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phones, Cameras, Electronics</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/practical/electronics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/practical/electronics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We encourage you to bring and use devices only to supplement your Holy Land experience. Otherwise try to &amp;ldquo;unplug&amp;rdquo; from daily life as much as possible. Make arrangements with work and other obligations to have them leave you alone and for you to be disconnected as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cell-phoneswi-fi&#34;&gt;Cell Phones/Wi-Fi&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will find using a US-based cellular voice/data service on a network in Israel will be expensive, but you have options.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wi-Fi is everywhere, including on the buses. Consider using Wi-Fi for voice/messaging.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your phone should have the ability to shut off cellular data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note that “SMS” messages are still sent using cellular data (so if your cellular data is off, you may not receive them).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are lots of messaging, audio, and video chat apps available for both Apple and Android that work over Wi-Fi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your carrier may offer a short-term international plan for cellular voice and/or data.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure it covers Israel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your company can’t be without you, see if they will pay for the international plan (mine did!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can bring an unlocked phone and buy a pre-paid SIM card once in Israel.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About 10 years ago, this was the way to go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nowadays, WiFi is everywhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You could tell folks back home that you’ll be unavailable!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protip&lt;/strong&gt;: Want to cut down on work voicemail when you return?  Include the following on your outgoing announcement:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain that you are out of the office until whichever date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State that you will NOT be checking voicemail while you are away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide information of someone to contact if they need something that can&amp;rsquo;t wait until you return
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of course that person and your boss should be able to reach you in a crisis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Otherwise, ask them to call back after you return&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And do not say &amp;ldquo;messages will be returned when I get back&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most people will want to respect your personal time and it&amp;rsquo;s often a &amp;ldquo;pride thing&amp;rdquo; that tells us our company won&amp;rsquo;t survive without us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cellphone etiquette&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please do not make or take calls during teachings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you MUST take a call while we are touring, please respect the “space” of those around you so everyone will have a great trip!
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The person next to you might be interested in your conversation but the person in front of you probably is not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your guides (and leaders) may frequently be on the phone coordinating logistics for our group, but they are “on the clock.” You are on vacation!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cameras&#34;&gt;Cameras&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of your cell phone as a swiss army knife; one tool with many uses.  Most cell phones have excellent cameras. Consider leaving the big DLSR at home!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for any opportunity to have one less thing to be a distraction, one less thing to carry around, one less thing to have to charge, one less thing to potentially leave behind somewhere (etc.)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m speaking from personal experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you have enough storage on your phone and a way to offload photos if you happen to run low on space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We typically have long days, so you may consider bringing a lightweight portable charger you can keep with you while touring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are bringing a separate camera, be sure to have sufficient batteries and memory sticks (unless you are bringing a computer to download photos on).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are bringing rechargeable batteries, consider bringing two sets; one to be left in the hotel room charging, the other out and about with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GoPros are great, but battery life is notoriously terrible (the older the model, the worse the battery life)! Plan accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    See our separate pages on &lt;a href=&#34;../photo-tips&#34;&gt;photography tips&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;convertersadapters&#34;&gt;Converters/Adapters:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electricity in Israel is 220v 50hz and their plugs are also configured differently than ours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will need an &lt;strong&gt;adapter&lt;/strong&gt; in order to plug in anything that needs recharging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most modern electronic devices smartphones, cameras, laptops) automatically convert the voltage so a separate converter generally isn’t needed.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check your power supply for the input voltage range. If it says something like 110-250v, all you need is an adapter for the plug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it only says 110v you will need a &lt;strong&gt;converter&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Never plug your 110V appliance into a 220v outlet using only an adapter.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cautions
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beware of cheap, poor-quality adapters. Price them on Amazon or wherever, and don’t buy the cheapest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always make sure your devices are charging before going to bed or you may wake up in the morning and find your device has not charged.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;**TIP-**bring a regular US power strip in your suitcase, and get a good quality European/Israeli adapter. You’ll be able to plug your devices into the power strip and won’t need individual adapters for each plug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You likely will not need a hair dryer as the hotels and guest-houses should have them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TIP&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t bring anything that needs ironing and you won&amp;rsquo;t need to bring an iron!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Other packing considerations</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/practical/other-items/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/practical/other-items/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Other items to bring&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bible&lt;/strong&gt; (hard copy or electronic) -
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want a hardcopy, consider a slimline version for size and weight reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider your phone as a &amp;ldquo;Swiss Army Knife&amp;rdquo; - you may wish to leave your hardcopy books and your large cameras at home and just use your phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure your Bible app can be used without an internet connection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/xnztR7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passport&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; … Passport … &lt;a href=&#34;../passport&#34;&gt;Passport&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also keep other travel documents handy such as your final flight and ground itinerary (to be provided by tour guide)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A travel pouch for these documents (i.e. a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss_1?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;amp;field-keywords=neck&amp;#43;travel&amp;#43;pouch&amp;amp;rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Aneck&amp;#43;travel&amp;#43;pouch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;neck pouch)&lt;/a&gt; is a good idea - your passport should be on your person unless you are in your hotel room&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebook&lt;/strong&gt; for taking notes and journal recordings
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: many people return and wish they had taken better notes. We will be visiting a lot of sites and things will start to run together. Bring a journal!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alternatively you can use something like Evernote to store both text and a few photos of each site; you can also create a simple blog for free with &lt;a href=&#34;https://postach.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;postach.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pens&lt;/strong&gt; (a pen w/ grip is helpful as sweating makes it hard to hold)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some bring a hi-lighter to map the routes we take on a map&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backpack&lt;/strong&gt; or Fanny pack - for carrying camera, wallet, pen, journal
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pack it, you carry it - &amp;ldquo;less is more&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medications&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prescription&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-prescription may include head/muscle ache relief, Immodium-d (better to have it and not need it than to need it and not have it!), sleep-aid, vitamins, or supplements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you forget something, there are drug stores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If applicable, bring a record of any important medical allergies, medicines, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Powdered drink pouches you can mix with a bottle of water, such as for electrolyte replenishment (Gatorade etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protein snacks, such as individual nut bags; avoid chocolate as it melts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small and large ziplock bags for snacks, collectibles (write on the bag what it is and where found)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is against Israeli law to remove historical artifacts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inflatable pillow or neck rest for use on the plane, eye mask, ear plugs (see &lt;a href=&#34;../flight-tips&#34;&gt;Jetlag&lt;/a&gt; article)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small bag (like a mesh tie bag) for items you want to leave on the bus for the day. The driver will always stay with the bus, or it will be locked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packs of disposable cloths (Wet Ones) may come in handy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hand sanitizer, sanitizing wipes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aloe for sunburn and baby or talcum powder for heat rash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you struggle with any hip, knee, or ankle pain, you may want to consider purchasing collapsible &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/s?k=Trekking&amp;#43;poles&amp;#43;collapsing&amp;amp;ref=nb_sb_noss&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;trekking poles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For women, bring feminine hygiene products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are prone to chaffing, bring anti-chafe balm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunscreen (the sport kinds are best as they are generally sweat proof) &amp;amp; Chapstick w/ SPF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    If you are planning to roll aboard luggage and not check, you will have the same liquid quantity restrictions as we have for domestic travel
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-not-to-bring&#34;&gt;What not to bring&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Books, excessive photo/video gear, or anything that adds unnecessary weight, bulk, or complexity that will slow you down or distract you from meeting with Yeshua/Jesus
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just use your phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
