<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Luke 4 | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/luke-4/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/tag/luke-4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Luke 4</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu9bdc4cc28a100eaa5c154301214e2807_480992_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Luke 4</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/luke-4/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>7. Immersion and Temptation</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb07/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In IMMERSION AND TEMPTATION, we briefly return to &lt;strong&gt;Nazareth&lt;/strong&gt;. More than two decades have elapsed since we last visited. Yeshua is no longer a precocious twelve-year-old boy; he is a grown man who has taken over His father Joseph’s carpenter trade. From Nazareth, we follow Yeshua’s family to the plains of the &lt;strong&gt;Jordan&lt;/strong&gt;, across from Jericho, where John the Immerser is at work, proclaiming the good news and immersing for repentance&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. After His immersion, we follow Yeshua out into the dry and waterless &lt;strong&gt;Judean&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Wilderness&lt;/strong&gt; between &lt;strong&gt;Jerusalem&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Jericho&lt;/strong&gt; where He spends forty days in prayer and fasting, concluding with His three temptations.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passages&lt;/strong&gt;: Matthew 3:13-4:11 (Mark 1:9-13, Luke 3:21-23, 4:1-13; John 1:29-34)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QMquTSUkTGE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#geography&#34;&gt;Geography:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#jesus-baptized-by-john-in-the-jordan&#34;&gt;Jesus baptized by John in the Jordan&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fulfill-all-righteousness&#34;&gt;Fulfill all Righteousness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-spirit-like-a-dove&#34;&gt;The Spirit like a Dove&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-three-temptations-of-jesus&#34;&gt;The three temptations of Jesus&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#into-the-wilderness&#34;&gt;Into the wilderness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#first-temptation-stone-to-bread&#34;&gt;First temptation: stone to bread&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#second-temptation-throw-yourself-down&#34;&gt;Second temptation: throw yourself down&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#third-temptation-all-the-kingdoms-of-the-world-if-you-bow&#34;&gt;Third temptation: all the kingdoms of the world if you bow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#worship-me&#34;&gt;Worship me&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion-the-devil-departs&#34;&gt;Conclusion: the devil departs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#lessons-from-the-temptations&#34;&gt;Lessons from the Temptations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#following-the-messiah-link&#34;&gt;Following the Messiah link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;geography&#34;&gt;Geography:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.png&#34; style=&#34;width:90%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This map&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; traces Jesus’ early ministry, including leaving Nazareth to be baptized by John (Mark 1:9) leading to His baptism in the Jordan (box 1), followed by His temptation in the Judean wilderness (box 2). We don’t know exactly where (or when) Jesus was baptized. Because of a few references, including the apparent proximity to Jerusalem (Mark 1:5) and the reference to “these stones” in the Luke and Matthew accounts suggest opposite Jericho near (or quite probably at) the location where Joshua led the Israelites across in Joshua 4. This site is marked by a traditional holy site today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not disputing a southern location for Jesus’ baptism, some scholars, including William Schlegel the publisher of this map, contend “Bethany beyond the Jordan” is not located across from Jericho but much further north in the Golan Heights (marked by box 3 on the map). They point out that it does not say that Jesus was baptized at Bethany; but in John’s gospel, it appears as if John is recollecting Jesus’ baptism which occurred at least 40 days earlier and in a different location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aubrey Taylor has noted that in the same region where Moses commissioned Joshua, and Elijah commissioned Elisha, Jesus receives a similar commission from John.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image2.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:75%&#34; alt=&#34;J:\Bethany\Matson15k1\Jordan River\Jordan River, mat23194.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:75%&#34; alt=&#34;Jordan River by Bethany beyond Jordan, tb060303267&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The photo on the top&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is a colorized version of an American Colony photograph taken between 1896 and 1946. The photo on the bottom&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is the same area today. The most significant issue in that part of the world, since ancient times and continues today is water rights. Before 1948 the area was sparsely populated. After 1948 with the founding of both the modern states of Israel as well as Jordan, the area began to grow, and all those new people needed food and food requires water from the Jordan river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;jesus-baptized-by-john-in-the-jordan&#34;&gt;Jesus baptized by John in the Jordan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 3:13-15&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mar 1:9&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John 1:29-31&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Then Jesus came from Galilee to the Jordan to John, to be baptized by him. John would have prevented him, saying, “I need to be baptized by you, and do you come to me?” But Jesus answered him, “Let it be so now, for thus it is fitting for us to fulfill all righteousness.” Then he consented.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In those days Jesus came from Nazareth of Galilee and was baptized by John in the Jordan.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The next day he saw Jesus coming toward him, and said, “Behold, the Lamb of God, who takes away the sin of the world! This is he of whom I said, ‘After me comes a man who ranks before me, because he was before me.’ I myself did not know him, but for this purpose I came baptizing with water, that he might be revealed to Israel.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it’s only a few verses in our Bibles, we need to remember that John and Jesus had probably never met until this day (and unlikely that John would remember doing a somersault in his mother Elizabeth’s womb over 30 years earlier); however, John 1:31 could also be interpreted that John initially did not recognize that Jesus was the Messiah, not that they were entirely unfamiliar with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, by now, we presume Joseph has died and Jesus has been left in charge of Mary and Jesus’ many siblings. John apparently recognized Jesus as soon as they saw each other and makes a Passover allusion to the sacrificial lamb and Isaiah 53:7: He was oppressed, and he was afflicted, yet he opened not his mouth; like a lamb that is led to the slaughter, and like a sheep that before its shearers is silent, so he opened not his mouth. John is certainly foreshadowing Jesus’ suffering and crucifixion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster paraphrases Matthew 3:14 as, “I need to be baptized by you WITH THE HOLY SPIRIT, yet you come to me to be baptized with water?”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fulfill-all-righteousness&#34;&gt;Fulfill all Righteousness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, Jesus Himself did not need to be baptized for his sins, so what does Jesus mean by “fulfilling all righteousness?” Keener notes that Jesus’ response indicates his identification with Israel in obedience to the Law and by extension, larger humanity who DID need purification&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. To fulfill all righteousness means it’s the proper way of doing things in the proper order. A prophet in the spirit and power of Elijah must arise, identify, declare, and anoint the Messiah (who must of course allow Himself to be anointed). By being baptized by John, Jeremy Dehut in Following the Messiah Jesus “testified to the authenticity and authority of John’s message and continued providing an example of faithful submission.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few lessons back we looked at how the verse “out of Egypt I have called my son” exemplifies how Jesus mirrors the nation. As we will see in the next section, Jesus’ 40-day fast recalls Israel’s 40 years in the wilderness. Just as God sustained Israel in the wilderness so He sustained Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we get to the question of why a Sinless Jesus would need a baptism of repentance, we must remember that Jesus is a perfect representative of the nation, just as He is a perfect and sinless representative of humankind. As a representative of Israel, Jesus “passes through the waters of the Jordan” just like the Nation did. His “repentance” (so to speak) represented the “corporate guilt and confession”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of His people. Taylor goes on to say that Jesus’ temptations can also be viewed in light of this representative role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-spirit-like-a-dove&#34;&gt;The Spirit like a Dove&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 17%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 16%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 25%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 17%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 23%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 3:16-17&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mar 1:9-11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luk 3:21-23&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John 1:32-34&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.16&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And when Jesus was baptized, immediately he went up from the water, and behold, the heavens were opened to him, and he saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove and coming to rest on him;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.3.17&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;17&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; and behold, a voice from heaven said, “This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.10&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And when he came up out of the water, immediately he saw the heavens being torn open and the Spirit descending on him like a dove.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.11&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And a voice came from heaven, “You are my beloved Son; with you I am well pleased.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.21&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;21&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Now when all the people were baptized, and when Jesus also had been baptized and was praying, the heavens were opened,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.22&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;22&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; and the Holy Spirit descended on him in bodily form, like a dove; and a voice came from heaven, “You are my beloved Son; with you I am well pleased.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.3.23&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;23&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Jesus, when he began his ministry, was about thirty years of age, being the son (as was supposed) of Joseph, the son of Heli,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;And John bore witness: “I saw the Spirit descend from heaven like a dove, and it remained on him. I myself did not know him, but he who sent me to baptize with water said to me, ‘He on whom you see the Spirit descend and remain, this is he who baptizes with the Holy Spirit.’ And I have seen and have borne witness that this is the Son of God.”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Psalm 2:7&lt;/sup&gt; I will tell of the decree: The LORD said to me, “You are my Son; today I have begotten you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Gen 22:2&lt;/sup&gt; He said, “Take your son, your only son Isaac, whom you love, and go to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering on one of the mountains of which I shall tell you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Isa 11:2&lt;/sup&gt; And the Spirit of the LORD shall rest upon him, the Spirit of wisdom and understanding, the Spirit of counsel and might, the Spirit of knowledge and the fear of the LORD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Isa 42:1&lt;/sup&gt; Behold my servant, whom I uphold, my chosen, in whom my soul delights; I have put my Spirit upon him; he will bring forth justice to the nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image4.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:60%; float:right&#34; /&gt;When I visited Israel in February 2013, I took this picture of a pair of doves at Jesus’ traditional baptism site. I wonder if they were only there for the tourists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that day many believed that God had gone silent. So, the heavens opening and the spirit poured out indicated that the Messianic era had arrived. John earlier proclaimed, “the kingdom of heaven is at hand” (Mat 3:1). “A kingdom needs a king and a messianic era needs a messiah.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God’s voice and John’s prophetic testimony are the two witnesses required to establish a matter; in this case, the stamp of approval on Jesus as Messiah. The Spirit would signify that the Messianic era is at hand. The spirit resting on Jesus could be an allusion to Genesis 1, where the Spirit of God moved over the surface of the waters, and Genesis 8, where the dove flew out over the waters and, finding no other place to land, came to “rest” on Noah (noach means rest in Hebrew). Despite our impression of doves as docile and peaceful, they are notoriously territorial. Lancaster writes, “His disciples probably understood Him to mean a sudden, startling rush of wind – only slightly less jarring than being struck by lightning.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My beloved son” could also be read as “my son, the beloved” or even “my son, whom I love” which also recalls Genesis 22 when Abraham is told “take your son, your only son Isaac, whom you love and go to the land of Moriah and offer him there as a burnt offering”. Isaac is a type or a foreshadow of Jesus who would be sacrificed, thus Lancaster notes in apostolic theology, the “beloved one” becomes a title for the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this seems to highlight the messianic prophecy of Isaiah 11:2 “And the spirit of the LORD shall rest upon Him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke 3:23 says Jesus was “about 30” when He began His ministry. We should not take this to mean exactly 30. The precise date of one’s birth was not especially relevant in the ancient world. Lancaster supposes that this is 28 CE, which if he was born in 5 or 6 BCE makes Jesus 34 years old here and then 36 years old when he died. According to Jewish tradition, Isaac was also 36 at the time of his binding on the altar in Genesis 22.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-three-temptations-of-jesus&#34;&gt;The three temptations of Jesus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;into-the-wilderness&#34;&gt;Into the wilderness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 35%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 4:1-2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mar 1:12-13a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luk 4:1-2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.1&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4:1&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Then Jesus was led up by the Spirit into the wilderness to be tempted by the devil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.2&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And after fasting forty days and forty nights, he was hungry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.12&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; The Spirit immediately drove him out into the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:41.1.13&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And he was in the wilderness forty days, being tempted by Satan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.4.1&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4:1&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And Jesus, full of the Holy Spirit, returned from the Jordan and was led by the Spirit in the wilderness&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:42.4.2&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; for forty days, being tempted by the devil. And he ate nothing during those days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image5.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:80%&#34; /&gt;Bolen writes, “Because of its lack of water and good routes, the Judean wilderness&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; has been (mostly) uninhabited throughout history. Consequently, it was an ideal place for those seeking refuge from enemies or retreat from the world. John the Baptist preached here, and it seems likely that this was the wilderness where Jesus was tempted.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener writes, “Jesus was led into the wilderness just as Israel was led. Just as Moses fasted for 40/40, so did Jesus.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In fact, Mark 1:12 emphatically says the spirit forcibly drove Jesus out into the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is a shadow of both Moses and Israel. They were tested and God sustained them all. Jesus passed the test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Christian traditions observe lent, where we abstain from certain pleasures, if not do a partial fast for 40 days between Ash Wednesday and Resurrection story. We do this in honor of Jesus’ 40 days in the wilderness. Jewish people similarly observe 40 days of Teshuva (“repentance”) which recalls the 40 years wandering in the wilderness (which is said to be one year for every day the spies were in the land). This concludes with Yom Kippur (Day of Atonement) which is a day of national fasting. Lancaster says, “Jewish liturgy treats the Day of Atonement as a day for dealing with Satan and his accusations. The liturgies of the day are filled with references to a legal showdown between Israel and the devil, which concludes with the scape goat being led out into the wilderness, symbolizing the defeat of evil.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-temptation-stone-to-bread&#34;&gt;First temptation: stone to bread&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 35%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 4:3-4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luk 4:3-4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.3&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And the tempter came and said to him, “If you are the Son of God, command these stones to become loaves of bread.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.4&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; But he answered, “It is written, “‘Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that comes from the mouth of God.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3 The devil said to him, “If you are the Son of God, command this stone to become bread.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 And Jesus answered him, “It is written, ‘Man shall not live by bread alone.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Deu 8:3&lt;/sup&gt; And he humbled you and let you hunger and fed you with manna, which you did not know, nor did your fathers know, that he might make you know that man does not live by bread alone, but man lives by every word that comes from the mouth of the LORD.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.34792in&#34; alt=&#34;C:\Users\Todd\Desktop\Files\sr pics\photobiblesr\Ascent of Adumim Roman road remains, tb113006722.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This photograph was taken in the Judean Wilderness, along the Ascent of Adummim, between Jericho and Jerusalem.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholars debate the moment in time when Jesus came to the full realization of His mission and destiny. Many speculate that it was at His baptism that the spirit descended. Lancaster speculates that the Satan’s temptations were an attempt to force Yeshua to question the revelation He just received. Maybe like in some movie where a normal person is given some superhuman ability, the Satan believes Jesus has the desire to try out His new superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three temptations will involve shortcuts to revealing His messianic identity and plan. Remember the phrase Jesus uses frequently between now and the triumphal entry: “My hour is not net come”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the first temptation is declaring that Jesus indeed trusts that revelation that He heard come from the mouth of the LORD. He did not need to prove it. Let’s break it down some more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Satan begins with “If you are the son of God.” One of the main limitations of the written word is that we have to use our imaginations with respect to voice inflection and body language. Did the Satan say this scoffingly, inquisitively, or matter-of-factly? Since the Satan is the accuser, it’s not too difficult to imagine him taunting Jesus with this challenge. “Since we know God made manna from heaven in the wilderness if you are that God, you should be able to do the same thing in this wilderness. And by the way, I know you are hungry. Why don’t you just go ahead and fix yourself something to eat.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus declines the invitation to demonstrate His messianic power. He will do it on His terms and in His timing. Jesus WILL provide bread, but it will be food for the people, not for Himself. He will serve others, not Himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is the Word and the Bread of Life who has come down from heaven. He quotes Deuteronomy 8:3, which is a passage about how “God tested Israel in the wilderness by causing them to hunger and feeding them with manna.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Physical bread will temporarily relieve hunger but the Bread of Life, the very Words of God will cure spiritual hunger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first temptation is declaring that Jesus indeed trusts that revelation that He heard come from the mouth of the LORD. He did not need to prove it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-temptation-throw-yourself-down&#34;&gt;Second temptation: throw yourself down&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 23%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 26%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 4:5-7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luk 4:9-12&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.5&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Then the devil took him to the holy city and set him on the pinnacle of the temple&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.6&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; and said to him, “If you are the Son of God, throw yourself down, for it is written, “‘He will command his angels concerning you,’ and “‘On their hands they will bear you up, lest you strike your foot against a stone.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.7&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Jesus said to him, “Again it is written, ‘You shall not put the Lord your God to the test.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;9 And he took him to Jerusalem and set him on the pinnacle of the temple and said to him, “If you are the Son of God, throw yourself down from here,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 for it is written, “‘He will command his angels concerning you, to guard you,’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 and “‘On their hands they will bear you up, lest you strike your foot against a stone.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12 And Jesus answered him, “It is said, ‘You shall not put the Lord your God to the test.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Psa 91:11-14 For he will command his angels concerning you to guard you in all your ways. [12] On their hands they will bear you up, lest you strike your foot against a stone. [13] You will tread on the lion and the adder; the young lion and the serpent you will trample underfoot. [14] “Because he holds fast to me in love, I will deliver him; I will protect him, because he knows my name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deu 6:13-16 It is the LORD your God you shall fear. Him you shall serve and by his name you shall swear. [14] You shall not go after other gods, the gods of the peoples who are around you— [15] for the LORD your God in your midst is a jealous God—lest the anger of the LORD your God be kindled against you, and he destroy you from off the face of the earth. [16] “You shall not put the LORD your God to the test, as you tested him at Massah.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we compare Matthew and Luke side-by-side we see that Luke reverses the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; and 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; temptations. Some may view this as the Gospel authors being unable to keep their stories straight, but another way of looking at it is that this demonstrates a lack of coordination and collusion among the authors. If one witness in a trial recalls she heard a dog bark and then a car horn, but another witness recalls she heard a car horn then a dog bark, we don’t typically assume one or the other is lying. It’s just a different recollection. The differences between Matthew and Luke are not significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is more significant is that leaping from a tall building is not typically a temptation to most people. The next matter is that before they were in the wilderness and now all of a sudden they are in Jerusalem. Scholars debate as to whether this is a vision, or whether they were supernaturally transported. I tend to vote against the vision. The leap has to be potentially fatal for the miracle the Satan is proposing to actually be miraculous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a photo of the southeastern corner of the Temple Mount.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The drop today is likely fatal but 2000 years ago, the Kidron valley below was much steeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image7.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:60%&#34; alt=&#34;C:\Users\Todd\Desktop\Files\sr pics\photobiblesr\Temple Mount southeastern corner, pinnacle, tb051908162.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a reminder that the Satan knows Scripture and he is an expert at making arguments. We need to be like Jesus and know the “whole council” of God so we don’t take Bible passages out of context, and don’t fall for it when others try to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Satan says, “look here. God says He will send His Psalm 91 angels to protect you.” Psalm 91 is a messianic passage (and the Satan knows this). Psalm 91 is a great passage and one we all would do well to memorize and rely on. However, a Tzaddiq (a righteous one) such as Jesus would have known that angelic protection is for ills that befall God’s servants, not for those who foolishly seek out danger. Therefore, we must know our Bible, and therefore we are going through the Gospels verse by verse in this series!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus counters with another passage from Deuteronomy. Note the context of “you shall not test the Lord” is not merely doing something foolish/sinful and asking God to make it right. The context is following after other gods spiritually. When we listen to the lies of the Satan, we are following after a false god. (ouch).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The testing at Massah refers to Exodus 17:7: And he called the name of the place Massah and Meribah, because of the quarreling of the people of Israel, and because they tested the LORD by saying, “Is the LORD among us or not?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-temptation-all-the-kingdoms-of-the-world-if-you-bow&#34;&gt;Third temptation: all the kingdoms of the world if you bow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 35%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 32%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 4:8-10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke 4:5-8&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.8&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Again, the devil took him to a very high mountain and showed him all the kingdoms of the world and their glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.9&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; And he said to him, “All these I will give you, if you will fall down and worship me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.10&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Then Jesus said to him, “Be gone, Satan! For it is written, “‘You shall worship the Lord your God and him only shall you serve.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5 And the devil took him up and showed him all the kingdoms of the world in a moment of time,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 and said to him, “To you I will give all this authority and their glory, for it has been delivered to me, and I give it to whom I will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 If you, then, will worship me, it will all be yours.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 And Jesus answered him, “It is written, “‘You shall worship the Lord your God, and him only shall you serve.’”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deut 6:13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Satan apparently is now convinced of Jesus’ messianic credentials, now offers Him a shortcut to usher in the Messianic Kingdom. Satan also likely knew the people were hoping for a conquering, military messiah. Here was a chance for Jesus to be this and skip all of that cross business. This might also be the Satan’s plea bargain; we make a deal here and I don’t go to the lake of fire later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writer to Hebrews reminds us that Jesus “has been tempted in all things as we are, yet without sin” (Hebrews 4:15). As Missler used to quip, “If I offer to sell you the Brooklyn Bridge, are you tempted to buy it from me? Probably not, because you are relatively certain that I don’t own it. For this to be a valid temptation, that means Jesus is acknowledging that Satan has ownership of these things, and they truly are his to give away. Jesus doesn’t challenge Satan’s ownership.” One of the many subthemes in the Bible is what I might call “things out of place.” We opened the Gospels with King Herod ruling over the land, who was neither born king nor born Jewish. Herod’s power and riches were juxtaposed against the rightful king who came lowly in a cave surrounded by deplorable shepherds. In the last lesson, we saw John the Baptist, the son of Zechariah who officiated in the temple in Jerusalem. John, a Levite, should have been in Jerusalem at the temple but instead, we find him “exiled” to the wilderness, while the usurping Sadducees are running the Temple. Here, the world that rightly belongs to God is under the authority of the Satan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t know which mountain. Mt. Nebo would have been nearby in the wilderness. Mt. Nebo is where Moses surveyed the land. Others have suggested Mt. Hermon in the far north of Israel and is the highest peak in the land of Israel. Mt. Hermon is intriguing because of its association with demonic activity in antiquity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;worship-me&#34;&gt;Worship me&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Satan said, “worship me,” he wasn’t necessarily asking Jesus to change His mind and start following Satan with His whole heart (although he certainly could have been). During the days of the seven churches in Revelation, Rome generally let people, particularly Jews, practice their religion without interference (depending on who was in charge). But often what they had to do was, one day a year, offer a sacrifice to the emperor. In the seven letters, Jesus sternly chides those who are compromising in this way. This is still idolatry, no matter how seemingly insignificant the idolatrous act is. Conversely, Jesus lavishly praises those in Smyrna and other cities who kept themselves pure from idolatry. In fact, the Bible uses an interesting metaphor for idolatry: adultery. Idolatry is spiritual fornication and unfaithfulness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a story of a mother who caught her child doing something and the response was “mom, I only did it once and it was only a little. I’m ok.” A few days later the mom made a batch of brownies and the son of course got very excited. He took one bite and the happiness immediately gagged. “What’s wrong honey,” said the mom. “These taste awful,” said the son. “What happened?” “Hmm that’s strange,” said the mom. “I only put a little bit of dog poo in the brownies. Not even a teaspoon. They should be ok.” Point made. Jesus demands complete purity. There will come a day when Jesus will take proper possession of the things of the earth that are currently in the hands of the usurper. There will be no shortcuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion-the-devil-departs&#34;&gt;Conclusion: the devil departs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 4:11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mar 1:13b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luk 4:13&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;verseid:40.4.11&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt; Then the devil left him, and behold, angels came and were ministering to him.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13 And he was with the wild animals, and the angels were ministering to him.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13 And when the devil had ended every temptation, he departed from him until an opportune time.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark and Luke give us interesting tidbits. Mark says he was with the wild animals and Luke says the devil departed until “an opportune time.” We infer that opportune time was at the Garden of Gethsemane. The animals underscore the point that Jesus was completely isolated. Satan often likes to attack us when we are isolated from other believers. The photo shows the Ibex, a type of wild goat that is common in the Judean wilderness.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image8.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.32222in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-from-the-temptations&#34;&gt;Lessons from the Temptations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus concludes each test the way any good rabbi would; He makes an appeal to Scripture. “As it is written…” should be a phrase we as Talmidim begin to use frequently as we continue to learn to be imitators of Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three temptations parallel the warning given in 1 John 2:15-17: Do not love the world or the things in the world. If anyone loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him. For all that is in the world—the desires of the flesh and the desires of the eyes and pride of life—is not from the Father but is from the world. And the world is passing away along with its desires, but whoever does the will of God abides forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bread – desire of the flesh&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kingdoms – desire of the eyes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw yourself down and angels will save – pride of life&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Satan is basically recycling the approach he used in the Garden: “So when the woman saw that the tree was good for food (flesh), and that it was a delight to the eyes (eyes), and that the tree was to be desired to make one wise (pride of life), she took of its fruit and ate, and she also gave some to her husband who was with her, and he ate” (Gen 3:6).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first Adam couldn’t resist the temptation, but the Last Adam did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;following-the-messiah-link&#34;&gt;Following the Messiah link&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Episode 3 of the “Following the Messiah” series covers the Baptism and Temptation of Jesus. It is very much worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ytb4DkglxRc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Immersion&lt;/em&gt;, accessed October 21, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_immersion_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_immersion_1.html&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Three Temptations&lt;/em&gt;, accessed October 21, 2022, &lt;a href=&#34;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/three_temptations_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/three_temptations_1.html&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William Schlegel, &lt;em&gt;The Satellite Bible Atlas&lt;/em&gt; (Israel: William Schlegel, 2013), 119.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aubrey L. Taylor, “Wilderness Events: The Baptism and Temptations of Jesus,” in &lt;em&gt;Lexham Geographic Commentary on the Gospels&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Barry J Beitzel (Bellingham, WA: Lexham Press, 2017), 56.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo: Todd Bolen, “Mark 1” (PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), fig. mat23194.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo: Bolen, fig. tb060303267.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. Thomas Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Boaz Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster, 2nd ed., vol. 3, Torah Club (Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014), 183.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig S. Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition (E-Sword) (Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014), loc. Mat 3:15.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jesus’ Was Tempted by the Devil! Following the Messiah: Ep 3&lt;/em&gt;, 2017, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ytb4DkglxRc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ytb4DkglxRc&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor, “Wilderness Events: The Baptism and Temptations of Jesus,” 58.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, 3:183.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 3:185.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, “Luke 4” (PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), fig. tb010703286.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, “Luke 4.”&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary&lt;/em&gt;, loc. Luk 4:1.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, 3:192.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, “Luke 4,” fig. tb113006722.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, 3:195.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, “Matthew 4” (PowerPoint handout, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), fig. tb051908162.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, “Mark 1,” fig. tb021906258.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Capernaum</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/gb13/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb3/gb13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a confrontation with the religious leaders in Judea, Yeshua seeks a place where He can conduct His ministry in the safety of relative obscurity. We follow Him back to the Galilee, but not back to Nazareth. Instead, He goes to the north shore of Lake Galilee for a visit to CAPERNAUM, the town of Simon Peter. We visit the village synagogue and Simon Peter’s house. Local tradition identifies a cave overlooking the lake near Capernaum and Tabgha as the “secluded place” where Yeshua used to pray. He says that He must leave Capernaum to take the good news of the kingdom to other villages. He invites the fishermen to join Him on the journey, but He does most of His miracles and teaching along the north shore of the lake within ten miles of Capernaum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vXLYuZTtAkY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LvOUOWyVpV0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12. This Day - A Prophet Without Honor</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb12/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-431-34&#34;&gt;John 4:31-34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-435-38&#34;&gt;John 4:35-38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-439&#34;&gt;John 4:39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-440-42&#34;&gt;John 4:40-42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-443-45&#34;&gt;John 4:43-45&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-446-49&#34;&gt;John 4:46-49&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-450-54&#34;&gt;John 4:50-54&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-413-15&#34;&gt;Luke 4:13-15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-416&#34;&gt;Luke 4:16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-417-20&#34;&gt;Luke 4:17-20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-421&#34;&gt;Luke 4:21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-422-24&#34;&gt;Luke 4:22-24&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#heal-thyself&#34;&gt;Heal Thyself&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#jesus-family&#34;&gt;Jesus’ family&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-425-28&#34;&gt;Luke 4:25-28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#luke-429-30&#34;&gt;Luke 4:29-30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In A PROPHET WITHOUT HONOR, we leave the village of Cana and follow Yeshua back to Nazareth to spend a quiet Shabbat in His hometown. The view from atop the Nazareth hill affords us a splendid view of the Jezreel Valley, Mount Tabor, and the surrounding territory. Take a walk around town and take in the sights as the shops close and people prepare for Sabbath. This is where our Master grew up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 1: John 4

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/g04kqUIr5gU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 2: Luke 4

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3EBTwb24T9E&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue in John 4, where the woman has left her waterpot at Jesus&amp;rsquo; feet as she ran back into town, claiming to have met someone who knows all about her. The disciples returned with food and were curious as to why Jesus was speaking alone with a Samaritan woman, but no one said anything. A talmid’s job is to model and imitate his rav/teacher, so I’m sure the disciples were wondering how far they were supposed to take this “interaction with Samaritans” thing. Jesus will tell them once we get to Luke 10. Everyone is our neighbor, and we’re supposed to love our neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this mini discourse on food, Jesus will stay in Samaria for a couple of days and then head back to Nazareth. We’ll pick up the narrative in Luke 4, where He is asked to teach on Shabbat in Nazareth. He proclaims Himself the Messiah, which signals a transition from a private to a public phase of His ministry. The people of Nazareth reject this as blasphemy. He somehow avoids a mob that wants to stone him and relocates to Capernaum to launch his public Galilean ministry. What happens there will fulfill the saying, “A prophet is without honor in his hometown.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have one more episode in what we categorize as Jesus’ “early ministry.” Next time, we will pick up John 5 in Jerusalem; after this, we’ll return to Capernaum and formally enter the next phase of Jesus’ earthly ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:4.125in;height:5.83333in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image2.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.06528in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schlaegel, in his supplemental study guide for the Satellite Bible Atlas, writes, “Neither war nor diplomacy over hundreds of years was able to break down the barriers between Jews and Samaritans. The Gospel of Jesus Christ did. Many Samaritans in the city believed in him (John 4:39-42).”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although we say this period closes Jesus’ private ministry, Jesus had been growing in popularity when He returned to Galilee. Word of His private miracles was spreading and many people reported what Jesus had been doing in Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an official from Capernaum heard that Jesus had returned to Galilee, he came up to Cana to plead with Jesus to heal his son. With a word, Jesus healed the boy from some 18 miles away. After this, or perhaps immediately before this, Jesus is in Nazareth, where He is rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-431-34&#34;&gt;John 4:31-34&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the disciples urged Him, saying, “Rabbi, eat something.” But He said to them, “I have food to eat that you do not know about.” So the disciples were saying to one another, “No one brought Him anything to eat, did he?” Jesus said to them, “My food is to do the will of Him who sent Me and to accomplish His work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we see, perhaps, a paradox. We opened John 4 with Jesus being tired and thirsty – we noted that ministry could be exhausting. While we can get exhausted by the ministry, it can also be incredibly nourishing and fulfilling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must recall His statement in the wilderness: “Man does not live on bread alone but on every word that comes from the mouth of God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:4.45161in;height:5.93548in&#34; alt=&#34;A picture containing person, cooking, meal, grill Description automatically generated&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image4.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:3.8735in;height:3.77501in&#34; alt=&#34;A person sitting at a table Description automatically generated with medium confidence&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image5.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.32153in&#34; alt=&#34;A picture containing person, dining table Description automatically generated&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These photos are from a demonstration of 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century food preparation techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One good suggestion is that when Jesus is on the Father’s mission, He is just as nourished and strengthened as if he had literal food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we go on mission trips, we start with the intent to bless others (and hopefully that does happen), but most of us return feeling like we were the ones blessed and spiritually nourished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Jesus makes statements like, “do the will of Him who sent me to accomplish His work,” we tend to see this as His work on the Cross.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is correct. Jesus will ultimately accomplish His Father’s work on the Cross – “It is finished” could be translated as “it is fulfilled” or “it is accomplished.” Tetelestai means “paid in full.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do need to keep the context in mind, however. He has not yet said anything about going to the Cross, so his Talmidim would not have interpreted Jesus’ statement as such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the near term, the Father’s Work includes Jesus’ teaching, healing, compassion, and breaking down barriers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, the talmidim are a picture of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Samaritan woman misunderstands His comment about water and she just met him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talmidim have been with Him for months now, and they are still misunderstanding him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the fun of our Christian walk is that we will never have Jesus completely figured out this side of Heaven. Every time we open His word, there is usually a new insight or aspect to Jesus we may not have noticed before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, Food and water are metaphors for spiritual truth&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water speaks of the need for salvation and regeneration in the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food represents doing the will of God – in other words, everything that comes after the moment of initial regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-435-38&#34;&gt;John 4:35-38&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Do you not say, ‘There are still four months, and then comes the harvest’? Behold, I tell you, raise your eyes and observe the fields, that they are white for harvest. “Already the one who reaps is receiving wages and is gathering fruit for eternal life, so that the one who sows and the one who reaps may rejoice together. “For in this case the saying is true: ‘One sows and another reaps.’ “I sent you to reap that for which you have not labored; others have labored, and you have come into their labor.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We harvest grain so we can have literal food; we sow and reap the Kingdom for spiritual nourishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Still four months until the harvest.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some see this as Jesus literally saying there are only four months until the harvest, and therefore this episode takes place in late December or early January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would be an odd time of year for a trip through the mountains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If so, it pokes a huge hole in the “heat of the day” argument about the woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus, who often used crop and harvest metaphors, may have been quoting a regional proverb not otherwise known to us today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, we have the proverb, “April showers bring May flowers.” This could refer to literal rain in the month of April, resulting in literal flowers, or the general truism that every action has a reaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus may be saying something like, “these fields of Samaria look bare to you because of your prejudice. You don’t see the Samaritans as worth saving. From my perspective, they are ripe for harvest. For God so loved the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Lift up your eyes” often has a negative connotation in Scripture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, Jesus is turning it around to possibly suggest His talmidim are blind to the mission field right in front of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps there was a sense among the talmidim that the time for harvest was not upon them – the sense that the harvest will only immediately precede the Messianic Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps they did not consider Samaritans as being eligible for harvest into the Kingdom. They are unreachable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are there “no go zones” in your ministry? By your words you may say there aren’t, but do your actions suggest certain people are unreachable for the Gospel? Be honest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fields white for harvest could refer to the Samaritans approaching in their white robes – even today, the Samaritan priests typically wear white, with colors reserved for those in leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Possibly, Jesus could be saying, “I sowed in the Samaritan woman, and she sowed in her town – we did the heavy lifting; now you take over.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster’s explanation:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sower = John the Baptist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reaper = Jesus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workers – the Talmidim&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time of the harvest = the present moment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fields are ripe = some are ready to receive the kingdom (such as the Samaritans here)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meaning: The harvest of souls for the kingdom begins now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-439&#34;&gt;John 4:39&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now from that city many of the Samaritans believed in Him because of the word of the woman who testified, “He told me all the things that I have done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talked about this last lesson but just to make the point again- if someone had just exposed every bad thing a person ever did, would you drop everything to meet that person, or would you run in the opposite direction for fear He might expose your sins next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Chosen,&lt;/em&gt; while still implying she was a morally fallen woman, handled this passage very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of the woman’s supposed snootiness or Jesus supposed sternness that most commentators love to imply was happening came through in their presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suggest we focus on Jesus’ love and compassion, and the woman’s restoration. And, of course, the disciples’ amazement that Samaritans are part of the plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I forget who said it but there’s a quip, “when you get to heaven, you will be surprised to see some people there who you thought were beyond God’s reach. Some people from your past may be surprised to see you for the same reason.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one is beyond God’s reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-440-42&#34;&gt;John 4:40-42&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when the Samaritans came to Jesus, they were asking Him to stay with them; and He stayed there two days. Many more believed because of His word; and they were saying to the woman, “It is no longer because of what you said that we believe, for we have heard for ourselves and know that this One truly is the Savior of the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Savior of the world” was a term used by Roman emperors to speak of themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the sources of tension, and one that would continue after Jesus’ time, is the Samaritans tended to be pro-Roman against the Jews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much like Herodium, the palace of the false king of the Jews was only a few miles from Bethlehem, the birthplace of the real king of the Jews; just a few miles from Jacob’s well was a temple to Augustus, “savior of the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those Samaritans with open eyes, Jesus, not Augustus, was the true savior of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-443-45&#34;&gt;John 4:43-45&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:4.37129in;height:3.04496in&#34; alt=&#34;A picture containing outdoor, sky, nature, grass Description automatically generated&#34; /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And after the two days, He departed from there for Galilee. For Jesus Himself testified that a prophet has no honor in his own country. So when He came to Galilee, the Galileans received Him, only because they had seen all the things that He did in Jerusalem at the feast; for they themselves also went to the feast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could read the first four verses of chapter four and come away with the impression Jesus was in a hurry to get to Galilee. We find here that is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot going on here that is not stated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purity customs (not from the Torah but man’s traditions) said that Jews and Samaritans considered each other unclean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With whom one lodged and dined was a BIG DEAL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could be called a Rosa Parks moment in Jesus’ ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although all four Gospels use the phrase, “A prophet without honor,” the synoptics use it in reference to Nazareth, while John uses it in reference to Judea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of John’s macro-narratives is Jesus’ rejection by the Jewish leadership – the very ones who should have authenticated Him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some commentators make a point that here and in verse 46, it says “He” and not “they” –&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the implication is that the disciples went on ahead, possibly because they couldn’t stomach (literally and figuratively) dining with Samaritans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a speculation that I don’t necessarily see but I can’t rule out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t know for sure that Jesus was left behind, but if He was, there could have been any number of reasons why. We aren’t told.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we’re following a strict chronology, the disciples have not yet been called to full-time ministry, so perhaps many of the disciples had jobs and families to attend to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-446-49&#34;&gt;John 4:46-49&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore He came again to Cana of Galilee, where He had made the water into wine. And there was a royal official whose son was sick at Capernaum. When he heard that Jesus had come from Judea into Galilee, he went to Him and began asking Him to come down and heal his son; for he was at the point of death. Then Jesus said to him, “Unless you people see signs and wonders, you simply will not believe.” The royal official said to Him, “Sir, come down before my child dies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is evidently trying to keep a low profile but His fame is spreading. People who went to the Passover in Jerusalem came back with stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy for us to say something like, “the Jews rejected their messiah.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nationally, this is true and certainly, the Jewish establishment rejected Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Jesus was WILDLY POPULAR among the people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, some of these were fair-weather fans only; some were followers and some were actually disciples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons the establishment wanted Jesus taken out was because of his popularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The royal official is unnamed but appears to be someone in Antipas’ administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we move through Jesus’ ministry, take a note of who is and is not Jewish; this is important to understanding Jesus’ messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This official appears to be Jewish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, someone who was with Jesus in Judea went back to Capernaum and told the official what he needed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial rebuff is reminiscent of Jesus’ words to Mary in John 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The public phase of His ministry has not yet started; not officially, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus uses the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; person plural in His rebuff, so perhaps the remark is not directed to the official but more to the people who wanted some entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-450-54&#34;&gt;John 4:50-54&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus said to him, “Go; your son is alive.” The man believed the word that Jesus spoke to him and went home. And as he was now going down, his slaves met him, saying that his son was alive. So he inquired of them the hour when he began to get better. Then they said to him, “Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him.” So the father knew that it was at that hour in which Jesus said to him, “Your son is alive”; and he himself believed, and his entire household. This is again a second sign that Jesus performed when He had come from Judea into Galilee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long-distance miracles suggest extraordinary power. “Jesus’ only prerequisite for such miracles is the seeker’s faith in His power.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commentators note that this story sounds similar to the healing of the Centurian’s servant in Luke 7. While some suggest the two events are one and the same, there are enough differences in the two narratives to suggest two separate healings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verse 54: “ this was a second time that Jesus came from Judea to the Galilee and performed a miracle.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John is obviously linking us back to John 2:11 and the first miracle at Cana.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-413-15&#34;&gt;Luke 4:13-15&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so when the devil had finished every temptation, he left Him until an opportune time. And Jesus returned to Galilee in the power of the Spirit, and news about Him spread through all the surrounding region. And He began teaching in their synagogues and was praised by all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke places the Nazareth event immediately after Jesus’ temptation in the Wilderness, though possibly an entire year elapsed between the Wilderness and Nazareth.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Was praised by all” is going to serve as a contrast to his reaction in Nazareth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He regularly attended synagogue services and taught.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verse 16 is going to say, “as was His custom.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hebrews 10:24 reminds us not to forsake the gathering together of believers. Jesus modeled this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He did not come to dismantle synagogue services or Judaism but to bring a course correction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster notes that 1st-century synagogues, unlike Jewish and Christian congregations today, did not have a single permanent teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Any competent teacher in the community or visiting rabbi might be asked to offer a Sabbath teaching.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-416&#34;&gt;Luke 4:16&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mat 13:54&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark 6:1-2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke 4:16&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;And He came to His hometown and began teaching them in their synagogue, with the result that they were astonished, and said, “Where did this man acquire this wisdom and these miraculous powers?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jesus went out from there and came into His hometown; and His disciples followed Him. And when the Sabbath came, He began to teach in the synagogue; and the many listeners were astonished, saying, “Where did this Man learn these things, and what is this wisdom that has been given to Him, and such miracles as these performed by His hands?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16 And He came to Nazareth, where He had been brought up; and as was His custom, He entered the synagogue on the Sabbath, and stood up to read.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew, if he’s attempting to be chronological, has it roughly halfway through His gospel (but He’s probably not attempting to be chronological).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some reconciliations would see a second visit to Nazareth – the first recorded by Luke and the second by Matthew and Mark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Luke was likely referencing Matthew and Mark (at least Mark) as he wrote, along with his own interviews and research, a single visit early in Jesus’ ministry seems more probable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe the residents of Nazareth were all descendants of David; if so, it makes their subsequent rejection all the more puzzling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nazareth means “branch town,” from Isaiah 11:1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isaiah 11:1-2 Then a shoot will spring from the stem of Jesse, And a Branch from his roots will bear fruit. [2] The Spirit of the LORD will rest on Him, The spirit of wisdom and understanding, The spirit of counsel and strength, The spirit of knowledge and the fear of the LORD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a decidedly messianic prophecy; in other words, the entire town was founded on the hope that the Messiah would one day come from Nazareth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet when that time came, they rejected the notion that one of their own could be the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we’re criticizing them (justifiably so) let us examine ourselves; would we have been any different?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-417-20&#34;&gt;Luke 4:17-20&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image7.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.875in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the scroll of Isaiah the prophet was handed to Him. And He unrolled the scroll and found the place where it was written: “THE SPIRIT OF THE LORD IS UPON ME, BECAUSE HE ANOINTED ME TO BRING GOOD NEWS TO THE POOR. HE HAS SENT ME TO PROCLAIM RELEASE TO CAPTIVES, AND RECOVERY OF SIGHT TO THE BLIND, TO SET FREE THOSE WHO ARE OPPRESSED, TO PROCLAIM THE FAVORABLE YEAR OF THE LORD.” And He rolled up the scroll, gave it back to the attendant, and sat down; and the eyes of all the people in the synagogue were intently directed at Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isaiah 61:1-2 The Spirit of the Lord GOD is upon me, Because the LORD anointed me To bring good news to the humble; He has sent me to bind up the brokenhearted, To proclaim release to captives And freedom to prisoners; To proclaim the favorable year of the LORD &lt;strong&gt;And the day of vengeance of our God;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone in attendance would have had Isaiah 61 memorized; it would have been conspicuous for him to leave out, “and the day of vengeance of our God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? In retrospect, we can see that in His first coming, He did not come to condemn the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If He had said, “the day of vengeance of our God,” He could not have said, “today, this scripture has been fulfilled.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience in that day would not yet have been able to make that conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless He explained why He left out the verse (as He does in The Chosen’s approach to the scene), the audience might have been &lt;em&gt;momentarily&lt;/em&gt; wondering why He did this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any concerns were about to be overshadowed by what He WOULD say next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image7.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.875in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Torah reading in Synagogues&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The synagogue tradition today is to read through the Torah in one Jewish year (50-54 weeks); however, we don’t know if this was the case 2000 years ago. Some suggest they were on a three-year cycle. After the Torah was read, a portion from the Prophets and Writings called the Haftarah was read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus was reading the Haftarah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that day, the lecturer stood to read the Torah and Haftarah, then sat to teach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know the Sabbath service in the first century included the above three elements (&lt;em&gt;Torah, haftarah, derashah).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acts 13:15 After the reading of the Law and the Prophets, the synagogue officials sent word to them, saying, “Brothers, if you have any word of exhortation for the people, say it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is not recorded, Messianic commentators assume Jesus also read the designated Torah portion that Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not know whether He picked Isaiah or whether it was assigned to Him&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In modern Torah reading annual cycles, the Haftara portion is assigned and is the same for that week’s portion every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t know whether this was the case in Jesus’ day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We suspect either way it was not a surprise to Him!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each section of the Isaiah passage is rich with Messianic overtones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, “the acceptable/favorable year of the LORD” appears to be a reference to the year of Jubilee. A year the slaves were set free, debts were cancelled and leased property reverted back to its owners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus came to cancel our spiritual debts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-421&#34;&gt;Luke 4:21&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now He began to say to them, “Today this Scripture has been fulfilled in your hearing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He possibly had part of a longer message where He either began or ended with our verse 21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He’s unquestionably claiming to be the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t miss that we’ve just entered new territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lesson could just as easily have been the opening of Jesus’ public Galilean ministry as the close of His private early ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aren’t quite sure where John 5 falls in the chronology, so we’ll cover that next time and group in with His early ministry. That chapter is John’s version of Jesus’ transition from private missions to publicly declaring who He is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-422-24&#34;&gt;Luke 4:22-24&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 33%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 33%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 33%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matthew 13&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mark 6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Luke 4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;55 “Is this not the carpenter’s son? Is His mother not called Mary, and His brothers, James, Joseph, Simon, and Judas?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;56 “And His sisters, are they not all with us? Where then did this Man acquire all these things?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;57 And they took offense at Him. But Jesus said to them, “A prophet is not dishonored except in his hometown and in his own household.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;58 And He did not do many miracles there because of their unbelief.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3 “Is this not the carpenter, the son of Mary and brother of James, Joses, Judas, and Simon? And are His sisters not here with us?” And they took offense at Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 Jesus said to them, “A prophet is not dishonored except in his hometown and among his own relatives, and in his own household.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 And He could not do any miracle there except that He laid His hands on a few sick people and healed them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 And He was amazed at their unbelief. And He was going around the villages, teaching.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;And all the people were speaking well of Him, and admiring the gracious words which were coming from His lips; and yet they were saying, “Is this not Joseph’s son?” And He said to them, “No doubt you will quote this proverb to Me: ‘Physician, heal yourself! All the miracles that we heard were done in Capernaum, do here in Your hometown as well.’” But He said, “Truly I say to you, no prophet is welcome in his hometown.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talked about whether the turning of the money changer’s tables in the Temple in John was the first of two or whether it only happened at the end of his ministry but John placed it early for a specific reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One argument in favor of there only being one event is that it might be unlikely for Jesus to “poke the bear” that early in His ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my view, NOW He’s about to “poke the bear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this instant, they are probably hanging on his every word but they still are inclined to view Him favorably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s about to change and He knows it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In fairness, we don’t know with certainty if the people in the audience entirely turned on Him or if there was a mix of supporters and detractors. The latter seems more likely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If count carefully, there are seven different reactions recorded across the three Gospels&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where did this man get these things?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s this wisdom that has been given Him?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where did this man get the power to do miracles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this not Joseph’s son?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this not the carpenter (himself)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this not Mary’s son and his brothers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are not his sisters here with us? (testimony of women?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first three questions are positive/accepting; the last three are negative/dismissive of His abilities.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One might expect this Davidic clan living in the hope of a hometown Messiah to be the first to acclaim that their own Yeshua son of Joseph as Messiah. On the contrary…He was just good-old Yeshua, the carpenter’s son.” Lancaster.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David was also rejected/dismissed by his father and brothers. “When Samuel anointed David, Jesse and David’s brothers were stunned.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heal-thyself&#34;&gt;Heal Thyself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same maxim is quoted in the Jewish Midrash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It means “prove your claims.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;jesus-family&#34;&gt;Jesus’ family&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We speculate that Joseph has since died.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had Joseph remained alive, Jesus (given His obvious skills as demonstrated when He was 12) might have been able to complete Beit Midrash and Beit Talmud to study under a prominent Sage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is, out of necessity and as the firstborn, He likely had to assume the role of family provider, which meant taking over His father’s carpentry/masonry business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, that’s all the townfolk saw Him as.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Matthew 13, Jesus was the oldest of at least seven children (Jesus, four brothers, and at least two sisters).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to preserve the tradition of Mary’s perpetual virginity, some suggest that the other children are children of Joseph by another wife or are actually cousins, not siblings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving tradition aside, reading all as children of Mary, with everyone after Jesus conceived in the usual manner, is supported by a plain reading of the text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The names provided are all common Jewish names, and ones that are shared by several disciples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 7:5 helps us out a little as we’re told none of Jesus’s brothers believed in Him until after the resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have evidence suggesting James (Yakov in Hebrew) was a Pharisee. If so, James had the opportunity for formal schooling that Jesus did not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the resurrection, James became the head of the Jerusalem assembly of believers, even to the point of having apostolic authority over the original disciples (including Peter, which must have been a fascinating dynamic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He appears to be well-regarded, even among the non-messianic Jews. He has the nickname James the Just, or we might say James the Righteous/Tzadik. The only way he would have earned this nickname is from strict Torah observance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This James is the author of the book of James and should not be confused with the two Apostles named James (James the Less (Mark 15:40) or James son of Alphaeus (Matthew 10:3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judas (Jude)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this is not the same as Judas who betrayed Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus’ brother Judas authored the book we know as Jude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simon and Joseph&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Simon is not Peter nor Simon the Zealot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Joseph is not the Joses mentioned in Mark 15:40.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Church tradition ascribes varying roles to Jesus’ brothers and sisters, but we have no other corroborating documentation to either support or refute this tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-425-28&#34;&gt;Luke 4:25-28&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25 “But I say to you in truth, there were many widows in Israel in the days of Elijah, when the sky was shut up for three years and six months, when a severe famine came over all the land;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;26 and yet Elijah was sent to none of them, but only to Zarephath, in the land of Sidon, to a woman who was a widow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;27 “And there were many with leprosy in Israel in the time of Elisha the prophet; and none of them was cleansed, but only Naaman the Syrian.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;28 And all the people in the synagogue were filled with rage as they heard these things;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus quotes a couple of miracles performed by Elijah and Elisha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Kings 17:9 “Arise, go to Zarephath, which belongs to Sidon, and stay there; behold, I have commanded a widow there to provide food for you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 Kings 5:14 So (Naaman) went down and dipped himself in the Jordan seven times, in accordance with the word of the man of God; and his flesh was restored like the flesh of a little child, and he was clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is an entertaining story and worth our study. 2 Kings 5.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may not see what the big deal is, but as Chuck Missler liked to say, whenever you and I are in danger of missing something, the people come to our rescue. They are enraged and it’s our task to find out why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some commentators see the problem is he’s mentioning the socially weak and marginalized, which offended the sensibilities of the town. That’s not it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He’s saying, actually prophesying, that Gentiles receive the things of God and Jews do not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just as Elijah and Elisha did not heal everyone, neither did Jesus heal everyone who needed it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some commentators interpret this as Jesus casting off Jews and Judaism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably know me well enough by now to realize that, in my humble opinion, this is not how to read this passage appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire focus of the upcoming segment of His ministry is going to be to the Jews and ONLY the Jews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He will tell His disciples, “do NOT go in way of the gentiles…rather go to the lost sheep of the house of Israel” (Matthew 10-5-6).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All He’s doing here is explaining that He will leave Nazareth and take His ministry elsewhere; specifically, He will take it to the JEWISH town of Capernaum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What He WAS doing was comparing Himself to two of Israel’s greatest prophets, and in so doing, comparing Nazareth to the likes of idolatrous Ahab and Jezebel, who rejected and tried to kill the prophets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rough paraphrase might be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surely some of you will tell Me to prove my claims of being Messiah by the signs and miracles you have heard me do in other places. Just as Elisha and Elijah did not do these miracles for everybody, you Nazarenes are not worthy of My miracles. I’m out.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;luke-429-30&#34;&gt;Luke 4:29-30&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and they got up and drove Him out of the city, and brought Him to the crest of the hill on which their city had been built, so that they could throw Him down from the cliff. But He passed through their midst and went on His way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image8.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.87361in&#34; alt=&#34;A picture containing outdoor, mountain, sky, nature Description automatically generated&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, even when Jews had the power of capital punishment (which at this time they did not) Jewish law required order and due process to criminal proceedings, particularly for a capital crime, such as blasphemy – and there is no chance an execution would have been allowed on Shabbat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of a lawless, nearly out of control mob, the Chosen elected to portray this scene as people serious about the Torah and about the Laws of Blasphemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chief Rabbi asked repeatedly for Jesus to recount His so-called “blasphemy”; When Jesus did not, the rabbi felt He had no choice under the law of Moses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I had always viewed it as an out-of-control mob I appreciated the lesson in keeping our options open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to revise my notes for this section after I watched the episode in Season 3. I’m Ok with that. I still lean towards the out-of-control mob angle, but I can entertain the other possibility too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should always be ready to update our conclusions when indicated. That’s being a good Berean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a coworker who liked to say, “we always reserve the right to get smarter.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a Berean does not mean you have to accept everything anyone says, however. It has to fit Scripture and it has to fit the context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as to avoid cruel and unusual punishment, the condemned would often be thrown from a cliff, with the thought that the numerous jagged rocks would at least render him unconscious, with the stones then thrown to finish him off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They would aim for the chest, not the head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the fall alone killed the person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was not necessarily the altitude of the fall but the fact one would lose his balance and be very likely to hit his head on a rock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that day, Nazareth was MUCH smaller than it is today; a walk to either the northern hill or far less likely the southern hill would have been a hike on a Sabbath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The southern hill is “venerated” by tour companies because it’s a low-hassle stop without going through Nazareth on the way to Capernaum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The views of the Jezreel valley are a spectacular place to remember Jesus’ declaration and remember the OT events in the historical books that happened right in front of the hill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We presume it was something supernatural that saved Him but remember, He did no miracles there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could have been His poise or his attitude that silenced them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or He potentially had to tussle His way through the crowd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, His hour had not yet come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope for Nazareth?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the years following His resurrection, the people of Nazareth became fervent believers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His brothers became leaders in the early Messianic Jewish movement and Nazareth appears to have been a center for Jewish believers.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even today, the Modern Hebrew word for “Christians” is “notzrim.” “Nazarenes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Matthew 4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Luke 4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;13 and leaving Nazareth, He came and settled in Capernaum, which is by the sea, in the region of Zebulun and Naphtali.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14 This happened so that what was spoken through Isaiah the prophet would be fulfilled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 “THE LAND OF ZEBULUN AND THE LAND OF NAPHTALI, BY THE WAY OF THE SEA, ON THE OTHER SIDE OF THE JORDAN, GALILEE OF THE GENTILES—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;16 THE PEOPLE WHO WERE SITTING IN DARKNESS SAW A GREAT LIGHT, AND THOSE WHO WERE SITTING IN THE LAND AND SHADOW OF DEATH, UPON THEM A LIGHT DAWNED.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31 And He came down to Capernaum, a city of Galilee; and He was teaching them on the Sabbath;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will pick this up two lessons from now when we get to Capernaum and Jesus public ministry. Next time we’ll have one more lesson in the “early ministry” category. John 5 and the Pools of Bethesda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener, Craig S. &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;. 2nd edition (E-Sword). Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, D. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by Boaz Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster. 2nd ed. 6 vols. Torah Club. Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Missler, Chuck. &lt;em&gt;The Gospel of Luke: A Commentary (Supplemental Notes)&lt;/em&gt;. Coeur d’Alene, ID: KOINONIA HOUSE, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schlegel, William. “The Land and the Bible: A Historical Geographical Companion to the Satellite Bible Atlas,” September 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern, David H. &lt;em&gt;Complete Jewish Bible : An English Version of the Tanakh and Brit Hadeshah&lt;/em&gt;. Revised Edition (E-Sword). Clarksville, Md: Lederer Messianic Publications, 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/a_prophet_without_honor_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/a_prophet_without_honor_1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vintage Video: 
 &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
   &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8akjSR2asLE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William Schlegel, “The Land and the Bible: A Historical Geographical Companion to the Satellite Bible Atlas,” September 2013, loc. Map 9-3, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. Thomas Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Boaz Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster, 2nd ed., Torah Club (Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014), 260.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 261.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig S. Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition (E-Sword) (Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014), loc. John 4:50-54.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David H. Stern, &lt;em&gt;Complete Jewish Bible : An English Version of the Tanakh and Brit Hadeshah&lt;/em&gt;, Revised Edition (E-Sword) (Clarksville, Md: Lederer Messianic Publications, 1998), loc. John 4:54.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chuck Missler, &lt;em&gt;The Gospel of Luke: A Commentary (Supplemental Notes)&lt;/em&gt; (Coeur d’Alene, ID: KOINONIA HOUSE, 2011), 64.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, 282.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 291.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 277.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 292.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 293.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 295.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
