<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>physical | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/physical/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/tag/physical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>physical</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu53652e90a6e4e4f125f22da2a993ec10_403021_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>physical</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/physical/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for Reducing Jetlag</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/practical/flight-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/practical/flight-tips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be prepared for a very long flight&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Except for flights to China, American Airlines&#39; proposed nonstop from DFW to TLV would be the carrier&amp;rsquo;s longest route out of DFW: 14:30 flying time; 6,982 nautical miles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If connecting from an east coast city, expect at least a 10 hour flight&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;general&#34;&gt;General&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good article here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifehacker.com/how-to-survive-a-long-haul-flight-with-finesse-1551468782&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How to make the best of a long-haul flight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    The #1 tip for acclimating to a new time zone is to be outside as much as possible.  Your internal clock will naturally sync up with the sun.  Really!
Conversely, the receptors in your skin react to artificial light the same way, especially blue light from screens.  This light tells your body you should be awake.  Don&amp;rsquo;t just wear eye shades, but cover up as much exposed skin as possible.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-to-bring-for-the-flight&#34;&gt;What to bring for the flight:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleep Aid:&lt;/strong&gt; We recommend that you consult your physician for possible sleep aids. Herbal remedies are also recommended. If this is you, you may wish to time when you take it so you aren’t groggy through dinner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neck Pillow&lt;/strong&gt;: This allows you to sleep sitting up without hurting your neck. The kind that blow up or wrap around your neck will take much less room in your carry-on bag. There &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/i8Dpfg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;are all kinds of different styles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleeping Shades:&lt;/strong&gt; Cloth eye covers that block light are essential.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ear Plugs:&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever sat next to a screaming baby on a flight? Noise-canceling head phones are also a great item when traveling.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can even get eyeshades have earphones built-in.  Who knew?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blankets&lt;/strong&gt;: If you do not like to use an airline blanket, you might want to purchase one that folds down to nothing so as not to take space in your carry-on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toothbrush/toothpaste/washcloth&lt;/strong&gt; for the morning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comfortable Shoes&lt;/strong&gt;: Wear comfortable and loose shoes on the overseas flight. Your feet may retain fluids over the course of the flight but should return to normal after landing. Some prefer sandals, however, your feet can get cold so be sure to have some socks available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Therapeutic Socks:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be sitting a long time. Deep Venous Thrombosis (DVT) is a real concern for any flight over 4 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are prone to leg edema you should purchase therapeutic socks and wear them for the duration of the flight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you know you are at risk, talk with your doctor to learn more about how to prevent blood clots,
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FYI - someone on one of our trips had never had an issue with leg edema&amp;hellip;until OUR trip. Therapeutic socks are inexpensive - better safe than sorry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everyone&lt;/strong&gt; consider doing leg stretches periodically while in your seat and getting up and stretching every so often (when permitted). As with domestic flights do not congregate in the galley or lavatory areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sleep-tips-for-the-overnight-flight&#34;&gt;Sleep Tips for the overnight flight&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assuming you can&amp;rsquo;t get upgraded to the &amp;ldquo;Flagship Business Class&amp;rdquo; with the sweet lie-flat seats, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably be stuck in a standard coach class seat.  If you have room and are on a plane that has two aisles, try to grab a seat in the middle section - it will be slightly quieter and darker than the seats by the windows.  If you&amp;rsquo;re a heavier sleeper, a window seat will help keep your head propped up.  Everything&amp;rsquo;s a trade off!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are assigned an aisle seat and want the best chance for uninterrupted sleep, see if you can trade for an interior seat to reduce your chances of being woken up. Conversely, if you say, &amp;ldquo;I have a small bladder and will be up a lot&amp;rdquo; it might score you an aisle seat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many people believe the less you eat, the better you sleep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Others suggest the following regimen as soon as you get to your seat:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kick off your shoes (or just wear flip flops so your feet can breathe)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a sleeping pill (or two) if it&amp;rsquo;s medically appropriate for you around 8:00 or 9:00pm Dallas time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On a flight that leaves from the east coast, they will serve dinner about an hour into the flight (non-stops from DFW will probably be a little later) - go ahead and eat but avoid soda, alcohol, and foods that are gas-inducing (beans, cabbage, onions, cucumber, anything greasy) - the portions are usually small enough that you&amp;rsquo;d be hard-pressed to feel &amp;ldquo;stuffed&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After dinner, throw on the eye shades, ear plugs (or noise-canceling headphones), get your head as comfortable as possible and try to sleep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to avoid the in-seat movies or other electronic screens- the blue light from the screen may interfere with sleep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you absolutely can&amp;rsquo;t sleep, please don&amp;rsquo;t be &amp;ldquo;that person&amp;rdquo; who leaves their reading light on the entire flight! Bring eye shades in case you are seated near &amp;ldquo;that person&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the means and wish to upgrade to premium economy or business class, go for it!
The rest of us may be jealous, but we would do the same thing if we could!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;approaching-ben-gurion&#34;&gt;Approaching Ben Gurion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As soon as you wake up (or after about every three hours if you absolutely can&amp;rsquo;t sleep), head to the bathroom to stretch (isometric and light calisthenics) and down a glass or two of water and try to sleep again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drinking lots of water (as much as 5 16.9 oz bottles!) is recommended -&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes if you drink water, you will have to get up and go to the lavatory, but that movement is also a good thing to help you with jet lag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They will likely serve a light breakfast about two hours prior to landing - you&amp;rsquo;ll know it&amp;rsquo;s coming when they flip all the lights back on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t want too long to use the bathroom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depending on the flight path, a window seat on the &amp;ldquo;A&amp;rdquo; side could get a good view of the New Testament lands of Greece, Crete, Cyprus, and Turkey as we approach Israel in the mid-afternoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At some point during the flight you will be asked to complete an Immigration entry form (the US will require this too on the return flight). Fill it out completely and hold onto it until you get to &lt;a href=&#34;../passport&#34;&gt;Passport control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;landing-at-ben-gurion&#34;&gt;Landing at Ben Gurion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how much you slept, you are likely to be at least a little &amp;ldquo;out of it&amp;rdquo; after the long flight&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before You Leave Your Seat:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have your Passport? Phone? Wallet? Camera? Glasses? Name Badge?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look around between seats, under the seat in front of you as well as under your own seat, etc; be eyes for others in our group as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you are now wearing your Name Badge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soak in the fact that you are now in a very special Land that God calls His own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;../passport&#34;&gt;separate section on Israeli Airport Security&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;returning-to-usa&#34;&gt;Returning to USA&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sleeping on the way home can sometimes be less of a challenge because our flight will usually leave very shortly after midnight local time.  Since we will have been on the go for most of the day, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably be tired. Follow the same advice above for sleeping and avoiding jet leg once back in Texas. Get lots of that Texas sunshine!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID Information for Travelers to Israel</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/physical/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/tour/israel2023/physical/covid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As of March 1, 2022 our understanding is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Covid vaccinations are no longer required for entry to Israel, or for US citizens returning
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In fact, Israel&amp;rsquo;s lifting of the vaccine requirement was the signal God used to tell us it was time to go!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As of now, masks remain required on all flights and, in Israel, in indoor public spaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A negative PCR test is required (&amp;ldquo;regardless of age or vaccination status&amp;rdquo;) to enter both countries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will pray these remaining restrictions are relaxed between now and the time we travel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course all of this information is subject to change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For better, if the pandemic is declared resolved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For worse, if COVID resurfaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will keep this page updated should requirements change.  A change for the worse, could mean we need to postpone our trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please make sure your trip cancellation insurance includes global health-related reasons, including your being unwilling/unable to comply with government COVID requirements that may be in place on the date of our departure.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
