<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>John 2 | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/john-2/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/tag/john-2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>John 2</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu9bdc4cc28a100eaa5c154301214e2807_480992_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>John 2</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/john-2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>8. The First Sign (22)</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb08/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In THE FIRST SIGN, we join Yeshua and His handful of followers in the Jordan River Valley near Jericho. We follow them north along the eastern side and pick up more disciples on Lake Galilee’s north shore in Bethsaida and Capernaum. A fishing boat takes us across the lake to Magdala.  From there, it’s a day’s walk to Cana of Galilee on the northern slopes of the Nazareth ridge, where Yeshua and His first followers attend a wedding. From there, we follow them back to Capernaum on the north shore of Lake Galilee, where they join a pilgrimage making their way down the Jordan Valley, following its eastern bank, before crossing near Jericho and ascending to Jerusalem for the Festival of Passover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-gospel-of-john-as-a-legal-document&#34;&gt;The Gospel of John as a legal document&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#who-were-the-ioudaioi&#34;&gt;Who were the &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#geographic-setting&#34;&gt;Geographic setting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-135-37&#34;&gt;John 1:35-37&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#walking-in-his-dust&#34;&gt;Walking in His dust&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-138-39&#34;&gt;John 1:38-39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-140-42&#34;&gt;John 1:40-42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-143-44&#34;&gt;John 1:43-44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-145-46&#34;&gt;John 1:45-46&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-147-49&#34;&gt;John 1:47-49&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-150-51&#34;&gt;John 1:50-51&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-21-2&#34;&gt;John 2:1-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-23-5&#34;&gt;John 2:3-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-26-8&#34;&gt;John 2:6-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-29-10&#34;&gt;John 2:9-10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-211-12&#34;&gt;John 2:11-12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 1:35-51&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4hPBHDlzpAU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John 2:1-12&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ct1QykjWK9U&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-gospel-of-john-as-a-legal-document&#34;&gt;The Gospel of John as a legal document&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 He came as a &lt;strong&gt;witness&lt;/strong&gt;, to bear witness about the light, that all might believe through him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 He was not the light, but came to bear &lt;strong&gt;witness&lt;/strong&gt; about the light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 Johnn bore &lt;strong&gt;witness&lt;/strong&gt; about him, and cried out, “This was he of whom I said, ‘He who comes after me ranks before me, because he was before me.’”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 And this is the &lt;strong&gt;testimony&lt;/strong&gt; of John, when the Jews sent priests and Levites from Jerusalem to ask him, “Who are you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20 He &lt;strong&gt;confessed&lt;/strong&gt;, and did not deny, but confessed, “I am not the Christ.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;21 And they &lt;strong&gt;asked&lt;/strong&gt; him, “What then? Are you Elijah?” He said, “I am not.” “Are you the Prophet?” And he answered, “No.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;22 So they said to him, “Who are you? &lt;strong&gt;We need to give an answer&lt;/strong&gt; to those who sent us. What do you say about yourself?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;31 I myself did not know him, but for this purpose I came baptizing with water, &lt;strong&gt;that he might be revealed&lt;/strong&gt; to Israel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;32 And John bore &lt;strong&gt;witness&lt;/strong&gt;: “I saw the Spirit descend from heaven like a dove, and it remained on him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;34 And I have seen and have borne &lt;strong&gt;witness&lt;/strong&gt; that this is the Son of God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-were-the-ioudaioi&#34;&gt;Who were the &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.875in&#34; alt=&#34;C:\PLBLsr\apr4\Priestly blessing during Sukkot at Western Wall, tb092302017.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The translation of Ioudaioi always and only as “Jews” sends the reader in the opposite direction from what the author intended.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will develop this in later lessons but John the Gospel Writer, is very loose with his terminology. &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt;, which is the word John uses that is typically translated as “the Jews”, could mean anything from all Jews, to all believing Jews, to those in leadership of the Jewish religious establishment, to those geographically in or from Judea, some other subset&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if Ioudaioi refers to the religious establishment, John may be indenting for us to understand a specific subset of that. For example, Nicodemus was part of the &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt; religious establishment, but we can be confident he is not part of the &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt; with whom Jesus has any quarrel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an analogy we could use the term “Americans” The Americans won the gold medal in 1980. All 300 million of us? No. 20 hockey players representing the country. We could also say the Americans bombed Syria. Well that doesn’t all 300 million of us, but maybe a squadron of planes acting on order from one President. We also say today that “the House passed” some piece of legislation; all that could mean is at least 50% of those present+ 1, not all 435 House members acting in unison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, many of us have learned to see the “Jews” especially as John uses it has a negative connotation to mean ALL Jews everywhere. The gospel of John has been used to support anti-Semitic behavior in the name of Jesus. This is incorrect and terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the 1st-century church consisted of &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt;, so it is an error to say that ALL &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt; are guilty of rejecting and killing Jesus. There are believing &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt; and rejecting &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt;. The temple establishment opposed to Jesus and ultimately those who arrested Him and had Him executed could have been a very small number. Perhaps less than 35 and maybe even less than 20: in other words, a very small group of hidden players acting behind the scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, we need to make sure some latent anti-Semitic bias is removed from our reading. We need to work to discern the context and which Ioudaioi group John is referencing. If the context is negative, it is probably only the “deep state” fraction of the Temple establishment. This group was primarily Sadducees and Herodians with a small number of Pharisees along for the ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we see the term “Ioudaioi” we will leave it untranslated to remind us that we need to be Bereans and explore the context in which John uses the term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;geographic-setting&#34;&gt;Geographic setting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image2.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:5.07014in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 1:28 tells us that “these things took place in Bethany across the Jordan where John was baptizing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good scholars dispute the location of “Bethany Beyond the Jordan”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Location of Jesus’ baptism is widely believed to be in the vicinity of Jericho, but this doesn’t mean that John the Baptist didn’t have different locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some, such as Schlaegel&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, hold that “Bethany” is actually north, in the Golan heights, which would account for disciples from Galilee being present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first four disciples known to be in Jesus’ company at this point are all from Bethsaida: Andrew, John (the unnamed disciple), Peter, and Philip.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter and Andrew would later move to Capernaum (Mark 1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems logical that Peter, Andrew, James and John probably had a fishing cooperative, perhaps as a customs tax avoidance ploy as one boat would be registered in Capernaum (Herod Antipas’ region) and the other in Bethsaida (Herod Philip’s region).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion with Nathaniel possibly takes place at Bethsaida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They will then make their way past Capernaum and Magdala, through the valley of the doves to Cana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the wedding miracle, they will return to Capernaum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-135-37&#34;&gt;John 1:35-37&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day again John was standing with two of his disciples, and he looked at Jesus as he walked by and said, “Behold, the Lamb of God!” The two disciples heard him say this, and they followed Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John would seem to place verse 35 as being the next afternoon following Jesus’ baptism where the spirit came down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might have been the next day but it didn’t need to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John, and indeed the entire eastern mindset, is not as bound to a strict chronological record as we in the west have been brought up with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;walking-in-his-dust&#34;&gt;Walking in His dust&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Like John, we should demonstrate humility and keep our eyes on God’s bigger picture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do nothing from selfish ambition or conceit, but in humility count others more significant than yourselves. Let each of you look not only to his own interests but also to the interests of others. (Php 2:3-4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In John 1:35, John the Baptist essentially refers two of his own disciples to Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a teacher saying, “you should really go to the church down the street; that teacher is better than I am”!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, this is essentially what John the Baptist says to his former disciples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It speaks of John’s humility and that fact that his eyes were on God’s bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is how it should be with us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-138-39&#34;&gt;John 1:38-39&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Jesus turned and saw them following and said to them, “What are you seeking?” And they said to him, “Rabbi” (which means Teacher), “where are you staying?” He said to them, “Come and you will see.” So they came and saw where he was staying, and they stayed with him that day, for it was about the tenth hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rabbi here is transliterated Hebrew, a clue that Jesus and His talmidim spoke Hebrew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other places, we will see Raboni, which is transliterated Aramaic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aramaic was the everyday language, while, we presume, Hebrew was used by the devout or in religious settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government language would have been Greek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They probably knew enough Greek to understand commercial transactions and to interact with Roman officials but it is highly doubtful they would have spoken Greek among themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Gospels, the word rabbi always speaks of Jesus (except in Matthew 23 where Jesus discusses the word itself).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rabbi in that day was more a term of respect and not, as it means today, a teacher with specific training and ordination who performs a specific role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What are you seeking?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus asks us the same question every day and every moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the disciples, we rarely answer the question directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We answer it by our choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Where are you staying?” is an indirect way of asking to follow Jesus. They were answering His question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll unpack this in a later lesson, but it appears that “calling disciples” was a process, not a one-time event (think of the job application and interview process).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Rabbi and his perspective talmidim would take some time to get to know each other before agreeing to a multi-year commitment to one-another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This viewpoint untangles the various “callings” of the disciples that are recorded in the gospels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come and See” – head’s up; pay attention; follow me and learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They stayed with Him that day for it was about the 10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; hour”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; hour is probably around 4pm (but it depends on the time of year; an hour wasn’t 60 minutes but 1/12 of daylight).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some have suggested this was erev-shabbat, Friday afternoon, and the disciples were hoping to score an invitation to spend Shabbat with the Master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They didn’t just stay with Jesus that “night” but “that day,” meaning Friday night and all day Saturday, Shabbat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you imagine spending Shabbat, a free day, with Jesus. No appointments, no phones or TV; talking Bible until late at night and then again the next morning perhaps after Shabbat prayers at the local synagogue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing Jesus, I bet the conversation wasn’t limited to just Bible study; I imagine Jesus challenged them to be better. Perhaps the conversation was uncomfortable but never awkward, because it’s Jesus, our ultimate fiduciary; the One who would lay down His life for our best interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their lives would never be the same; they had found the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many times have we breezed past a Bible verse like “and they stayed with Him that day” and not really thought about the implications?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-140-42&#34;&gt;John 1:40-42&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the two who heard John speak and followed Jesus was Andrew, Simon Peter&amp;rsquo;s brother. He first found his own brother Simon and said to him, “We have found the Messiah” (which means Christ). He brought him to Jesus. Jesus looked at him and said, “You are Simon the son of John. You shall be called Cephas” (which means Peter).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learn that one of the two talmidim who spent shabbat with Yeshua that day was Andrew. Scholars presume the other was John himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simon Peter, Andrew, James, and John probably grew up together and were likely in their mid-teens when they first met Jesus.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Messiah means “anointed one”; it is a title, which in Greek is translated as Christ. Given the above discussion, his disciples would have referred to Jesus as the Mashiach, Messiah, not “Christ”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A subtle miracle here: Jesus and Peter had not met before, yet Jesus knows not only his first name but his family name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Jew would have recognized this as a sign of a prophet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cephas is a transliteration of Kefa, which means “rock”; rock in Greek is “petros”, which is how we get Peter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably a prophetic nickname about Peter’s future role in the early church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to imagine that it baffled Shimon at the time. “Why are you calling me that? We just met.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He brought him to Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Augustine reportedly said, “John’s Gospel is deep enough for an elephant to swim yet shallow enough for a child not to drown.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He finds the messiah. He tells someone else he has found the messiah. He brings that someone else to the messiah. That someone else changed the world for Messiah. (I said that, not Augustine!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-143-44&#34;&gt;John 1:43-44&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day Jesus decided to go to Galilee. He found Philip and said to him, “Follow me.” Now Philip was from Bethsaida, the city of Andrew and Peter.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A disciple of that day would be no more inclined to drop everything and follow a complete stranger than we would be today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus casting some sort of spell over his disciples to make them follow him blindly is entirely inconsistent with Jesus’ later passages to count the cost before answering the call to be His disciple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, even though the text doesn’t say this, it seems safe to infer that Philip and Jesus met previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I know I’m usually the first to point out “the text doesn’t say that,” but this is where we need to be Bereans and exclude potential conclusions that are contradicted elsewhere in the Bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While I wasn’t there and anything could have happened, on the surface, Philip following Jesus blindly is not consistent with other portions of scripture and is not consistent with what we think we know about 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century discipleship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beit Tzaidah – house of fish nets, or more simply “fish town”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By piecing together various biblical and historical clues, scholars speculate that John’s father Zebedee ran a sizable fishing business that included a partnership with Simon and Andrew as well as his own sons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholars began excavating “et Tell” and many have concluded it is the ancient Bethsaida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem in identifying et-Tell with Bethsaida is its distance from the Sea of Galilee and its elevation above the ancient level of the lake&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been there and it’s not so much the distance from the lake as the fact that it is a much higher elevation, even if we account for potentially higher lake levels back in Jesus’ day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BUT excavators have concluded that the village contained a fisherman’s home based on their discovery of two types of lead net weights. One weight was round, of the so-called musket type, and the second was elongated, similar in shape to a crooked needle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mentioned by name seven times in the Gospels, Bethsaida is one of the most frequently mentioned cities in the New Testament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-145-46&#34;&gt;John 1:45-46&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philip found Nathanael and said to him, “We have found him of whom Moses in the Law and also the prophets wrote, Jesus of Nazareth, the son of Joseph.” Nathanael said to him, “Can anything good come out of Nazareth?” Philip said to him, “Come and see.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one of whom Moses spoke was the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deut 18:15-18 “The LORD your God will raise up for you a prophet like me from among you, from your brothers—it is to him you shall listen— just as you desired of the LORD your God at Horeb on the day of the assembly, when you said, ‘Let me not hear again the voice of the LORD my God or see this great fire any more, lest I die.’ And the LORD said to me, ‘They are right in what they have spoken. I will raise up for them a prophet like you from among their brothers. And I will put my words in his mouth, and he shall speak to them all that I command him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acts 3:22 Moses said, ‘The Lord God will raise up for you a prophet like me from your brothers. You shall listen to him in whatever he tells you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though we don’t have legal terms, note how everyone is testifying, as Philip is here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathaniel also testifies to Nazareth’s insignificance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No more than 200 people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the Davidic connections and the fact that they were likely insular, it is possible outsiders viewed the people of Nazareth as somehow affiliated with the corrupt Jerusalem leadership, which would have been a negative for other Galileans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 21 tells us that Nathaniel is from Cana, which makes the statement about Nazareth that much more of a burn; Cana was as insignificant as Nazareth was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholars believe Nathaniel and Bartholomew are one and the same.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-147-49&#34;&gt;John 1:47-49&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus saw Nathanael coming toward him and said of him, “Behold, an Israelite indeed, in whom there is no deceit!” Nathanael said to him, “How do you know me?” Jesus answered him, “Before Philip called you, when you were under the fig tree, I saw you.” Nathanael answered him, “Rabbi, you are the Son of God! You are the King of Israel!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Nathaniel’s skepticism, Jesus testifies in Nathaniel’s favor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathaniel means “God gave,” or perhaps “God’s gift.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fig tree reference is apparently something only Nathaniel understood, though generally, the fig tree represents national Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Symbolically, trees also represented knowledge and teachers often taught under trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There might be a subtle pun: Israel/Jacob WAS a man of deceit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the vision of the angels ascending and descending which Jesus will reference in the next segment, Jacob was fleeing precisely because of his deceit of Esau.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lizorkin speculates that John’s intended audience might have been non-&lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt; followers of Israel’s God; for example, Samaritans and Essenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If so, Nathaniel’s pronouncement carries more significance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is not just King of the &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt;, He is King of all Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-150-51&#34;&gt;John 1:50-51&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus answered him, “Because I said to you, ‘I saw you under the fig tree,’ do you believe? You will see greater things than these.” And he said to him, “Truly, truly, I say to you, you will see heaven opened, and the angels of God ascending and descending on the Son of Man.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly, truly is literally, “amen, amen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Heaven opened” indicates a major revelation from God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This imagery evokes Jacob’s dream in Genesis 28:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And he dreamed, and behold, there was a ladder set up on the earth, and the top of it reached to heaven. And behold, the angels of God were ascending and descending on it! And behold, the LORD stood above it and said, “I am the LORD, the God of Abraham your father and the God of Isaac. The land on which you lie I will give to you and to your offspring.” (Gen 28:12-13)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathaniel could have been reading Genesis 28 as he sat under the fig tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Samaritans have a specific attachment to Jacob and his favorite son, Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In John 4 we will be at Jacob’s well in Sychar, where the Samaritan woman will ask, “Are you greater than our father Jacob?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, Jesus is seemingly anticipating that question and His answer is an emphatic “YES.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The angels Jacob saw are not ascending and descending at a place in Samaria but upon Jesus Himself.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is the bridge/ladder between heaven and earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-21-2&#34;&gt;John 2:1-2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.29514in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the third day there was a wedding at Cana in Galilee, and the mother of Jesus was there. Jesus also was invited to the wedding with his disciples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could refer to the third day of the week, Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, the third day of creation, was the day God said “It was good” twice (1:10 and 1:12).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it is the “day of the double blessing,” some speculate that weddings were often held on Tuesdays, but this is disputed&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could also mean simply three days had elapsed since the discussion with Nathaniel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may also be literary bracketing; in John 2:19, Jesus says, “Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John is not necessarily chronological; while in our minds, John 2 occurs when Jesus is still relatively obscure, it is possible that wedding occurred after Jesus and his disciples had gained some regional notoriety and would be honored guests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the map&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, you can see there are two contenders for Cana; one is off the beaten path, and the other happens to be on the main road from Nazareth to Tiberias (in other words, easier for the tour busses)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most scholars I’ve come across tend to side with the less accessible site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than officiating the wedding, Lancaster says that Jewish sages were invited to liven things up. The Talmud records the disciples of Hillel would sing before the bride and others added joy in various ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find this tidbit fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there another wedding at some point in our future that Jesus will preside over where He will add joy? YES. You can read about it in Revelation 19 and all of the various wedding feast references in the New Testament – there are several of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus was about to inject more joy to be sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-23-5&#34;&gt;John 2:3-5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the wine ran out, the mother of Jesus said to him, “They have no wine.” And Jesus said to her, “Woman, what does this have to do with me? My hour has not yet come.” His mother said to the servants, “Do whatever he tells you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is today, if the host runs out of food or drink at a wedding it would be a major social faux-pas. 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Century Jewish wedding celebrations typically lasted for seven days and the host was responsible for providing this quantity of wine to his invited and uninvited guests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commentator John Lightfoot believes that Mary might have had a formal role in the planning of the feast and was not merely being a busy body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Messianic Age is often depicted as a wedding banquet with free-flowing wine&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Holy One, blessed be He, will make a banquet for the righteous in the Garden of Eden…He will give them to drink wine preserved in its grapes since the six days of creation” (Numbers Rabbah 13:2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was Mary asking for the inauguration of the Messianic Age, and this is why Jesus replies as He does?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reply by Jesus to Mary’s request is not nearly as cold-sounding as it is in English and he is not disobeying the commandment to honor His mother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can imagine Mary struggled to understand all of the various signs and wonders that she pondered in her heart since before Jesus was born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From her response, “it is evident she was neither dissatisfied nor put off&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;” by Jesus’ remark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern speculates that Jesus was attempting to curtail Mary’s natural pride as the mother of the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus WOULD address the literal problem Mary brought to Him; but He would not do it in the public way that she hoped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We say often that the people wanted a political messiah, not the suffering messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mary didn’t want the political Messiah, then perhaps she wanted the happy, festive messiah, not the sword-piercing messiah (that prophecy in Luke 2:23 was probably still bothering her)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all need to be careful not to make God in our image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film series “The Chosen” takes the angle that Mary is not looking for personal glory but is merely trying to save her friend the public shame of running out of wine.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of Jesus reply being curt or disrespectful, the question is inquisitive, “why are you telling me this?” He then reiterates that it’s not the time for a public sign. To which Mary says “please…” – Jesus being Jesus figures out a way to honor His mother but have the sign kept quiet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I like about this portrayal is that it challenges the common narrative that Jesus was being rude. It gives us another way to look at the story – as long as it is still faithful to the Bible I think we should get comfortable with holding a couple of open options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting that many of the earliest Jewish commentaries weren’t commentaries as we think of them but paraphrases that creatively add in details that are omitted by the text. For example, the Jewish targum on Genesis 1:2 reads, “And the earth was vacancy and desolation, solitary of the sons of men, and void of every animal; and darkness was upon the face of the abyss, and the Spirit of mercies from before the Lord breathed upon the face of the waters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While always need to make sure any paraphrase lines up with scripture, God did give us the gift of imagination. There’s a time and a place for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase the exchange:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary: They have no more wine. I know you are the promised Messiah who is supposed to bring in the endless supply of wine. So bring some now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus: What can I do about it now? The Messianic Era when the supply of wine will be inexhaustible has not yet come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary (undaunted and in faith): Do whatever He tells you.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though it wasn’t His time, the wedding feast at Cana, carries prophetic anticipation to the ultimate wedding feast, the Marriage Supper of the Lamb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-26-8&#34;&gt;John 2:6-8&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there were six stone water jars there for the Ioudaioi’s rites of purification, each holding twenty or thirty gallons. Jesus said to the servants, “Fill the jars with water.” And they filled them up to the brim. And he said to them, “Now draw some out and take it to the master of the feast.” So they took it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, &lt;em&gt;Ioudaioi&lt;/em&gt; refers not to a people but to proper religious procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another suggestion that John is explaining the situation for non-Jewish readers, but ones who were loosely familiar with the procedure (as he doesn’t go into great detail about the reason for the purification rite).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though John may have been written to non-Jewish Israelites such as Samaritans, Jesus is clear that the Jewish method is the correct one (“Salvation is of the Jews.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do learn a couple of things about the Ioudaioi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ioudiaoi were not necessarily limited to the geographic terrotiry of Jerusalem or even Judea. This is in Cana in Galilee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not every reference to Ioudaioi is referring to the temple establishment; as is the case here, it could be followers of the Jewish system&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the audience were Jews as say in Matthew’s gospel, this qualifier would have been entirely unnecessary; John apparently expects his audience to be with purification rituals, but not necessarily JEWISH purification rituals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the size of the “jars” – they are almost as big as wine barrels – a significant quantity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John doesn’t tend to use numbers and details by accident so there is likely some significance to the six stone jars used for ceremonial washing – unfortunately, what that symbolism might have been is lost on us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first of seven major miracles in John’s gospel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John is testifying that he was an eyewitness that creation submitted to Jesus’ authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The master of the feast was responsible for the details of the banquet freeing up the host to attend to his guests and the festivities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He pronounced the blessings over the food and wine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiously, the first blessing over the first cup of wine was called the kos habesorah – cup of the good news.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The blessing was to declare and certify the bride’s purity.&lt;/strong&gt; Wow. Let that sink in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also was tasked with controlling the flow of food and drink; thus he would have been responsible for running out of wine prematurely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-29-10&#34;&gt;John 2:9-10&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When the master of the feast tasted the water now become wine, and did not know where it came from (though the servants who had drawn the water knew, the master of the feast called the bridegroom and said to him, “Everyone serves the good wine first, and when people have drunk freely, then the poor wine. But you have kept the good wine until now.””&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the story is very familiar to us, this was a very private miracle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener notes that drunkenness to be part of the celebration at Cana is unlikely and the wine was often diluted 2:1 or 3:1.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-211-12&#34;&gt;John 2:11-12&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This, the first of his signs, Jesus did at Cana in Galilee, and manifested his glory. And his disciples believed in him. After this he went down to Capernaum, with his mother and his brothers and his disciples, and they stayed there for a few days.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verse 11 is our memory verse for this lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John gives us the reason for the wine miracle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Stern says, the reason is “to anchor the trust of his new talmidim in the glory of God as manifested through Him.”&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson began with Andrew proclaiming Jesus as the one Moses spoke of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moses’ first miracle was water to blood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus’ first miracle was water to wine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is unlikely to be a coincidence (the rabbis say “coincidence is not a kosher word.”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We look forward to OUR great messianic wedding banquet where wine will flow in abundance and Jesus will proclaim the wedding blessings over His bride.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolen, Todd. “John 1.” PowerPoint presentation presented at the Photo Companion to the Bible: John, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keener, Craig S. &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;. 2nd edition (E-Sword). Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, D. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by Boaz Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster. 2nd ed. 6 vols. Torah Club. Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lizorkin-Eyzenberg, Eli. &lt;em&gt;The Jewish Gospel of John: Discovering Jesus, King of All Israel&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by Ronald S. Weinbaum. Jewish Studies for Christians, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schlegel, William. “Satellite Bible Atlas: Historical Geography of the Bible.” Israel: SkyLand Publishing, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———. “The Land and the Bible: A Historical Geographical Companion to the Satellite Bible Atlas,” September 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern, David H. &lt;em&gt;Jewish New Testament Commentary: A Companion Volume to the Jewish New Testament&lt;/em&gt;. E-Sword edition. Clarksville, Md.: Lederer Messianic Publications, 1992.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Chosen Season 1, Episode 5: The Wedding Gift&lt;/em&gt;, 2019. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.angel.com/watch/the-chosen/episode/64956907-c5cb-4bdb-8ba1-e8528f74e4cf/season-1/episode-5/the-wedding-gift&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.angel.com/watch/the-chosen/episode/64956907-c5cb-4bdb-8ba1-e8528f74e4cf/season-1/episode-5/the-wedding-gift&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/come_and_see_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/come_and_see_1.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_first_sign_1.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://friends.ffoz.org/resources/portion-connections/the_first_sign_1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vintage Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/siLcYcZ6zi8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eli Lizorkin-Eyzenberg, &lt;em&gt;The Jewish Gospel of John: Discovering Jesus, King of All Israel&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Ronald S. Weinbaum (Jewish Studies for Christians, 2015), loc. 401.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Bolen, “John 1” (PowerPoint presentation, Photo Companion to the Bible: John, Santa Clarita, CA, 2018), fig. tb092302017.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William Schlegel, &lt;em&gt;Satellite Bible Atlas: Historical Geography of the Bible&lt;/em&gt; (Israel: SkyLand Publishing, 2016), Map 9-3 Early Ministry of Jesus and John the Baptist.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William Schlegel, “The Land and the Bible: A Historical Geographical Companion to the Satellite Bible Atlas,” September 2013, 162, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bibleplaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/The-Land-and-the-Bible.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. Thomas Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Boaz Michael and Stephen D. Lancaster, 2nd ed., Torah Club (Marshfield, MO: First Fruits of Zion, 2014), 215.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 218.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lizorkin-Eyzenberg, &lt;em&gt;The Jewish Gospel of John&lt;/em&gt;, 21.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, 221.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schlegel, “Satellite Bible Atlas”, Map 9-3 Early Ministry of Jesus and John the Baptist.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, 224.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David H. Stern, &lt;em&gt;Jewish New Testament Commentary: A Companion Volume to the Jewish New Testament&lt;/em&gt;, E-Sword edition (Clarksville, Md.: Lederer Messianic Publications, 1992), loc. John 2:4-5.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Chosen Season 1, Episode 5: The Wedding Gift&lt;/em&gt;, 2019, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.angel.com/watch/the-chosen/episode/64956907-c5cb-4bdb-8ba1-e8528f74e4cf/season-1/episode-5/the-wedding-gift&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.angel.com/watch/the-chosen/episode/64956907-c5cb-4bdb-8ba1-e8528f74e4cf/season-1/episode-5/the-wedding-gift&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, &lt;em&gt;Chronicles of the Messiah&lt;/em&gt;, 224.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster, 226.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig S. Keener, &lt;em&gt;The IVP Bible Background Commentary: New Testament&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition (E-Sword) (Downers Grove, Illinois: IVP Academic, 2014), loc. John 2:9-10.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern, &lt;em&gt;Jewish New Testament Commentary&lt;/em&gt;, loc. John 2:11.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Jerusalem</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#geography&#34;&gt;Geography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-213-17--the-passover-of-the-ioudaioi&#34;&gt;John 2:13-17 – The Passover of the Ioudaioi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeshua is IN JERUSALEM, the holy city, for the Passover festival and remains in Judea for a few extra weeks while His disciples immerse new penitents. Meanwhile, John the Immerser moves his work into Samaria and begins immersing “at Aenon near Salim,” leaving Yeshua and His followers to baptize in the area around Jerusalem. Salim is a fertile valley in Samaria east of Shechem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7PNBs7G9F3Y&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “First” Passover&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “First” overturning of the tables&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick at Night&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 3:16&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many scholars believe John is recording separate accounts from the synoptic gospels (Matthew, Mark, and Luke) while others contend John is interweaving the same events and is not necessarily interested in following a strict chronology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem with treating them each as separate is that we would end up with Jesus celebrating five or six Passovers during the time of his public ministry. You can’t fit more than four Passovers in a 3-year public ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, if Jesus drove out the profiteers one year, it’s easy to see they would be right back at it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For reasons we have discussed I tend to believe Luke follows a strict chronology, but whichever view you hold on this I would recommend not holding on to it too tightly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, focus on what each gospel writer is trying to communicate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;geography&#34;&gt;Geography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.png&#34; style=&#34;width:5.30217in;height:7.5in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ended last lesson with the wedding at Cana (box 4) and Jesus spending a few days in Capernaum. Now, an unknown amout of time has passed and the next major event John records is the “first” Passover in Jerusalem, represented as event #5 according to Schlaegel , who views John’s recount of the temple cleansing as a separate event from the cleansing at Jesus’ final Passover as recorded in the synoptic Gospels. The counter-argument is that John is not as interested in chronology and could be placing the later event here for his own purposes. There are very smart people on both sides of the argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-213-17--the-passover-of-the-ioudaioi&#34;&gt;John 2:13-17 – The Passover of the Ioudaioi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image2.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.50311in;height:4.35in&#34; alt=&#34;C:\Users\Public\_Bethany\john2plus\Samaritan Passover, courtyard with men, tb043007194.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 The Passover of the Ioudaioi was at hand, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Eli believes John specifies the Passover of the Ioudaioi to differentiate from the Passover of the Shomrim, the Samaritans because John has the Samaritans as one of his intended audiences. The Qumranites also held their own Passover according to their own calendar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Samaritans are still around today and continue to celebrate a biblical Passover in much the same way that they have for more than two thousand years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the temple in Jerusalem does not exist, Jews do not practice animal sacrifice and thus the closest we can get to the practices of the first century is at the Samaritan celebration each year on Mount Gerizim.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a Jewish audience, and even to most gentiles, it would not be necessary to specify that it was a Jewish Passover; he could have just said “Passover.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.875in&#34; alt=&#34;C:\PLBL\03 Jerusalem\Southern Temple Mount Excavations\Shops underneath staircase of Robinson&amp;#39;s Arch, tb020101216.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14 In the temple he found those who were selling oxen and sheep and pigeons, and the money-changers sitting there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 And making a whip of cords, he drove them all out of the temple, with the sheep and oxen. And he poured out the coins of the money-changers and overturned their tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;16 And he told those who sold the pigeons, “Take these things away; do not make my Father&amp;rsquo;s house a house of trade.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17 His disciples remembered that it was written, “Zeal for your house will consume me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Archaeologists have discovered shops built outside the Temple Mount on both the western and southern walls. Jesus presumably had no objection to these. What He took offense with was the commercial activity that had invaded the places intended for worship on the Temple Mount itself. tb020101216&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- --&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shops occupied the space underneath the monumental staircase that passed over Robinson’s Arch to provide access to the temple courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also that the things the people were selling were necessary for the Passover procedures at the temple and the money changers served an entirely practical purpose. Keener notes that money changers were needed to standardize the various foreign currencies of the pilgrims so the local sellers didn’t have to worry about “exchange rates” if I can use that term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can surmise that just like today a tourist can get swindled with an unfair exchange rate and a merchant can overcharge the unsuspecting, the same thing must have been happening at the temple. Dishonest money changers and merchants were profiteering at the expense of God’s faithful, likely in collusion with each other. Today that is called racketeering and is very much frowned upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talked a little about whether this cleansing is the same as the one the synoptic gospels record at the end of Jesus’ ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately we recommend to not focus on whether this was the same or different events but focus on what each gospel is teaching us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Eli notes that the quote John uses “Zeal for your house will consume me” is different from the quote the synoptic writers use, “my house shall be called a prayer for all nations, but you have made it a robber’s den.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John has in view an issue of purity whereas the synoptics appear to have a concern for the negative impression the spectacle of buying and selling has on the Gentiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Eli sees John as providing evidence that the temple is unfit for proper worship because it is being controlled by apostates. It needed to be cleansed of this impurity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image4.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.32222in&#34; alt=&#34;C:\Users\Public\_Bethany\john2plus\Fallen stones from Temple Mount destruction, tb090705034.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;18 So the Ioudaioi said to him, “What sign do you show us for doing these things?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 Jesus answered them, “Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20 The Ioudaioi then said, “It has taken forty-six years to build this temple, and will you raise it up in three days?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;21 But he was speaking about the temple of his body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meaning of Ioudaioi here is different than the meaning in verse 13. Before it referd to all jews or a Jewish religious observance in contrast to some other religious observance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, it appears to mean a few representatives of the Sadducean temple authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For reasons we can only speculate, John never uses the term Saducee (this is a big clue that the first part of John 8, while historically accurate, was not written by John. It appears to be a later scribal insertion.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pharisees were not in charge of the temple and, assuming this is early in Jesus’ ministry, Pharisees were similarly interested in the purity of worship and probably agreed with Jesus’ actions here (though they were unlikely to admit it publicly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few points where we might be tempted to place the wrong emphasis in a sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We probably read this as, “what SIGNS do you show us for doing these things?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More likely it should be, “what signs do you SHOW US for doing these things?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sadducees thought they were the authority; one of John’s themes is the Sadducees are the usurpers – Jesus is the rightful authority no matter what the Sadducees think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo: Archaeologists excavated this area in the 1990s and left these stones in place as a testimony to the Roman destruction in AD 70. Archaeologists have estimated that if all the Herodian stones which are in secondary use around Jerusalem were gathered together, almost the entire height of the Temple Mount walls could be reconstructed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While here, Jesus wasn’t necessarily predicting the destruction of the Literal Temple, in Luke 21 Jesus does exactly this. He says “not one stone will be left upon another” – today you can visit the southwest corner at the base of the temple mount and see that this prophecy was not only fulfilled, but literally fulfilled. Not one stone was left upon another&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tb090705034&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;22 When therefore he was raised from the dead, his disciples remembered that he had said this, and they believed the Scripture and the word that Jesus had spoken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;23 Now when he was in Jerusalem at the Passover Feast, many believed in his name when they saw the signs that he was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;24 But Jesus on his part did not entrust himself to them, because he knew all people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25 and needed no one to bear witness about man, for he himself knew what was in man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because Jesus is perfect, He is perfectly compassionate. He didn’t just heal for the sake of healing; he performed these miraculous acts as acts of compassion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lancaster: “In Jewish thought a person’s name conveys authority. To believe on the name of Yeshua is to accept His authority as an Agent of God. They believed Him to be the promised Messiah”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verse 24 reads strange to us, “He did not need anyone’s testimony about a person because he knew what was within a person, or some translations have “within the heart of man.” This could be another way of saying that he told others to not tell anyone. He does not need man’s testimony and in fact preferred to keep a low profile for a number of reasons. He did not want to be seen as one who wanted to attract big crowds, though ultimately big crowds are exactly what happened. He also did not want to attract the attention of the establishment and roman authorities prematurely. He was not fomenting a revolution. He will say repeatedly that “my hour has not yet come.”. We can see the traps of fame very clearly today. People latch on to powerful and influential people for their own ulterior motives. Jesus wanted no part of such people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John is also attesting to Jesus’ divinity. Just as with Nethaniel under the fig tree, Jesus knows what is in man’s hearts – things only God can know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 3:1-35&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Now there was a man of the Pharisees named Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 This man came to Jesus by night and said to him, “Rabbi, we know that you are a teacher come from God, for no one can do these signs that you do unless God is with him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 Jesus answered him, “Truly, truly, I say to you, unless one is born again he cannot see the kingdom of God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 Nicodemus said to him, “How can a man be born when he is old? Can he enter a second time into his mother&amp;rsquo;s womb and be born?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 Jesus answered, “Truly, truly, I say to you, unless one is born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter the kingdom of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 That which is born of the flesh is flesh, and that which is born of the Spirit is spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 Do not marvel that I said to you, ‘You must be born again.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 The wind blows where it wishes, and you hear its sound, but you do not know where it comes from or where it goes. So it is with everyone who is born of the Spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9 Nicodemus said to him, “How can these things be?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 Jesus answered him, “Are you the teacher of Israel and yet you do not understand these things?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 Truly, truly, I say to you, we speak of what we know, and bear witness to what we have seen, but you do not receive our testimony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12 If I have told you earthly things and you do not believe, how can you believe if I tell you heavenly things?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 No one has ascended into heaven except he who descended from heaven, the Son of Man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14 And as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, so must the Son of Man be lifted up,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 that whoever believes in him may have eternal life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10. In Judea (22)</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb2/gb10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-314-16&#34;&gt;John 3:14-16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-317-18&#34;&gt;John 3:17-18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-319&#34;&gt;John 3:19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-320-21&#34;&gt;John 3:20-21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#john-326&#34;&gt;John 3:26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VscqxOd9aZA&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image19.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.4265in;height:0.42654in&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image20.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.4265in;height:0.42654in&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image21.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.4265in;height:0.42654in&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image22.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image23.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.40333in;height:4.11in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.4265in;height:0.42654in&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some commentators see 3:16-21 as John the apostle writing his own commentary in summation of the Nicodemus dialogue. Others see the passage as Jesus’ own words, continuing the dialogue with Nicodemus. I would favor these being Jesus’ words, but I can see why people think they might be John’s there are certainly some similarities to passages such as chapter 1, which we know are John’s writings. Ultimately, we would say John is inspired by the Holy Spirit so we can be confident John 3:16 is from the mouth of God, even if not spoken by Jesus to Nicodemus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we don’t want to do is view John 3:16-21 as a separate thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image26.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image27.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:6.73667in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.4265in;height:0.42654in&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image30.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image23.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.40333in;height:4.11in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image31.png&#34; style=&#34;width:2.61in;height:2.57667in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.4265in;height:0.42654in&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HAD to return to Galilee through Samaria. Usually Jews would avoid Samaritans and take the way down the mountain through Jericho then head north along the Jordan. This time, Jesus is going to head due north along the way of the patriarchs, the &amp;lt;click&amp;gt; same road Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob traveled when they needed to go north/south.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-314-16&#34;&gt;John 3:14-16&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image34.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is still answering Nicodemus’ question, “how can these things be?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Only Son” recalls Genesis 22 and Abraham’s near offering of Isaac, where Isaac is called Abraham’s “only” (or “unique”) son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 3:16 is famous precisely because of the fact it requires no additional insight or commentary to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Son of God expresses the true nature of Jesus eternal and essential being. He is the LOGOS made flesh, the Son has emanated forth from God.” That’s a quote from Lancaster’s commentary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stern notes that while Matthew presents Jesus as coming for the lost sheep of Israel, John emphasies that Jesus has come to Jews and Gentiles alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image35.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God loves His creation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He gives His creation that which is most precious to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is God’s unique son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus was fully aware that he would have to die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eternal suffering is punishment not only for the inevitable consequence of sin, but now, in rejecting God’s provision for that sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the individual who trusts in Jesus, eternal life means not only in the future beyond the grave, but positive life now in Jesus – life more abundantly. – from David Stern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the Jewish concept of verbs is always tied to action. Belief is not mere intellectual acknowledgment, but a life that reflects a fundamental trust in and reliance on Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-317-18&#34;&gt;John 3:17-18&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image39.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a debate about whether 3:16-21 is Jesus still speaking to Nicodemus or whether the conversation ends at 3:15, and 16-21 is John’s commentary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supporters of the later view note the similarity between this passage (verse 18 for example) and John 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Either way, these words are powerful and for the most part, self-explanatory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note the tie-in to believing in His name in Chapter 2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first-coming was not to bring judgment. That is handled the second coming – read the book of Revelation for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember this thought that he did not come to condemn when we get to the scene at the synagogue at Nazareth. Jesus is going to read from Isaiah 61 but He’s going to omit a line that turns out to be very telling in differentiating between the first and second comings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image40.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:7.11111in;height:4in&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;John (or Jesus) is continuing to contrast light versus dark, innocent vs guilty, saved vs John 3:18 condemned (based on faith, not lineage or works), righteous versus wicked,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Dead Sea scrolls also make these contrasts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This American Colony photograph was taken between 1900 and 1920.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mat02208&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-319&#34;&gt;John 3:19&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image44.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is now compared to a light coming into the world, which certainly recalls Genesis 1:3-4. As we studied back in the first lesson, there are many parallels with John 1 and Genesis 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image45.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:7.11111in;height:4in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jesus’s day, the city would not have been as well-lit after dark. A quick Greek lesson – we often hear that the word “&lt;em&gt;agape&lt;/em&gt;” means God’s perfect love. Jerusalem from the Mount of Olives at night (from the east)o o Verse 19 reads, men &lt;em&gt;agapao&lt;/em&gt; the darkness&amp;hellip;because their deeds are evil. o It’s better to think of Agape as to be totally and completely given over to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you totally and completely given over to God, or do we give part to God but save part for the world?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Note the design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The passage begins with the dark heart (i.e. lies) of man and the meeting with Nicodemus is in the literal darkness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The passage ends with the truth and light of God. o As a literary form, this type of bracketing is common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spiritually, John’s point is the believer passes from death to life; from darkness to light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to look at a verse like verse 19 and conclude that is only referring to people who reject God. Well, of course it is, but what we forget is that was you and me at one point. Our sin nature still agapao’s darkness rather than light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tb031505530b&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-320-21&#34;&gt;John 3:20-21&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image49.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who agapao darkness, the last thing they want is to have their deeds exposed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For disciples, who believe in the Son (John 3:16), this faith results in the believer moving into the light. Such belief is supposed to manifest in good deeds; thus the believer is unafraid to have the light expose righteous works.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John 3:36 reiterates this thought of obedience. “Whoever believes in the Son has eternal life; whoever does not obey the Son shall not see life, but the wrath of God remains on him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The church at learge today teaches, “just believe and you’re in”. As if our faith is all boiled down to acknowledging a certain set of facts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;True talmidim, Believe Him, walk with Him, and follow Him and OBEY him o Lancaster writes, “Belief in Him needs to result in repentance and turning towards God.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
 &lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image50.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:7.11111in;height:4in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nicodemus came with questions. Perhaps he initially left with More questions but God rewards a heart that seeks after Him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We know from John 7 and John 19 that Nicodemus was and is a believer. Despite his wealth and his status, His interview with Jesus changed His life forever. Nicodemus is one person I’m looking forward to meeting one day in the age to come.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mat14450h&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image52.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John’s imprisonment is reported in Mat 14:3-12 and Mark 6:17-29.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is some speculation that John the gospel writer is the unnamed Jew.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image53.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:7.11111in;height:4in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hills in the distance belong to Gilead, in the modern country of Jordan. The ponds in the distance reflect the availability of water from springs here and are used for raising fish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The themes of purification, living water, spirit are throughout the early chapters of John.John 3:23&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ch 1: waters of baptism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ch 2: stone jars of purification and cleansing/purifying of the temple o Ch 3: born of water and spirit and this discussion beginning with v. 22 o Ch 4: the Woman at the Well and the discussion of living water&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ch 5: the false waters of the Asklepion of Bethesda versus the One who can bring true restoration and purification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also references to purification by water in chapters 7, 9 13, and 19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among many contrasts, John is pointing out that Jesus is the ceremonially pure one in contrast to the general world at large and the temple establishment in particular&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tbs99019810&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;john-326&#34;&gt;John 3:26&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image57.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 4:2 is going to clarify that Jesus was not immersing but his talmidim were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image61.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John describes his role in the form of a parable o Bride: Israel o Groom: Messiah o Friend: John&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bringing the Bride to the Groom: John’s ministry of immersion and repentance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voice: Jesus’ call or Jesus going public with His ministry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meaning: “John’s role was only to prepare Israel for Messiah and then step aside.” (Lancaster, COM 247)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John did not want his own works to overshadow Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While John’s and possibly Jesus’ disciples were beginning to form a Jordan River Rivalry, John is uninterested in the dispute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only is John NOT upset, he is joyful. Weddings are supposed to be joyful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lancaster suggests John is playing the role of Moses, who brings the bride (Israel) to meet the groom (God).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verse 30 is an important one for Talmidim. It’s not about us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we are ambassadors for Jesus, we put His interests first and ours second.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Walking In His Dust&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talmidim keep our eyes on God’s bigger picture.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ephesians 4:1-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I therefore, a prisoner for the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lord, urge you to walk in a manner worthy of the calling to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which you have been called, with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all &lt;strong&gt;humility&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;gentleness&lt;/strong&gt;, with &lt;strong&gt;patience&lt;/strong&gt;, bearing with one&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;another in &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt;, eager to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;maintain the &lt;strong&gt;unity&lt;/strong&gt; of the Spirit in the bond of peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image62.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image63.png&#34; style=&#34;width:1.96333in;height:2.18667in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.42662in;height:0.42654in&#34; /&gt;We see for a second time John’s humility. The first was when he allowed two of his disciples to switch teachers. The more we can keep our own pride and ego in check, the more the Light of Jesus can shine through us. The Ultimate goal is when people see us, they don’t see us, they see Jesus through us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 100%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 84%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 15%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John 3:31-33&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image64.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Corinthians 15:47-49 The first man&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;was from the earth, a man of dust; the second man is from heaven. As was the man of dust, so also are those who are of the dust, and as is the man of heaven, so also are those who are of heaven. Just as we have borne the image of the man of dust, we shall also bear the image of the man of heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.4265in;height:0.42654in&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John now moves into a discourse comparing the earthly man vs the heavenly man. Paul framed this in terms of the first Adam vs the last adam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image66.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:7.11111in;height:4in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image67.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:2.74036in;height:4.19443in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image68.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:3.21254in;height:2.40941in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.47407in;height:0.47407in&#34; /&gt;Note the recurring themes of “witness,” “testimony,” and so forth. Discovered in Cave 4 of Qumran in the early 1950s, this text contains five biblical verses that focused on the coming of the Messiah. Cave 4 is the famous cave where many books of the Old Testament were found,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;including a complete copy of Isaiah.Dead Sea Scroll 4Q175 Testimonia (“Messianic Anthology”), 1st century BC John 3:32&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is another instance where John seemingly breaks off from quoting someone and adds his own commentary. This passage is a little clearer than John 3:16-21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 3:16 is clearly a continuation of the discussion with Nicodemus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, John is picking up the mystical discourse of the Preexistent One he established in Chapter 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we’ve talked about before; John is focused with establishing (giving witness) to who Jesus is, whereas the other gospels focus on what jesus said, did and felt, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the synoptic gospels say “the kingdom of heaven is at hand,” John is going to say “Light has come into the world,” because “light” is who Jesus is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tb060108053&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 65%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&#34;width: 34%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John 3:34-36&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image72.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;Whoever receives his testimony sets his seal to this, that God is true. For he whom God has sent utters the words of God, for he gives the Spirit without measure. The Father loves the Son and has given all things into his hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever believes in the Son has eternal life; whoever does not obey the Son shall not see life, but the wrath of God remains on him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;John 10:29&lt;/sup&gt; My Father, who has given them to me, is greater than all, and no one is able to snatch them out of the Father&#39;s hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 28:18 And Jesus came and said to them, “All authority in heaven and on earth has been given to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.4265in;height:0.42654in&#34; /&gt;On wrath: Romans 1:182:8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seal = authentication, like a notary’s stamp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We take a passage such as “the spirit without measure” for granted, but it was not a simple topic in Jesus’ day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Psalm 51, David could pray, “take not your Spirit from me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we have been sealed by the Spirit as described by the apostolic documents, we can NOT pray this prayer, nor would it ever occur to us to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Judaism of the day, only the righteous could merit the Spirit (in a grand sense, that is still true today).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the concept of authorization is present in John’s gospel. The Son is the fully authorized representative of the Father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For God to give the Spirit without measure would have been another seismic shift in their thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John, again stresses Jesus authority by saying the father has given all things &amp;lt;read references&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can’t read the Bible and come up with multiple ways to salvation. Either believe in the Son and have eternal life, or disobey and experience God’s wrath. I suppose that makes us narrow minded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;john-41-4-references&#34;&gt;John 4:1-4 References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image73.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.4265in;height:0.42654in&#34; /&gt;Now when Jesus learned that the &lt;em&gt;Pharisees&lt;/em&gt; had heard that Jesus was making and baptizing more disciples than John (although Jesus himself did not baptize, but only his disciples), he left Judea and departed again for Galilee. And he had to pass through Samaria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chapter breaks can be most unfortunate because we subconsciously view them as a scene shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John needs to be read in one sitting because everything ties together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Son, who is the Father’s authenticated representative, gives the Spirit without measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the Son, is going to widen the people’s narrow view of who is eligible to receive the Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus popularity was growing, but Jesus was not ready to go full throttle with public ministry in Judea, so he makes a strategic retreat back to Galilee. This is one reason I tend to see the overturning of the tables as occurring at the end of Jesus’ ministry, but John places it early to tell his version of the story. It seems odd that Jesus would have make spectical in Jerusalem, not caring who he angered, but then retreated here not wanting a confrontation. I might be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth mentioning again that when John says “Pharisees” we need to remember that John uses this term very generically, to include herodians and sadducees as well as the party of the Pharisees. In other words, the whole religious establishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We need to look closely at the context to decide whether we have Pharisees or Sadducees in view. There is a big difference,” writes Lancaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s like someone saying “the politicians” and we need to figure out whether they are liberal or conservative, corrupt or clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, the Pharisees were all about having disciples and followers. They were all about the purity of the Law and as yet, Jesus had done nothing to arouse their suspicion. If overturning the tables had happened here, the Pharisees probably would have applauded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;26&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image74.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:7.11111in;height:4in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image75.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:5.97689in;height:4in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image76.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:2.96612in;height:4.19451in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image6.png&#34; style=&#34;width:0.47407in;height:0.47407in&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;27&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image80.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:7.11111in;height:4in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image81.jpg&#34; style=&#34;width:6.4in;height:3.6in&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image82.png&#34; style=&#34;width:3.12667in;height:3.61667in&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;29&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
