<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2023 Israel trip blogs | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/sites/2023-blog/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/sites/2023-blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>2023 Israel trip blogs</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu9bdc4cc28a100eaa5c154301214e2807_480992_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>2023 Israel trip blogs</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/sites/2023-blog/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>2023 Trip Journal #1: Shephelah</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/sites/2023-blog/23-trip-journal-1-shephelah/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/sites/2023-blog/23-trip-journal-1-shephelah/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;compromising--january-11-2023&#34;&gt;Compromising – January 11, 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was especially exciting because, although this is not my first time in Israel, every site we visited was one I&amp;rsquo;d not seen before.  The theme of the day was compromising (Samson at Beth Shemesh) vs. being faithful (David v. Goliath at the Valley of Elah).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;related-devotionals&#34;&gt;Related Devotionals:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Azekah: 
 &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
   &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U2QqSph7j7Q&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;

Bet Guvrin: 
 &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
   &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zqSC8LS1KbI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;yad-hashmonah&#34;&gt;Yad HaShmonah&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We began the day by visiting Yad HaShmonah biblical garden.  The first thing our guide Ronan pointed it is that in the Bible, a garden has nothing to do with flowers.   It revolves around the seven spices of Deuteronomy 8: wheat, barley, grapes, figs, pomegranates, olives, and dates.  There is also a replica watchtower, synagogue, and rolling stone tomb.  In general, we learned all about life in ancient Israel.  This is very near the area of Kiryat Jearim where we recounted the saga of the Ark&amp;rsquo;s capture and subsequent return by the Philistines in 1st Samuel 4-7.  The story began by the Israelites&amp;rsquo; going into battle without God.  Then instead of calling upon God the way Joshua and Moses did, they thought all they needed was the Ark, which was basically supposed to be a good luck charm of sorts.  It&amp;rsquo;s a great story full of geographic references and, more importantly, personal application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;beth-shemesh&#34;&gt;Beth Shemesh&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We next moved just over the hill to Beth Shemesh and the Sorek valley, which is the setting of one of the more famous compromisers, Samson.  &lt;em&gt;Almost&lt;/em&gt; every location referenced in Judges 13-16 is visible from Beth Shemesh and almost every act of Samson involves some form of compromise.  Yet, there he is in Hebrews 11.  That should give all of us hope!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also at Beth Shemesh was an example of an ancient cistern. Pastor Randy then had us read Jeremiah 38 where Jeremiah was thrown into a muddy cistern.  As we were standing in a slightly muddy cistern, the passage came to life.  The photo below is looking up at the roof with the opening.  The cave was completely dark without flashlights.  Other references to being thrown into or lifted out of a pit such as Psalm 40 and &lt;em&gt;possibly&lt;/em&gt; Jesus before Caiaphas also came to mind (in what could be Caiaphas’ house, they found a dungeon/pit, where possibly prisoners were kept.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:8.66667in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;azekah&#34;&gt;Azekah&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there it was to Azekah and the story of David and Goliath.  Azekah is a hill overlooking the valley.  We could see the hills where 1 Samuel 17 records the Philistine and Israelite armies, and of course the valley itself, where we stopped to gather 5 smooth stones from the brook just as David did.  On this day, David did not compromise.  Of the many directions Pastor Rich could have with this wonderful story, he focused on David as the unlikely savior of Israel and how Jesus is also unlikely.  He&amp;rsquo;s not the Hero you&amp;rsquo;re looking for.     &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a quick devotional I recorded [youtube url=&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U2QqSph7j7Q&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U2QqSph7j7Q&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;].  We also discussed some reasons from archeology we can have even more confidence in the biblical account of David and Solomon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image2.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:8.66667in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bet-guvrin&#34;&gt;Bet Guvrin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We concluded the day with a visit to Bet Guvrin, known in Old Testament times as Mareshah.  This is the home of Micah the prophet.  In Micah 6, God calls the hills around Mareshah to be the jury as he presents his case.   Here is another brief devotional: [youtube url=&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zqSC8LS1KbI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zqSC8LS1KbI&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then took a beautiful sunset/dusk drive through the Negev desert and Judean wilderness on our way to the hotel at the Dead Sea.  Here is our route according to Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:6.02014in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More tomorrow!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#2 Wilderness and Negev - 1/12/23</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/sites/2023-blog/honor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/sites/2023-blog/honor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dead Sea Devotional&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was another full day of activities centered around the Dead Sea and Judean wilderness.  The general theme of the day was honor.    We started with a walk along the strand of the Dead Sea as the sun was rising over the &lt;strong&gt;Moab&lt;/strong&gt; mountains.  Ronan  talked about the honor and faithfulness of Ruth the Moabitiess.  In the photo below, the Moab mountains are visible through the haze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image1.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:4.875in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Masada&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then drove to  &lt;strong&gt;Masada&lt;/strong&gt; . Masada means &amp;ldquo;fortress&amp;rdquo; in Hebrew.  It was a palace/fortress Herod built for himself that ended up being used by Jewish rebels.  After the Temple was burned in AD 70, the last 1000 holdouts fled here and made it their last stand.  It holds the same symbolism as the Alamo does in Texas history.  As the Romans were about to storm the top of the fortress, Josephus records that 10 men were tasked with killing their friend&amp;rsquo;s and family and burning/destroying anything of value.  This was a better outcome in their view than being subject to Roman punishment.  Finally the last man standing fell on his sword and when the Romans scaled the wall.  We toured the historic site and learned a lot about 1st century life. As we exited, we walked down a path that parallels the Roman siege ramp, where the Romans breached the walls to find no booty to plunder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the drive from Masada, we learned about the geographic and geologic distinctions among the three words that get translated into English as &amp;ldquo;desert&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;wilderness.&amp;rdquo;  Bmidbar, which is also the name of the book of Numbers in the Hebrew Bible is relatively fertile with shade and water available.  The next type, Tsiya, has no food or shelter.  What happened was villages sprang up about a day&amp;rsquo;s journey apart.  The third type is Yeshimon.  In this type there truly is nothing for days.  Grumbling while in a Tsiyo or Yehimon would be more understandible, but the Israelites grumbled in the Bmidbar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kfar Hanokdim&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then traveled to a location called &lt;strong&gt;Kfar Hanokdim,&lt;/strong&gt; which is a recreated Bedouin village and it is great example of Jews and Arabs working together.  A Jewish man wanted to preserve the hospitality culture that he believed his people have lost (and how much more have WE lost it in the west?), so he approached a group of Arab bedouins who were still living that lifestyle about creating a living museum.   My roommate Jeremy was selected to get 10 sheep from point A to point B about 50 feet away.  It was virtually impossible.  The lessons are certainly there for folks in leadership, but also it was a reminder that we are the stubborn sheep prone to wandering from our Shepherd. We did get to ride camels also. My camel is pictured below.  I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how to interpret his facial expession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image2.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:8.66667in&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This set up the main discussion on Abraham and Hospitality in Genesis 18-19.  I recorded a brief video devo here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gPqCrqMDyXM&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tel Arad&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of time constraints, we were not able to get to Tel Arad, which was a location I had really wanted to see.  One thing about traveling here is &amp;ldquo;blessed are the flexible.&amp;rdquo;  In the bus, we received a fantastic teaching on the history and application of Arad.  It was a place that had a nearly identical replica of the Jerusalem temple.  The first problem is what&amp;rsquo;s another temple doing outside of Jerusalem and what are Jews doing worshipping there?  It gets worse.  On one pillar there was a dedication inscribed &amp;ldquo;to YHWH and his Asherah.&amp;rdquo;   Asherah is a pagan fertility goddess.  So we&amp;rsquo;re forced to ask &amp;ldquo;what in the world was going on here?&amp;rdquo;  After we&amp;rsquo;re done pointing fingers at those dishonoring God, we can&amp;rsquo;t forget to look in the mirror.  What are things we are worshipping alongside of God and bringing dishonor to Him?  What stories do our purchases,  video streaming queues, and internet histories tell?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dead Sea Float&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ended the day with a dip in the &lt;strong&gt;Dead Sea&lt;/strong&gt; - The salinity is about 10x that in oceans, which makes it impossible to sink.  The mineral content means the water is also poisonous to drink. Many claim healing properties from the water and mud from the lake&amp;rsquo;s floor, so it&amp;rsquo;s a tradition to &amp;ldquo;mud up&amp;rdquo; before a dip.  This reminded me of a contrast to living water versus deadly water.  Again, back to our bank accounts and netflix queues: might we actually be ingesting poison water by the things we take in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a brief video of me covered in mud talking about living water!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vb6lfETOmWY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was a day filled with great lessons and an exponentially deeper understanding of God&amp;rsquo;s word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s route from Google Maps (starting and ending at the Dead Sea public beach).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/media/image3.png&#34; style=&#34;width:6.5in;height:7.53333in&#34; /&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
