<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Matthew 1 | Talmidim Way</title>
    <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/matthew-1/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://talmidimway.com/tag/matthew-1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Matthew 1</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 talmidimway.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://talmidimway.com/media/logo_hu53652e90a6e4e4f125f22da2a993ec10_403021_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Matthew 1</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/tag/matthew-1/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Genealogies</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb03-portions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/portions/gospels/gb1/gb03-portions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-apparently-josephs-genealogy-in-matthew-and-marys-in-luke&#34;&gt;3. Apparently Joseph&amp;rsquo;s genealogy in Matthew and Mary&amp;rsquo;s in Luke&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The book of the genealogy of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abraham was the father of Isaac, and Isaac the father of Jacob, and Jacob the father of Judah and his brothers,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Judah the father of Perez and Zerah by Tamar, and Perez the father of Hezron, and Hezron the father of Ram,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Ram the father of Amminadab, and Amminadab the father of Nahshon, and Nahshon the father of Salmon,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Salmon the father of Boaz by Rahab, and Boaz the father of Obed by Ruth, and Obed the father of Jesse,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Jesse the father of David the king. And David was the father of Solomon by the wife of Uriah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Solomon the father of Rehoboam, and Rehoboam the father of Abijah, and Abijah the father of Asaph,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Asaph the father of Jehoshaphat, and Jehoshaphat the father of Joram, and Joram the father of Uzziah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Uzziah the father of Jotham, and Jotham the father of Ahaz, and Ahaz the father of Hezekiah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Hezekiah the father of Manasseh, and Manasseh the father of Amos, and Amos the father of Josiah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Josiah the father of Jechoniah and his brothers, at the time of the deportation to Babylon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And after the deportation to Babylon: Jechoniah was the father of Shealtiel, and Shealtiel the father of Zerubbabel,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Zerubbabel the father of Abiud, and Abiud the father of Eliakim, and Eliakim the father of Azor,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Azor the father of Zadok, and Zadok the father of Achim, and Achim the father of Eliud,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Eliud the father of Eleazar, and Eleazar the father of Matthan, and Matthan the father of Jacob,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Jacob the father of Joseph the husband of Mary, of whom Jesus was born, who is called Christ.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So all the generations from Abraham to David were fourteen generations, and from David to the deportation to Babylon fourteen generations, and from the deportation to Babylon to the Christ fourteen generations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luke 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jesus, when he began his ministry, was about thirty years of age, being the son (as was supposed) of Joseph, the son of Heli,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Matthat, the son of Levi, the son of Melchi, the son of Jannai, the son of Joseph,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Mattathias, the son of Amos, the son of Nahum, the son of Esli, the son of Naggai,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Maath, the son of Mattathias, the son of Semein, the son of Josech, the son of Joda,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Joanan, the son of Rhesa, the son of Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, the son of Neri,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Melchi, the son of Addi, the son of Cosam, the son of Elmadam, the son of Er,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Joshua, the son of Eliezer, the son of Jorim, the son of Matthat, the son of Levi,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Simeon, the son of Judah, the son of Joseph, the son of Jonam, the son of Eliakim,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Melea, the son of Menna, the son of Mattatha, the son of Nathan, the son of David,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Jesse, the son of Obed, the son of Boaz, the son of Sala, the son of Nahshon,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Amminadab, the son of Admin, the son of Arni, the son of Hezron, the son of Perez, the son of Judah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Jacob, the son of Isaac, the son of Abraham, the son of Terah, the son of Nahor,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Serug, the son of Reu, the son of Peleg, the son of Eber, the son of Shelah,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Cainan, the son of Arphaxad, the son of Shem, the son of Noah, the son of Lamech,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Methuselah, the son of Enoch, the son of Jared, the son of Mahalaleel, the son of Cainan,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the son of Enos, the son of Seth, the son of Adam, the son of God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/3-genealogies&#34;  class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Click to read the full Gospel Backgrounds lesson&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3. Genealogies</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/3-genealogies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/3-genealogies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LzkfziqSCps&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4a. Nativity Part I</title>
      <link>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/4a-nativity-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://talmidimway.com/commentary/gospels/gb1/4a-nativity-part-i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none d-xl-none &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hMJcruBECds&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written commentary coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
